<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright (c) Contributors to the Eclipse Foundation
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
   
    SPDX-License-Identifier: Apache-2.0 
 -->

<chapter label="6" revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="framework.resource"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Resource API Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.resource-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.resource"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This section describes the API for the generic
    Requirement-Capability model as introduced in the <xref
    linkend="framework.module.dependencies"/>. This API is not used directly
    by the Framework, the purpose of specifying this base API is to allow it
    to be used as building block for other specifications.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Resource</emphasis> - An entity that can be
          installed in an Environment where it will provide its Capabilities
          when all its Requirements are satisfied.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Environment</emphasis> - A framework or container
          that contains one or more Resources.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Namespace</emphasis> - Defines the semantics of the
          Requirements and Capabilities; a Requirement can only match a
          Capability when they are in the same Namespace. A Namespace is
          similar to a type in an object oriented language.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Requirement</emphasis> - An assertion on a
          Capability in a Namespace. The assertion uses the OSGi filter
          language to match the attributes of a Capability. The filter is
          specified as a directive; a Requirement can also have other
          directives and attributes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Capability</emphasis> - An attribute based
          description of a quality of a Resource when installed in an
          Environment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Wiring</emphasis> - The wired state of a
          Resource.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Wire</emphasis> - Connects a Requirement to a
          matching Capability.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="i1764826">
        <title>Class diagram for org.osgi.resource</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.000in"
                       contentwidth="6.415in" fileref="resource-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resources</title>

    <para>The OSGi dependency model is introduced in <xref
    linkend="framework.module.dependencies"/> ; it is based on a generic
    <emphasis>Requirements/Capability</emphasis> model. In this model a
    <emphasis>Resource</emphasis> models something that can be installed in an
    <emphasis>Environment</emphasis> but has Requirements that must be
    satisfied by Capabilities available in that the Environment. However, once
    it is installed and resolved into the Environment it provides its declared
    Capabilities to that Environment. Bundles are Resources, an example of a
    Requirement is an Import-Package clause, and an example of a Capability is
    an Export-Package clause.</para>

    <para>The <code>org.osgi.resource</code> package contains a base API that
    defines a number of interfaces that model this generic model.</para>

    <para>The <code>org.osgi.framework.wiring</code> package provides an API
    for reflecting the wiring of an OSGi Framework. The purpose of the
    separation is to allow the management agents to treat the system in a
    uniform way. That is, it allows a wide array of resources and environments
    to be modeled, and thus managed, in a uniform way. The Resource API is
    therefore primarily a building block for other specifications.</para>

    <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.Capability"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.Requirement"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> class are almost identical in their signature.
    They both provide the following methods:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>getAttributes()</code> - Return a map with the
        attributes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>getDirectives()</code> - Return a map with the
        directives</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>getNamespace()</code> - Return the Namespace</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>getResource()</code> - Return the Resource</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The key difference between a Requirement and a Capability is that a
    Capability provides attributes that are matched by an OSGi filter
    specified in a Requirement's <code>filter</code> directive.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Namespaces</title>

    <para>The <emphasis>Namespace</emphasis> acts as the type of a Capability
    and Requirement. A Capability and a Requirement can only match when they
    are in the same Namespace. The Namespaces in use by the OSGi Core
    specification are defined in <xref linkend="framework.namespaces"/>. Other
    specifications can, however, define their own Namespaces.</para>

    <para>A Namespace defines:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Requirement Attributes</emphasis> - Any attributes
        that are allowed to be used on a Requirement declaration.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Requirement Directives</emphasis> - Any directives
        that are allowed to be used on a Requirement declaration.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Capability Attributes</emphasis> - Any attributes that
        are allowed to be used on a Capability, these attributes are available
        for matching.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Capability Directives</emphasis> - Any defined
        directives that are allowed to be used on the Capability</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Semantics</emphasis> - The Namespace definition
        defines what the meaning is of a Capability. This can include actions
        in the Environment like for example being wired with certain
        rules.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Matching</title>

      <para>A Requirement matches a Capability when:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>They have the same Namespace, and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Requirement's filter matches the Capability's attributes,
          and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the Namespace is an <code>osgi.wiring.*</code> Namespace
          then the <code>mandatory</code> directive must be supported.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Other Namespaces must not introduce additional matching
      rules.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resolution</title>

    <para>Before a Resource can provide its functionality it must be
    <emphasis>resolved</emphasis> against the Environment. The Environment can
    provide a number of Capabilities of its own but in general the
    Capabilities come from the of the installed Resources. The
    <emphasis>resolver</emphasis> must find a set of
    <emphasis>Wires</emphasis> between Requirements and Capabilities in an
    Environment such that each mandatory Requirement is satisfied with at
    least one Capability, and the constraints of the involved Namespaces are
    all met.</para>

    <para>Resolving is an NP-complete problem since there are many solutions,
    it is easy to test if a solution is right, but there is no algorithm to
    calculate a solution. In practice, for the OSGi resolvers it is possible
    to find solutions in a reasonable amount of time. However, the nature of
    NP-complete problems makes it difficult to set exact rules: many solutions
    are correct. Constraining the resolvers too much would stifle innovation
    and likely cause performance problems.</para>

    <para>In general the Environment has an existing
    <emphasis>Wiring</emphasis> state for already installed Resources. The
    resolver then calculates a resolution, which is a set of Wires that should
    be added to the existing Wiring state by installing the Resources. A Wire
    is a connection from a Requirement to a Capability. A Requirement or
    Capability is <emphasis>declared</emphasis> in a Resource. This is
    depicted in <xref linkend="i1769129"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1769129">
      <title>Wire and declared Resources</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="0.690in"
                     contentwidth="6.185in" fileref="wire-resources.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section>
      <title>Hosted Requirements and Capabilities</title>

      <para>Though each Capability and Requirement is declared in a Resource,
      it can however be <emphasis>hosted</emphasis> by another Resource. For
      example, when a Fragment has an Export-Package header it is in reality
      its host that will provide that package. There is therefore a clear
      distinction between the Resource that declares the
      Capability/Requirement and the run time Wiring state that hosts that
      Capability. For this reason, a Wire connects a Requirement and a
      Capability but links separately to the Resources that host the
      Requirement and the Capability. <xref linkend="i1769742"/> depicts a
      hosted Capability. The Capability from the Fragment bundle is hosted by
      Host A and Host B.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i1769742">
        <title>Hosted Capability Example</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.858in"
                       contentwidth="6.242in" fileref="hosted-cap-example.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>For this reason, the <xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wire"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> class provides the following methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wire.getRequirement--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Requirement wired from.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wire.getRequirer--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Resource that hosts the
          Requirement.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wire.getCapability--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Capability that is wired to.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wire.getProvider--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Resource that hosts the
          Capability.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Resolution</title>

      <para>Requirements can be <code>optional</code> or
      <code>mandatory</code>, as specified in the <code>resolution</code>
      directive, which is only available on the Requirement. Optional
      Requirements do not have to be satisfied by the Resolver. Environments
      can be eager or relaxed in finding Resources to resolve optional
      Requirements. All mandatory Requirements of a Resource must be satisfied
      before that Resource's Capabilities can be provided to the
      Environment.</para>

      <para>The syntax of the resolution directive is therefore:</para>

      <programlisting>resolution ::= 'optional' | 'mandatory'</programlisting>

      <para>The default is <code>mandatory</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Effectiveness</title>

      <para>Both Requirements and Capabilities support the
      <code>effective</code> directive. This directive provides a name that
      can be used by the Environment to control the resolving process. During
      a resolve process, the Environment can then decide one or more names
      that must match the <code>effective</code> directive.</para>

      <para>For the OSGi Framework, the name <code>resolve</code> is reserved,
      this is also the default. This is the only value that makes a Requirement 
      or Capability effective during the OSGi Framework's standard resolve process.
      The syntax is therefore:</para>

      <programlisting>effective ::= &lt;name&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Requirements and Capabilities may specify alternative values for the
      <code>effective</code> directive. A widely adopted convention is the value
      <code>active</code>, which is defined in the 
      <code>org.osgi.resource.Namespace.EFFECTIVE_ACTIVE</code> constant. 
      This value can be used to indicate requirements that must be present for a 
      bundle to be active and executable, such as runtime service dependencies. 
      However, requirements and capabilities with <code>effective:=active</code> 
      are ignored by the OSGi Framework's standard resolve process.</para>

      <para>The <code>active</code> effective time is a convention that enables 
      tooling providers to share a common vocabulary when working with runtime 
      dependencies. For example, build and provisioning tools like bnd can use 
      this convention to distinguish between compile-time resolve dependencies and 
      runtime active dependencies. When applications use the <xref 
      linkend="service.resolver"/> directly, they can specify which 
      <code>effective</code> values to consider during resolution through the 
      <code>ResolveContext.isEffective</code> method, as described in <xref 
      linkend="service.resolver"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Mandatory Attributes</title>

      <para>If a Capability has declared a <code>mandatory</code> directive
      and the Namespace starts with <code>osgi.wiring</code> then it mandates
      that the names listed directive are used in the filter and must match.
      The syntax for the mandatory attribute is:</para>

      <programlisting>mandatory   ::= extended ( ',' extended )*</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Cardinality</title>

      <para>The cardinality directive defines if a Requirement can be wired to
      multiple Capabilities or must be wired to at most one. The syntax for
      the directive is:</para>

      <programlisting>cardinality ::= 'single' | 'multiple'</programlisting>

      <para>The default is <code>single</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Class Space Consistency</title>

      <para>Though the Requirement/Capability model is generic it is linked
      closely with the class loading architecture of OSGi frameworks,
      particularly class space consistency, see <xref
      linkend="framework.module.constraint.solving"/>. For this reason, each
      Capability can specify its <emphasis>uses constraints</emphasis> with
      the <code>uses</code> Capability directive. The uses directive always
      contains a comma separated list of package names. The resolver must
      ensure that any resolution does not violate the class space consistency
      based on these constraints. Uses constraints can be specified on any
      Capability, not just Capabilities related to class loading, and are
      always about Java packages. The syntax of the directive is:</para>

      <programlisting>uses ::= package-name ( ',' package-name )*</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Wiring</title>

    <para>A resolver calculates a set of Wires between Requirements and
    Capabilities based on an existing, potentially empty, state. The existing
    state in the Environment is represented in a set of <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wiring" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> objects. Such
    an object represents the Wiring state of a Resource in an Environment. It
    provides access to all hosted Requirements and Capabilities as well as
    existing Wires. It has the following methods to conveniently provide
    access to the state:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wiring.getResource--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The related Resource.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wiring.getProvidedResourceWires-String-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get any Wires, in the given Namespace, where
        the related Resource is the provider.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wiring.getRequiredResourceWires-String-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get any Wires, in the given Namespace, where
        the related Resource is the requirer.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wiring.getResourceCapabilities-String-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get the hosted Capabilities of the related
        Resource.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.resource.Wiring.getResourceRequirements-String-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get the hosted Requirements of the related
        Resource.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
