<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="109"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="service.io" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>IO Connector Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.io-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.io"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para xml:id="i1306290">Communication is at the heart of OSGi Framework
    functionality. Therefore, a flexible and extendable communication API is
    needed: one that can handle all the complications that arise out of the
    Reference Architecture. These obstacles could include different
    communication protocols based on different networks, firewalls,
    intermittent connectivity, and others.</para>

    <para>Therefore, this IO Connector Service specification adopts the <xref
    linkend="i1304655"/> (J2ME) <code>javax.microedition.io</code> packages as
    a basic communications infrastructure. In J2ME, this API is also called
    the Connector framework. A key aspect of this framework is that the
    connection is configured by a single string, the URI.</para>

    <para>In J2ME, the Connector framework can be extended by the vendor of
    the Virtual Machine, but cannot be extended at run-time by other code.
    Therefore, this specification defines a service that adopts the flexible
    model of the Connector framework, but allows bundles to extend the
    Connector Services into different communication domains.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Abstract</emphasis> - Provide an intermediate layer
          that abstracts the actual protocol and devices from the bundle using
          it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Extendable</emphasis> - Allow third-party bundles to
          extend the system with new protocols and devices.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Layered</emphasis> - Allow a protocol to be layered
          on top of lower layer protocols or devices.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Configurable</emphasis> - Allow the selection of an
          actual protocol/device by means of configuration data.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Compatibility</emphasis> - Be compatible with
          existing standards.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Connector Service</emphasis> - The service that
          performs the same function, creating connections from different
          providers, as the static methods in the Connector framework of
          <code>javax.microediton.io</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Connection Factory</emphasis> - A service that
          extends the Connector service with more schemes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Scheme</emphasis> - A protocol or device that is
          supported in the Connector framework.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure pgwide="1">
        <title>Class Diagram, org.osgi.service.io (jmi is
        javax.microedition.io)</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="4.440in"
                       contentwidth="6.500in" fileref="io-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Connector Framework</title>

    <para>The <xref linkend="i1304655"/> specification introduces a package
    for communicating with back-end systems. The requirements for this package
    are very similar to the following OSGi requirements:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Small footprint</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Allows many different implementations simultaneously</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Simple to use</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Simple configuration</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The key design goal of the Connector framework is to allow an
    application to use a communication mechanism/protocol without
    understanding implementation details.</para>

    <para>An application passes a Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) to the
    <code>java.microedition.io.Connector</code> class, and receives an object
    implementing one or more <code>Connection</code> interfaces. The
    <code>java.microedition.io.Connector</code> class uses the scheme in the
    URI to locate the appropriate Connection Factory service. The remainder of
    the URI may contain parameters that are used by the Connection Factory
    service to establish the connection; for example, they may contain the
    baud rate for a serial connection. Some examples:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>sms://+46705950899;expiry=24h;reply=yes;type=9</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>datagram://:53</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>socket://www.acme.com:5302</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>comm://COM1;baudrate=9600;databits=9</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>file:c:/autoexec.bat</code></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The <code>javax.microedition.io</code> API itself does not prescribe
    any schemes. It is up to the implementer of this package to include a
    number of extensions that provide the schemes. The
    <code>javax.microedition.io.Connector</code> class dispatches a request to
    a class which provides an implementation of a <code>Connection</code>
    interface. J2ME does not specify how this dispatching takes place, but
    implementations usually offer a proprietary mechanism to connect user
    defined classes that can provide new schemes.</para>

    <para>The Connector framework defines a taxonomy of communication
    mechanisms with a number of interfaces. For example, a
    <code>javax.microedition.io.InputConnection</code> interface indicates
    that the connection supports the input stream semantics, such as an I/O
    port. A <code>javax.microedition.io.DatagramConnection</code> interface
    indicates that communication should take place with messages.</para>

    <para>When a <code>javax.microedition.io.Connector.open</code> method is
    called, it returns a <code>javax.microedition.io.Connection</code> object.
    The interfaces implemented by this object define the type of the
    communication session. The following interfaces may be implemented:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>HttpConnection</emphasis> - A
        <code>javax.microedition.io.ContentConnection</code> with specific
        HTTP support.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>DatagramConnection</emphasis> - A connection that can
        be used to send and receive datagrams.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>OutputConnection</emphasis> - A connection that can be
        used for streaming output.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>InputConnection</emphasis> - A connection that can be
        used for streaming input.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>StreamConnection</emphasis> - A connection that is
        both input and output.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>StreamConnectionNotifier</emphasis> - Can be used to
        wait for incoming stream connection requests.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>ContentConnection</emphasis> - A
        <code>javax.microedition.io.StreamConnection</code> that provides
        information about the type, encoding, and length of the
        information.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para xml:id="i1304228">Bundles using this approach must indicate to the
    Operator what kind of interfaces they expect to receive. The operator must
    then configure the bundle with a URI that contains the scheme and
    appropriate options that match the bundle's expectations. Well-written
    bundles are flexible enough to communicate with any of the types of
    <code>javax.microedition.io.Connection</code> interfaces they have
    specified. For example, a bundle should support <code>
    javax.microedition.io. StreamConnection</code> as well as <code>
    javax.microedition.io. DatagramConnection</code> objects in the
    appropriate direction ( input or output).</para>

    <para>The following code example shows a bundle that sends an alarm
    message with the help of the <code>javax.microedition.io.Connector</code>
    framework:</para>

    <programlisting>public class Alarm {
    String uri;
    public Alarm(String uri) { this.uri = uri; }
    private void send(byte[] msg) {
        while ( true ) try {
            Connection  connection = Connector.open( uri );
            DataOutputStream    dout = null;
        if ( connection instanceof OutputConnection ) {
                dout = ((OutputConnection)
                    connection).openDataOutputStream();
          dout.write( msg );
        }
        else if (connection instanceof DatagramConnection){
                DatagramConnection dgc = 
                    (DatagramConnection) connection;
          Datagram datagram = dgc.newDatagram( 
                    msg, msg.length );
          dgc.send( datagram );
        } else {
            error( "No configuration for alarm" );
            return;
        }
        connection.close();
      } catch( Exception e ) { ... }
   }
}</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Connector Service</title>

    <para>The <code>javax.microedition.io.Connector</code> framework matches
    the requirements for OSGi applications very well. The actual creation of
    connections, however, is handled through static methods in the
    <code>javax.microedition.io.Connector</code> class. This approach does not
    mesh well with the OSGi service registry and dynamic life-cycle
    management.</para>

    <para>This specification therefore introduces the Connector Service. The
    methods of the <code>ConnectorService</code> interface have the same
    signatures as the static methods of the
    <code>javax.microedition.io.Connector</code> class.</para>

    <para xml:id="i1304230">Each <code>javax.microedition.io.Connection</code>
    object returned by a Connector Service must implement interfaces from the
    <code>javax.microedition.io</code> package. Implementations must strictly
    follow the semantics that are associated with these interfaces.</para>

    <para>The Connector Service must provide all the schemes provided by the
    exporter of the <code>javax.microedition.io</code> package. The Connection
    Factory services must have priority over schemes implemented in the Java
    run-time environment. For example, if a Connection Factory provides the
    <code>http</code> scheme and a built-in implementation exists, then the
    Connector Service must use the Connection Factory service with the
    <code>http</code> scheme.</para>

    <para>Bundles that want to use the Connector Service should first obtain a
    <code>ConnectorService</code> service object. This object contains
    <code>open</code> methods that should be called to get a new
    <code>javax.microedition.io.Connection</code> object.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Providing New Schemes</title>

    <para xml:id="i1333973">The Connector Service must be able to be extended
    with the Connection Factory service. Bundles that can provide new schemes
    must register a <code>ConnectionFactory</code> service object.</para>

    <para>The Connector Service must listen for registrations of new
    <code>ConnectionFactory</code> service objects and make the supplied
    schemes available to bundles that create connections.</para>

    <para>Implementing a Connection Factory service requires implementing the
    following method:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.io.ConnectionFactory.createConnection-String-int-boolean-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Creates a new connection object from the
        given URI.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Connection Factory service must be registered with the
    <code>IO_SCHEME</code> property to indicate the provided scheme to the Connector
    Service. The value of this property must be a
    <code>String[]</code>.</para>

    <para>If multiple Connection Factory services register with the same
    scheme, the Connector Service should select the Connection Factory service
    with the highest value for the <code>service.ranking</code> service
    registration property, or if more than one Connection Factory service has
    the highest value, the Connection Factory service with the lowest
    <code>service.id</code> is selected.</para>

    <para>The following example shows how a Connection Factory service may be
    implemented. The example will return a
    <code>javax.microedition.io.InputConnection</code> object that returns the
    value of the URI after removing the scheme identifier.</para>

    <programlisting>public class ConnectionFactoryImpl 
    implements BundleActivator, ConnectionFactory {
        public void start( BundleContext context ) {
            Hashtable properties = new Hashtable();
            properties.put( IO_SCHEME, new String[]{"data"} );
            context.registerService(
                ConnectorService.class.getName(), 
                this, properties );
        }
        public void stop( BundleContext context ) {}

        public Connection createConnection( 
            String uri, int mode, boolean timeouts  ) {
            return new DataConnection(uri); 
        }
}

class DataConnection 
    implements javax.microedition.io.InputConnection {
    String uri;
    DataConnection( String uri ) {this.uri = uri;}
    public DataInputStream openDataInputStream() 
        throws IOException {
        return new DataInputStream( openInputStream() );
    }

    public InputStream openInputStream() throws IOException {
        byte [] buf = uri.getBytes();
        return new ByteArrayInputStream(buf,5,buf.length-5);
    }
    public void close() {}
}</programlisting>

    <section xml:id="i1304323">
      <title>Orphaned Connection Objects</title>

      <para>When a Connection Factory service is unregistered, it must close
      all <code>Connection</code> objects that are still open. Closing these
      <code>Connection</code> objects should make these objects unusable, and
      they should subsequently throw an <code>IOException</code> when
      used.</para>

      <para>Bundles should not unnecessarily hang onto objects they retrieved
      from services. Implementations of Connection Factory services should
      program defensively and ensure that resource allocation is minimized
      when a <code>Connection</code> object is closed.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Execution Environment</title>

    <para xml:id="i1304326">The <code>javax.microedition.io</code> package is
    available in J2ME configurations/profiles, but is not present in J2SE,
    J2EE, and the OSGi minimum execution requirements.</para>

    <para>Implementations of the Connector Service that are targeted for all
    environments should carry their own implementation of the
    <code>javax.microedition.io</code> package and export it.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para xml:id="i1318067">The OSGi Connector Service is a key service
    available in the Framework. A malicious bundle which provides this service
    can spoof any communication. Therefore, it is paramount that the
    <code>ServicePermission[ConnectorService, REGISTER]</code> is given only
    to a trusted bundle. <code>ServicePermission[ConnectorService,GET]</code>
    may be handed to bundles that are allowed to communicate to the external
    world.</para>

    <para><code>ServicePermission[ConnectionFactory, REGISTER]</code> should
    also be restricted to trusted bundles because they can implement specific
    protocols or access devices.
    <code>ServicePermission[ConnectionFactory,GET]</code> should be limited to
    trusted bundles that implement the Connector Service.</para>

    <para>Implementations of Connection Factory services must perform all I/O
    operations within a privileged region. For example, an implementation of
    the <code>sms:</code> scheme must have permission to access the mobile
    phone, and should not require the bundle that opened the connection to
    have this permission. Normally, the operations need to be implemented in a
    <code>doPrivileged</code> method or in a separate thread.</para>

    <para>If a specific Connection Factory service needs more detailed
    permissions than provided by the OSGi or Java 2, it may create a new
    specific Permission sub-class for its purpose.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.io.xml"/>

  <section xml:id="i1304653">
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1304655"><title>Java 2 Micro
      Edition</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javame/index.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed><title>J2ME Foundation
      Profile</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detailid=46"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
