<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="122"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="service.remoteserviceadmin"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Remote Service Admin Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The <xref linkend="intro.core.release" xrefstyle="template:%t"/>
    framework specifies a model where bundles can use distributed services.
    The basic model for OSGi remote services is that a bundle can register
    services that are <emphasis>exported</emphasis> to a communication
    <emphasis>Endpoint</emphasis> and use services that are
    <emphasis>imported</emphasis> from a communication Endpoint. However,
    chapter <xref linkend="service.remoteservices"/> does not explain
    <emphasis>what</emphasis> services are exported and/or imported; it leaves
    such decisions to the distribution provider. The distribution provider
    therefore performs multiple roles and cannot be leveraged by other bundles
    in scenarios that the distribution provider had not foreseen.</para>

    <para>The primary role of the distribution provider is purely mechanical;
    it creates Endpoints and registers service proxies and enables their
    communication. The second role is about the policies around the desired
    topology. The third role is discovery. To establish a specific topology it
    is necessary to find out about exported services in other
    frameworks.</para>

    <para>This specification therefore defines an API for the distribution
    provider and discovery of services in a network. A management agent can
    use this API to provide an actual distribution policy. This management
    agent, called the Topology Manager, can control the export and import of
    services delegating the intrinsic knowledge of the low level details of
    communication protocols, proxying of services, and discovering services in
    the network to services defined in this specification.</para>

    <para>This specification is an extension of the Remote Service chapter.
    Though some aspects are repeated in this specification, a full
    understanding of the Remote Services chapter is required for full
    understanding of this document.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Simple</emphasis> - Make it as simple as possible
          for a Topology Manager to implement distribution policies.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dynamic</emphasis> - Discover available Endpoints
          dynamically, for example through a discovery protocol like <xref
          linkend="i1788834"/> or <xref linkend="i1789952"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Inform</emphasis> - Provide a mechanism to inform
          other parties about created and removed Endpoints.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Configuration</emphasis> - Allow bundles to describe
          Endpoints as a bundle resource that are provided to the Distribution
          Provider.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Selective</emphasis> - Not all parties are
          interested in all services. Endpoint registries must be able to
          express the scope of services they are interested in.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Multiple</emphasis> - Allow the collaboration of
          multiple Topology Managers, Remote Service Admin services, and
          Discovery Providers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dynamic</emphasis> - Allow the dynamic discovery of
          Endpoints.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Federated</emphasis> - Enable a global view of all
          available services in a distributed environment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Remote Service Admin</emphasis> - An implementation
          of this specification provides the mechanisms to import and export
          services through a set of configuration types. The Remote Service
          Admin service is a passive Distribution Provider, not taking any
          action to export or import itself.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Topology Manager</emphasis> - The Topology Manager
          provides the policy for importing and exporting services through the
          Remote Service Admin service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Endpoint</emphasis> - An Endpoint is a
          communications access mechanism to a service in another framework, a
          (web) service, another process, or a queue or topic destination,
          etc., requiring some protocol for communications.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Endpoint Description</emphasis> - A properties based
          description of an Endpoint. Endpoint Descriptions can be exchanged
          between different frameworks to create connections to each other's
          services. Endpoint Descriptions can also be created to Endpoints not
          originating in an OSGi Framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Endpoint Description Provider</emphasis> - A party
          that can inform others about the existence of Endpoints.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Endpoint Event Listener</emphasis> – A listener
          service that receives events relating to Endpoints that match its
          scope. This Endpoint Event Listener is used symmetrically to
          implement a federated registry. The Topology Manager can use it to
          notify interested parties about created and removed Endpoints, as
          well as to receive notifications from other parties, potentially
          remote, about their available Endpoints.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Endpoint Listener</emphasis> – An older version of
          the Endpoint Event Listener defined by version <code>1.0</code> of
          this specification. The Endpoint Event Listener supersedes the
          Endpoint Listener, and should be used in preference where
          possible.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Remote Service Admin Listener</emphasis> - A
          listener service that is informed of all the primitive actions that
          the Remote Service Admin performs like importing and exporting as
          well as errors.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Endpoint Configuration Extender</emphasis> - A
          bundle that can detect configuration data describing an Endpoint
          Description in a bundle resource, using the extender pattern.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Discovery</emphasis> – An Endpoint Event Listener
          that detects the Endpoint Descriptions through some discovery
          protocol.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Cluster</emphasis> - A group of computing systems
          that closely work together, usually in a fast network.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="i1706087">
        <title>Remote Service Admin Entities</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.570in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="rsa-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>Topology Managers are responsible for the distribution policies of
      a OSGi framework. To implement a policy, a Topology Manager must be
      aware of the environment, for this reason, it can register:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Service listeners to detect services that can be exported
          according to the Remote Services chapter.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Listener and Find Hook services to detect bundles that have an
          interest in specific services that potentially could be
          imported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A Remote Service Admin Listener service to detect the activity
          of other Topology Managers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Endpoint Event Listener and Endpoint Listener services to
          detect Endpoints that are made available through discovery
          protocols, configuration data, or other means.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Using this information, the manager implements a topology using
      the Remote Service Admin service. A Topology Manager that wants to
      export a service can create an <emphasis>Export Registration</emphasis>
      by providing one or more Remote Service Admin services a Service
      Reference plus a Map with the required properties. A Remote Service
      Admin service then creates a number of Endpoints based on the available
      configuration types and returns a collection of
      <code>ExportRegistration</code> objects. A collection is returned
      because a single service can be exported to multiple Endpoints depending
      on the available configuration type properties.</para>

      <para>Each Export Registration is specific for the caller and represents
      an existing or newly created Endpoint. The Export Registration
      associates the exported Service Reference with an <emphasis>Endpoint
      Description</emphasis>. If there are problems with the export operation,
      the Remote Service Admin service reports these on the Export
      Registration objects. That is, not all the returned Export Registrations
      have to be valid.</para>

      <para>An Endpoint Description is a property based description of an
      Endpoint. Some of these properties are defined in this specification,
      other properties are defined by configuration types. These configuration
      types must follow the same rules as the configuration types defined in
      the Remote Services chapter. Remote Service Admin services that support
      the configuration types in the Endpoint Description can import a service
      from that Endpoint solely based on that Endpoint Description.</para>

      <para>In similar vein, the Topology Manager can import a service from a
      remote system by creating an Import Registration out of an Endpoint
      Description. The Remote Service Admin service then registers a service
      that is a proxy for the remote Endpoint and returns an
      <code>ImportRegistration</code> object. If there are problems with the
      import, the Remote Service Admin service that cannot be detected early,
      then the Remote Service Admin service reports these on the returned
      <code>ImportRegistration</code> object.</para>

      <para>For introspection, the Remote Service Admin can list its current
      set of Import and Export References so that a Topology Manager can get
      the current state. The Remote Service Admin service also informs all
      Topology Managers and observers of the creation, deletion, and errors of
      Import and Export Registrations through the Remote Service Admin
      Listener service. Interested parties like the Topology Manager can
      register such a service and will be called back with the initial state
      as well as any subsequent changes.</para>

      <para>An important aspect of the Topology Manager is the distributed
      nature of the scenarios it plays an orchestrating role in. A Topology
      Manager needs to be aware of Endpoints in the network, not just the ones
      provided by Remote Service Admin services in its local framework. The
      Endpoint Event Listener service is specified for this purpose. This
      service is provided for both directions, symmetrically. That is, it is
      used by the Topology Manager to inform any observers about the existence
      of Endpoints that are locally available, as well as for parties that
      represent a discovery mechanism. For example Endpoints available on
      other systems, Endpoint Descriptions embedded in resources in bundles,
      or Endpoint Descriptions that are available in some other form.</para>

      <para>Endpoint Event Listener services are not always interested in the
      complete set of available Endpoints because this set can potentially be
      very large. For example, if a remote registry like <xref
      linkend="i1789020"/> is used then the number of Endpoints can run into
      the thousands or more. An Endpoint Event Listener service can therefore
      scope the set of Endpoints with an OSGi LDAP style filter. Parties that
      can provide information about Endpoints must only notify Endpoint Event
      Listener services when the Endpoint Description falls within the scope
      of the Endpoint Listener service. Parties that use some discovery
      mechanism can use the scope to trigger directed searches across the
      network.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Endpoint Listener Services</title>

        <para>The <code>1.0</code> version of this specification defined an
        Endpoint Listener service, which has an identical purpose and similar
        behaviors to an Endpoint Event Listener service. Unfortunately the
        design of the Endpoint Listener limited its extensibility, meaning
        that it had to be replaced in version <code>1.1</code> of this
        specification.</para>

        <para>In order to maintain backward compatible interoperability with
        Remote Service Admin <code>1.0</code> actors, Remote Service Admin
        <code>1.1</code> actors must continue to register Endpoint Listener
        services as well as Endpoint Event Listener services. They must also
        continue to call Endpoint Listener services as well as
        EndpointEventListener services.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Actors</title>

    <para>The OSGi Remote Services specification is about the distribution of
    services. This specification does not outline the details of how the
    distribution provider knows the desired topology, this policy aspect is
    left up to implementations. In many situations, this is a desirable
    architecture because it provides freedom of implementation to the
    distribution provider. However, such an architecture does not enable a
    separation of the mechanisms and <emphasis>policy</emphasis>. Therefore,
    this Remote Service Admin specification provides an architecture that
    enables a separate bundle from the distribution provider to define the
    topology. It splits the responsibility of the Remote Service specification
    in a number of <emphasis>roles</emphasis>. These roles can all have
    different implementations but they can collaborate through the services
    defined in this specification. These roles are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Topology Manager</emphasis>s - Topology Managers are
        the (anonymous) players that implement the policies for distributing
        services; they are closely aligned with the concept of an OSGi
        <emphasis>management agent</emphasis>. It is expected that Topology
        Managers will be developed for scenarios like import/export all
        applicable services, configuration based imports- and exports, and
        scenarios like fail-over, load-balancing, as well as standards like
        domain managers for the <xref linkend="i1789031"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Remote Service Admin</emphasis> - The Remote Service
        Admin service provides the basic mechanism to import and export
        services. This service is policy free; it will not distribute services
        without explicitly being told so. A OSGi framework can host multiple
        Remote Service Admin services that, for example, support different
        configuration types.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Discovery</emphasis> - To implement a distribution
        policy, a Topology Manager must be aware of what Endpoints are
        available. This specification provides an abstraction of a
        <emphasis>federated Endpoint registry</emphasis>. This registry can be
        used to both publish as well as consume Endpoints from many different
        sources. The federated registry is defined for local services but is
        intended to be used with standard and proprietary service discovery
        protocols. The federated registry is implemented with the Endpoint
        Event Listener service.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>These roles are depicted in <xref linkend="i1817848"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1817848">
      <title>Roles</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.194in"
                     contentwidth="6.240in" fileref="roles.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Topology Managers</title>

    <para>Distributed processing has become mainstream because of the massive
    scale required for Internet applications. Only with distributed
    architectures is it possible to scale systems to <emphasis>Internet
    size</emphasis> with hundreds of millions of users. To allow a system to
    scale, servers are grouped in clusters where they can work in unison or
    geographically dispersed in even larger configurations. The distribution
    of the work-load is crucial for the amount of scalability provided by an
    architecture and often has domain specific dispatching techniques. For
    example, the hash of a user id can be used to select the correct profile
    database server. In this fast moving world it is very unlikely that a
    single architecture or distribution policy would be sufficient to satisfy
    many users. It is therefore that this specification separates the
    <emphasis>how</emphasis> from the <emphasis>what</emphasis>. The complex
    mechanics of importing and exporting services are managed by a Remote
    Service Admin service (the how) while the different policies are
    implemented by Topology Managers (the what). This separation of concerns
    enables the development of Topology Managers that can run on many
    different systems, providing high user functionality. For example, a
    Topology Manager could implement a fail-over policy where some strategic
    services are redirected when their connections fail. Other Topology
    Managers could use a discovery protocol like SLP to find out about other
    systems in a cluster and automatically configure the cluster.</para>

    <para>The key value of this architecture is demonstrated by the example of
    an <emphasis>SCA domain controller</emphasis>. An SCA domain controller
    receives a description of a domain (a set of systems and modules) and must
    ensure that the proper connections are made between the participating SCA
    modules. By splitting the roles, an SCA domain manager can be developed
    that can run on any compatible Remote Service Admin service
    implementation.</para>

    <section xml:id="i1812921">
      <title>Multiple Topology Managers</title>

      <para>There is no restriction on the number of Topology Managers, nor is
      there a restriction on the number of Remote Service Admin service
      implementations. It is up to the deployer of the OSGi framework to
      select the appropriate set of these service implementations. It is the
      responsibility of the Topology Managers to listen to the Remote Service
      Admin Listener and track Endpoints created and deleted by other Topology
      Managers and act appropriately.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="service.remoteserviceadmin-example.policies">
      <title>Example Use Cases</title>

      <section>
        <title>Promiscuous Policy</title>

        <para>A <emphasis>cluster</emphasis> is a set of machines that are
        connected in a network. The simplest policy for a Topology Manager is
        to share exported services in such a cluster. Such a policy is very
        easy to implement with the Remote Services Admin service. In the most
        basic form, this Topology Manager would use some multicast protocol to
        communicate with its peers. These peers would exchange
        <code>EndpointDescription</code> objects of exported services. Each
        Topology Manager would then import any exported service.</para>

        <para>This scenario can be improved by separating the promiscuous
        policy from the discovery. Instead of embedding the multicast
        protocol, a Topology manager could use the Endpoint Event Listener
        service. This service allows the discovery of remote services. At the
        same time, the Topology Manager could tell all other Endpoint Event
        Listener services about the services it has created, allowing them to
        be used by others in the network.</para>

        <para>Splitting the Topology Manager and discovery in two bundles
        allows different implementations of the discovery bundle, for example,
        to use different protocols. See <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.namespace.TopologyNamespace.PROMISCUOUS_POLICY"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Fail Over</title>

        <para>A more elaborate scheme is a <emphasis>fail-over
        policy</emphasis>. In such a policy a service can be replaced by a
        service from another machine. There are many ways to implement such a
        policy, an simple example strategy is provided here for
        illustration.</para>

        <para>A Fail-Over Topology Manager is given a list of stateless
        services that require fail-over, for example through the <xref
        linkend="service.cm"/>. The Fail-Over Manager tracks the systems in
        the its cluster that provide such services. This tracking can use an
        embedded protocol or it can be based on the Endpoint Event Listener
        service model.</para>

        <para>In the Fail-Over policy, the fail-over manager only imports a
        single service and then tracks the error status of the imported
        service through the Remote Service Admin Listener service. If it
        detects the service is becoming unavailable, it closes the
        corresponding Import Registration and imports a service from an
        alternative system instead. In <xref linkend="i1819899"/>, there are 4
        systems in a cluster. The topology/fail-over manager ensures that
        there is always one of the services in system <code>A</code>, <code>
        B</code>, or <code>C</code> available in <code>D</code>.</para>

        <figure xml:id="i1819899">
          <title>Fail Over Scenario in a cluster</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.852in"
                         contentwidth="4.901in" fileref="fail-over.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>There are many possible variations on this scenario. The
        managers could exchange load information, allowing the service switch
        to be influenced by the load of the target systems. The important
        aspect is that the Topology Manager can ignore the complex details of
        discovery protocols, communication protocols, and service proxying and
        instead focus on the topology. See <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.namespace.TopologyNamespace.FAIL_OVER_POLICY"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.remoteserviceadmin.endpointdescription">
    <title>Endpoint Description</title>

    <para>An <emphasis>Endpoint</emphasis> is a point of rendezvous of
    distribution providers. It is created by an exporting distribution
    provider or some other party, and is used by importing distribution
    providers to create a connection. An <emphasis>Endpoint
    Description</emphasis> describes an Endpoint in such a way that an
    importing Remote Service Admin service can create this connection if it
    recognizes the <emphasis>configuration type</emphasis> that is used for
    that Endpoint. The configuration type consists of a name and a set of
    properties associated with that name.</para>

    <para>The core concept of the Endpoint Description is a Map of properties.
    The structure of this map is the same as service properties, and the
    defined properties are closely aligned with the properties of an imported
    service. An <code>EndpointDescription</code> object must only consist of
    the data types that are supported for service properties. This makes the
    property map serializable with many different mechanisms. The
    <code>EndpointDescription</code> class provides a convenient way to access
    the properties in a type safe way.</para>

    <para>An Endpoint Description has case insensitive keys, just like the
    Service Reference's properties.</para>

    <para>The properties map must contain all the prescribed service
    properties of the exported service after intents have been processed, as
    if the service was registered as an imported service. That is, the map
    must not contain any properties that start with
    <code>service.exported.*</code> but it must contain the
    <code>service.imported</code>.* variation of these properties. The
    Endpoint Description must reflect the imported service properties because
    this simplifies the use of filters from the service hooks. Filters applied
    to the Endpoint Description can then be the same filters as applied by a
    bundle to select an imported service from the service registry.</para>

    <para>The properties that can be used in an Endpoint Description are
    listed in <xref
    linkend="service.remoteserviceadmin-endpoint.properties"/>. The
    <code>RemoteConstants</code> class contains the constants for all of these
    property names.</para>

    <table xml:id="service.remoteserviceadmin-endpoint.properties">
      <title>Endpoint Properties</title>

      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2.5*"/>

        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

        <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="4.5*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Endpoint Property Name</entry>

            <entry>Type</entry>

            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><code>service.exported.*</code></entry>

            <entry><para/></entry>

            <entry><para>Must not be set</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>service.imported</code></entry>

            <entry><code>*</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Must always be set to some value. See <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteConstants.SERVICE_IMPORTED"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>objectClass</code></entry>

            <entry><code>String[]</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Must be set to the value of
            <code>service.exported.interfaces</code>, of the exported service
            after expanding any wildcards. Though this property will be
            overridden by the framework for the corresponding service
            registration, it must be set in the Endpoint Description to
            simplify the filter matching. These interface names are available
            with the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getInterfaces--"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>service.intents</code></entry>

            <entry><code>String+</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Intents implemented by the exporting distribution
            provider and, if applicable, the exported service itself. Any
            qualified intents must have their expanded form present. These
            expanded intents are available with the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getIntents--"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. See <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteConstants.SERVICE_INTENTS"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>endpoint.service.id</code></entry>

            <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The service id of the exported service. Can be absent
            or 0 if the corresponding Endpoint is not for an OSGi service. The
            remote service id is available as <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getServiceId--"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. See also <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteConstants.ENDPOINT_SERVICE_ID"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>endpoint.framework.uuid</code></entry>

            <entry><code>String</code></entry>

            <entry><para>A universally unique id identifying the instance of
            the exporting framework. Can be absent if the corresponding
            Endpoint is not for an OSGi service. See <xref
            linkend="i1887500"/>. The remote framework UUID is available with
            the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getFrameworkUUID--"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. See also <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteConstants.ENDPOINT_FRAMEWORK_UUID"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>endpoint.id</code></entry>

            <entry><code>String</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The Id for this Endpoint, can never be
            <code>null</code>. This information is available with the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getId--"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. See <xref linkend="i1887496"/> and also
            <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteConstants.ENDPOINT_ID"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><code>endpoint.package.</code></para><para><code>&#160;version.&lt;package-name&gt;</code></para></entry>

            <entry><code>String</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The Java package version for the embedded
            &lt;package&gt;. For example, the property
            <code>endpoint.package.version.com.acme=1.3</code> describes the
            version for the <code>com.acme</code> package. The version for a
            package can be obtained with the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getPackageVersion-String-"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para> <para>The version does not have to
            be set, if not set, the value must be assumed to be
            0.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>service.imported.configs</code></entry>

            <entry><code>String+</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The configuration types that can be used to implement
            the corresponding Endpoint. This property maps to the
            corresponding property in the Remote Services chapter. This
            property can be obtained with the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getConfigurationTypes--"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para> <para>The Export
            Registration has all the possible configuration types, where the
            Import Registration reports the configuration type actually used.
            <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteConstants.SERVICE_IMPORTED_CONFIGS"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&lt;config&gt;.*</code></entry>

            <entry><code>*</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Where <code>&lt;config&gt;</code> is one of the
            configuration type names listed in
            <code>service.imported.configs</code>. The content of these
            properties must be valid for creating a connection to the Endpoint
            in another framework. That is, any locally readable URLs from
            bundles must be converted in such a form that they can be read by
            the importing framework. How this is done is configuration type
            specific.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>*</code></entry>

            <entry><code>*</code></entry>

            <entry><para>All remaining public service properties must be
            present (that is, not starting with full stop (<code>'.'
            \u002E</code>)). If the values can not be marshaled by the
            Distribution Provider then they must be ignored.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The <code>EndpointDescription</code> class has a number of
    constructors that make it convenient to instantiate it for different
    purposes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.EndpointDescription-Map-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Instantiate the Endpoint Description from a
        <code>Map</code> object.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.EndpointDescription-ServiceReference-Map-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Instantiate an Endpoint Description based on
        a Service Reference and a Map. The base properties of this Endpoint
        Description are the Service Reference properties but the properties in
        the given Map must override any of their case variants in the Service
        Reference. This allows the construction of an Endpoint Description
        from an exportable service while still allowing overrides of specific
        properties by the Topology Manager.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Endpoint Description must use the allowed properties as given in
    <xref linkend="service.remoteserviceadmin-endpoint.properties"
    xrefstyle="template:Table %n on page %p"/>. The Endpoint Description must
    automatically skip any <code>service.exported.*</code> properties.</para>

    <para>The Endpoint Description provides the following methods to access
    the properties in a more convenient way:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getInterfaces--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Answers a list of Java interface names.
        These are the interfaces under which the services must be registered.
        These interface names can also be found at the
        <code>objectClass</code> property. A service can only be imported when
        there is at least one Java interface name available.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getConfigurationTypes--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Answer the configuration types that are used
        for exporting this Endpoint. The configuration types are associated
        with a number of properties.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getId--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns an Id uniquely identifying an
        Endpoint. The syntax of this Id should be defined in the specification
        for the associated configuration type. Two Endpoint Descriptions with
        the same Id describe the same Endpoint.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getFrameworkUUID--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get a Universally Unique Identifier (UUID)
        for the framework instance that has created the Endpoint, <xref
        linkend="i1887500"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getServiceId--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get the service id for the framework
        instance that has created the Endpoint. If there is no service on the
        remote side the value must be 0.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getPackageVersion-String-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get the version for the given
        package.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getIntents--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get the list of specified intents.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointDescription.getProperties--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get all the properties.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Two Endpoint Descriptions are deemed equal when their Endpoint Id is
    equal. The Endpoint Id is a mandatory property of an Endpoint Description,
    it is further described at <xref linkend="i1887496"/>. The hash code is
    therefore also based on the Endpoint Id.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Validity</title>

      <para>A valid Endpoint Description must at least satisfy the following
      assertions:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>It must have a non-<code>null</code> Id that uniquely
          identifies the Endpoint</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It must at least have one Java interface name</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It must at least have one configuration type set</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any version for the packages must have a valid version
          syntax.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Mutability</title>

      <para>An <code>EndpointDescription</code> object is immutable and with
      all final fields. It can be freely used between different
      threads.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1887496">
      <title>Endpoint Id</title>

      <para>An Endpoint Id is an opaque unique identifier for an Endpoint.
      This uniqueness must at least hold for the entire network in which the
      Endpoint is used. There is no syntax defined for this string except that
      white space at the beginning and ending must be ignored. The actual
      syntax for this Endpoint Id must be defined by the actual configuration
      type.</para>

      <para>Two Endpoint Descriptions are deemed identical when their Endpoint
      Id is equal. The Endpoint Ids must be compared as string compares with
      leading and trailing spaces removed. The Endpoint Description class must
      use the <code>String</code> class' hash Code from the Endpoint Id as its
      own <code>hashCode</code>.</para>

      <para>The simplest way to ensure that a growth in the number of
      EndpointDescriptions and/or the size of the connected group does not
      violate the required uniqueness of Endpoint Ids is for implementations
      to make their Endpoint Ids globally unique. This protects against
      clashes regardless of changes to the connected group.</para>

      <para>Whilst globally unique identifiers (GUIDs) are a simple solution
      to the Endpoint Id uniqueness problem, they are not easy to implement in
      all environments. In some systems they can be prohibitively expensive to
      create, or of insufficient entropy to be genuinely unique. Some
      distribution providers may therefore choose not to use random
      GUIDs.</para>

      <para>In the case where no globally unique value is used the following
      actions are recommended (although not required).</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Distribution Providers protect against intra-framework clashes
          using some known value unique to the service, for example the
          service id.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Distribution Providers protect against inter-provider
          collisions within a single framework by using some unique value,
          such as the distribution provider's bundle id. The distribution
          provider bundle's symbolic name is insufficient, as there may be
          multiple versions of the same distribution provider installed within
          a single framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Distribution Providers protect against inter-framework
          collisions using some value unique to the framework, such as the
          framework UUID.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1887500">
      <title>Framework UUID</title>

      <para>Each framework registers its services with a service id that is
      only unique for that specific framework. The OSGi framework is not a
      singleton, making it possible that a single VM process holds multiple
      OSGi frameworks. Therefore, to identify an OSGi service uniquely it is
      necessary to identify the framework that has registered it. This
      identifier is a <emphasis>Universally Unique IDentifier</emphasis>
      (UUID) that is set for each framework. This UUID is contained in the
      following framework property:</para>

      <programlisting>org.osgi.framework.uuid</programlisting>

      <para>If an Endpoint Description has no associated OSGi service then the
      UUID of that Endpoint Description must not be set and its service id
      must be 0.</para>

      <para>A local Endpoint Description will have its framework UUID set to
      the local framework. This makes it straightforward to filter for
      Endpoint Descriptions that are describing local Endpoints or that
      describe remote Endpoints. For example, a manager can take the filter
      from a listener and ensure that it is only getting remote Endpoint
      Descriptions:</para>

      <programlisting>(&amp;
  (!
    (service.remote.framework.uuid
       =72dc5fd9-5f8f-4f8f-9821-9ebb433a5b72)
  )
  (objectClass=org.osgi.service.log.LogService)
)</programlisting>

      <para>Where <code>72dc5fd9-5f8f-4f8f-9821-9ebb433a5b72</code> is the
      UUID of the local framework. A discovery bundle can register the
      following filter in its scope to receive all locally generated
      Endpoints:</para>

      <programlisting>(service.remote.framework.uuid
       =72dc5fd9-5f8f-4f8f-9821-9ebb433a5b72)</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1887526">
      <title>Resource Containment</title>

      <para>Configuration types can use URLs to point to local resources
      describing in detail the Endpoint parameters for specific protocols.
      However, the purpose of an Endpoint Description is to describe an
      Endpoint to a remote system. This implies that there is some marshaling
      process that will transfer the Endpoint Description to another process.
      This other process is unlikely to be able to access resource URLs. Local
      bundle resource URLs are only usable in the framework that originates
      them but even HTTP based URLs can easily run into problems due to
      firewalls or lack of routing.</para>

      <para>Therefore, the properties for a configuration type should be
      stored in such a way that the receiving process can access them. One way
      to achieve this is to contain the configuration properties completely in
      the Endpoint Description and ensure they only use the basic data types
      that the remote services chapter in the core requires every Distribution
      Provider to support.</para>

      <para>The Endpoint Description XML format provides an <code>xml</code>
      element that is specifically added to make it easy to embed XML based
      configuration documents. The XML Schema is defined in <xref
      linkend="i1889341"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.remoteserviceadmin-rsa.service">
    <title>Remote Service Admin</title>

    <para>The Remote Service Admin service abstracts the core functionality of
    a distribution provider: exporting a service to an Endpoint and importing
    services from an Endpoint. However, in contrast with the distribution
    provider of the Remote Services specification, the Remote Service Admin
    service must be told explicitly what services to import and export.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Exporting</title>

      <para>An exportable service can be exported with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin.exportService-ServiceReference-Map-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This method creates a number of
      Endpoints by inspecting the merged properties from the Service Reference
      and the given Map. Any property in the Map overrides the Service
      Reference properties, regardless of case. That is, if the map contains a
      key then it will override any case variant of this key in the Service
      Reference. However, if the Map contains the <code>objectClass</code> or
      <code>service.id</code> property key in any case variant, then these
      properties must not override the Service Reference's value.</para>

      <para>The Remote Service Admin service must interpret the merged
      properties according to the Remote Services chapter. This means that it
      must look at the following properties (as defined in chapter <xref
      linkend="service.remoteservices"/> ):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.exported.configs</code> - <code>(String+
          )</code> A list of configuration types that should be used to export
          this service. Each configuration type represents the configuration
          parameters for an Endpoint. A Remote Service Admin service should
          create an Endpoint for each configuration type that it supports and
          ignore the types it does not recognize. If this property is not set,
          then the Remote Service Admin implementation must choose a
          convenient configuration type that then must be reported on the
          Endpoint Description with the <code>service.imported.configs</code>
          associated with the returned Export Registration.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.exported.intents</code> - (
          <code>String+)</code> A list of intents that the Remote Service
          Admin service must implement to distribute the given service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.exported.intents.extra</code> -
          <code>(String+)</code> This property is merged with the
          <code>service.exported.intents</code> property.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.exported.interfaces</code> -
          <code>(String+)</code> This property must be set; it marks this
          service for export and defines the interfaces. The list members must
          all be contained in the types listed in the <code>objectClass</code>
          service property from the Service Reference. The single value of an
          asterisk (<code>'*' \u002A</code>) indicates all interfaces in the
          registration's <code>objectClass</code> property and ignore the
          classes. Being able to set this property outside the Service
          Reference implies that the Topology Manager can export any
          registered service, also services not specifically marked to be
          exported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.intents</code> - <code>(String+)</code> A list
          of intents that this service has implemented.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A Topology Manager cannot remove properties, <code>null</code> is
      invalid as a property value.</para>

      <para>The Remote Service Admin returns a collection of
      <code>ExportRegistration</code> objects. This collection must contain an
      entry for each configuration type the Remote Service Admin has
      recognized. Unrecognized configuration types must be ignored. Recognized
      configuration types which require intents that are not supported by the
      Remote Service Admin must also be ignored. However, it is possible that
      this list contains <emphasis>invalid registrations</emphasis>, see <xref
      linkend="i1791501"/>.</para>

      <para>If a Service was already exported then the Remote Service Admin
      must still return a new <code>ExportRegistration</code> object that is
      linked with the earlier registrations. That is, an Endpoint can be
      shared between multiple Export Registrations. The Remote Service Admin
      service must ensure that the corresponding Endpoint remains available as
      long as there is at least one open Export Registration for that
      Endpoint.</para>

      <para>For each successful creation of an export registration, the Remote
      Service Admin service must publish an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.EXPORT_REGISTRATION"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event, see <xref linkend="i1736220"/>. This
      event must be emitted, even if the Endpoint already existed and is thus
      shared with another Export Registration. If the creation of an Endpoint
      runs into an error, an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.EXPORT_ERROR"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event must be emitted.</para>

      <para>Each valid Export Registration corresponds to an Endpoint for the
      given service. This Endpoint must remain active until all of the Export
      Registrations are closed that share this Endpoint.</para>

      <para>The Endpoint can now be published so that other processes or
      systems can import this Endpoint. To aid with this import, the Export
      Registration has a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ExportRegistration.getExportReference--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method that returns an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ExportReference"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object. This reference provides the following
      information:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ExportReference.getExportedEndpoint--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This is the associated Endpoint
          Description. This Endpoint Description is a properties based
          description of an Endpoint. The property keys and their semantics
          are outlined in <xref
          linkend="service.remoteserviceadmin.endpointdescription"/>. It can
          be used to inform other systems of the availability of an
          Endpoint.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ExportReference.getExportedService--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Service Reference to the exported
          service.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Both methods must return <code>null</code> when the associated
      Export Registration is closed.</para>

      <para>A Distribution Provider that recognizes the configuration type in
      an Endpoint can create a connection to an Endpoint on other systems as
      long as firewalls and networks permit. The Endpoint Description can
      therefore be communicated to other systems to announce the availability
      of an Endpoint. The Topology Manager can optionally announce the
      availability of an Endpoint to the Endpoint Event Listener services, see
      <xref linkend="i1751493"/>. The decision to announce the availability of
      an Endpoint is one of the policies that is provided by a specific
      Topology Manager.</para>

      <para>The Export Registrations remain open until:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Explicitly closed by the Topology Manager, or</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Remote Service Admin service is no longer used by the
          Topology Manager that created the Export Registration.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the Remote Service Admin service can no longer maintain the
      corresponding Endpoint due to failures than these should be reported
      through the events. However, the registrations should remain open until
      explicitly closed by the Topology Manager.</para>

      <para>See <xref linkend="i1736585"/> for more information.</para>

      <para>The Export Registrations are not permanent; persistence is in the
      realm of the Topology Manager.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Importing</title>

      <para>To import a service, a Topology Manager must have an Endpoint
      Description that describes the Endpoint the imported service should
      connect to. With this Endpoint Description, a Remote Service Admin
      service can then import the corresponding Endpoint. A Topology Manager
      can obtain these Endpoint Descriptions through internal configuration;
      it can use the discovery model enabled by the Endpoint Event Listener
      service, see <xref linkend="i1751493"/>, or some alternate means.</para>

      <para>A service can be imported with the Remote Service Admin <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin.importService-EndpointDescription-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This method takes an Endpoint
      Description and picks one of the embedded configuration types to
      establish a connection with the corresponding Endpoint to create a local
      service proxy. This proxy can then be mapped to either a remote OSGi
      service or an alternative, for example a web service. In certain cases
      the service proxy can be lazy, only verifying the reachability of the
      Endpoint when it is actually invoked for the first time. This implies
      that a service proxy can block when invoked until the proper
      communication setup has taken place.</para>

      <para>If the Remote Service Admin service does not recognize any of the
      configuration types then it must return <code>null</code>. If there are
      multiple configuration types recognized then the Remote Service Admin is
      free to select any one of the recognized types.</para>

      <para>The Remote Service Admin service must ensure that service
      properties are according to the Remote Services chapter for an imported
      service. This means that it must register the following
      properties:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.imported</code> - <code>(*)</code> Must be set
          to any value.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.imported.configs</code> - <code>(String+)</code>
          The configuration information used to import this service. Any
          associated properties for this configuration types must be properly
          mapped to the importing system. For example, a URL in these
          properties must point to a valid resource when used in the importing
          framework, see <xref linkend="i1887526"/>. Multiple configuration
          types can be listed if they are synonyms for exactly the same
          Endpoint that is used to export this service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.intents</code> - <code>(String+)</code> The
          Remote Service Admin must set this property to convey the combined
          intents of:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The exporting service, and</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The intents that the exporting distribution provider adds,
              and</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The intents that the importing distribution provider
              adds.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any additional properties listed in the Endpoint Description
          that should not be excluded. See <xref
          linkend="service.remoteserviceadmin.endpointdescription"/> for more
          details about the properties in the Endpoint Description.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A Remote Service Admin service must strictly follow the rules for
      importing a service as outlined in the Remote Services chapter.</para>

      <para>The Remote Service Admin must return an
      <code>ImportRegistration</code> object or <code>null</code>. Even if an
      Import Registration is returned, it can still be an <emphasis>invalid
      registration</emphasis>, see <xref linkend="i1791501"/> if the setup of
      the connection failed asynchronously. The Import Registration must
      always be a new object. Each valid Import Registration corresponds to a
      proxy service, potentially shared, that was created for the given
      Endpoint. The issues around proxying are described in <xref
      linkend="i1742961"/>.</para>

      <para>For each successful creation of an import registration, the Remote
      Service Admin service must publish an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.IMPORT_REGISTRATION"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event, if there is an error it must publish an
      <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.IMPORT_ERROR"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, see <xref linkend="i1736220"/>.</para>

      <para>For more information see <xref linkend="i1736585"/>.</para>

      <para>The Import Registration provides access to an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ImportReference"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ImportRegistration.getImportReference--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This object has the following methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ImportReference.getImportedEndpoint--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Provides the Endpoint Description for this
          imported service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ImportReference.getImportedService--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Provides the Service Reference for the
          service proxy.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Import Registration will remain open as long as:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The corresponding remote Endpoint remains available,
          and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Remote Service Admin service is still in use by the
          Topology Manager that created the Import Registration.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>That is, the Import Registrations are not permanent, any
      persistence is in the realm of the Topology Manager. See <xref
      linkend="i1736585"/> for more details.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Updates</title>

      <para>Services Registrations are dynamic and service properties may
      change during the lifetime of a service. Remote services must mirror
      these dynamics without making it appear as though the service has become
      unavailable. This requires that the exporting distribution provider and
      the importing distribution provider support the changing of service
      properties.</para>

      <para>There are two types of service properties:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Properties that are intended to be consumed by the
          distribution provider, such as: the exported interfaces and
          configuration types, exported intents and configuration type
          specific properties. These properties are typically prefixed with
          <code>'service.'</code> or <code>'endpoint.'</code> see <xref
          linkend="service.remoteserviceadmin-endpoint.properties"
          xrefstyle="template:Table %n on page %p"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Service properties not intended for the distribution provider.
          These are typically used to communicate information to the consumer
          of the service and are often specific to the domain of the
          service.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following methods to support the updating of service
      properties on Export Registrations and the propagation of these updates
      to the remote proxies via Import Registrations.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>ExportRegistration.<xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ExportRegistration.update-Map-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Allows the Topology Manager to update an
          existing export registration it created after receiving a
          notification of changed properties on the remoted service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ImportRegistration.<xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ImportRegistration.update-EndpointDescription-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Allows the Topology Manager to update the
          import registration representing a remote service after the remote
          service properties have been updated. Typically the topology manager
          is notified of such change via the Discovery mechanism.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The distribution provider must support the updates of service
      properties <emphasis>not</emphasis> intended for the distribution
      provider, where supported property values are as defined in the
      <emphasis>Filter Syntax</emphasis> of <xref linkend="intro.core.release"
      xrefstyle="template:%t"/>. Distribution providers may support updates to
      a wider set of properties or data types, but these may fail with other
      implementations.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reflection</title>

      <para>The Remote Service Admin service provides the following methods to
      get the list of the current exported and imported services:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin.getExportedServices--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - List the Export References for services
          that are exported by this Remote Service Admin service as directed
          by any of the Topology Managers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin.getImportedEndpoints--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - List the Import References for services
          that have been imported by this Remote Service Admin service as
          directed by any of the Topology Managers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1736585">
      <title>Registration Life Cycle</title>

      <para>All registrations obtained through a Remote Service Admin service
      are life cycle bound to the Topology Manager that created it. That is,
      if a Topology Manager ungets its Remote Service Admin service, all
      registrations obtained through this service must automatically be
      closed. This model ensures that all registrations are properly closed if
      either the Remote Service Admin or the Topology Manager stops because in
      both cases the framework performs the unget automatically. Such behavior
      can be achieved by implementing the Remote Service Admin service as a
      Service Factory.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1791501">
      <title>Invalid Registrations</title>

      <para>The Remote Service Admin service is explicitly allowed to return
      <emphasis>invalid</emphasis> Import and Export Registrations. First, in
      a communications stack it can take time to discover that there are
      issues, allowing the registration to return before it has completed can
      potentially save time. Second, it allows the Topology Manager to
      discover problems with the configuration information. Without the
      invalid Export Registrations, the Topology Manager would have to scan
      the log or associate the Remote Service Admin Events with a specific
      import/export method call, something that can be difficult to do.</para>

      <para>If the registration is invalid, the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ExportRegistration.getException--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method must return a <code>Throwable</code>
      object. If the registration has initialized correctly, this method will
      return <code>null</code>. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ExportRegistration.getExportReference--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.ImportRegistration.getImportReference--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods must throw an Illegal State Exception
      when the registration is invalid. A Remote Service Admin service is
      allowed to block for a reasonable amount of time when any of these
      methods is called, including the <code>getException</code> method, to
      finish initialization.</para>

      <para>An invalid registration can be considered as never having been
      opened, it is therefore not necessary to close it; however, closing an
      invalid or closed registration must be a dummy operation and never throw
      an Exception. However, a failed registration must generate a
      corresponding error event.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1742961">
      <title>Proxying</title>

      <para>It is the responsibility of the Remote Service Admin service to
      properly proxy an imported service. This specification does not mandate
      the technique used to proxy an Endpoint as a service in the OSGi
      framework. The OSGi Remote Services specification allows a distribution
      provider to limit what it can proxy.</para>

      <para>One of the primary aspects of a proxy is to ensure class space
      consistency between the exporting bundle and importing bundles. This can
      require the generation of a proxy-per-bundle to match the proper class
      spaces. It is the responsibility of the Remote Service Admin to ensure
      that no Class Cast Exceptions occur.</para>

      <para>A common technique to achieve maximum class space compatibility is
      to use a Service Factory. A Service Factory provides the calling bundle
      when it first gets the service, making it straightforward to verify the
      package version of the interface that the calling bundle uses. Knowing
      the bundle that requests the service allows the creation of specialized
      proxies for each bundle. The interface class(es) for the proxy can then
      be loaded directly from the bundle, ensuring class compatibility.
      Interfaces should be loadable by the bundle otherwise that bundle can
      not use the interface in its code. If an interface cannot be loaded then
      it can be skipped. A dedicated class loader can then be created that has
      visibility to all these interfaces and is used to define the proxy
      class. This design ensures proper visibility and consistency.
      Implementations can optimize this model by sharing compatible class
      loaders between bundles.</para>

      <para>The proxy will have to call arbitrary methods on arbitrary
      services. This has a large number of security implications, see <xref
      linkend="i1789427"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1751493">
    <title>Discovery</title>

    <para>The topology of the distributed system is decided by the Topology
    Manager. However, in a distributed environment, the Topology Manager needs
    to <emphasis>discover</emphasis> Endpoints in other frameworks. There is a
    very large number of ways how a Topology Manager could learn about other
    Endpoints, ranging from static configuration, a centralized
    administration, all the way to fully dynamic discovery protocols like the
    Service Location Protocol (SLP) or JGroups. To support the required
    flexibility, this specification defines an <emphasis>Endpoint Event
    Listener</emphasis> service that allows the dissemination of Endpoint
    information. This service provides a symmetric solution because the
    problem is symmetric: it is used by a Topology Manager to announce changes
    in its local topology as well as find out about other Endpoint
    Descriptions. Where those other Endpoint Descriptions come from can vary
    widely. This design is depicted in <xref linkend="i1753219"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1753219">
      <title>Examples</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.532in"
                     contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="topology-example.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The design of the Endpoint Event Listener allows a federated
    registry of Endpoint Descriptions. Any party that is interested in
    Endpoint Descriptions should register an Endpoint Event Listener service.
    This will signal that it is interested in topology information to any
    <emphasis>Endpoint Description Providers</emphasis>. Each Endpoint Event
    Listener service must be registered with a service property that holds a
    set of filter strings to indicate the <emphasis>scope</emphasis> of its
    interest. These filters must match an Endpoint Description before the
    corresponding Endpoint Event Listener service is notified of the
    availability of an Endpoint Description. Scoping is intended to limit the
    delivery of unnecessary Endpoint Descriptions as well as signal the need
    for specific Endpoints.</para>

    <para>In addition to providing an Endpoint Event Listener actors must
    provide an Endpoint Listener. This may, or may not, be the same service
    object as the Endpoint Event Listener. Registering an Endpoint Listener in
    addition to an Endpoint Event Listener ensures that Endpoint announcements
    from version <code>1.0</code> actors will continue to be visible. If a
    service object is advertised as both an Endpoint Listener
    <emphasis>and</emphasis> an Endpoint Event Listener then version
    <code>1.1</code> actors must use the Endpoint Event Listener interface of
    the service in preference, and not call it as an Endpoint Listener. For
    this reason the Endpoint Listener interface is marked as
    <code>Deprecated</code>. The reason that the Endpoint Event Listener
    interface should be preferred is that it supports more advanced
    notification types, such as modification events.</para>

    <para>A Topology Manager has knowledge of its local Endpoints and is
    likely to be only interested in remote Endpoints. It can therefore set the
    scope to only match remote Endpoint Descriptions. See <xref
    linkend="i1887500"/> for how to limit the scope to local or remote
    Endpoints. At the same time, a Topology manager should inform any locally
    registered Endpoint Event Listener and Endpoint Listener services about
    Endpoints that it has created or deleted.</para>

    <para>This architecture allows many different use cases. For example, a
    bundle could display a map of the topology by registering an Endpoint
    Event Listener with a scope for local Endpoints. Another example is the
    use of SLP to announce local Endpoints to a network and to discover remote
    Endpoints from other parties on this network.</para>

    <para>An instance of this design is shown in <xref linkend="i1751511"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>. In this figure, there are 3
    frameworks that collaborate through some discovery bundle. The
    <code>Top</code> framework has created an Endpoint and decides to notify
    all Endpoint Event Listeners and Endpoint Listeners registered in this
    framework that are scoped to this new Endpoint. Local bundle
    <code>D</code> has set its scope to all Endpoint Descriptions that
    originate from its local framework, it therefore receives the Endpoint
    Description from <code>T</code>. Bundle <code>D</code> then sends the
    Endpoint Description to all its peers on the network.</para>

    <para>In the <code>Quark</code> framework, the manager bundle
    <code>T</code> has expressed an interest by setting its scope to a filter
    that matches the Endpoint Description from the <code>Top</code> framework.
    When the bundle <code>D</code> on the <code>Quark</code> framework
    receives the Endpoint Description from bundle <code>D</code> on the
    <code>Top</code> framework, it matches it against all local Endpoint Event
    Listener's scope. In this case, the local manager bundle <code>T</code>
    matches and is given the Endpoint Description. The manager then uses the
    Remote Service Admin service to import the exported service described by
    the given Endpoint Description.</para>

    <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="i1751511">
      <title>Endpoint Discovery Architecture. T=Topology Manager,
      D=Discovery</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.692in"
                     contentwidth="4.924in"
                     fileref="endpoint-discovery-architecture.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The previous description is just one of the possible usages of the
    Endpoint Event Listener. For example, the discovery bundles could
    communicate the scopes to their peers. These peers could then register an
    Endpoint Event Listener per peer, minimizing the network traffic because
    Endpoint Descriptions do not have to be broadcast to all peers.</para>

    <para>Another alternative usage is described in <xref
    linkend="i1889341"/>. In this chapter the extender pattern is used to
    retrieve Endpoint Descriptions from resources in locally active
    bundles.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Scope and Filters</title>

      <para>An Endpoint Event Listener or Endpoint Listener service is
      registered with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointEventListener.ENDPOINT_LISTENER_SCOPE"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service property. This property, which is
      <code>String+</code>, must be set and must contain at least one filter.
      If there is not at least one filter, then that Endpoint Event Listener
      or Endpoint Listener must not receive any Endpoint Descriptions.</para>

      <para>Each filter in the scope is applied against the properties of the
      Endpoint Description until one succeeds. Only if one succeeds is the
      Endpoint informed about the existence of an Endpoint.</para>

      <para>The Endpoint Description is designed to reflect the properties of
      the imported service, there is therefore a correspondence with the
      filters that are used by bundles that are listening for service
      registrations. The purpose of this design is to match the filter
      available through Listener Hook services, see <xref
      linkend="i1755239"/>.</para>

      <para>However, the purpose of the filters is more generic than just this
      use case. It can also be used to specify the interest in local Endpoints
      or remote Endpoints. For example, Topology Managers are only interested
      in remote Endpoints while discoverers are only interested in local
      Endpoints. It is easy to discriminate between local and remote by
      filtering on the <code>endpoint.framework.uuid</code> property. Endpoint
      Descriptions contain the Universally Unique ID (UUID) of the originating
      framework. This UUID must be available from the local framework as well.
      See <xref linkend="i1887500"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Endpoint Event Listener Interface</title>

      <para>The <code>EndpointEventListener</code> interface has the following
      method:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointEventListener.endpointChanged-EndpointEvent-String-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – Notify the Endpoint Event Listener of
          changes to an Endpoint. The change could entail the addition or
          removal of an Endpoint or the modification of the properties of an
          existing Endpoint. Multiple identical events should be counted as a
          single such event.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>These methods must only be called if the Endpoint Event Listener
      service has a filter in its scope that matches the Endpoint Description
      properties.</para>

      <para>The Endpoint Event Listener interface is
      <emphasis>idempotent</emphasis>. Endpoint Description Providers must
      inform an Endpoint Event Listener service (and its deprecated
      predecessor Endpoint Listener service) that is registered of all their
      matching Endpoints. The only way to find out about all available
      Endpoints is to register an Endpoint Event Listener (or Endpoint
      Listener) that is then informed by all available Endpoint Description
      Providers of their known Endpoint Descriptions that match their
      scope.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Endpoint Listener Interface</title>

      <para>The <code>EndpointListener</code> interface is marked as
      <code>Deprecated</code> because the <code>EndpointEventListener</code>
      interface must be used in preference when both are implemented by the
      same object. The <code>EndpointEvent</code> interface has the following
      methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointListener.endpointAdded-EndpointDescription-String-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – Notify the Endpoint Listener of a new
          Endpoint Description. The second parameter is the filter that
          matched the Endpoint Description. Registering the same Endpoint
          multiple times counts as a single registration.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointListener.endpointRemoved-EndpointDescription-String-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – Notify the Endpoint Listener that the
          provided Endpoint Description is no longer available.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>These methods must only be called if the Endpoint Listener service
      has a filter in its scope that matches the Endpoint Description
      properties. The reason for the filter string in the methods is to
      simplify and speed up matching an Endpoint Description to the cause of
      interest. For example, if the Listener Hook is used to do on demand
      import of services, then the filter can be associated with the Listener
      Info of the hook, see <xref linkend="i1755239"/>. If multiple filters in
      the scope match the Endpoint Description than the first filter in the
      scope must be passed.</para>

      <para>The Endpoint Listener interface is
      <emphasis>idempotent</emphasis>. Endpoint Description Providers must
      inform an Endpoint Listener service that is registered of all their
      matching Endpoints.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Endpoint Event Listener and Endpoint Listener
      Implementations</title>

      <para>An Endpoint Event Listener service tracks the known Endpoints in
      its given scope. There are potentially a large number of bundles
      involved in creating this federated registry of Endpoints. To ensure
      that no Endpoint Descriptions are orphaned or unnecessarily missed, an
      Endpoint Event Listener implementation must follow the following
      rules:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Registration</emphasis> – The Endpoint Event
          Listener service is called with an event of type <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointEvent.ADDED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> for all known Endpoint Descriptions that the
          bundles in the local framework are aware of. Similarly, Endpoint
          Listener services are called with an <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointListener.endpointAdded-EndpointDescription-String-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method for all these.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Tracking providers</emphasis> – An Endpoint Event
          Listener or Endpoint Listener must track the bundles that provide it
          with Endpoint Descriptions. If a bundle that provided Endpoint
          Descriptions is stopped, all Endpoint Descriptions that were
          provided by that bundle must be removed. This can be implemented
          straightforwardly with a Service Factory.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Scope modification</emphasis> – An Endpoint Event
          Listener or Endpoint Listener is allowed to modify the set of
          filters in its scope through a service property modification. This
          modification must result in new and/or existing Endpoint
          Descriptions to be added, however, existing Endpoints that are no
          longer in scope are not required to be explicitly removed by the
          their sources. It is the responsibility for the Endpoint Listener to
          remove these orphaned Endpoint Description from its view.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Endpoint mutability</emphasis> – An Endpoint
          Description can change its Properties. The way this is handled is
          different for Endpoint Event Listeners and Endpoint Listeners. An
          Endpoint Event Listener receives a change event of type <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointEvent.MODIFIED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> when the Properties of an existing Endpoint
          are modified. If the modification means that the Endpoint no longer
          matches the listener scope an event of type <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointEvent.MODIFIED_ENDMATCH"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> is sent instead. Endpoint Listener services
          receive a sequence of <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointListener.endpointRemoved-EndpointDescription-String-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.EndpointListener.endpointAdded-EndpointDescription-String-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> callbacks when the Properties of an Endpoint
          are modified.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Endpoint Descriptions can be added from different sources and
      providers of Endpoint Descriptions often use asynchronous and
      potentially unreliable communications. An implementation must therefore
      handle the addition of multiple equal Endpoint Descriptions from
      different sources as well as from the same source. Implementations must
      not count the number of registrations, a remove operation of an Endpoint
      Description is final for each source. That is, if source <code>A</code>
      added Endpoint Description <code>e</code>, then it can only be removed
      by source <code>A</code>. However, if source <code>A</code> added
      <code>e</code> multiple times, then it only needs to be removed once.
      Removals of Endpoint Descriptions that have not been added (or were
      removed before) should be ignored.</para>

      <para>The discovery of Endpoints is a fundamentally indeterministic
      process and implementations of Endpoint Event Listener services should
      realize that there are no guarantees that an added Endpoint Description
      is always describing a valid Endpoint.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Endpoint Description Providers</title>

      <para>The Endpoint Event Listener and Endpoint Listener services are
      based on an asynchronous, unreliable, best effort model because there
      are few guarantees in a distributed world. It is the task of an Endpoint
      Description Provider, for example a discovery bundle, to keep the
      Endpoint Event Listener services up to date of any Endpoint Descriptions
      the provider is aware of and that match the tracked service's
      scope.</para>

      <para>If an Endpoint Event Listener or Endpoint Listener service is
      registered, a provider must add all matching Endpoint Descriptions that
      it is aware of and match the tracked listener's scope. This can be done
      during registration or asynchronously later. For example, it is possible
      to use the filters in the scope to request remote systems for any
      Endpoint Descriptions that match those filters. For expediency reasons,
      the service registration event should not be delayed until those results
      return; it is therefore applicable to add these Endpoint Descriptions
      later when the returns from the remote systems finally arrive.</para>

      <para>If a tracked listener service object is advertised as both an
      Endpoint Event Listener and an Endpoint Listener then the
      EndpointDescription Provider must ignore the
      <code>EndpointListener</code> interface, and treat the listener only as
      an Endpoint Event Listener. Remote Service Admin <code>1.0</code> actors
      will be unaware of the <code>EndpointEventListener</code> interface, and
      will treat the service object purely as an Endpoint Listener. This
      restriction ensures that all actors will treat the service either as an
      Endpoint Event Listener, or an Endpoint Listener, but never as both. As
      a result the listener service will not have to disambiguate duplicate
      events from a single source. If an Endpoint Description Provider uses
      both the Endpoint Listener and Endpoint Event Listener interfaces of a
      single service object then the resulting behavior is undefined. The
      implementation may detect the misuse and throw an Exception, process or
      ignore the events from one of the interfaces, or it may simply corrupt
      the internal registry of Endpoints within the listener.</para>

      <para>A tracked Endpoint Event Listener or Endpoint Listener is allowed
      to modify its scope by setting new properties on its Service
      Registration. An Endpoint Description provider must process the new
      scope and add any newly matching Endpoint Descriptions. It is not
      necessary to remove any Endpoint Descriptions that were added before but
      no longer match the new scope. Removing those orphaned descriptions is
      the responsibility of the listener implementation.</para>

      <para>It is not necessary to remove any registered Endpoint Descriptions
      when the Endpoint Event Listener or Endpoint Listener is unregistered;
      also here it is the responsibility of the listener to do the proper
      cleanup.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1755239">
      <title>On Demand</title>

      <para>A common distribution policy is to import services that are being
      listened for by local bundles. For example, when a bundle opens a
      Service Tracker on the Log Service, a Topology Manager could be notified
      and attempt to find a Log Service in the local cluster and then import
      this service in the local Service Registry.</para>

      <para>The OSGi framework provides service hooks for exactly this
      purpose. A Topology Manager can register a Listener Hook service and
      receive the information about bundles that have specified an interests
      in specific services.</para>

      <para>For example, a bundle creates the following Service
      Tracker:</para>

      <programlisting>ServiceTracker st = new ServiceTracker(context, 
        LogService.class.getName() );
st.open();</programlisting>

      <para>This Service Tracker will register a Service Listener with the
      OSGi framework. This will cause the framework to add a
      <code>ListenerInfo</code> to any Listener Hook services. The
      <code>getFilter</code> method on a <code>ListenerInfo</code> object
      provides a filter that is directly applicable for the Endpoint Event
      Listener's scope. In the previous example, this would be the
      filter:</para>

      <programlisting>(objectClass=org.osgi.service.log.LogService)</programlisting>

      <para>A Topology Manager could verify if this listener is satisfied.
      That is, if it has at least one service. If no such service could be
      found, it could then add this filter to its Endpoint Event Listener's
      scope to detect remote implementations of this service. If such an
      Endpoint is detected, it could then request the import of this service
      through the Remote Service Admin service.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1736220">
    <title>Events</title>

    <para>The Remote Service Admin service must synchronously inform any
    Remote Service Admin Listener services of events as they happen. Client of
    the events should return quickly and not perform any but trivial
    processing in the same thread.</para>

    <para>The following event types are defined:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.EXPORT_ERROR"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An exported service has run into an
        unrecoverable error, although the Export Registration has not been
        closed yet. The event carries the Export Registration as well as the
        Exception that caused the problem, if present.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.EXPORT_REGISTRATION"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Remote Service Admin has registered a
        new Export Registration.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.EXPORT_UNREGISTRATION"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An Export Registration has been closed, the
        service is no longer exported and the Endpoint is no longer active
        when this was the last registration for that service/Endpoint
        combination.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.EXPORT_UPDATE"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An exported service is updated. The service
        properties have changed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.EXPORT_WARNING"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An exported service is experiencing problems
        but the Endpoint is still available.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.IMPORT_ERROR"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An imported service has run into a fatal
        error and has been shut down. The Import Registration should be closed
        by the Topology Manager that created them.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.IMPORT_REGISTRATION"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A new Import Registration was created for a
        potentially existing service/Endpoint combination.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.IMPORT_UNREGISTRATION"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An Import Registration was closed, removing
        the proxy if this was the last registration.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.IMPORT_UPDATE"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An imported service is updated. The service
        properties have changed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.IMPORT_WARNING"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An imported service is experiencing problems
        but can continue to function.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The following properties are available on the event:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.getType--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The type of the event.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.getException--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Any exception, if present.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.getExportReference--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An export reference, if applicable.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.getImportReference--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An import reference, if applicable.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminEvent.getSource--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The source of the event, the Remote Service
        Admin service.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Event Admin Mapping</title>

      <para>All Remote Service Admin events must be posted, which is
      asynchronously, to the Event Admin service, if present, under the
      following topic:</para>

      <programlisting>org/osgi/service/remoteserviceadmin/&lt;type&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Where <code>&lt;type&gt;</code> represents the type of the event,
      for example <code>IMPORT_ERROR</code>.</para>

      <para>The Event Admin event must have the following properties:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle</code> - <code>(Bundle)</code> The Remote Service
          Admin bundle</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.id</code> - (<code>Long</code>) The id of the
          Remote Service Admin bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.symbolicname</code> - (<code>String</code>) The
          Bundle Symbolic Name of the Remote Service Admin
          <code>bundle.version</code> - (<code>Version</code>) The version of
          the Remote Service Admin bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.signer</code> - (<code>String[]</code>) Signer of
          the Remote Service Admin bundle</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>exception</code> - (Throwable) The Exception, if
          present. Also reported on the <code>cause</code> property for
          backward compatibility.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>exception.class</code> - (<code>String</code>) The
          fully-qualified class name of the attached Exception.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>exception.message</code> -( <code>String)</code> The
          message of the attached exception. Only set if the Exception message
          is not <code>null</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>endpoint.service.id</code> - (<code>Long</code>) Remote
          service id, if present</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>endpoint.framework.uuid</code> - (<code>String</code>)
          Remote service's Framework UUID, if present</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>endpoint.id</code> - (<code>String</code>) The id of the
          Endpoint, if present</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>objectClass</code> - <code>(String[])</code> The
          interface names, if present</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.imported.configs</code> - (<code>String+</code>)
          The configuration types of the imported services, if present</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>timestamp</code> - (<code>Long</code>) The time when the
          event occurred</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>event</code> - (<code>RemoteServiceAdminEvent</code>)
          The <code>RemoteServiceAdminEvent</code> object that caused this
          event.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1889341">
    <title>Endpoint Description Extender Format</title>

    <para>The Endpoint Description Extender format is a possibility to deliver
    Endpoint Descriptions in bundles. This section defines an XML schema and
    how to locate XML definition resources that use this schema to define
    Endpoint Descriptions. The definition resource is a simple property based
    model that can define the same information as the properties on an
    imported service. If a bundle with the description is
    <emphasis>ready</emphasis> (<code>ACTIVE</code> or lazy activation and in
    the <code>STARTING</code> state), then this static description can be
    disseminated through the Endpoint Event Listeners that have specified an
    interest in this description. If the bundle is stopped, the corresponding
    Endpoints must be removed.</para>

    <para>XML documents containing remote service descriptions must be
    specified by the Remote-Service header in the manifest. The structure of
    the Remote Service header is:</para>

    <programlisting>Remote-Service ::= header // See Common Header Syntax in Core</programlisting>

    <para>The value of the header is a comma separated list of paths. A path
    is:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A directory if it ends with a solidus (<code>'/' \u002F</code>).
        A directory is scanned for <code>*.xml</code> files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A path with wildcards. Such a path can use the wildcards in its
        last component, as defined in the <code>findEntries</code>
        method.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A complete path, not having wildcards not ending in a solidus
        (<code>'/' \u002F</code>).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Remote-Service header has no architected directives or
    attributes, unrecognized attributes and directives must be ignored.</para>

    <para>A Remote-Service manifest header specified in a fragment must be
    ignored. However, XML documents referenced by a bundle's Remote-Service
    manifest header can be contained in attached fragments. The required
    behavior for this is implemented in the <code>findEntries</code>
    method.</para>

    <para>The extender must process each XML document specified in this
    header. If an XML document specified by the header cannot be located in
    the bundle and its attached fragments, the extender must log an error
    message with the Log Service, if present, and continue.</para>

    <para>For example:</para>

    <programlisting>Remote-Service: lib/, remote/osgi/*.dsc, cnf/google.xml</programlisting>

    <para>This matches all resources in the lib directory matching
    <code>*.xml</code>, all resources in the <code>/remote/osgi</code>
    directory that end with <code>.dsc</code>, as well as the
    <code>google.xml</code> resource in the <code>cnf</code> directory.</para>

    <para>The namespace of these XML resources must be:</para>

    <programlisting> <code>http://www.osgi.org/xmlns/rsa/v1.0.0</code></programlisting>

    <para>This namespace describes a set of Endpoint Descriptions, where each
    Endpoint Description can provide a set of properties. The structure of
    this schema is:</para>

    <programlisting>endpoint-descriptions  ::= &lt;endpoint-description&gt;*
endpoint-description   ::= &lt;property&gt;*
property               ::= ( &lt;array&gt; | &lt;list&gt; | &lt;set&gt;| &lt;xml&gt; )?
array                  ::= &lt;value&gt; *
list                   ::= &lt;value&gt; *
set                    ::= &lt;value&gt; *
xml                    ::= &lt;*&gt; *</programlisting>

    <para>This structure is depicted in <xref linkend="i1889373"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1889373">
      <title>Endpoint Description XML Structure</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.427in"
                     contentwidth="6.262in"
                     fileref="endpoint-xml-structure.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The <code>property</code> element has the attributes listed in table
    <xref linkend="service.remoteserviceadmin-property.attributes"/>.</para>

    <table xml:id="service.remoteserviceadmin-property.attributes">
      <title>Property Attributes</title>

      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>

        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

        <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="3*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Attribute</entry>

            <entry>Type</entry>

            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><code>name</code></entry>

            <entry><code>String</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The required name of the property. The type maps to
            the XML Schema <code>xsd:string</code> type.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>value-type</code></entry>

            <entry><para><code>&#160;&#160;String</code></para><para><code>|
            long</code></para><para><code>| Long</code></para><para><code>|
            double</code></para><para><code>|
            Double</code></para><para><code>| float</code></para><para><code>|
            Float</code></para><para><code>| int</code></para><para><code>|
            Integer</code></para><para><code>| byte</code></para><para><code>|
            Byte</code></para><para><code>| char</code></para><para><code>|
            Character</code></para><para><code>|
            boolean</code></para><para><code>|
            Boolean</code></para><para><code>|
            short</code></para><para><code>| Short</code></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The optional type name of the property, the default
            is <code>String</code>. Any value in the value attribute or the
            value element when collections are used must be converted to the
            corresponding Java types. If the primitive form, for example
            <code>byte</code>, is specified for non-array types, then the
            value must be silently converted to the corresponding wrapper
            type.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>value</code></entry>

            <entry><code>String</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The value. Must be converted to the specified type if
            this is not the <code>String</code> type. The <code>value</code>
            attribute must not be used when the <code>property</code> element
            has a child element.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>A property can have an <code>array</code>, <code>list</code>,
    <code>set</code>, or <code>xml</code> child element. If a child element is
    present then it is an error if the <code>value</code> attribute is
    defined. It is also an error of there is no child element and no
    <code>value</code> attribute.</para>

    <para>The <code>array</code>, <code>list</code>, or <code>set</code> are
    <emphasis>multi-valued</emphasis>. That is, they contain 0 or more
    <code>value</code> elements. A value element contains text (a string) that
    must be converted to the given value-type or if not specified, left as is.
    Conversion must <emphasis>trim</emphasis> the leading and trailing white
    space characters as defined in the <code>Character.isWhitespace</code>
    method. No trimming must be done for strings. An array of primitive
    integers like <code>int[] {1,42,97}</code> can be encoded as
    follows:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;property name="integers" value-type="int"&gt;
    &lt;array&gt;
        &lt;value&gt; 1&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;42&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;97&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;/array&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The <code>xml</code> element is used to convey XML from other
    namespaces, it is allowed to contain one foreign XML root element, with
    any number of children, that will act as the root element of an XML
    document. This root element will be included in the corresponding property
    as a string. The XML element must be a valid XML document but not contain
    the XML processing instructions, the part between the <code>&lt;?</code>
    and <code>?&gt;</code>. The <code>value-type</code> of the property must
    be <code>String</code> or not set when an <code>xml</code> element is
    used, using another type is invalid.</para>

    <para>The <code>xml</code> element can be used to embed configuration
    information, making the Endpoint Description self contained.</para>

    <para>The following is an example of an <code>endpoint-descriptions</code>
    resource.</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;endpoint-descriptions xmlns="http://www.osgi.org/xmlns/rsa/v1.0.0"&gt;
    &lt;endpoint-description&gt;
        &lt;property name="service.intents"&gt;
            &lt;list&gt;
                &lt;value&gt;SOAP&lt;/value&gt;
                &lt;value&gt;HTTP&lt;/value&gt;
            &lt;/list&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;property name="endpoint.id" value="http://ws.acme.com:9000/hello"/&gt; 
        &lt;property name="endpoint.package.version.com.acme" value="4.2"/&gt;
        &lt;property name="objectClass"&gt;
            &lt;array&gt;
                &lt;value&gt;com.acme.Foo&lt;/value&gt;
            &lt;/array&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;property name="service.imported.configs" value="com.acme"/&gt;
        &lt;property name="com.acme.ws.xml"&gt;
            &lt;xml&gt;
                &lt;config xmlns="http://acme.com/defs"&gt;
                    &lt;port&gt;1029&lt;/port&gt;
                    &lt;host&gt;www.acme.com&lt;/host&gt;
                &lt;/config&gt;
            &lt;/xml&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;/endpoint-description&gt;
&lt;/endpoint-descriptions&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Besides being in a separate resource, the static configuration as
    described here could also be part of a larger XML file. In that case the
    parser must ignore elements not part of the
    <code>http://www.osgi.org/xmlns/rsa/v1.0.0</code> namespace schema.</para>

    <section>
      <title>XML Schema</title>

      <para>This namespace of the schema is:</para>

      <programlisting>http://www.osgi.org/xmlns/rsa/v1.0.0</programlisting>

      <programlisting role="pgwide"><xi:include encoding="utf-8"
          href="../../generated/xmlns/rsa/v1.0.0/rsa.xsd" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Capability Namespaces</title>

    <section>
      <title>Local Discovery Extender</title>

      <para>A bundle containing Endpoint Description Extender resources can
      indicate its dependency on the Remote Service Admin extender by
      declaring a requirement on the <code>osgi.extender</code>
      namespace.</para>

      <programlisting>Require-Capability: osgi.extender;
    filter:="(&amp;(osgi.extender=osgi.remoteserviceadmin.localdiscovery)
             (version&gt;=1.0)(!(version&gt;=2.0)))"</programlisting>

      <para>With this constraint declared a bundle that depends on the
      extender will fail to resolve if no extender is present in the
      framework.</para>

      <para>Implementations of this specification must provide this extender
      capability at version 1.0 as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.extender;
    osgi.extender="osgi.remoteserviceadmin.localdiscovery";
    version:Version="1.0";
    uses:="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin"</programlisting>

      <para>The reason that the extender capability is declared at version 1.0
      is because the extender is unchanged from version 1.0 of this
      specification.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Discovery Provider Capability</title>

      <para>Discovery Providers use the
      <code>osgi.remoteserviceadmin.discovery</code> namespace to declare
      themselves as such. The version defined for this namespace indicates the
      version of this specification that the discovery provider
      supports.</para>

      <para>This namespace has a defined attribute, <code>protocols</code> of
      type <code>List&lt;String&gt;</code>, which contains a list of the
      discovery protocols supported by the discovery provider. Local discovery
      providers (using the <xref linkend="i1889341"/>), should use the value
      <code>local</code> to indicate that they support this. Additionally, it
      defines a <code>version</code> attribute. Other values for the protocols
      attribute are implementation specific.</para>

      <table pgwide="1">
        <title>osgi.remoteserviceadmin.discovery Namespace</title>

        <tgroup cols="6">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="5" colwidth="3.5*"/>

          <colspec colnum="6" colwidth="7*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Name</entry>

              <entry>Kind</entry>

              <entry>M/O</entry>

              <entry>Type</entry>

              <entry>Syntax</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>protocols</code></entry>

              <entry><code>CA</code></entry>

              <entry><code>M</code></entry>

              <entry><code>List&lt;String&gt;</code></entry>

              <entry><code>symbolic-name</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The discovery protocols supported. A value of
              <code>local</code> indicates support for the <xref
              linkend="i1889341"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>version</code></entry>

              <entry><code>CA</code></entry>

              <entry><code>M</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Version</code></entry>

              <entry><code>version</code></entry>

              <entry><para>This version must correspond to the version of the
              Remote Service Admin specification.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Example: A discovery provider that provides local and SLP
      discovery:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.remoteserviceadmin.discovery;
    protocols:List&lt;String&gt;="SLP,local"; version:Version=1.1</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Distribution Provider Capability</title>

      <para>Distribution providers advertise their supported distribution
      mechanisms using configuration types. These are selected at runtime
      using the <code>service.exported.configs</code> service property.
      Distribution providers can use the
      <code>osgi.remoteserviceadmin.distribution</code> namespace with
      attribute <code>configs</code>, of type <code>List&lt;String&gt;</code>,
      to advertise the supported config types.</para>

      <table pgwide="1">
        <title>osgi.remoteserviceadmin.distribution Namespace</title>

        <tgroup cols="6">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="5" colwidth="3.5*"/>

          <colspec colnum="6" colwidth="7*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Name</entry>

              <entry>Kind</entry>

              <entry>M/O</entry>

              <entry>Type</entry>

              <entry>Syntax</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>configs</code></entry>

              <entry><code>CA</code></entry>

              <entry><code>M</code></entry>

              <entry><code>List&lt;String&gt;</code></entry>

              <entry><code>symbolic-name</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Supported configuration types. See <xref
              linkend="service.remoteserviceadmin.endpointdescription"/>
              .</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>version</code></entry>

              <entry><code>CA</code></entry>

              <entry><code>M</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Version</code></entry>

              <entry><code>version</code></entry>

              <entry><para>This version must correspond to the version of the
              Remote Service Admin specification.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Example: A Distribution provider that supports the
      <code>org.acme.jaxws</code> and <code>org.acme.jaxrs</code>
      configuration types:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.remoteserviceadmin.distribution;
    configs:List&lt;String&gt;="org.acme.jaxws,org.acme.jaxrs"; version:Version=1.1</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Topology Manager Capability</title>

      <para>Remote Service Admin topology managers may use different policies
      when determining which services to export and/or import. Topology
      managers use the namespace <code>osgi.remoteserviceadmin.topology</code>
      to declare this behavior. This namespace defines the <code>policy</code>
      attribute of type <code>List&lt;String&gt;</code>. Values are
      implementation specific, but example definitions can be found at <xref
      linkend="service.remoteserviceadmin-example.policies"/>.</para>

      <table pgwide="1">
        <title>osgi.remoteserviceadmin.topology Namespace</title>

        <tgroup cols="6">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="5" colwidth="3.5*"/>

          <colspec colnum="6" colwidth="7*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Name</entry>

              <entry>Kind</entry>

              <entry>M/O</entry>

              <entry>Type</entry>

              <entry>Syntax</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>policy</code></entry>

              <entry><code>CA</code></entry>

              <entry><code>M</code></entry>

              <entry><code>List&lt;String&gt;</code></entry>

              <entry><code>symbolic-name</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The policy used for importing and exporting
              services. In general the policy is implementation
              specific.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>version</code></entry>

              <entry><code>CA</code></entry>

              <entry><code>M</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Version</code></entry>

              <entry><code>version</code></entry>

              <entry><para>This version must correspond to the version of the
              Remote Service Admin specification.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Example: A Topology manager that supports a
      <emphasis>promiscuous</emphasis> policy:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.remoteserviceadmin.topology;
    policy:List&lt;String&gt;=promiscuous; version:Version=1.1</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Service Capability</title>

      <para>The Distribution Provider provides the <link
      linkend="service.remoteserviceadmin-rsa.service"> <emphasis>Remote
      Service Admin</emphasis></link> service. To inform tools about this
      service it must provide the <link
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"><code>osgi.service</code></link>
      namespace representing the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service. This capability must also declare a
      uses constraint for the <code>org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin</code>
      package:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.service;
  objectClass:List&lt;String&gt;=
    "org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin";
  uses:="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin"</programlisting>

      <para>This capability must follow the rules defined for the <xref
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Advice to implementations</title>

    <para>This section is not intended to be normative, but offers advice to
    implementations as to how the complexity of supporting both the new
    Endpoint Event Listener and Endpoint Listener services can be managed and
    minimized. This advice applies to both Discovery Providers and Topology
    Managers implementing Remote Service Admin <code>1.1</code>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Notifying listeners</title>

      <para>Endpoint Event Listeners and Endpoint Listeners have a very
      similar behavior and lifecycle. They also use the same property names to
      define their scope filter. It is therefore relatively simple for an
      Endpoint Description Provider to notify both Endpoint Listener and
      Endpoint Event Listeners using a single code path.</para>

      <para>One possible mechanism is to track both the listener types using
      the same Service Tracker. If the tracked Service Reference advertises
      the <code>EndpointEventListener</code> interface then it must be treated
      as an Endpoint Event Listener. If not then the Endpoint Listener service
      can be wrapped in an adapter that converts Endpoint Event Listener
      events into the appropriate Endpoint Listener calls. The main
      notification code path can then treat every listener as an Endpoint
      Event Listener.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Receiving Endpoint lifecycle notifications</title>

      <para>The Remote Service Admin <code>1.1</code> specification is
      backward compatible with version <code>1.0</code>, meaning that version
      1.1 actors must register an Endpoint Listener service. There is no
      restriction requiring this listener to be the same service as the
      Endpoint Event Listener, however there is a significant advantage to
      combining the listeners into a single service registration.</para>

      <para>By making the two listeners a single service object a bundle can
      guarantee that it will not receive multiple notifications for the same
      event. If the service registrations are separate then Endpoint
      Description Providers will see two separate listeners, and notify them
      both. As a single service registration only one event will occur, and
      using the highest mutually supported version of the Remote Service Admin
      Specification.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1789427">
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>From a security point of view distribution is a significant threat.
    A Distribution Provider requires very significant capabilities to be able
    to proxy services. In many situations it will be required to grant the
    distribution provider All Permission. It is therefore highly recommended
    that Distribution Providers use trusted links and ensure that it is not
    possible to attack a system through the Remote Services Admin service and
    used discovery protocols.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Import and Export Registrations</title>

      <para>Import and Export Registrations are
      <emphasis>capabilities</emphasis>. That is, they can only be obtained
      when the caller has the proper permissions but once obtained they are no
      longer checked. The caller should therefore be careful to share those
      objects with other bundles. Export and Import References are free to
      share.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Endpoint Permission</title>

      <para>The Remote Service Admin implementation requires a large set of
      permissions because it must be able to distribute potentially any
      service. Giving these extensive capabilities to all Topology Managers
      would make it harder to developer general Topology Managers that
      implements specific scenarios. For this reason, this specification
      provides an Endpoint Permission.</para>

      <para>When an Endpoint Permission must be verified, it must be created
      with an Endpoint Description as argument, like:</para>

      <programlisting>sm.checkPermission( new EndpointPermission(anEndpoint,localUUID,READ));</programlisting>

      <para>The standard name and action constructor is used to define a
      permission. The name argument is a filter expression. The filter for an
      Endpoint Permission is applied to the properties of an Endpoint
      Description. The <code>localUUID</code> must map to the UUID of the
      framework of the caller of this constructor, see <xref
      linkend="i1887500"/>. This <code>localUUID</code> is used to allow a the
      permissions to use the <code>&lt;&lt;LOCAL&gt;&gt;</code> magic name in
      the permission filter to refer to the local framework.</para>

      <para>The filter expression can use the following magic value:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>&lt;&lt;LOCAL&gt;&gt;</code> - This value represents the
          framework UUID of the framework that this bundle belongs to. The
          following example restricts the visibility to descriptions of local
          Endpoints:</para>

          <programlisting>  ALLOW { 
    ...EndpointPermission
         "(endpoint.framework.uuid=&lt;&lt;LOCAL&gt;&gt;)" 
         "READ" }</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>An Endpoint Permission that has the actions listed in the
      following table.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Endpoint Permission Actions</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="0.8*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="3.1*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Action</entry>

              <entry>Methods</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>IMPORT</code></entry>

              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin.importService-EndpointDescription-"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Import an Endpoint</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>EXPORT</code></entry>

              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin.exportService-ServiceReference-Map-"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Export a service</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>READ</code></entry>

              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin.getExportedServices--"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdmin.getImportedEndpoints--"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.RemoteServiceAdminListener.remoteAdminEvent-RemoteServiceAdminEvent-"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>See the presence of distributed services. The
              <code>IMPORT</code> and <code>EXPORT</code> action imply
              <code>READ</code>. Distribution of events to the Remote Service
              Admin Listener. The Remote Service Admin must verify that the
              listener's bundle has the proper permission. No events should be
              delivered that are not implied.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.remoteserviceadmin.namespace.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1693238"><title>OSGi Service Property
      Namespace</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://www.osgi.org/service-property-namespace/"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="i1709441"><title>UUIDs</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universally_Unique_Identifier"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1788834"><title>Service Location Protocol
      (SLP)</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Service_Location_Protocol"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="i1789952"><title>JGroups</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.jgroups.org/"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="i1789020"><title>UDDI</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_Description_Discovery_and_Integration"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1789031"><title>Service Component Architecture
      (SCA)</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.osoa.org/display/Main/Home"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
