<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="56" revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="framework.weavinghooks"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Weaving Hook Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Bytecode weaving is a popular technique that transforms class files
    to provide additional functionality. This is a powerful technique that,
    when used with care, can significantly reduce the coding effort for
    mundane programming chores.</para>

    <para>This specification provides a means for a handler bundle to
    intercept any bundle class loading calls in the framework, transform the
    byte codes, and add new dynamic imports. A means for observing the final
    weaving results, both before and after they take effect, is also
    provided.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Ordering</emphasis> - Allow a weaver to weave a
          bundle before it is loaded and used.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dynamic Imports</emphasis> - Support additional
          imports.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Strategy</emphasis> - Support both Static and
          Dynamic Weaving strategies.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>No Metadata</emphasis> - Allow standard bundles,
          without any specific metadata, to be woven.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Java API</emphasis> - Use the existing Java byte
          code transformation APIs where possible.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Multiple</emphasis> - Allow for multiple weavers per
          bundle in a defined order.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Observation</emphasis> - Allow woven class state
          transitions to be observed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Weaving Hook</emphasis> - A service registered by a
          bundle that wants to weave other bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Woven Class</emphasis> - An object representing the
          class to be woven.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Woven Class Listener</emphasis> - A service
          registered by a bundle that wants to observe woven class state
          transitions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Byte Code Weaving</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.437in"
                       contentwidth="4.959in"
                       fileref="weavinghooks-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <section>
      <title>Tracing</title>

      <para>For tracing purposes, a bundle can weave a trace entry and exit
      message around each method. This can be done with byte code weaving by
      inserting a call to a service at the beginning and end of a method. In
      this example, a service is created that has two methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>trace(Bundle)</code> - Byte code weave the given bundle
          with trace entry and exit methods.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>untrace(Bundle)</code> - Remove any weavings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The strategy chosen here is simple. The weaver registers a Weaving
      Hook service so it receives all class loads. Any such class load is
      checked against a set of bundles that needs tracing, any class from a
      traced bundle is then woven with the trace information. If a bundle is
      to be traced, the set is updated and the bundle is refreshed to ensure
      all classes are loaded anew so the tracing code can be woven in.</para>

      <programlisting>public class TracingWeaver implements WeavingHook {
    final Set&lt;Bundle&gt; bundles = new HashSet&lt;Bundle&gt;();
    final List&lt;String&gt; imports = Arrays.asList(
        "com.acme.trace;version=\"[1,2)\""); 
    BundleContext context;</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>weave</code> method is the service method of the Weaving
      Hook service. It receives a <code>WovenClass</code> object that provides
      the information about the class to be woven. In this case, the
      <code>bundles</code> field contains the bundles to be woven, so this is
      checked first. If the to-be-loaded class is in one of the traced
      bundles, the byte codes are changed to provide trace information.
      Otherwise the no change is made.</para>

      <para>In general, weaving code will require new imports for the
      to-be-woven bundle. These imports can be added by adding Dynamic Import
      Package clauses to the list received from the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.getDynamicImports--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This is a list of <code>String</code>
      objects, the syntax of each string is equal to a clause in the
      DynamicImport-Package header. See <xref
      linkend="framework.module.dynamicimportpackage"/> for the proper
      syntax.</para>

      <programlisting>    public void weave(WovenClass classInfo) {
        BundleWiring bw = classInfo.getBundleWiring(); 
        Bundle b = bw.getBundle(); 
        if (bundles.contains(b)) {
            byte [] woven = weaveTracing(classInfo.getBytes());
            if (!classInfo.getDynamicImports().containsAll(imports))
                classInfo.getDynamicImports().addAll(imports);
            classInfo.setBytes(woven);
        }
    }</programlisting>

      <para>The following <code>trace</code> method is called when a bundle
      must be traced. It ignores the request if the bundle is already traced.
      Otherwise, it will add the bundle to the set of traced bundles and
      refresh the bundle.</para>

      <programlisting>    public void trace(Bundle b) {
        if (bundles.add(b))
            refresh(b);
    }</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>untrace</code> method is the reverse:</para>

      <programlisting>    public void untrace(Bundle b) {
        if (bundles.remove(b))
            refresh(b);
    }</programlisting>

      <para>The refresh method uses the Bundle Wiring API to refresh a bundle.
      Refreshing a bundle will throw away its class loader so that all used
      classes are reloaded when needed.</para>

      <programlisting>    private void refresh(Bundle b) {
        Bundle fwb = context.getBundle(0);
        FrameworkWiring fw = fwb.adapt(FrameworkWiring.class);
        fw.refreshBundles(Arrays.asList(b));
    }</programlisting>

      <para>The trace method that does the final weaving is left as an
      exercise to the reader:</para>

      <programlisting>    byte[] weaveTracing(byte[] bytes) {
        ..
    }       
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Isolation</title>

      <para>The <xref linkend="framework.resolverhooks"/> allows bundles to be
      separated into various regions isolated by sharing policies. The dynamic
      imports added in the tracing example will need to be taken into account
      by the sharing policies of regions containing bundles whose classes were
      woven in order for the bundles to resolve. This can be accomplished
      using a Woven Class Listener. Using a Weaving Hook would not be
      appropriate since there is no guarantee that a Weaving Hook observes the
      final list of dynamic imports.</para>

      <para>The region registers a Woven Class Listener service so it receives
      notifications of Woven Class state transitions. The sharing policy of
      the region containing the bundle whose class was woven is updated with
      the dynamic imports, if any. This action occurs while the Woven Class is
      in the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state to ensure the region is prepared to accept
      the imports before the bundle wiring is updated upon entering the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.DEFINED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state. The region is initialized with the set of
      bundles composing it and a static sharing policy consisting of
      namespaces mapped to sets of filters indicating the allowed
      capabilities.</para>

      <programlisting>public class Region implements WovenClassListener, ResolverHook {
    final Set&lt;Bundle&gt; bundles;
    final Map&lt;String, Set&lt;Filter&gt;&gt; policy;</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>modified</code> method is the service method of the
      Woven Class Listener service. It receives a Woven Class object that
      provides the information about the woven class that underwent a state
      transition. If the current state is <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, and the associated bundle is part of the
      region, the sharing policy is updated with the additional dynamic
      imports, if any.</para>

      <programlisting>    public void modified(WovenClass wovenClass) {
        if ((wovenClass.getState() &amp; WovenClass.TRANSFORMED) == 0)
            return;
        Bundle bundle = wovenClass.getBundleWiring().getBundle();
        if (!bundles.contains(bundle))
           return;
        Set&lt;Filter&gt; filters = policy.get(PackageNamespace.PACKAGE_NAMESPACE);
        for (String dynamicImport : wovenClass.getDynamicImports())
            filters.add(toFilter(dynamicImport));
    }</programlisting>

      <para>The region also implements <code>ResolverHook</code>. When the
      <code>filterMatches</code> method is called, the requirement is
      inspected to see if its matching capabilities are allowed into the
      region. If not, the list of candidates is cleared.</para>

      <programlisting>    public void filterMatches(BundleRequirement requirement, 
            Collection&lt;BundleCapability&gt; candidates) {
        Bundle bundle = requirement.getRevision().getBundle();
        if (!bundles.contains(bundle))
            return;
        String namespace = requirement.getNamespace();
        if (!policy.containsKey(namespace))
            return;
        Map&lt;String, String&gt; directives = requirement.getDirectives();
        String filter = directives.get(
            PackageNamespace.REQUIREMENT_FILTER_DIRECTIVE);
        Set&lt;Filter&gt; filters = policy.get(namespace);
        if (!filters.contains(toFilter(filter)))
            candidates.clear();
    }</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>toFilter</code> method responsible for converting the
      requirement filters and dynamic import package clauses into a Filter is
      left as an exercise to the reader.</para>

      <programlisting>    private Filter toFilter(String s) {
        ...
    }
}</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Weaving Hook</title>

    <para>The Weaving Hook service is a <xref
    linkend="framework.weavinghooks-whiteboard.pattern.ref"/> service. Any
    party that wants to participate in weaving classes can register such a
    service. The framework obtains the Weaving Hook services and calls their
    <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WeavingHook.weave-WovenClass-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method for each class that must be loaded. The
    Weaving Hook services must be called in the service ranking order. See
    <xref linkend="framework.service.servicerankingorder"/>.</para>

    <para>The Weaving Hook <code>weave</code> method is called with a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object that represents the class to be woven. This
    class is similar to the Java <code>ClassFileTransformer</code> class but
    adds bundle wiring information and can be made available in environments
    prior to Java 5. The methods must all be called in privileged blocks. See
    <xref linkend="framework.lifecycle.privilegedcallbacks"/>.</para>

    <para>The <code>WovenClass</code> object provides access to:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.getClassName--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The name of the class being loaded,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.getBundleWiring--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The bundle wiring, which provides access to
        the bundle, the bundle class loaders and the capabilities.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.getProtectionDomain--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The protection domain it is being defined
        in, and</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.getBytes--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The class bytes to be defined.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A Weaving Hook service can use the <code>WovenClass</code> object to
    decide to weave or not to weave. This decision can be based on the bundle
    wiring, the class name, the protection domain, or the bytes. For example,
    the following code checks if the class comes from a specific
    bundle:</para>

    <programlisting>if (wovenClass.getBundleWiring().getBundle().equals(mybundle))
  ...</programlisting>

    <para>If the Weaving Hook service decides to weave the class, it must
    calculate new bytes for the provided Woven Class, these bytes can be set
    with the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.setBytes-byte---"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This implies that ordering is relevant.
    Weaving Hook services that are lower in ranking (called later) will weave
    any of the changes of higher ranking Weaving Hook services. Not all
    combinations of Weaving Hook services will therefore work as
    expected.</para>

    <para>Weaving a class can create new dependencies that are unknown to the
    woven class. In the trace example, the entry and exit traces require
    access to the tracing subsystem, a dependency the original class did not
    have. The <code>WovenClass</code> object allows these extra imports to be
    added as new dynamic import package clauses. The current set of dynamic
    imports for the Woven Class is available from the <code>WovenClass</code>
    <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.getDynamicImports--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This method returns a mutable list of
    <code>String</code> during the <code>weave</code> method, the Weaving Hook
    service can add new dynamic import package clauses to this list while the
    <code>weave</code> method is active. The syntax of the strings is defined
    by the DynamicImport-Package header, see <xref
    linkend="framework.module.dynamicimportpackage"/>. The dynamic imports
    must have a valid syntax, otherwise an Illegal Argument Exception must be
    thrown. These dynamically added dependencies are made visible through the
    <xref linkend="framework.wiring"/> as new requirements. The
    <code>getRevision</code> method of these requirements must return the
    Bundle Revision of the bundle that is woven; that revision will not
    include these synthetic requirements in the
    <code>getDeclaredRequirements</code> method.</para>

    <para>Dynamic imports are the last resort for the framework to find a
    provider when the normal imports fail. The woven class dynamic imports are
    consulted after the dynamic imports specified in the bundle's manifest.
    Frameworks must append all additional dynamic imports in the given order
    but are expected to filter out duplicates for performance reasons.</para>

    <para>The management of the dynamic import is error prone and should be
    handled with care because dynamic imports use wildcards. Wildcards make
    the ordering of the imports important. In the pathological case, a full
    wildcard in the beginning (for example in the manifest) will void any more
    specific clauses that were added by Handlers. Handlers should be as
    specific as possible when adding dynamic import clauses.</para>

    <para>In many cases the additional imports must refer to classes that the
    Handler is already resolved to. In an OSGi framework, the same package can
    be present multiple times. A Handler should therefore ensure that the
    woven bundle gets wired to the correct bundle. One way to achieve this is
    to include the bundle-version and bundle-symbolic-name synthetic
    attributes that are available on every exported package.</para>

    <programlisting>com.acme.weavesupport.core;version=1.2;bundle-version=3.2; «
    bundle-symbolic-name=com.acme.weavesupport</programlisting>

    <para>After calling the last Weaving Hook service, the
    <code>WovenClass</code> object is made <emphasis>complete</emphasis>. The
    framework must make the <code>WovenClass</code> object immutable when it
    is complete. After the Woven Class is complete, the current bytes are then
    used to define the new class. Attempts to modify it, or any of its
    properties, must throw an Exception. After completion, the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.getBytes--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method must return a copy of the byte array that
    was used to define the class.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Concurrency</title>

      <para>Class loads can occur at any time and Weaving Hook services must
      be able to handle concurrent as well as re-entrant calls to the weave
      method. The framework should not hold any locks when calling the Weaving
      Hook services, and Weaving Hook service implementations must be
      thread-safe. Furthermore Weaving Hook services may be re-entrant, and
      should be careful to avoid cycles when weaving.</para>

      <para>For example when a class is being woven, the Weaving Hook may
      implicitly load a class by having a reference to it or the Weaving Hook
      can explicitly load a class. This new class load will also pass through
      the Weaving Hook service, so care must be taken to avoid infinite
      looping.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Error Handling</title>

      <para>Weaving hooks are very low level and care must be taken by the
      Weaving Hook services to not disrupt normal class loading. In the case
      that a weaving hook throws an unexpected exception the framework must do
      the following:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the exception is not a Weaving Exception:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The framework must blacklist the weaving hook registration
              and never call that Weaving Hook service again as long as it is
              registered. This Weaving Hook service is considered
              <emphasis>blacklisted</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A framework event of type <code>ERROR</code> should be
          published that must include the Exception thrown by the Weaving Hook
          service. The source must be the bundle registering the Weaving Hook
          service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <code>WovenClass</code> object must be marked as complete.
          All remaining Weaving Hook services must be skipped.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The bundle class loader must throw a
          <code>ClassFormatError</code> with the cause being the exception
          thrown by the Weaving Hook service.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="framework.weavinghooks-wovenclasslistener">
    <title>Woven Class Listener</title>

    <para>The Woven Class Listener service is a <xref
    linkend="framework.weavinghooks-whiteboard.pattern.ref"/> service. Any
    party that wants to receive notifications of woven class state transitions
    can register such a service. The framework obtains the Woven Class
    Listener services and calls their <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClassListener.modified-WovenClass-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method whenever a Woven Class undergoes a state
    transition. The framework must not obtain Woven Class Listener services if there 
    are no Weaving Hook services registered. In this case, if the party needs to receive 
    notifications of woven class state transitions then a no-op Weaving Hook service implementation 
    can be registered to ensure Woven Class Listener services are called.</para>

    <para>The Woven Class Listener <code>modified</code> method is called with
    a <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object that represents the woven class that
    underwent a state transition. The method must be called in a privileged
    block. See <xref
    linkend="framework.lifecycle.privilegedcallbacks"/>.</para>

    <para>The following diagram depicts the state transitions of a Woven
    Class.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Woven Class State Diagram</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.017in"
                     contentwidth="7.125in" fileref="wovenClass-states.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Woven Class Listeners are not notified of the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state because the Woven Class is mutable and
    listeners are not permitted to mutate the Woven Class. For all states
    observed by Woven Class Listeners, the Woven Class is effectively
    immutable. The first notification received for a given Woven Class is
    either the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMING_FAILED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state. The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state occurs after all Weaving Hooks have been
    notified but before the class has been defined or the bundle wiring has
    been updated for any additional dynamic imports. The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMING_FAILED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state occurs if any Weaving Hook throws an
    exception. After the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state, a Woven Class can transition to either the
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.DEFINED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state or the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.DEFINE_FAILED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state. The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.DEFINED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state occurs when the class was defined
    successfully and after the bundle wiring has been updated. The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.DEFINE_FAILED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state occurs if a class definition error
    occurred.</para>

    <para><xref linkend="framework.weavinghooks-woven.class.state.table"/>
    describes the states of a Woven Class in more detail.</para>

    <table xml:id="framework.weavinghooks-woven.class.state.table">
      <title>Woven Class State Table</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1.5*"/>

        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>State</entry>

            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMING"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>A bundle class load request was
            made.</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Weaving is incomplete.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The class is undefined.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The Woven Class is mutable.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Weaving Hooks are notified but Woven Class Listeners
                  are not.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMED"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>All Weaving Hooks have been
            notified.</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Weaving is complete.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The class is undefined.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The Woven Class is effectively immutable.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Woven Class Listeners are notified.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.TRANSFORMING_FAILED"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>A Weaving Hook threw an
            exception.</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Weaving is incomplete.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The class is undefined.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The Woven Class is effectively immutable.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Woven Class Listeners are notified.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.DEFINED"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>All Woven Class Listeners have been notified. The
            class has been defined.</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Weaving is complete.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The class is defined.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The Woven Class is effectively immutable.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Woven Class Listeners are notified.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.DEFINE_FAILED"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>All Weaving Hooks have been notified. A class
            definition failure occurred.</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Weaving is complete.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The class is undefined.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The Woven Class is effectively immutable.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Woven Class Listeners are notified.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <section>
      <title>Concurrency</title>

      <para>Class loads can occur at any time, and Woven Class Listeners must
      be able to handle concurrent calls to the <code>modified</code> method.
      The framework should not hold any locks when calling Woven Class
      Listeners, and Woven Class Listener implementations must be thread-safe.
      Woven Class Listeners must be synchronously called by the framework when
      a Woven Class completes a state transition. The woven class processing
      will not proceed until all Woven Class Listeners are done.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Error Handling</title>

      <para>Woven Class Listeners must not cause the weaving process to fail.
      If a Woven Class Listener throws an exception, the framework should log
      the exception but otherwise ignore it.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <section>
      <title>Weaving Hooks</title>

      <para>All hooks described in this specification are highly complex
      facilities that require great care in their implementation to maintain
      the Framework invariants. It is therefore important that in a secure
      system the permission to register these hooks is only given to
      privileged bundles.</para>

      <para>In this case, the user of the hook services is the framework.
      Therefore, there is never a need to provide:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>ServicePermission[..WeavingHook,GET]</code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Implementers of these hooks must have:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>ServicePermission[..WeavingHook,REGISTER]</code> for
          Weaving Hook services.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In addition, a Weaving Hook must have Admin Permission with the
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.AdminPermission.WEAVE"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> action to be able to use the methods on the
      <code>WovenClass</code> object that mutate the state like <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.setBytes-byte---"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.getBytes--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, and the mutating methods on the list returned
      by <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.WovenClass.getDynamicImports--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. Moreover, a Weaving Hook must have Package
      Permission with the <code>IMPORT</code> action in order to add or
      replace dynamic imports.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Woven Bundles</title>

      <para>The Framework must grant implied <code>PackagePermission[somePkg,
      IMPORT]</code> permissions to bundles whose classes are being woven with
      additional dynamic imports, assuming the weaver has a matching package
      import permission. The permission check for the weaver must occur during
      any call to the list that results in the addition or setting of a
      dynamic import. If the check fails, a SecurityException must be thrown.
      If it succeeds, the implied permission must be granted to the woven
      bundle immediately before defining the class.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Woven Class Listeners</title>

      <para>Implementers of these listeners must have:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>ServicePermission[..WovenClassListener,REGISTER]</code>
          for Woven Class Listener services.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="framework.weavinghooks-whiteboard.pattern.ref"><title>Whiteboard
      Pattern</title>https://www.osgi.org/wp-content/uploads/whiteboard1.pdf</bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
