<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="1" revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="introduction"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This compendium contains the specifications of all current OSGi
  services.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Reader Level</title>

    <para>This specification is written for the following audiences:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Application developers</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Framework and system service developers (system
        developers)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Architects</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>This specification assumes that the reader has at least one year of
    practical experience in writing Java programs. Experience with embedded
    systems and server-environments is a plus. Application developers must be
    aware that the OSGi environment is significantly more dynamic than
    traditional desktop or server environments.</para>

    <para>System developers require a very deep understanding of Java. At
    least three years of Java coding experience in a system environment is
    recommended. A Framework implementation will use areas of Java that are
    not normally encountered in traditional applications. Detailed
    understanding is required of class loaders, garbage collection, Java 2
    security, and Java native library loading.</para>

    <para>Architects should focus on the introduction of each subject. This
    introduction contains a general overview of the subject, the requirements
    that influenced its design, and a short description of its operation as
    well as the entities that are used. The introductory sections require
    knowledge of Java concepts like classes and interfaces, but should not
    require coding experience.</para>

    <para>Most of these specifications are equally applicable to application
    developers and system developers.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Version Information</title>

    <para>This document is the IoT Specification for the OSGi
    Compendium <xref endterm="iot.book-release" linkend="iot.book"/>.</para>

    <section xml:id="intro.core.release">
      <title>OSGi Core Release 7</title>

      <para>This specification is based on the OSGi Core Release 7. This
      specification can be downloaded from:</para>

      <programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://www.osgi.org/developer/specifications/"/></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Component Versions</title>

      <para>Components in this specification have their own specification
      version, independent of this specification. The following table
      summarizes the packages and specification versions for the different
      subjects.</para>

      <table pgwide="1">
        <title>Packages and versions</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="3*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3.5*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="0.8*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Item</entry>

              <entry>Package</entry>

              <entry>Version</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.onem2m"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="service.onem2m-version"
              linkend="service.onem2m"/></code></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>When a component is represented in a bundle, a
      <code>version</code> attribute is needed in the declaration of the
      Import-Package or Export-Package manifest headers.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i311124"><title>OSGi
      Specifications</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://www.osgi.org/developer/specifications/"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>

</chapter>
