<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="128"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="service.war"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Web Applications Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo xml:id="service.war-version">Version 1.0</releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The Java EE Servlet model has provided the backbone of web based
    applications written in Java. Given the popularity of the Servlet model,
    it is desirable to provide a seamless experience for deploying existing
    and new web applications to Servlet containers operating on the OSGi
    framework. Previously, the Http Service in the catalog of OSGi compendium
    services was the only model specified in OSGi to support the Servlet
    programming model. However, the Http Service, as defined in that
    specification, is focused on the run time, as well as manual construction
    of the servlet context, and thus does not actually support the standard
    Servlet packaging and deployment model based on the Web Application
    Archive, or WAR format.</para>

    <para>This specification defines the Web Application Bundle, which is a
    bundle that performs the same role as the WAR in Java EE. A WAB uses the
    OSGi life cycle and class/resource loading rules instead of the standard
    Java EE environment. WABs are normal bundles and can leverage the full set
    of features of the OSGi framework.</para>

    <para>Web applications can also be installed as traditional WARs through a
    manifest rewriting process. During the install, a WAR is transformed into
    a WAB. This specification was based on ideas developed in <xref
    linkend="i3102743"/>.</para>

    <para>This Web Application Specification provides support for web
    applications written to the Servlet 2.5 specification, or later. Given
    that Java Server Pages, or JSPs, are an integral part of the Java EE web
    application framework, this specification also supports the JSP 2.1
    specification or greater if present. This specification details how a web
    application packaged as a WAR may be installed into an OSGi framework, as
    well as how this application may interact with, and obtain, OSGi
    services.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Extender</emphasis> - Enable the configuration of
          components inside a bundle based on configuration data provided by
          the bundle developer.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Services</emphasis> - Enable the use of OSGi
          services within a Web Application.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Deployment</emphasis> - Define a mechanism to deploy
          Web Applications, both OSGi aware and non OSGi aware, in the OSGi
          environment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>WAR File Support</emphasis> - Transparently enhance
          the contents of a WAR's manifest during installation to add any
          headers necessary to deploy a WAR as an OSGi bundle.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web Container</emphasis> - The implementation of
          this specification. Consists of a Web Extender, a Web URL Handler
          and a Servlet and Java Server Pages Web Runtime environment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web Application</emphasis> - A program that has web
          accessible content. A Web Application is defined by <xref
          linkend="i3076362"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web Application Archive (WAR)</emphasis> - The Java
          EE standard resource format layout of a JAR file that contains a
          deployable Web Application.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web Application Bundle</emphasis> - A Web
          Application deployed as an OSGi bundle, also called a WAB.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>WAB</emphasis> - The acronym for a Web Application
          Bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web Extender</emphasis> - An extender bundle that
          deploys the Web Application Bundle to the Web Runtime based on the
          Web Application Bundle's state.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web URL Handler</emphasis> - A URL handler which
          transforms a Web Application Archive (WAR) to conform to the OSGi
          specifications during installation by installing the WAR through a
          special URL so that it becomes a Web Application Bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web Runtime</emphasis> - A Java Server Pages and
          Servlet environment, receiving the web requests and translating them
          to servlet calls, either from Web Application servlets or other
          classes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web Component</emphasis> - A Servlet or Java Server
          Page (JSP).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Servlet</emphasis> - An object implementing the
          Servlet interface; this is for the request handler model in the
          Servlet Specification.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Servlet Context</emphasis> - The model representing
          the Web Application in the Servlet Specification.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Java Server Page (JSP)</emphasis> - A declarative,
          template based model for generating content through Servlets that is
          optionally supported by the Web Runtime.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Context Path</emphasis> - The URI path prefix of any
          content accessible in a Web Application.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure xml:id="i3084702">
        <title>Web Container Entities</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.028in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="web-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3100968">
      <title>Dependencies</title>

      <para>The package dependencies for the clients of this specification are
      listed in the following table.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Dependency versions</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="3*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1.5*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="3*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Packages</entry>

              <entry>Export Version</entry>

              <entry>Client Import Range</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet</code></entry>

              <entry><code>2.5</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[2.5,3.0)</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet.http</code></entry>

              <entry><code>2.5</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[2.5,3.0)</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet.jsp.el</code></entry>

              <entry><code>2.1</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[2.1,3.0)</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet.jsp.jstl.core</code></entry>

              <entry><code>1.2</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[1.2,2.0)</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet.jsp.jstl.fmt</code></entry>

              <entry><code>1.2</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[1.2,2.0)</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet.jsp.jstl.sql</code></entry>

              <entry><code>1.2</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[1.2,2.0)</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet.jsp.jstl.tlv</code></entry>

              <entry><code>1.2</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[1.2,2.0)</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet.jsp.resources</code></entry>

              <entry><code>2.1</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[2.1,3.0)</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet.jsp.tagext</code></entry>

              <entry><code>2.1</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[2.1,3.0)</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>javax.servlet.jsp</code></entry>

              <entry><code>2.1</code></entry>

              <entry><code>[2.1,3.0)</code></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>JSP is optional for the Web Runtime.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>The Web Application Specification is composed of a number of
      cooperating parts, which are implemented by a <emphasis>Web
      Container</emphasis>. A Web Container consists of:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web Extender</emphasis> - Responsible for deploying
          Web Application Bundles (WAB) to a Web Runtime,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web Runtime</emphasis> - Provides support for
          Servlet and optionally for JSPs, and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Web URL Handler</emphasis> - Provides on-the-fly
          enhancements of non-OSGi aware Web ARchives (WAR) so that they can
          be installed as a WAB.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>WABs are standard OSGi bundles with additional headers in the
      manifest that serve as deployment instructions to the Web Extender. WABs
      can also contain the Java EE defined <code>web.xml</code> descriptor in
      the <code>WEB-INF</code>/ directory. When the Web Extender detects that
      a WAB is ready the Web Extender deploys the WAB to the Web Runtime using
      information contained in the <code>web.xml</code> descriptor and the
      appropriate manifest headers. The Bundle Context of the WAB is made
      available as a Servlet Context attribute. From that point, the Web
      Runtime will use the information in the WAB to serve content to any
      requests. Both dynamic as well as static content can be provided.</para>

      <para>The Web URL Handler allows the deployment of an unmodified WAR as
      a WAB into the OSGi framework. This Web URL Handler provides a URL
      stream handler with the <code>webbundle:</code> scheme. Installing a WAR
      with this scheme allows the Web URL Handler to interpose itself as a
      filter on the input stream of the contents of the WAR, transforming the
      contents of the WAR into a WAB. The Web URL Handler rewrites the
      manifest by adding necessary headers to turn the WAR into a valid WAB.
      Additional headers can be added to the manifest that serve as
      instructions to the Web Extender.</para>

      <para>After a WAB has been deployed to the Web Runtime, the Web
      Application can interact with the OSGi framework via the provided Bundle
      Context. The Servlet Context associated with this WAB follows the same
      life cycle as the WAB. That is, when the underlying Web Application
      Bundle is started, the Web Application is deployed to the Web Runtime.
      When the underlying Web Application Bundle is stopped because of a
      failure or other reason, the Web Application is undeployed from the Web
      Run-time.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Web Container</title>

    <para>A Web Container is the implementation of this specification. It
    consists of the following parts:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Web Extender</emphasis> - Detects Web Application
        Bundles (WAB) and tracks their life cycle. Ready WABs are deployed to
        the Web Runtime.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Web Runtime</emphasis> - A runtime environment for a
        Web Application that supports the <xref linkend="i3076808"/> and <xref
        linkend="i3076835"/> or later. The Web Runtime receives web requests
        and calls the appropriate methods on servlets. Servlets can be
        implemented by classes or Java Server Pages.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Web URL Handler</emphasis> - A URL stream handler
        providing the <code>webbundle:</code> scheme. This scheme can be used
        to install WARs in an OSGi framework. The Web URL Handler will then
        automatically add the required OSGi manifest headers.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The extender, runtime, and handler can all be implemented in the
    same or different bundles and use unspecified mechanisms to communicate.
    This specification uses the defined names of the sub-parts as the actor;
    the term Web Container is the general name for this collection of
    actors.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Web Application Bundle</title>

    <para>Bundles are the deployment and management entities under OSGi. A
    <emphasis>Web Application Bundle</emphasis> (WAB) is deployed as an OSGi
    bundle in an OSGi framework, where each WAB provides a single
    <emphasis>Web Application</emphasis>. A Web Application can make use of
    the <xref linkend="i3076808"/> and <xref linkend="i3076835"/> programming
    models, or later, to provide content for the web.</para>

    <para>A WAB is defined as a normal OSGi bundle that contains web
    accessible content, both static and dynamic. There are no restrictions on
    bundles. A Web Application can be packaged as a WAB during application
    development, or it can be transparently created at bundle install time
    from a standard Web Application aRchive (WAR) via transformation by the
    Web URL Handler, see <xref linkend="i3100445"/>.</para>

    <para>A WAB is a valid OSGi bundle and as such must fully describe its
    dependencies and exports (if any). As Web Applications are modularized
    further into multiple bundles (and not deployed as WAR files only) it is
    possible that a WAB can have dependencies on other bundles.</para>

    <para>A WAB may be installed into the framework using the
    <code>BundleContext.installBundle</code> methods. Once installed, a WAB's
    life cycle is managed just like any other bundle in the framework. This
    life cycle is tracked by the Web Extender who will then deploy the Web
    Application to the Web Runtime when the WAB is ready and will undeploy it
    when the WAB is no longer ready. This state is depicted in <xref
    linkend="i3086869"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i3086869">
      <title>State diagram Web Application</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.139in"
                     contentwidth="7.125in" fileref="web-app-states.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section xml:id="i3077053">
      <title>WAB Definition</title>

      <para>A WAB is differentiated from non Web Application bundles through
      the specification of the additional manifest header:</para>

      <programlisting>Web-ContextPath ::= path</programlisting>

      <para>The Web-ContextPath header specifies the value of the
      <emphasis>Context Path</emphasis> of the Web Application. All web
      accessible content of the Web Application is available on the web server
      relative to this Context Path. For example, if the context path is
      <code>/sales</code>, then the URL would be something like:
      <code>http://www.acme.com/sales</code>. The Context Path must always
      begin with a solidus (<code>'/' \u002F</code>).</para>

      <para>The Web Extender must not recognize a bundle as a Web Application
      unless the Web-ContextPath header is present in its manifest and the
      header value is a valid path for the bundle.</para>

      <para>A WAB can optionally contain a <code>web.xml</code> resource to
      specify additional configuration. This <code>web.xml</code> must be
      found with the Bundle <code>findEntries</code> method at the
      path:</para>

      <programlisting> <code>WEB-INF/web.xml</code></programlisting>

      <para>The <code>findEntries</code> method includes fragments, allowing
      the <code>web.xml</code> to be provided by a fragment. The Web Extender
      must fully support a <code>web.xml</code> descriptor that specifies
      Servlets, Filters, or Listeners whose classes are required by the
      WAB.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Starting the Web Application Bundle</title>

      <para>A WAB's Web Application must be <emphasis>deployed</emphasis>
      while the WAB is <emphasis>ready</emphasis>. Deployed means that the Web
      Application is available for web requests. Once deployed, a WAB can
      serve its web content on the given Context Path. Ready is when the
      WAB:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Is in the <code>ACTIVE</code> state, or</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Has a <code>lazy</code> activation policy and is in the
          <code>STARTING</code> state.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Web Extender should ensure that serving static content from
      the WAB does not activate the WAB when it has a <code>lazy</code>
      activation policy.</para>

      <para>To deploy the WAB, the Web Extender must initiate the deploying of
      the Web Application into a Web Runtime. This is outlined in the
      following steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Wait for the WAB to become ready. The following steps can take
          place asynchronously with the starting of the WAB.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Post an <code>org/osgi/service/web/DEPLOYING</code> event. See
          <xref linkend="i3089230"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Validate that the <code>Web-ContextPath</code> manifest header
          does not match the Context Path of any other currently deployed web
          application. If the Context Path value is already in use by another
          Web Application, then the Web Application must not be deployed, and
          the deployment fails, see <xref linkend="i3078658"/>. The Web
          Extender should log the collision. If the prior Web Application with
          the same Context Path is undeployed later, this Web Application
          should be considered as a candidate, see <xref
          linkend="i3091603"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Web Runtime processes deployment information by processing
          the <code>web.xml</code> descriptor, if present. The Web Container
          must perform the necessary initialization of Web Components in the
          WAB as described in the <xref linkend="i3076808"/>. This involves
          the following sub-steps in the given order:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Create a Servlet Context for the Web Application.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Instantiate configured Servlet event listeners.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Instantiate configured application filter instances
              etc.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The Web Runtime is required to complete instantiation of
          listeners prior to the start of execution of the first request into
          the Web Application by the Web Runtime. Attribute changes to the
          Servlet Context and Http Session objects can occur concurrently. The
          Servlet Container is not required to synchronize the resulting
          notifications to attribute listener classes. Listener classes that
          maintain state are responsible for the integrity of the data and
          should handle this case explicitly.</para>

          <para>If event listeners or filters are used in the
          <code>web.xml</code>, then the Web Runtime will load the
          corresponding classes from the bundle activating the bundle if it
          was lazily started. Such a configuration will therefore not act
          lazily.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Publish the Servlet Context as a service with identifying
          service properties, see <xref linkend="i3078599"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Post an <code>org/osgi/service/web/DEPLOYED</code> event to
          indicate that the web application is now available. See <xref
          linkend="i3089230"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>If at any moment before the
      <code>org/osgi/service/web/DEPLOYED</code> event is published the
      deployment of the WAB fails, then the WAB deployment fails, see <xref
      linkend="i3078658"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3078658">
      <title>Failure</title>

      <para>Any validation failures must prevent the Web Application from
      being accessible via HTTP, and must result in a
      <code>org/osgi/service/web/FAILED</code> event being posted. See <xref
      linkend="i3089230"/>. The situation after the failure must be as if the
      WAB was never deployed.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3078599">
      <title>Publishing the Servlet Context</title>

      <para>To help management agents with tracking the state of Web
      Applications, the Web Extender must register the Servlet Context of the
      WAB as a service, using the Bundle Context of the WAB. The Servlet
      Context service must be registered with the service properties listed in
      the following table.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Servlet Context Service Properties</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="3*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Property Name</entry>

              <entry>Type</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>osgi.web.symbolicname</code></entry>

              <entry><code>String</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The symbolic name for the Web Application
              Bundle</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>osgi.web.version</code></entry>

              <entry><code>String</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The version of the Web Application Bundle. If no
              Bundle-Version is specified in the manifest then this property
              must not be set.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>osgi.web.contextpath</code></entry>

              <entry><code>String</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The Context Path from which the WAB's content will
              be served.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3096883">
      <title>Static Content</title>

      <para>A deployed WAB provides content on requests from the web. For
      certain access paths, this can serve content from the resources of the
      web application: this is called <emphasis>static content</emphasis>. A
      Web Runtime must use the Servlet Context resource access methods to
      service static content, the resource loading strategy for these methods
      is based on the <code>findEntries</code> method, see <xref
      linkend="i3082990"/>. For confidentiality reasons, a Web Runtime must
      not return any static content for paths that start with one of the
      following prefixes:</para>

      <programlisting>WEB-INF/
OSGI-INF/
META-INF/
OSGI-OPT/</programlisting>

      <para>These <emphasis>protected directories</emphasis> are intended to
      shield code content used for dynamic content generation from
      accidentally being served over the web, which is a potential attack
      route. In the servlet specification, the <code>WEB-INF</code>/ directory
      in the WAR is protected in such a way. However, this protection is not
      complete. A dependent JAR can actually be placed outside the WEB-INF
      directory that can then be served as static content. The same is true
      for a WAB. Though the protected directories must never be served over
      the web, there are no other checks required to verify that no content
      can be served that is also available from the Bundle class path.</para>

      <para>It is the responsibility of the author of the WAB to ensure that
      confidential information remains confidential by placing it in one of
      the protected directories. WAB bundles should be constructed in such a
      way that they do not accidentally expose code or confidential
      information. The simplest way to achieve this is to follow the WAR model
      where code is placed in the <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> directory and
      this directory is placed on the Bundle's class path as the first entry.
      For example:</para>

      <programlisting>Bundle-ClassPath: WEB-INF/classes, WEB-INF/lib/acme.jar</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Dynamic Content</title>

      <para>Dynamic content is content that uses code to generate the content,
      for example a servlet. This code must be loaded from the bundle with the
      Bundle <code>loadClass</code> method, following all the Bundle class
      path rules.</para>

      <para>Unlike a WAR, a WAB is not constrained to package classes and code
      resources in the <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> directory or dependent
      JARs in <code>WEB-INF/lib/</code> only. These entries can be packaged in
      any way that's valid for an OSGi bundle as long as such directories and
      JARs are part of bundle class path as set with the Bundle-ClassPath
      header and any attached fragments. JARs that are specified in the
      Bundle-ClassPath header are treated like JARs in the
      <code>WEB-INF/lib/</code> directory of the Servlet specification.
      Similarly, any directory that is part of the Bundle-ClassPath header is
      treated like <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> directory of the Servlet
      specification.</para>

      <para>Like WARs, code content that is placed outside the protected
      directories can be served up to clients as static content.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Content Serving Example</title>

      <para>This example consists of a WAB with the following contents:</para>

      <programlisting>acme.jar:
    Bundle-ClassPath: WEB-INF/classes, LIB/bar.jar
    Web-ContextPath: /acme

    WEB-INF/lib/foo.jar
    LIB/bar.jar
    index.html
    favicon.ico</programlisting>

      <para>The content of the embedded JARs <code>foo.jar</code> and
      <code>bar.jar</code> is:</para>

      <programlisting>foo.jar:                bar.jar:
    META-INF/foo.tld        META-INF/bar.tld
    foo/FooTag.class        bar/BarTag.class</programlisting>

      <para>Assuming there are no special rules in place then the following
      lists specifies the result of a number of web requests for static
      content:</para>

      <programlisting>/acme/index.html            acme.wab:index.html
/acme/favicon.ico           acme.wab:favicon.ico
/acme/WEB-INF/lib/foo.jar   not found because protecteddirectory
/acme/LIB/bar.jar           acme.wab:LIB/bar.jar  (code, but not protected)</programlisting>

      <para>In this example, the tag classes in <code>bar.jar</code> must be
      found (if JSP is supported) but the tag classes in <code>foo.jar</code>
      must not because <code>foo.jar</code> is not part of the bundle class
      path.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3091603">
      <title>Stopping the Web Application Bundle</title>

      <para>A web application is stopped by stopping the corresponding WAB. In
      response to a WAB <code>STOPPING</code> event, the Web Extender must
      <emphasis>undeploy</emphasis> the corresponding Web Application from the
      Servlet Container and clean up any resources. This undeploying must
      occur synchronously with the WAB's stopping event. This will involve the
      following steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>An <code>org/osgi/service/web/UNDEPLOYING</code> event is
          posted to signal that a Web Application will be removed. See <xref
          linkend="i3089230"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Unregister the corresponding Servlet Context service</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Web Runtime must stop serving content from the Web
          Application.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Web Runtime must clean up any Web Application specific
          resources as per servlet 2.5 specification.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Emit an <code>org/osgi/service/web/UNDEPLOYED</code> event.
          See <xref linkend="i3089230"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It is possible that there are one or more
          <emphasis>colliding</emphasis> WABs because they had the same
          Context Path as this stopped WAB. If such colliding WABs exists then
          the Web Extender must attempt to deploy the colliding WAB with the
          lowest bundle id.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Any failure during undeploying should be logged but must not stop
      the cleaning up of resources and notification of (other) listeners as
      well as handling any collisions.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Uninstalling the Web Application Bundle</title>

      <para>A web application can be uninstalled by uninstalling the
      corresponding WAB. The WAB will be uninstalled from the OSGi
      framework.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Stopping of the Web Extender</title>

      <para>When the Web Extender is stopped all deployed WABs are undeployed
      as described in <xref linkend="i3091603"/>. Although the WAB is
      undeployed it remains in the <code>ACTIVE</code> state. When the Web
      Extender leaves the <code>STOPPING</code> state all WABs will have been
      undeployed.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i3100445">
    <title>Web URL Handler</title>

    <para>The Web URL Handler acts as a filter on the Input Stream of an
    install operation. It receives the WAB or WAR and it then generates a JAR
    that conforms to the WAB specification by rewriting the manifest resource.
    This process is depicted in <xref linkend="i3100518"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i3100518">
      <title>Web URL Handler</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.498in"
                     contentwidth="7.000in"
                     fileref="webbundle-url-handler.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When the Web Container bundle is installed it must provide the
    <code>webbundle:</code> scheme to the URL class. The Web URL Handler has
    two primary responsibilities:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>WAB</emphasis> - If the source is already a bundle
        then only the Web-ContextPath can be set or overwritten.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>WAR</emphasis> - If the source is a WAR (that is, it
        must not contain any OSGi defined headers) then convert the WAR into a
        WAB.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Web URL Handler can take parameters from the query arguments of
    the install URL, see <xref linkend="i3086131"/>.</para>

    <para>The URL handler must validate query parameters, and ensure that the
    manifest rewriting results in valid OSGi headers. Any validation failures
    must result in Bundle Exception being thrown and the bundle install must
    fail.</para>

    <para>Once a WAB is generated and installed, its life cycle is managed
    just like any other bundle in the framework.</para>

    <section>
      <title>URL Scheme</title>

      <para>The Web URL Handler's scheme is defined to be:</para>

      <programlisting>scheme     ::= 'webbundle:' embedded '?' web-params
embedded   ::= &lt;embedded URL according to RFC 1738&gt;
web-params ::= ( web-param ( '&amp;' web-param )* )?
web-param  ::= &lt;key&gt; '=' &lt;value&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>web-param</code> &lt;<code>key&gt;</code> and
      <code>&lt;value&gt;</code> as well as the <code>&lt;embedded
      url&gt;</code> must follow <xref linkend="i3079490"/> for their escaping
      and character set rules.A Web URL must further follow all the rules of a
      URL. Whitespaces are not allowed between terms.</para>

      <para>An example for a <code>webbundle:</code> URL:</para>

      <programlisting>webbundle:http://www.acme.com:8021/sales.war?Web-ContextPath=/sales</programlisting>

      <para>Any URL scheme understood by the framework can be embedded, such
      as an <code>http:</code>, or <code>file:</code> URL. Some forms of
      embedded URL also contain URL query parameters and this must be
      supported. The embedded URL most be encoded as a standard URL. That is,
      the control characters like colon (<code>':' \u003A</code>), solidus
      (<code>'/' \u002F</code>), percent (<code>'%' \u0025</code>), and
      ampersand (<code>'&amp;' \u0026</code>) must not be encoded. Thus the
      value returned from the <code>getPath</code> method may contain a query
      part. Any implementation must take care to preserve both the query
      parameters for the embedded URL, and for the complete
      <code>webbundle:</code> URL. A question mark must always follow the
      embedded URL to simplify this processing. The following example shows an
      HTTP URL with some query parameters:</para>

      <programlisting>webbundle:http://www.acme.com/sales?id=123?Bundle-SymbolicName=com.example&amp;
                                             Web-ContextPath=/</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>URL Parsing</title>

      <para>The <code>URL</code> object for a <code>webbundle:</code> URL must
      return the following values for the given methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>getProtocol</code> - <code>webbundle</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>getPath</code> - The complete embedded URL</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>getQuery</code> - The parameters for processing of the
          manifest.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For the following example:</para>

      <programlisting>webbundle:http://acme.com/repo?war=example.war?Web-ContextPath=/sales</programlisting>

      <para>The aforementioned methods must return:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>getProtocol</code> - <code>webbundle</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>getPath</code> -
          <code>http://acme.com/repo?war=example.war</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>getQuery</code> -
          <code>Web-ContextPath=/sales</code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3086131">
      <title>URL Parameters</title>

      <para>All the parameters in the <code>webbundle:</code> URL are optional
      except for the Web-ContextPath parameter. The parameter names are case
      insensitive, but their values must be treated as case sensitive. <xref
      linkend="service.war-webbundle.url.parameters"/> describes the
      parameters that must be supported by any <code>webbundle:</code> URL
      Stream handler. A Web URL Handler is allowed to support additional
      parameters.</para>

      <table xml:id="service.war-webbundle.url.parameters">
        <title>Web bundle URL Parameters</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2.5*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Parameter Name</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-SymbolicName</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The desired symbolic name for the resulting
              WAB.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-Version</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The version of the resulting WAB. The value of this
              parameter must follow the OSGi versioning syntax.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-ManifestVersion</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The desired bundle manifest version. Currently, the
              only valid value for this parameter is
              <code>2</code>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Import-Package</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A list of packages that the war file depends
              on.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Web-ContextPath</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The Context Path from which the Servlet Container
              should serve content from the resulting WAB. This is the only
              valid parameter when the input JAR is already a bundle. This
              parameter must be specified.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>WAB Modification</title>

      <para>The Web URL Handler can set or modify the Web-ContextPath of a WAB
      if the input source is already a bundle. It must be considered as a
      bundle when any of the OSGi defined headers listed in <xref
      linkend="service.war-webbundle.url.parameters"/> is present in the
      bundle.</para>

      <para>For WAB Modification, the Web URL Handler must only support the
      Web-ContextPath parameter and it must not modify any existing headers
      other than the Web-ContextPath. Any other parameter given must result in
      a Bundle Exception.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>WAR Manifest Processing</title>

      <para>The Web URL Handler is designed to support the transparent
      deployment of Java EE Web ARchives (WAR). Such WARs are ignorant of the
      requirements of the underlying OSGi framework that hosts the Web
      Runtime. These WARs are not proper OSGi bundles because they do not
      contain the necessary metadata in the manifest. For example, a WAR
      without a Bundle-ManifestVersion, Import-Package, and other headers
      cannot operate in an OSGi framework.</para>

      <para>The Web URL Handler implementation copies the contents of the
      embedded URL to the output and rewrites the manifest headers based on
      the given parameters. The result must be a WAB.</para>

      <para>Any parameters specified must be treated as manifest headers for
      the web. The following manifest headers must be set to the following
      values if not specified:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Bundle-ManifestVersion</code> - Must be set to 2.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>Bundle-SymbolicName</code> - Generated in an
          implementation specific way.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>Bundle-ClassPath</code> - Must consist of:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><code>WEB-INF/classes</code></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>All JARs from the <code>WEB-INF/lib</code> directory in
              the WAR. The order of these embedded JARs is unspecified.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If these JARs declare dependencies in their manifest on
              other JARs in the bundle, then these jars must also be appended
              to the Bundle-ClassPath header. The process of detecting JAR
              dependencies must be performed recursively as indicated in the
              Servlet Specification.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>Web-ContextPath</code> - The Web-ContextPath must be
          specified as a parameter. This Context Path should start with a
          leading solidus (<code>'/' \u002F</code>). The Web URL handler must
          add the preceding solidus it if it is not present.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Web URL Handler is responsible for managing the import
      dependencies of the WAR. Implementations are free to handle the import
      dependencies in an implementation defined way. They can augment the
      Import-Package header with byte-code analysis information, add a fixed
      set of clauses, and/or use the DynamicImport-Package header as last
      resort.</para>

      <para>Any other manifest headers defined as a parameter or WAR manifest
      header not described in this section must be copied to the WAB manifest
      by the Web URL Handler. Such an header must not be modified.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Signed WAR files</title>

      <para>When a signed WAR file is installed using the Web URL Handler,
      then the manifest rewriting process invalidates the signatures in the
      bundle. The OSGi specification requires fully signed bundles for
      security reasons, security resources in partially signed bundles are
      ignored.</para>

      <para>If the use of the signing metadata is required, the WAR must be
      converted to a WAB during development and then signed. In this case, the
      Web URL Handler cannot be used. If the Web URL Handler is presented with
      a signed WAR, the manifest name sections that contain the resource's
      check sums must be stripped out by the URL stream handler. Any signer
      files ( <code>*.SF</code> and their corresponding <code>DSA/RSA</code>
      signature files) must also be removed.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i3089230">
    <title>Events</title>

    <para>The Web Extender must track all WABs in the OSGi framework in which
    the Web Extender is installed. The Web Extender must post Event Admin
    events, which is asynchronous, at crucial points in its processing. The
    topic of the event must be one of the following values:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>org/osgi/service/web/DEPLOYING</code> - The Web Extender
        has accepted a WAB and started the process of deploying a Web
        Application.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>org/osgi/service/web/DEPLOYED</code> - The Web Extender
        has finished deploying a Web Application, and the Web Application is
        now available for web requests on its Context Path.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>org/osgi/service/web/UNDEPLOYING</code> - The web extender
        started undeploying the Web Application in response to its
        corresponding WAB being stopped or the Web Extender is stopped.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>org/osgi/service/web/UNDEPLOYED</code> - The Web Extender
        has undeployed the Web Application. The application is no longer
        available for web requests.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>org/osgi/service/web/FAILED</code> - The Web Extender has
        failed to deploy the Web Application, this event can be fired after
        the <code>DEPLOYING</code> event has fired and indicates that no
        DEPLOYED event will be fired.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For each event topic above, the following properties must be
    published:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>bundle.symbolicName</code> - (<code>String</code>) The
        bundle symbolic name of the WAB.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>bundle.id</code> - (<code>Long</code>) The bundle id of
        the WAB.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>bundle</code> - (<code>Bundle)</code> The Bundle object of
        the WAB.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>bundle.version</code> - (<code>Version)</code> The version
        of the WAB.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>context.path</code> - (<code>String</code>) The Context
        Path of the Web Application.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>timestamp - (Long</code>) The time when the event
        occurred</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>extender.bundle</code> - (<code>Bundle</code>) The
        <code>Bundle</code> object of the Web Extender Bundle</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>extender.bundle.id</code> - (<code>Long</code>) The id of
        the Web Extender Bundle.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>extender.bundle.symbolicName</code> -
        (<code>String)</code> The symbolic name of the Web Extender
        Bundle.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>extender.bundle.version</code> - (<code>Version</code>)
        The version of the Web Extender Bundle.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In addition, the <code>org/osgi/service/web/FAILED</code> event must
    also have the following property:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>exception</code> - (Throwable) If an exception caused the
        failure, an exception detailing the error that occurred during the
        deployment of the WAB.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>collision</code> - (<code>String</code>) If a name
        collision occurred, the Web-ContextPath that had a collision</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>collision.bundles</code> -
        (<code>Collection&lt;Long&gt;</code>) If a name collision occurred, a
        collection of bundle ids that all have the same value for the
        Web-ContextPath manifest header.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interacting with the OSGi Environment</title>

    <section>
      <title>Bundle Context Access</title>

      <para>In order to properly integrate in an OSGi environment, a Web
      Application can access the OSGi service registry for publishing its
      services, accessing services provided by other bundles, and listening to
      bundle and service events to track the life cycle of these artifacts.
      This requires access to the Bundle Context of the WAB.</para>

      <para>The Web Extender must make the Bundle Context of the corresponding
      WAB available to the Web Application via the Servlet Context
      <code>osgi-bundlecontext</code> attribute. A Servlet can obtain a Bundle
      Context as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>BundleContext ctxt = (BundleContext) 
    servletContext.getAttribute("osgi-bundlecontext");</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Other Component Models</title>

      <para>Web Applications sometimes need to inter-operate with services
      provided by other component models, such as a Declarative Services or
      Blueprint. Per the Servlet specification, the Servlet Container owns the
      life cycle of a Servlet; the life cycle of the Servlet must be
      subordinate to the life cycle of the Servlet Context, which is only
      dependent on the life cycle of the WAB. Interactions between different
      bundles are facilitated by the OSGi service registry. This interaction
      can be managed in several ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A Servlet can obtain a Bundle Context from the Servlet Context
          for performing service registry operations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Via the JNDI Specification and the <code>osgi:service</code>
          JNDI namespace. The OSGi JNDI specification describes how OSGi
          services can be made available via the JNDI URL Context. It defines
          an <code>osgi:service</code> namespace and leverages URL Context
          factories to facilitate JNDI integration with the OSGi service
          registry.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Per this specification, it is not possible to make the Servlet
      life cycle dependent on the availability of specific services. Any
      synchronization and service dependency management must therefore be done
      by the Web Application itself.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3082990">
      <title>Resource Lookup</title>

      <para>The <code>getResource</code> and <code>getResourceAsStream</code>
      methods of the <code>ServletContext</code> interface are used to access
      resources in the web application. For a WAB, these resources must be
      found according to the <code>findEntries</code> method, this method
      includes fragments. For the <code>getResource</code> and
      <code>getResourceAsStream</code> method, if multiple resources are
      found, then the first one must be used.</para>

      <para>Since the <code>getResource</code> and
      <code>getResourceAsStream</code> methods do not support wildcards while
      the <code>findEntries</code> method does it is necessary to escape the
      wildcard asterisk (<code>'*' \u002A</code>) with prefixing it with a
      reverse solidus (<code>'\' \u005C</code>). This implies that a reverse
      solidus must be escaped with an extra reverse solidus. For example, the
      path <code>foo\bar*</code> must be escaped to
      <code>foo\\bar\*</code>.</para>

      <para>The <code>getResourcePaths</code> method must map to the Bundle
      <code>getEntryPaths</code> method, its return type is a Set and can not
      handle multiples. However, the paths from the <code>getEntryPaths</code>
      method are relative while the methods of the
      <code>getResourcePaths</code> must be absolute.</para>

      <para>For example, assume the following manifest for a bundle:</para>

      <programlisting>Bundle-ClassPath: localized, WEB-INF
...</programlisting>

      <para>This WAB has an attached fragment <code>acme-de.jar</code> with
      the following content:</para>

      <programlisting>META-INF/MANIFEST.MF
localized/logo.png</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>getResource</code> method for
      <code>localized/logo.png</code> uses the <code>findEntries</code> method
      to find a resource in the directory <code>/localized</code> and the
      resource <code>logo.png</code>. Assuming the host bundle has no
      <code>localized/</code> directory, the Web Runtime must serve the
      <code>logo.png</code> resource from the <code>acme-de.jar</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Resource Injection and Annotations</title>

      <para>The Web Application <code>web.xml</code> descriptor can specify
      the <code>metadata-complete</code> attribute on the <code>web-app</code>
      element. This attribute defines whether the <code>web.xml</code>
      descriptor is <emphasis>complete</emphasis>, or whether the classes in
      the bundle should be examined for deployment annotations. If the
      <code>metadata-complete</code> attribute is set to <code>true</code>,
      the Web Runtime must ignore any servlet annotations present in the class
      files of the Web Application. Otherwise, if the
      <code>metadata-complete</code> attribute is not specified, or is set to
      <code>false</code>, the container should process the class files of the
      Web Application for annotations, if supported.</para>

      <para>A WAB can make use of the annotations defined by <xref
      linkend="i3081342"/> if supported by the Web Extender. Such a WAB must
      import the packages the annotations are contained in. A Web Extender
      that does not support the use of JSR 250 annotations must not process a
      WAB that imports the annotations package.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Java Server Pages Support</title>

      <para>Java Server Pages (JSP) is a rendering technology for template
      based web page construction. This specification supports <xref
      linkend="i3076835"/> if available with the Web Runtime. The
      <code>servlet</code> element in a <code>web.xml</code> descriptor is
      used to describe both types of Web Components. JSP components are
      defined implicitly in the <code>web.xml</code> descriptor through the
      use of an implicit <code>.jsp</code> extension mapping, or explicitly
      through the use of a <code>jsp-group</code> element.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Compilation</title>

      <para>A Web Runtime compiles a JSP page into a Servlet, either during
      the deployment phase, or at the time of request processing, and
      dispatches the request to an instance of such a dynamically created
      class. Often times, the compilation task is delegated to a separate JSP
      compiler that will be responsible for identifying the necessary tag
      libraries, and generating the corresponding Servlet. The container then
      proceeds to load the dynamically generated class, creates an instance
      and dispatches the servlet request to that instance.</para>

      <para>Supporting in-line compilation of a JSP inside a bundle will
      require that the Web Runtime maintains a private area where it can store
      such compiled classes. The Web Runtime can leverage its private bundle
      storage area. The Web Runtime can construct a special class loader to
      load generated JSP classes such that classes from the bundle class path
      are visible to newly compiled JSP classes.</para>

      <para>The JSP specification does not describe how JSP pages are
      dynamically compiled or reloaded. Various Web Runtime implementations
      handle the aspects in proprietary ways. This specification does not
      bring forward any explicit requirements for supporting dynamic aspects
      of JSP pages.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>The security aspects of this specification are defined by the <xref
    linkend="i3076808"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3110503"><title>Java Enterprise Edition Release
      5</title><biblioid class="uri">Java 1.5.0 Packages <link
      xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javaee/tech/javaee5-jsp-135162.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3076362"><title>Java EE Web
      Applications</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javaee/tech/webapps-138511.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3076808"><title>Servlet 2.5
      specification</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://jcp.org/aboutJava/communityprocess/mrel/jsr154/index.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3076835"><title>JSP 2.1
      specification</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://jcp.org/aboutJava/communityprocess/final/jsr245/index.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3102743"><title>PAX Web Extender</title><biblioid
      class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://team.ops4j.org/wiki/display/paxweb/Pax+Web"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3079490"><title>Uniform Resource Locators, RFC
      1738</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1738.txt"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3081342"><title>JSR 250 Common Annotations for the
      Java Platform</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://jcp.org/aboutJava/communityprocess/pfd/jsr250/index.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
