<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="1" revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>When the OSGi Alliance started in 1998, the focus was in residential
  gateways the organization's name contained the word
  <emphasis>gateway</emphasis> before it was changed to the OSGi Alliance.
  Since that time, OSGi flourished in several different markets. With the
  release of the OSGi Residential Specification in January 2012, it made it
  also to widespread adoption for residential gateways/home gateways. This is
  due to the fact that:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Hardware cost of service gateways have been reduced.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Capabilities of those small devices increased many fold.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The number of devices in a household has increased.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Smart Home has become mainstream due to the growing interest in
      the Internet-of-Things (IoT).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The need for interoperability due to the increasing amount of
      communication protocols.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Always-on and broadband access to the Internet has become
      pervasive.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>This specification, produced by the OSGi Residential Expert Group
  (REG), defines a set of new and refined service specifications that focus on
  the residential market. The REG is chartered to define the requirements and
  specifications to tailor the OSGi framework for fixed network connected
  devices. Examples of such devices include residential gateways, building
  automation controllers, white goods, consumer electronics and many
  others.</para>

  <para>Technical areas addressed by the REG include the requirements,
  functional specifications, and APIs for gateway devices. The first release
  of the OSGi Residential Specification resolved the requirements of
  inter-operation with existing management systems and protocols, the need to
  remotely manage user applications life cycle as well as the need for
  large-scale deployments and adequate security.</para>

  <para>With this second release of the OSGi Residential Specification we
  introduce new specifications for abstracting devices, sensors, actuators,
  etc. from their corresponding communication protocols and facilitate the
  development of new innovative application and services. This release also
  contains specifications that address device connectivity via the EnOcean
  wireless protocol, USB and serial port. With the Resource Monitoring
  Specification, resources consumed by bundles can be monitored in order to
  fairly share resources and preserve the overall quality of service. The
  Network Interface Information Service Specification enables dynamic
  discovery of changes in the network interface.</para>

  <para>It is not suggested, or expected, that a solution will support all
  listed specifications. More likely, platform providers define their specific
  runtime environment. It is highly recommended to choose the mandatory and
  optional services defined by the <xref linkend="i435333"/> as a basis. A
  solution can further include other core and compendium services that are not
  listed as part the Residential Specification.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Overview of the Residential Specifications</title>

    <section>
      <title>Remote Management</title>

      <para>Support for remotely managing the service and their applications
      is essential to all systems that are installed on customer's premises.
      The specification therefore has special focus on large scale remote
      management of the OSGi Framework. The architecture provides a solution
      to allow management over different protocols although the primary focus
      is to allow the use Broadband Forum's suite of specifications on an OSGi
      residential gateway. This section introduces the related
      specifications.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dmt Admin Service Specification - </emphasis>The Dmt
          Admin Service specification provides an API for a remote manager to
          manage the device and its diverse services running on it. The Dmt
          Admin provides a generic tree structure, the Device Management Tree
          (DMT), to a Protocol Adapter. The nodes of those trees are
          implemented by the devices and services. Different Protocol Adapters
          can leverage the same DMT for different protocols. The Dmt Admin
          service also provides guidelines for object models that can be made
          available over different protocols. For more details see the <xref
          linkend="service.dmt"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Residential Device Management</emphasis> - This
          specification defines a Residential Management Tree, the RMT. This
          tree provides a general Dmt Admin object model that allows browsing
          and managing the OSGi Framework remotely over different Protocol
          Adapters. The RMT provides access to the Framework and the Log
          service. It also provides a filter function on top of Dmt Admin. See
          the <xref linkend="dmtree.residential"/> for details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>TR-157a3 Software Module</emphasis> - <xref
          linkend="i434640"/> has defined a generic model for mapping software
          modules in <xref linkend="i437933"/>. This specification provides a
          recommended mapping for the generic concepts to the OSGi Framework
          concepts. See <xref linkend="tr157softwaremodules"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>TR-069 Connector Service Specification</emphasis> -
          The Dmt Admin service and the TR-069 protocol have different
          semantics and primitives. This specification contains the <xref
          linkend="service.tr069todmt"/>. This specification provides an API
          based on the TR-069 Remote Procedure Calls concept that is
          implemented on top of Dmt Admin. This connector supports data
          conversion and the object modeling constructs defined in the Dmt
          Admin service, <xref
          linkend="service.dmt.osgiobjectmodeling"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuration, Monitoring and Management Services</title>

      <para>The OSGi Framework is unique in that it does not hide anything,
      all aspects are manageable from the system itself. To locally manage the
      system, the following services are available:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Conditional Permission Admin Service
          Specification</emphasis> - The Conditional Permission Admin service
          allows an operator to control the Java Permissions to be granted to
          the bundles running on the OSGi Framework using a condition based
          model. See <xref linkend="intro.core.release"
          xrefstyle="template:%t"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Permission Admin Service Specification</emphasis> -
          The Permission Admin service allows an operator to control the Java
          Permissions to be granted to the bundles running on the OSGi
          Framework based on the bundle location. Permission Admin has been
          superseded by Conditional Permission Admin, but is included for
          backwards compatibility. See <xref linkend="intro.core.release"
          xrefstyle="template:%t"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>URL Handlers Service Specification</emphasis> - This
          specification standardizes the mechanism to extend the Java run-time
          with new URL schemes and content handlers. Dynamically extending the
          URL schemes that are supported in an OSGi Framework is a very
          powerful concept to provide more functionality to existing
          applications. See <xref linkend="intro.core.release"
          xrefstyle="template:%t"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>User Admin Service Specification</emphasis> - The
          User Admin Service specification provides authorization for OSGi
          Framework actions based on authenticated users instead of using the
          Java code-based permission model. See the <xref
          linkend="service.useradmin"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Initial Provisioning Specification</emphasis> - The
          Initial Provisioning specification defines how a Management Agent
          and other initial bundles can be deployed on an uninitialized OSGi
          Framework. It gives a structured view of the problems and their
          corresponding resolution methods. The purpose of this specification
          is to enable the management of a Framework by an operator, and
          (optionally) to hand over the management of the Framework later to
          another operator. See the <xref linkend="service.provisioning"/> for
          more details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Configuration Admin Service Specification</emphasis>
          - The Configuration Admin service allows an operator or an
          application bundle developer to set the configuration information of
          bundles. See <xref linkend="service.cm"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Metatype Service Specification</emphasis> - The
          Metatype specification defines interfaces that allow bundle
          developers to describe attribute types in a computer readable form
          using metadata. It is mostly used in conjunction with the
          Configuration Admin Service. See <xref linkend="service.metatype"/>
          for details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Network Interface Information Service
          Specification</emphasis> - The Network Interface Information Service
          specification defines services that provides a standard way for
          bundles to receive notifications about changes in the network
          interfaces and IP addresses. See <xref
          linkend="service.network"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Resource Monitoring Specification</emphasis> - The
          Resource Monitoring specification defines an API for applications to
          monitor hardware resources consumed by any set of bundles. Monitored
          data may enable applications to take decisions on management actions
          to apply. Resource management actions are mentioned as examples in
          this chapter including actions on the lifecycle of components,
          bundles, the framework and the JVM, Java threads, and the raising of
          exceptions. See <xref linkend="service.resourcemonitoring"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Component Models</title>

      <para>Component models allow the code in bundles to remain unaware of
      OSGi API by using Dependency Injection (DI) while still providing full
      support for the OSGi service model.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Declarative Services Specification</emphasis> - The
          Declarative Services specification provides dependency injection for
          services. It handles the service life cycle dynamics by notifying
          the component or managing the components life cycle. See <xref
          linkend="service.component"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>HTTP and Servlets</title>

      <para>HTTP Server and Servlets functions are often needed for the
      residential gateway. The Specification contains this
      specification:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Http Service Specification</emphasis> - Developers
          typically need to develop communication and user interface solutions
          for standard technologies such as HTTP, HTML, XML, and servlets. See
          the <xref linkend="service.http"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Event models</title>

      <para>The OSGi service model is based on synchronous APIs. Support for
      asynchronous invocations and event driven interactions usually involves
      the definition of listeners. However, this model does not scale well for
      fine grained events that must be dispatched to many different handlers.
      The Specification therefore contains the Event Admin Service
      Specification:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Admin Service Specification</emphasis> - The
          Event Admin service provides an inter-bundle communication
          mechanism. It is based on a event publish and subscribe model,
          popular in many message based systems. See <xref
          linkend="service.event"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Device Interoperability</title>

      <para>A residential gateway can directly attach devices, for example via
      a USB adapter, through a home network. There is therefore a need to have
      a unified device abstraction, discovery and control model. For this
      purpose, this Specification contains the following services:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Device Access Specification</emphasis> - The Device
          Access specification supports the coordination of automatic
          detection and attachment of existing devices on an OSGi Framework,
          facilitates hot-plugging and -unplugging of new devices, and
          downloads and installs device drivers on demand. See <xref
          linkend="service.device"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="service.upnp" xrefstyle="template:%t"/> - The
          UPnP specification specifies how OSGi bundles can be developed that
          inter-operate with UPnP (Universal Plug and Play) devices and UPnP
          control points. The specification is based on <xref
          linkend="i437630"/>. See <xref linkend="service.upnp"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Device Abstraction Layer Specification</emphasis> -
          The Device Abstraction Layer specification provides a unified
          interface for application developers to interact with sensor,
          devices, etc. connected to a gateway. Application developers don't
          have to deal with protocol specific details which simplifies the
          development of their applications. See <xref
          linkend="service.dal"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Device Abstraction Layer Functions
          Specification</emphasis> - The Device Abstraction Layer Functions
          specification defines a minimal set of basic device operations and
          the related properties. They can be extended or replaced to cover
          domain specific scenarios. The set is not closed and can be
          incorporated with vendor specific functions. There is support for
          control, monitoring and metering information. See <xref
          linkend="service.dal.functions"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="service.enocean" xrefstyle="template:%t"/> -
          This specification defines how OSGi bundles can be developed to
          discover and control EnOcean devices on the one hand, and act as
          EnOcean devices and interoperate with EnOcean clients on the other
          hand. In particular, a Java mapping is provided for the standard
          representation of EnOcean devices called EnOcean Equipment Profile
          (EEP). See <xref linkend="service.enocean"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>USB Information Device Category
          Specification</emphasis> - The USB Information Device Category
          specification defines a new device category for USB devices in order
          to handle the integration of communication protocols, for example,
          ZigBee and Z-Wave via USB dongles. See <xref
          linkend="service.usbinfo"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Serial Device Service Specification</emphasis> - The
          Serial Device Service specification defines an API to communicate
          with controllers connected to a serial port. See <xref
          linkend="service.serial"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Miscellaneous Supporting Services</title>

      <para>Services providing solutions to common infrastructure requirements
      include:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Log Service Specification</emphasis> - Provides a
          general purpose message logger for the OSGi Framework. See the <xref
          linkend="service.log"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>XML Parser Service Specification</emphasis> -
          Addresses how the classes defined in JAXP can be used in an OSGi
          Framework. See <xref linkend="util.xml"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Promises Specification</emphasis> - An asynchronous
          programming model by which clients retrieve the result of the
          asynchronous task. See <xref linkend="util.promise"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Version Information</title>

    <para>This document is the Residential Specification for the OSGi
    Residential <xref endterm="residential.book-release"
    linkend="residential.book"/>.</para>

    <section xml:id="intro.core.release">
      <title>OSGi Core Release 6</title>

      <para>This specification is based on the OSGi Core Release 6. This
      specification can be downloaded from:</para>

      <programlisting>https://www.osgi.org/developer/specifications/</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Component Versions</title>

      <para>Components in this specification have their own specification
      version, independent of this specification. The following table
      summarizes the packages and specification versions for the different
      subjects.</para>

      <table pgwide="1">
        <title>Packages and versions</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="3*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2.5*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="0.8*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Item</entry>

              <entry>Package(s)</entry>

              <entry>Version</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="dmtree.residential"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.dmt.residential"/></code><superscript>*</superscript></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.dmt.residential-version"
              linkend="dmtree.residential"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.log"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.log"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.log.admin"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.log.stream"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.log-version"
              linkend="service.log"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.http"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.http"/></code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.http-version"
              linkend="service.http"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.device"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.device"/></code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.device-version"
              linkend="service.device"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.cm"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.cm"/></code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.cm-version"
              linkend="service.cm"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.metatype"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.metatype"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.metatype.annotations"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.metatype-version"
              linkend="service.metatype"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.useradmin"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.useradmin"/></code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.useradmin-version"
              linkend="service.useradmin"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.provisioning"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.provisioning"/></code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              endterm="org.osgi.service.provisioning-version"
              linkend="service.provisioning"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.upnp"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp"/></code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.upnp-version"
              linkend="service.upnp"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.component"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.component"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.component.annotations"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.component.propertytypes"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.component.runtime"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.component.runtime.dto"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.component-version"
              linkend="service.component"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.event"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event"/></code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.event-version"
              linkend="service.event"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.dmt"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.dmt"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.dmt.notification"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.dmt.notification.spi"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.dmt.security"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.dmt.spi"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.dmt-version"
              linkend="service.dmt"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.tr069todmt"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.tr069todmt"/></code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.tr069todmt-version"
              linkend="service.tr069todmt"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.namespaces"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.namespace.contract"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.namespace.extender"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.namespace.implementation"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.namespace.service"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.namespace.unresolvable"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="service.namespaces-version"
              linkend="service.namespaces"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.enocean"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.enocean-version"
              linkend="service.enocean"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.dal"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.dal"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.dal-version"
              linkend="service.dal"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.dal.functions"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.dal.functions"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.dal.functions.data"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              endterm="org.osgi.service.dal.functions-version"
              linkend="service.dal.functions"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.network"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.networkadapter"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              endterm="org.osgi.service.networkadapter-version"
              linkend="service.network"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.resourcemonitoring"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref
              endterm="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring-version"
              linkend="service.resourcemonitoring"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.usbinfo"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.usbinfo"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.usbinfo-version"
              linkend="service.usbinfo"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="service.serial"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.serial"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.serial-version"
              linkend="service.serial"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="util.xml"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><code><xref linkend="org.osgi.util.xml"/></code></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.util.xml-version"
              linkend="util.xml"/></code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="util.promise"
              xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

              <entry><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.util.promise"/></code></para><para><code><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.util.function"/></code></para></entry>

              <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.util.promise-version"
              linkend="util.promise"/></code></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para><superscript>*</superscript> - This is not a Java package but
      contains DMT Types.</para>

      <para>When a component is represented in a bundle, a
      <code>version</code> attribute is needed in the declaration of the
      Import-Package or Export-Package manifest headers.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i310173"><title>Bradner, S., Key words for use in
      RFCs to Indicate Requirement
      Levels</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt"/>, March
      1997.</biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i434636"><title>Home Gateway
      Initiative</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.homegatewayinitiative.org"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i435333"><title>HG Requirements for HGI Open
      Platform
      2.0</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.homegatewayinitiative.org/publis/HGI-RD048-HG_Requirements_for_HGI_Open_Platform_2_0_published_text.pdf"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i434644"><title>UPnP™
      Forum</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://upnp.org"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i434640"><title>Broadband
      Forum</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.broadband-forum.org"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i437630"><title>UPnP Device Architecture
      1.0</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.upnp.org/specs/arch/UPnP-arch-DeviceArchitecture-v1.0.pdf"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i437933"><title>TR-157 Amendment 3 Component
      Objects for
      CWMP</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.broadband-forum.org/technical/download/TR-157_Amendment-3.pdf"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Updated <xref linkend="service.namespaces"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
