<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="144"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="service.resourcemonitoring"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Resource Monitoring Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Applications, executed on an OSGi platform, need hardware resources
    (CPU, memory, disk, storage space) and software resources (sockets,
    threads). As these resources are limited, applications have to share them
    in order to preserve system quality of service. This is a general fact in
    OSGi business cases where multiple bundles share the OSGi framework. This
    is especially the case when the framework is shared by distinct tenants,
    which are responsible for distinct set of bundles running with their own
    business logic and lifecycle.</para>

    <para>The chapter defines an API for applications to monitor hardware
    resources consumed by any set of bundles. The bundle is the smallest unit
    that can be considered as a resource context, the entity that is
    monitored. Monitored data may enable applications to take decisions on
    management actions to apply. Resource management actions are mentioned as
    examples in this chapter, for example, actions on the lifecycle of
    components, bundles, the framework and the JVM, Java threads, raise of
    exceptions.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Essentials</title>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Monitoring</emphasis> - Bundle execution
        resource usage is monitored.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Granular activation</emphasis> - The resource
        monitoring service can be activated and deactivated per bundle or per
        bundle set.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Extensibility</emphasis> - Five resource types are
        specified (CPU, memory, disk storage, alive thread and in-use
        sockets). The list of monitored resource types is extensible and
        query-able.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Eventing</emphasis> - The resource monitoring service
        notifies interested entities of exceeded limits.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Entities</title>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Resource Context</emphasis> - A logical entity for
        resource accounting. A context may be related to a single bundle or a
        set of bundles.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>System Resource Context</emphasis> - Resource context
        of the core framework.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Platform Resource Context</emphasis> - A Resource
        context monitoring the resource usage of the platform as a
        whole.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Resource Monitor</emphasis> - Monitors the usage of a
        specific resource type for a specific Resource Context. Resource
        Monitors track resource usage. They hold Resource Thresholds
        instances. Resource Monitor object implementation may depend on
        standard or proprietary JVM APIs, and on operating system
        features.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Resource Monitor Factory</emphasis> - A factory
        creating Resource Monitor instances for every Resource Context.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>CPU Monitor</emphasis> - Resource Monitor used to
        monitor CPU.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Memory Monitor</emphasis> - Resource Monitor used to
        monitor memory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Socket Monitor</emphasis> - Resource Monitor used to
        monitor socket resource.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Disk Storage Monitor</emphasis> - Resource Monitor for
        disk storage usage.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Thread Monitor</emphasis> - Resource Monitor used to
        monitor alive Java Thread objects.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Resource Listener</emphasis> - A Resource Listener
        receives resource threshold notifications.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Resource Event</emphasis> - A Resource Event defines a
        notification to be synchronously sent to Resource Listener
        instances.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Resource Context Listener</emphasis> - A Resource
        Context Listener receives notifications about resource context
        creation and configuration.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Resource Context Event</emphasis> - A Resource Context
        Event defines a notification to be sent to Resource Context Listeners
        instances.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Resource Monitoring Service</emphasis> - This is a
        singleton entity which manages Resource Context instances. It is used
        to create new Resource Context instances and to enumerate existing
        contexts.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Resource Monitoring Client</emphasis> - Makes any
        decision to ensure the quality of the service of the system. They use
        the Resource Monitoring Service to create Resource Context instances.
        It configures them by adding bundles and Resource Monitors.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure xml:id="service.resourcemonitoring_bibliomixed_id_20141210_15h18_rfc_fig_2">
      <title>Resource monitoring class diagram specification.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.5in"
                     contentwidth="5.000in"
                     fileref="service.resourcemonitoring_resource_monitoring_specification_class_diagram_rev_01.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Operation Summary</title>

    <para>Resource Monitoring Clients use the Resource Monitoring Service
    service to create Resource Contexts. These clients set bundles or group of
    bundles to Resource Contexts. They also request every Resource Monitor
    Factory to create Resource Monitors for a resource type. These Resource
    Monitors are associated to a single Resource Context.</para>

    <para>When activated, Resource Monitors provide the current resource usage
    per Resource Context. Then, they check whether the current resource usage
    is compatible with the thresholds held by their associated Resource
    Listeners. When one of these thresholds is violated, the related Resource
    Monitor notifies the Resource Listener holding this threshold.</para>

    <para>The Resource Monitoring Service manages the set of Resource
    Contexts. Resource Contexts are persistent between platform restarts.
    Resource Context Listeners are notified when a Resource Context is created
    or deleted or when a Resource Context configuration (that is, adding or
    removing of bundle) is updated.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resource Context</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance is a logical entity used to account
    resource usage. Every Resource Context defines a bundle scope which can be
    either a single bundle or a set of bundles. Once the bundle scope is
    defined, resources used by those bundles are monitored through a set of
    per-resource-type Resource Monitor instances.</para>

    <para>Resource Context instances are persistent. The persistence of those
    instances is directly managed by the Resource Monitoring Service
    instance.</para>

    <para>Each Resource Context is uniquely identified by a name. It can be
    retrieved through the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.getName--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. It can not be changed, that is it is
    definitively set when the Resource Context instance is created.</para>

    <para>The Resource Context bundle scope is retrieved through the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.getBundleIds--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This bundle scope can be extended through
    the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.addBundle-long-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. Bundles can also be removed from a
    Resource Context through the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.removeBundle-long-ResourceContext-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. For this last method, a Resource Context
    instance MAY be specified in order to associate the removed bundle to
    another Resource Context instance.</para>

    <para>Resource Monitor instances are retrieved through <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.getMonitor-String-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method or the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.getMonitors--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The list of available resource types is
    retrieved through the Resource Monitoring Service singleton
    instance.</para>

    <para>Resource Monitor instances are added to and removed from a Resource
    Context instance by calling either <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.addResourceMonitor-ResourceMonitor-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method or <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.removeResourceMonitor-ResourceMonitor-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. Both methods SHOULD only be called by
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitorFactory"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instances (see <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitorFactory.createResourceMonitor-ResourceContext-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method).</para>

    <para>A Resource Context is retrieved through the Resource Monitoring
    Service service.</para>

    <para>A Resource Context instance can be deleted through <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.removeContext-ResourceContext-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The Resource Context input argument then
    defines a destination Resource Context instance for the bundles belonging
    to the to-be-removed Resource Context instance.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>System Resource Context</title>

    <para>The System Resource Context is the Resource Context of the execution
    environment for the running OSGi bundles. It includes the resources of
    bundle "0". It is retrieved through the Resource Monitoring Service
    service.</para>

    <para>The name of this context is “system”. See <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitoringService.SYSTEM_CONTEXT_NAME"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Framework Resource Context</title>

    <para>The Framework Resource Context is a Resource Context monitoring
    resources of the platform as a whole. It is retrieved through the Resource
    Monitoring Service service. This Resource Context holds all hosted bundles
    allowing access to the whole platform resource consumption.</para>

    <para>The name of this context is “framework”. See <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitoringService.FRAMEWORK_CONTEXT_NAME"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resource Monitor</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance monitors a resource type consumed by the
    bundles of a specific Resource Context instance.</para>

    <para>A Resource Context instance holds at most one Resource Monitor
    instance per monitor-able resource type. Resource Monitor instances are
    retrieved through their related Resource Context instance. Resource
    Monitor instances give access to their related Resource Context instance
    through a call to See <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.getContext--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

    <para>The monitored resource type is retrieved through the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.getResourceType--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

    <para>The current usage of a resource consumed by a Resource Context
    instance is given through the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.getUsage--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This method returns a Java Object to be
    casted to the appropriate Java object type depending on the Resource type.
    The next table provides the expected Java Object type for each specified
    resource type:</para>

    <table frame="all">
      <title>Table of resource types.</title>

      <tgroup align="left" cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>

        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>

        <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="1*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Type of Resource</entry>

            <entry>Expected Java Object type</entry>

            <entry>Value description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tfoot>
          <row>
            <entry>Disk storage space</entry>

            <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

            <entry>Bytes on the bundle persistent storage area.</entry>
          </row>
        </tfoot>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>CPU</entry>

            <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

            <entry>Cumulative CPU time in ns.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Memory</entry>

            <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

            <entry>Allocated memory in bytes.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Threads</entry>

            <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

            <entry>Number of alive thread.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Socket</entry>

            <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

            <entry>Number of in-use socket.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>For example, for a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.MemoryMonitor"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance, a call to <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.getUsage--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> returns a Long java object indicating the amount
    of memory the related Resource Context instance is consuming.</para>

    <para>A Resource Monitor instance is enabled and disabled through <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.enable--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.disable--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods. The state (enabled or disabled) of a
    Resource Monitor is retrieved through a call to <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.isEnabled--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. Enable and disable monitoring mechanisms
    on-the-fly on localized set of bundles may be crucial for performance
    issues. See <xref
    linkend="service.resourcemonitoring_bibliomixed_id_20150105_11h45_1"/>.</para>

    <para>A Resource Monitor instance can also be deleted (<xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.delete--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method). <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.isDeleted--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method returns true if the ResourceMonitor
    instance has been deleted.</para>

    <para>Five types of Resource Monitor are specified:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para>CPU Monitor</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Memory Monitor</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Socket Monitor</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Disk Storage Monitor</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Thread Monitor</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The support of any Resource Monitor is optional. This list MAY be
    extended by the solution vendor. The list of the types that are supported
    on the OSGi platform can be computed by querying <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitorFactory"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> services. Resource monitoring algorithms may vary
    with factories, see <xref
    linkend="service.resourcemonitoring_bibliomixed_id_20150105_11h46_2"/>.
    They are out of the scope of this specification.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resource Monitor Factory</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitorFactory"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> is a service that provides Resource Monitor
    instances of a specific resource type (for example, <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.CPUMonitor"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.MemoryMonitor"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, etc.) for every Resource Context.</para>

    <para>Every Resource Monitor Factory service is registered with the
    <code>org.osgi.resourcemonitoring.ResourceType</code> mandatory property,
    see <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitorFactory.RESOURCE_TYPE_PROPERTY"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This property indicates which type of Resource
    Monitor a Resource Monitor Factory is able to create. The type can also be
    retrieved through a call to <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitorFactory.getType--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The type MUST be unique (two Resource Monitor
    Factory services MUST not have the same type).</para>

    <para>New Resource Monitor instances are created by a call to <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitorFactory.createResourceMonitor-ResourceContext-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This method returns a new Resource Monitor
    instance associated to the provided Resource Context instance. The
    ResourceMonitorFactory MUST call <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContext.addResourceMonitor-ResourceMonitor-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> to associate the newly created ResourceMonitor
    with the provided ResourceContext instance. The newly created Resource
    Monitor is disabled, that is, it is initially not monitoring the Resource
    Context resource consumption. It can be activated through a call to <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.enable--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>

    <para>Resource Monitor instances are deleted by calling <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitor.delete--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

    <para>A Resource Monitor instance MUST only be created through its <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitorFactory"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>

    <para>Resource Monitor Factory instances should be only used by the
    Resource Monitoring Service singleton instance. The Resource Monitoring
    Service singleton instance performs a service lookup on all existing
    Resource Monitor Factories. It uses a Resource Monitor Factory instance
    when it has to create a new Resource Context instance and their associated
    Resource Monitor instances.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>CPU Monitor</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.CPUMonitor"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance is a Resource Monitor used to monitor the
    CPU usage of the bundles belonging to a Resource Context.</para>

    <para>CPU usage and thresholds are expressed as a cumulative number of
    nanoseconds (long). The encapsulated value can be retrieved with the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.CPUMonitor.getCPUUsage--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

    <para>In case where a threshold is reached, the CPU Monitor instance
    generates an event triggering Resource Monitoring Clients defined
    corrective actions (for example, decrease thread priority).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Memory Monitor</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.MemoryMonitor"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance monitors and limits the memory used by
    the bundles of a Resource Context instance.</para>

    <para>Memory is accounted as bytes. Memory usage and thresholds are long
    java objects. The encapsulated value can be retrieved through the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.MemoryMonitor.getMemoryUsage--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

    <para>When an error threshold is reached, the next memory allocation MAY
    be prevented by the system and MAY throw a specific Exception in the
    associated context.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Socket Monitor</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.SocketMonitor"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance monitors and limits the number of
    existing sockets (for example, TCP, UDP) which are considered to be in use
    (for example, listening for incoming packet, bound, or sending outgoing
    packets).</para>

    <para>A Socket is considered to be in-use state when a native socket file
    descriptor is created. It leaves this state when this socket file
    descriptor is deleted.</para>

    <para>The number of in-use sockets is a long. The encapsulated value can
    be retrieved using <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.SocketMonitor.getSocketUsage--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

    <para>When an <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> threshold is reached, the next socket file
    descriptor creation in the associated context MAY throw a
    SocketException.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Disk Storage Monitor</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.DiskStorageMonitor"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance monitors and limits the use of persistent
    storage within Bundle Persistent Storage Area a Resource Context (the
    bundles actually belonging to it) consumes.</para>

    <para>Disk Storage is expressed as a number of bytes of type long. The
    encapsulated value can be retrieved using <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.DiskStorageMonitor.getUsedDiskStorage--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

    <para>An IOException MAY be thrown in the associated context when an <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> threshold is reached.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Thread Monitor</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.ThreadMonitor"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance monitors and limits the number of alive
    Java Thread objects for a Resource Context instance. A Thread is
    considered to be alive when it is in the <code>RUNNABLE</code>,
    <code>BLOCKED</code>, <code>WAITING</code> or <code>TIMED_WAITING</code>
    thread state.</para>

    <para>Usage and thresholds are Java int objects. The encapsulated value
    can be retrieved using <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.ThreadMonitor.getAliveThreads--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

    <para>When an <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> threshold is reached, any further thread
    activation will be prevented in the associated context. An InternalError
    exception MAY also be thrown in the associated context.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resource Listener</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> receives notifications about resource usage for a
    specific Resource Context and a specific type of resource. A notification
    will be sent to a Resource Listener when one of its thresholds is
    violated.</para>

    <para>A Resource Listener holds two types of threshold:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para>A lower threshold type. This kind of threshold is reached when
        the monitored resource usage decreases below the threshold.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>An upper threshold type. An upper threshold is reached when the
        monitored resource usage exceeds this threshold.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Each of them have two levels:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para>a <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> level.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>an <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> level.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A threshold has the following state diagram, which transitions are
    associated to events:</para>

    <figure xml:id="service.resourcemonitoring_bibliomixed_id_20141211_16h06_rfc_fig_3">
      <title>Threshold state diagram.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.5in"
                     fileref="ResourceThresholdState.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>A threshold state depends on the current consumption of resource and
    the type of threshold (upper or lower threshold).</para>

    <para>A Resource Listener is registered as an OSGi service. The
    implementer must provide the two following mandatory properties:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener.RESOURCE_CONTEXT"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> property – a String defining the name of
        Resource Context for which the Listener want to receive threshold
        notifications.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener.RESOURCE_TYPE"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> property – a String defining which type of
        resource the listener wants to monitor.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>It also has to provide at least one of these four properties when
    registered as an OSGi service:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener.UPPER_WARNING_THRESHOLD"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener.UPPER_ERROR_THRESHOLD"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener.LOWER_WARNING_THRESHOLD"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener.LOWER_ERROR_THRESHOLD"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>These properties are mapped to the four types of threshold values a
    Resource Listener may support. The service properties are used to notify
    the associated Resource Monitor when one of these threshold values is
    modified.</para>

    <para>Threshold values can also be retrieved through a set of getter
    methods. All of these methods returns a <code>Comparable</code> object
    used by the associated Resource Monitor in order to determine the current
    state of the current usage.</para>

    <para><xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener.RESOURCE_CONTEXT"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener.RESOURCE_TYPE"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> properties are used by Resource Monitors to
    identify their associated Resource Listeners. Once associated, a Resource
    Monitor retrieves the threshold settings using service properties. When
    one of its thresholds is reached, the Resource Monitor calls <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceListener.notify-ResourceEvent-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>

    <para>Two examples of resource consumption are explained below, first with
    in-use sockets monitoring, second with CPU monitoring. The next picture
    shows the state diagram of the number of in-use state socket over the
    time.</para>

    <figure xml:id="service.resourcemonitoring_bibliomixed_id_20141211_16h07_rfc_fig_4">
      <title>Number of in-use sockets over the time.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.5in"
                     fileref="LowerAndUpperThreshold.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In our example, the lower warning threshold and the lower error
    threshold of the Resource Listener are respectively set to 10 and 5. When
    the number of in-use sockets decreases under 10, the usage goes from the
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.NORMAL"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state and the Resource Listener receives a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event. If the number of in-use state sockets
    decreases again and goes down to 5, the usage goes from the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state and the Resource Listener receives a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Resource Event.</para>

    <para>The upper threshold is also set. The upper warning threshold and the
    upper error threshold are respectively set to 100 and 1000 in-use state
    sockets. When the number of sockets reaches 100, the usage goes from the
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.NORMAL"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state and the Resource Listener receives a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Resource Event. If this number is still increasing
    and exceeds 1000, then the usage goes from the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state and the Resource Listener receives an <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Resource Event.</para>

    <para>This is a typical use case for a Java Web server. Indeed, one of the
    most important quality of service indicator is the number of in-use state
    sockets a java web server is handling. A low number of in-use state
    sockets may indicate the java web server encounters network problems. On
    the contrary, a high number of in-use state socket may be the result of an
    external network attack or it could also indicates the java web server is
    overused and its administrator should take actions to load-balance the
    charge to another java web server instance.</para>

    <para>For other resource types, only upper thresholds may be useful. The
    next diagram shows the CPU consumption a Resource Context is using over
    the time:</para>

    <figure xml:id="service.resourcemonitoring_bibliomixed_id_20141211_16h08_rfc_fig_5">
      <title>CPU consumption (%) over the time – Upper Threshold.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.5in"
                     fileref="UpperThreshold.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In this example, only the upper threshold is set. The upper warning
    threshold is set to 50%, the error one is set to 75%. CPU consumption
    fluctuates between 0 and 50%, the usage is in the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.NORMAL"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state. Then it increases and reaches 50%. The
    usage then goes from the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.NORMAL"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state and the Resource Listener holding the
    threshold receives a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Resource Event.</para>

    <para>Afterwards, CPU consumption decreases under 50%; the usage goes from
    the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.NORMAL"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state. The related Resource listener receives a
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.NORMAL"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Resource Event.</para>

    <para>It then increases again and exceeds 50%. The usage goes to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state. CPU consumption is still increasing and
    exceeds 75%. At this moment, the usage goes from the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state and the related Resource Listener receives
    an <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Resource Event.</para>

    <para>After some seconds in the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state, the Resource Listener implementation stops
    the bundle in order to preserve the quality of service.</para>

    <para>The choice of the type of threshold (lower or upper, or both of
    them) depends on the type of resource and the needs of the Resource
    Monitoring Clients providing the Resource Listener. Other resources like
    the free memory may take advantage of a lower threshold.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resource Event</title>

    <para>A <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance is an event synchronously sent to a
    Resource Listener when one of its thresholds is reached. This event is
    notified to a Resource Listener through a call to
    ResourceListener.notify(ResourceEvent).</para>

    <para>A Resource Event has a type among the following ones:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.ERROR"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The resource consumption reaches either the
        upper or the lower error threshold of the Resource Listener receiving
        this event.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.WARNING"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The resource consumption reaches either the
        upper or the lower warning threshold of the Resource Listener
        receiving this event.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.NORMAL"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The resource consumption is back from
        warning or error state to normal state.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Resource Listener instance analyzes this event by calling the
    following methods:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.getValue--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method returns the resource consumption at the
        time when the Resource Event instance was generated.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.isUpperThreshold--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method returns true if the reached threshold
        is an upper threshold type. If this method returns false, this is a
        lower threshold.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.getType--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method indicates the state (WARNING, ERROR, or
        NORMAL) of the resource usage.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceEvent.getContext--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method returns the Resource Context instance
        related to this event. The Resource Listener can use it to retrieve
        the Resource Monitor instance. For example,
        <code>event.getContext().getMonitor(event.getResourceType())</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resource Context Listener</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextListener"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance receives notifications about Resource
    Context lifecycle and configuration.</para>

    <para>A notification will be sent when:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para>A Resource Context is created.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A Resource Context is updated, that is, a bundle has been added
        or removed from a Resource Context instance.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A Resource Context is deleted.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>An application which is interested in notifications has to register
    a Resource Context Listener instance as an OSGi service. The application
    may provide a set of properties at registration time to reduce the number
    of notifications a Resource Listener instance will receive. The available
    property is:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextListener.RESOURCE_CONTEXT"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> property – An array of String defining the
        name of Resource Context instances. If defined, a Resource Listener
        instance will only receive notifications related to these specified
        Resource Context instances.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A Resource Context Listener instance is notified through a call to
    <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextListener.notify-ResourceContextEvent-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resource Context Event</title>

    <para>A <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instance is an event sent to Resource Context
    Listener instances through a call to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextListener.notify-ResourceContextEvent-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

    <para>A Resource Context Event has a type among the four following
    ones:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.RESOURCE_CONTEXT_CREATED"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – A new Resource Context instance has been
        created.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.RESOURCE_CONTEXT_REMOVED"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – A Resource Context instance has been
        deleted.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.BUNDLE_ADDED"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – A bundle has been added in the scope of a
        Resource Context instance.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.BUNDLE_REMOVED"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – A bundle has been removed from the scope of
        a Resource Context instance.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In the case of a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.RESOURCE_CONTEXT_CREATED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event or a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.RESOURCE_CONTEXT_REMOVED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event, a call to <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.getContext--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> returns the targeted Resource Context
    instance.</para>

    <para>In the case of a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.BUNDLE_ADDED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> type or <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.BUNDLE_REMOVED"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> type, <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.getBundleId--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> returns the id of the bundle to be added to or
    removed from. The related Resource Context instance is given by a call to
    <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceContextEvent.getContext--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resource Monitoring Service</title>

    <para>The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitoringService"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> manages the Resource Context instances. The
    Resource Monitoring Service is available through the OSGi service
    registry.</para>

    <para>This service holds the existing Resource Context instances. Resource
    Context instances are created by calling the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitoringService.createContext-String-ResourceContext-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The caller provides a context name as a
    string and optionally a template as a ResourceContext object.</para>

    <para>The list of existing Resource Context instances can be retrieved
    through the following methods:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitoringService.getContext-String-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – returns the ResourceContext with the
        specified resource context name.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitoringService.getContext-long-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – returns the ResourceContext associated to
        the provided bundle id.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.ResourceMonitoringService.listContext--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – retrieve all existing Resource Context
        instances as an array.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Resource Monitoring Service singleton manages the persistence of
    the Resource Context instances. The following properties are
    stored:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para>name of the Resource Context.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>list of the bundles belonging to the Resource Context.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>list of the Resource Monitor instances. For each one: the
        sampling period, and the monitoring period.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The way the Resource Monitoring Service persists the Resource
    Context instances is implementation specific. The implementer is free to
    use any file format and file location it wants. At startup, the Resource
    Monitoring Service will load the persisted Resource Context instances to
    restore the state prior to shutdown.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resource Monitoring Client</title>

    <para>A Resource Monitoring Client uses the Resource Monitoring Service
    singleton instance to apply Resource Monitoring policies. These entities
    MAY:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para>create and configure Resource Context instances (resource
        thresholds, bundle scope)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>take any decisions (stop a bundle, uninstall a bundle) if a
        Resource Context exceeds resource limit.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>These policies are out of the scope of this specification.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>It is recommended that
    <code>ServicePermission[ResourceMonitoringService|ResourceMonitoringFactory|ResourceListener,
    REGISTER|GET]</code> be used sparingly and only for bundles that are
    trusted.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.resourcemonitoring.monitor.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.resourcemonitoring_bibliomixed_id_20150105_11h45_1"><title>Adaptive
      Monitoring of End-user OSGi based Home Boxes</title>Y. Maurel, A.
      Bottaro, R. Kopetz, and K. Attouchi. Component Base Software
      Engineering, 15th ACM SIGSOFT International Symposium on Component-Based
      Software Engineering, CBSE'2012, Bertinoro, Italy, June
      2012.</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.resourcemonitoring_bibliomixed_id_20150105_11h46_2"><title>Memory
      Monitoring in a Multi-tenant OSGi Execution Environment</title>K.
      Attouchi, G. Thomas, A. Bottaro, and G. Muller. Proceedings of the 17th
      ACM SIGSOFT symposium on Component Based Software Engineering, CBSE’14,
      Lille, France, July 2014.</bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
