<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright (c) Contributors to the Eclipse Foundation
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
   
    SPDX-License-Identifier: Apache-2.0 
 -->
<chapter label="127"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="service.jpa"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>JPA Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.jpa-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The Java Persistence API (JPA) is a specification that sets a
    standard for persistently storing objects in enterprise and non-enterprise
    Java based environments. JPA provides an Object Relational Mapping (ORM)
    model that is configured through persistence descriptors. This Java
    Persistence Service specification defines how persistence units can be
    published in an OSGi framework, how client bundles can find these
    persistence units, how database drivers are found with the <xref
    linkend="service.jdbc"/>, as well as how JPA providers can be made
    available within an OSGi framework.</para>

    <para>Applications can be managed or they can be unmanaged. Managed
    applications run inside a Java EE Container and unmanaged applications run
    in a Java SE environment. The managed case requires a provider interface
    that can be used by the container, while in the unmanaged case the JPA
    provider is responsible for supporting the client directly. This
    specification is about the unmanaged model of JPA except in the areas
    where the managed model is explicitly mentioned. Additionally, multiple
    concurrent providers for the unmanaged case are not supported.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dependencies</emphasis> - There must be a way for
          persistence clients, if they so require, to manage their
          dependencies on a compatible persistence unit.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Compatibility</emphasis> - The Persistence Unit
          service must be able to function in non-managed mode according to
          existing standards and interfaces outlined in the JPA
          specification.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Modularity</emphasis> - Persistent classes and their
          accompanying configuration can exist in a separate bundle from the
          client that is operating on them using the Persistence Unit
          service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>JDBC</emphasis> - Leverage the <xref
          linkend="service.jdbc"/> for access to the database.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>JPA</emphasis> - The Java Persistence API, <xref
          linkend="i3075842.1"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>JPA Provider</emphasis> - An implementation of JPA,
          providing the Persistence Provider and JPA Services to Java EE
          Containers and Client Bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Interface Bundle</emphasis> - A bundle containing
          the interfaces and classes in the <code>javax.persistence</code>
          namespace (and its sub-namespaces) that are defined by the JPA
          specification.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Persistence Bundle</emphasis> - A bundle that
          includes, a Meta-Persistence header, one or more Persistence
          Descriptor resources, and the entity classes specified by the
          Persistence Units in those resources.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Client Bundle</emphasis> - The bundle that uses the
          Persistence Bundle to retrieve and store objects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Persistence Descriptor</emphasis> - A resource
          describing one or more Persistence Units.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Persistence Unit</emphasis> - A named configuration
          for the object-relational mappings and database access as defined in
          a Persistence Descriptor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Entity Manager</emphasis> - The interface that
          provides the control point of retrieving and persisting objects in a
          relational database based on a single Persistence Unit for a single
          session.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Entity Manager Factory</emphasis> - A service that
          can create Entity Managers based on a Persistence Unit for different
          sessions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Entity Manager Factory Builder</emphasis> - A
          service that can build an Entity Manager Factory for a specific
          Persistence Unit with extra configuration parameters.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Managed Client</emphasis> - A Client Bundle that is
          managed by a Container</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Static Client</emphasis> - A Client that uses the
          static factory methods in the Persistence class instead of
          services.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Static Persistence</emphasis> - The actor that
          enables the use of the <code>Persistence</code> class static factory
          methods to obtain an Entity Manager Factory.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>JDBC Provider</emphasis> - The bundle providing a
          Data Source Factory service.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>JPA Service overview</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="4.229in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="jpa-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3113425">
      <title>Dependencies</title>

      <para>This specification requires a minimum JPA version of 2.1.
      Implementations may choose to support newer versions of JPA, for example
      version 2.2, but must offer the JavaJPA contract at version 2.1 as well
      as any future versions that they support.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>A JPA Provider tracks Persistence Bundles; a Persistence Bundle
      contains a Meta-Persistence manifest header. This manifest header
      enumerates the Persistence Descriptor resources in the Persistence
      Bundle. Each resource's XML schema is defined by the JPA specification.
      The JPA Provider reads the resource accordingly and extracts the
      information for one or more Persistence Units. For each found
      Persistence Unit, the JPA Provider registers an Entity Manager Factory
      Builder service. If the database is defined in the Persistence Unit,
      then the JPA Provider registers an Entity Manager Factory service during
      the availability of the corresponding Data Source Factory.</para>

      <para>The identification of these services is handled through a number
      of service properties. The Entity Manager Factory service is named by
      the standard JPA interface, the Builder version is OSGi specific; it is
      used when the Client Bundle needs to create an Entity Manager Factory
      based on configuration properties.</para>

      <para>A Client Bundle that wants to persist or retrieve its entity
      classes depends on an Entity Manager Factory (Builder) service that
      corresponds to a Persistence Unit that lists the entity classes. If such
      a service is available, the client can use this service to get an Entity
      Manager, allowing the client to retrieve and persist objects as long as
      the originating Entity Manager Factory (Builder) service is
      registered.</para>

      <para>In a non-OSGi environment, it is customary to get an Entity
      Manager Factory through the <code>Persistence</code> class. This
      <code>Persistence</code> class provides a number of static methods that
      give access to any locally available JPA providers. This approach is not
      recommended in an OSGi environment due to class loading and start
      ordering issues. However, OSGi environments can support access through
      this static factory with a Static Persistence bundle.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>JPA Overview</title>

    <para>Java Persistence API (JPA) is a specification that is part of <xref
    linkend="i3091015"/>. This OSGi Specification is based on <xref
    linkend="i3075794"/>, <xref linkend="i3075842"/> and <xref
    linkend="i3075842.1"/>. This section provides an overview of JPA as
    specified in the JCP. The purpose of this section is to introduce the
    concepts behind JPA and define the terminology that will be used in the
    remainder of the chapter.</para>

    <para>The purpose of JPA is to simplify access to relational databases for
    applications on the object-oriented Java platform. JPA provides support
    for storing and retrieving objects in a relational database. The JPA
    specification defines in detail how objects are mapped to tables and
    columns under the full control of the application. The core classes
    involved are depicted in <xref linkend="i3105110"/>.</para>

    <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="i3105110">
      <title>JPA Client View</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.800in"
                     contentwidth="6.246in" fileref="client-view.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The JPA specifications define a number of concepts that are defined
    in this section for the purpose of this OSGi specification. However, the
    full syntax and semantics are defined in the JPA specifications.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Persistence</title>

      <para>Classes that are stored and retrieved through JPA are called the
      <emphasis>entity classes</emphasis>. In this specification, the concept
      of entity classes includes the <emphasis>embeddable</emphasis> classes,
      which are classes that do not have any persistent identity, and mapped
      super classes that allow mappings, but are not themselves persistent.
      Entity classes are not required to implement any interface or extend a
      specific superclass, they are Plain Old Java Objects (POJOs). It is the
      responsibility of the <emphasis>JPA Provider</emphasis> to connect to a
      database and map the store and retrieve operations of the entity classes
      to their tables and columns. For performance reasons, the entity classes
      are sometimes <emphasis>enhanced</emphasis>. This enhancement can take
      place during build time, deploy time, or during class loading time. Some
      enhancements use byte code weaving, some enhancements are based on
      sub-classing.</para>

      <para>The JPA Provider cannot automatically perform its persistence
      tasks; it requires configuration information. This configuration
      information is stored in the <emphasis>Persistence
      Descriptor</emphasis>. A Persistence Descriptor is an XML file according
      of one of the two following namespaces:</para>

      <programlisting>http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/persistence/persistence_1_0.xsd
http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/persistence/persistence_2_0.xsd</programlisting>

      <para>The JPA standard Persistence Descriptor must be stored in
      <code>META-INF/persistence.xml</code>. It is usually in the same class
      path entry (like a JAR or directory) as the entity classes.</para>

      <para>The JPA Provider parses the Persistence Descriptor and extracts
      one or more <emphasis>Persistence Units</emphasis>. A Persistence Unit
      includes the following aspects:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Name</emphasis> - Every Persistence Unit must have a
          name to identify it to clients. For example:
          <code>Accounting</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Provider Selection</emphasis> - Restriction to a
          specific JPA Provider, usually because there are dependencies in the
          application code on provider specific functionality.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>JDBC Driver Selection</emphasis> - Selects the JDBC
          driver, the principal and the credentials for selecting and
          accessing a relational database. See <xref
          linkend="i3112211"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Properties</emphasis> - Standard and JPA Provider
          specific properties.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The object-relational mappings are stored in special mapping
      resources or are specified in annotations.</para>

      <para>A Persistence Unit can be <emphasis>complete</emphasis> or
      <emphasis>incomplete</emphasis>. A complete Persistence Unit identifies
      the database driver that is needed for the Persistence Unit, though it
      does not have to contain the credentials. An incomplete Persistence Unit
      lacks this information.</para>

      <para>The relations between the class path, its entries, the entity
      classes, the Persistence Descriptor and the Persistence Unit is depicted
      in <xref linkend="i3092836"
      xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i3092836">
        <title>JPA Configuration</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.800in"
                       contentwidth="6.264in" fileref="configuration.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>JPA recognizes the concept of a <emphasis>persistence
      root</emphasis>. The persistence root is the root of the JAR (or
      directory) on the class path that contains the
      <code>META-INF/persistence.xml</code> resource.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JPA Provider</title>

      <para>The JPA specifications provide support for multiple JPA Providers
      in the same application. An Application selects a JPA Provider through
      the <code>Persistence</code> class, using static factory methods. One of
      these methods accepts a map with <emphasis>configuration
      properties</emphasis>. Configuration properties can override information
      specified in a Persistence Unit or these properties add new information
      to the Persistence Unit.</para>

      <para>The default implementation of the <code>Persistence</code> class
      discovers providers through the Java EE services model, this model
      requires a text resource in the class path entry called:</para>

      <programlisting> <code>META-INF/services/javax.persistence.PersistenceProvider</code> </programlisting>

      <para>This text resource contains the name of the JPA Provider
      implementation class.</para>

      <para>The <code>Persistence</code> class
      <code>createEntityManagerFactory</code> method provides the JPA Provider
      with the name of a Persistence Unit. The JPA Provider must then scan the
      class path for any <code>META-INF/persistence.xml</code> entries, these
      are the available Persistence Descriptors. It then extracts the
      Persistence Units to find the requested Persistence Unit. If no such
      Persistence Unit can be found, or the JPA Provider is restricted from
      servicing this Persistence Unit, then <code>null</code> is returned. The
      Persistence class will then continue to try the next found or registered
      JPA Provider.</para>

      <para>A Persistence Unit can restrict JPA Providers by specifying a
      <emphasis>JPA Provider class</emphasis>, this introduces a
      <emphasis>provider dependency</emphasis>. The specified JPA Provider
      class must implement the <code>PersistenceProvider</code> interface.
      This <emphasis>implementation class name</emphasis> must be available
      from the JPA Provider's documentation. JPA Providers that do not own the
      specified JPA Provider class must ignore such a Persistence Unit.</para>

      <para>Otherwise, if the Persistence Unit is not restricted, the JPA
      Provider is <emphasis>assigned</emphasis> to this Persistence Unit; it
      must be ready to provide an <code>EntityManagerFactory</code> object
      when the application requests one.</para>

      <para>The JPA Provider uses the Persistence Unit, together with any
      additional configuration properties, to construct an <emphasis>Entity
      Manager Factory</emphasis>. The application then uses this Entity
      Manager Factory to construct an <emphasis>Entity Manager</emphasis>,
      optionally providing additional configuration properties. The Entity
      Manager then provides the operations for the application to store and
      retrieve entity classes from the database.</para>

      <para>The additional configuration properties provided with the creation
      of the Entity Manager Factory or the Entity Manager are often used to
      specify the database driver and the credentials. This allows the
      Persistence Unit to be specified without committing to a specific
      database, leaving the choice to the application at runtime.</para>

      <para>The relations between the application, Entity Manager, Entity
      Manager Factory and the JPA Provider are depicted in <xref
      linkend="i3094282" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i3094282">
        <title>JPA Dynamic Model</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.200in"
                       contentwidth="6.264in" fileref="dynamic-model.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3112132">
      <title>Managed and Unmanaged</title>

      <para>The JPA specifications make a distinction between a
      <emphasis>managed</emphasis> and an <emphasis>unmanaged</emphasis> mode.
      In the managed mode the presence of a Java EE Container is assumed. Such
      a container provides many services for its contained applications like
      transaction handling, dependency injection, etc. One of these aspects
      can be the interface to the relational database. The JPA specifications
      therefore have defined a special method for Java EE Containers to manage
      the persistence aspects of their Managed Clients. This method is the
      <code>createContainerEntityManagerFactory</code> method on the
      <code>PersistenceProvider</code> interface. This method is purely
      intended for Java EE Containers and should not be used in other
      environments.</para>

      <para>The other method on the <code>PersistenceProvider</code> interface
      is intended to be used by the <code>Persistence</code> class static
      factory methods. The Persistence class searches for an appropriate JPA
      Provider by asking all available JPA Providers to create an Entity
      Manager Factory based on configuration properties. The first JPA
      Provider that is capable of providing an Entity Manager Factory wins.
      The use of these static factory methods is called the
      <emphasis>unmanaged mode</emphasis>. It requires a JPA Provider to scan
      the class path to find the assigned Persistence Units.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3112211">
      <title>JDBC Access in JPA</title>

      <para>A Persistence Unit is configured to work with a relational
      database. JPA Providers communicate with a relational database through
      compliant JDBC database drivers. The database and driver parameters are
      specified in the Persistence Unit or configured during Entity Manager
      Factory or Entity Manager creation with the configuration properties.
      The configuration properties for selecting a database in non-managed
      mode were proprietary in JPA 1.0 but have been standardized in version
      2.0 of JPA:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.persistence.jdbc.driver</code> - Fully-qualified
          name of the driver class</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.persistence.jdbc.url</code> - Driver-specific URL
          to indicate database information</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.persistence.jdbc.user</code> - User name to use
          when obtaining connections</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.persistence.jdbc.password</code> - Password to use
          when obtaining connections</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Bundles with Persistence</title>

    <para>The primary goal of this specification is to simplify the
    programming model for bundles that need persistence. In this specification
    there are two application roles:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Persistence Bundle</emphasis> - A Persistence Bundle
        contains the entity classes and one or more Persistence Descriptors,
        each providing one or more Persistence Units.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Client Bundle</emphasis> -A Client Bundle contains the
        code that manipulates the entity classes and uses an Entity Manager to
        store and retrieve these entity classes with a relational database.
        The Client Bundle obtains the required Entity Manager(s) via a service
        based model.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>These roles can be combined in a single bundle.</para>

    <section xml:id="i3096192">
      <title>Services</title>

      <para>A JPA Provider uses Persistence Units to provide Client Bundles
      with a configured <emphasis>Entity Manager Factory</emphasis> service
      and/or an <emphasis>Entity Manager Factory Builder</emphasis> service
      for each assigned Persistence Unit:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Entity Manager Factory service</emphasis> - Provides
          an <code>EntityManagerFactory</code> object that depends on a
          complete Persistence Unit. That is, it is associated with a
          registered Data Source Factory service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Entity Manager Factory Builder service</emphasis> -
          The Entity Manager Factory Builder service provides the capability
          of creating an <code>EntityManagerFactory</code> object with
          additional configuration properties. The Entity Manager Factory
          Builder service also provides information about the JPA Provider
          that will be used to create the <code>EntityManagerFactory</code>
          object.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>These services are collectively called the <emphasis>JPA
      Services</emphasis>. Entity Managers obtained from such JPA Services can
      only be used to operate on entity classes associated with their
      corresponding Persistence Unit.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Persistence Bundle</title>

      <para>A <emphasis>Persistence Bundle</emphasis> is a bundle that
      specifies the Meta-Persistence header, see <xref linkend="i3088219"/>.
      This header refers to one or more Persistence Descriptors in the
      Persistence Bundle. Commonly, this is the
      <code>META-INF/persistence.xml</code> resource. This location is the
      standard for non-OSGi environments, however an OSGi bundle can also use
      other locations as well as multiple resources.</para>

      <para>For example, the contents of a simple Persistence Bundle with a
      single <code>Person</code> entity class could look like:</para>

      <programlisting>META-INF/
META-INF/MANIFEST.MF
OSGI-INF/address.xml
com/acme/Person.class</programlisting>

      <para>The corresponding manifest would then look like:</para>

      <programlisting>Manifest-Version: 1.0
Bundle-ManifestVersion: 2
Meta-Persistence: OSGI-INF/address.xml
Bundle-SymbolicName: com.acme.simple.persistence
Bundle-Version: 3.2.4.200912231004</programlisting>

      <para>A Persistence Bundle is a normal bundle; it must follow all the
      rules of OSGi and can use all OSGi constructs like Bundle-ClassPath,
      fragment bundles, import packages, export packages, etc. However, there
      is one limitation: any entity classes must originate in the bundle's
      JAR, it cannot come from a fragment. This requirement is necessary to
      simplify enhancing entity classes.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Client Bundles</title>

      <para>A Client Bundle uses the entity classes from a Persistence Bundle
      to provide its required functionality. To store and retrieve these
      entity classes a Client Bundle requires an Entity Manager that is
      configured for the corresponding Persistence Unit.</para>

      <para>An Entity Manager is intended to be used by a single session, it
      is not thread safe. Therefore, a client needs an Entity Manager Factory
      to create an Entity Manager. In an OSGi environment, there are multiple
      routes to obtain an Entity Manager Factory.</para>

      <para>A JPA Provider must register an Entity Manager Factory service for
      each assigned Persistence Unit that is <emphasis>complete</emphasis>.
      Complete means that it is a configured Persistence Unit, including the
      reference to the relational database. The Entity Manager Factory service
      is therefore bound to a Data Source Factory service and Client Bundles
      should not attempt to rebind the Data Source Factory with the
      configuration properties of the <code>createEntityManager(Map)</code>
      method. See <xref linkend="i3115644"/> for the consequences. If the Data
      Source Factory must be bound by the Client Bundle then the Client Bundle
      should use the <xref linkend="i3095031"/>.</para>

      <para>The Entity Manager Factory service must be registered with the
      service properties as defined in <xref linkend="i3087143"/>. These
      are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>osgi.unit.name</code> - (<code>String</code>) The name
          of the Persistence Unit</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>osgi.unit.version</code> - (<code>String</code>) The
          version of the associated Persistence Bundle</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>osgi.unit.provider</code> - (<code>String</code>) The
          implementation class name of the JPA Provider</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The life cycle of the Entity Manager Factory service is bound to
      the Persistence Bundle, the JPA Provider, and the selected Data Source
      Factory service.</para>

      <para>A Client Bundle that wants to use an Entity Manager Factory
      service should therefore use an appropriate filter to select the Entity
      Manager Factory service that corresponds to its required Persistence
      Unit. For example, the following snippet uses Declarative Services, see
      <xref linkend="service.component"/>, to statically depend on such a
      service:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;reference name="accounting"
   target="(&amp;amp;(osgi.unit.name=Accounting)(osgi.unit.version=3.2.*))"
    interface="javax.persistence.EntityManagerFactory"/&gt;</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3095031">
      <title>Custom Configured Entity Manager</title>

      <para>If a Client Bundle needs to provide configuration properties for
      the creation of an Entity Manager Factory it should use the
      <emphasis>Entity Manager Factory Builder</emphasis> service. This can
      for example be used to provide the database selection properties when
      the Persistence Unit is incomplete or if the database selection needs to
      be overridden. The Entity Manager Factory Builder service also provides
      information about the JPA Provider that will be used to create the
      Entity Manager Factory. This information can be used by the Client
      Bundle when determining what (if any) JPA Provider implementation
      specific configuration that the Client Bundle will provide.</para>

      <para>The Entity Manager Factory Builder service's life cycle must not
      depend on the availability of any Data Source Factory, even if a JDBC
      driver class name is specified in the Persistence Descriptor. The Entity
      Manager Factory Builder service is registered with the same service
      properties as the corresponding Entity Factory service, see <xref
      linkend="i3087143"/>.</para>

      <para>The following methods are defined on the
      <code>EntityManagerFactoryBuilder</code> interface:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa.EntityManagerFactoryBuilder.createEntityManagerFactory-Map-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns a custom configured
          <code>EntityManagerFactory</code> instance for the Persistence Unit
          associated with the service. Accepts a map with the configuration
          properties to be applied during Entity Manager Factory creation. The
          method must return a proper Entity Manager Factory or throw an
          Exception.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa.EntityManagerFactoryBuilder.getPersistenceProviderName--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns the name of the
          <code>PersistenceProvider</code> implementation class used in Entity
          Manager Factory creation. This name will be the same as the value of
          the <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa.EntityManagerFactoryBuilder.JPA_UNIT_PROVIDER"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service property.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa.EntityManagerFactoryBuilder.getPersistenceProviderBundle--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns the bundle JPA Provider
          implementation bundle which provides the
          <code>PersistenceProvider</code>. If the Persistence Provider was
          provided as an OSGi service then this method must return the bundle
          which registered the service. Otherwise this method must return the
          bundle which loaded the <code>PersistenceProvider</code>
          implementation class.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The <code>createEntityManagerFactory</code> method allows standard
      and vendor-specific properties to be passed in and applied to the Entity
      Manager Factory being created. However, some properties cannot be
      honored by the aforementioned method. For example, the
      <code>javax.persistence.provider</code> JPA property, as a means to
      specify a specific JPA Provider at runtime, cannot be supported because
      the JPA Provider has already been decided; it is the JPA Provider that
      registered the Entity Manager Factory Builder service. A JPA Provider
      should throw an Exception if it recognizes the property but it cannot
      use the property when specified through the builder. Unrecognized
      properties must be ignored.</para>

      <para>Once an Entity Manager Factory is created the specified Data
      Source becomes associated with the Entity Manager Factory. It is
      therefore not possible to re-associate an Entity Manager Factory with
      another Data Source by providing different properties. A JPA Provider
      must throw an Exception when an attempt is made to re-specify the
      database properties. See <xref linkend="i3115644"/> for further
      information.</para>

      <para>As an example, a sample snippet of a client that wants to operate
      on a persistence unit named <code>Accounting</code> and pass in the JDBC
      user name and password properties is:</para>

      <programlisting>ServiceReference[] refs = context.getServiceReferences(
    EntityManagerFactoryBuilder.class.getName(),
    "(osgi.unit.name=Accounting)");
if ( refs != null ) {
    EntityManagerFactoryBuilder emfBuilder = 
        (EntityManagerFactoryBuilder) context.getService(refs[0]);
    if ( emfBuilder != null ) {
      Map&lt;String,Object&gt; props = new HashMap&lt;String,Object&gt;();
      props.put("javax.persistence.jdbc.user", userString);
      props.put("javax.persistence.jdbc.password",passwordString);
      EntityManagerFactory emf = emfBuilder.createEntityManagerFactory(props);
      EntityManager em = emf.createEntityManager();
     ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>The example does not handle the dynamic dependencies on the
      associated Data Source Factory service.</para>

      <section xml:id="service.jpa-std.config.props">
        <title>Supported configuration properties</title>

        <para>The <xref linkend="i3075842.1"/> specification adds a
        significant number of standard property names. These properties are
        used both for runtime control, and also for configuring JPA
        persistence units as they are created.</para>

        <para>The EntityManagerFactoryBuilder service must support the defined
        property names as per the JPA specification. In most cases this will
        be accomplished by passing the values directly to the Persistence
        Provider, but in some cases it may require further action from the JPA
        Service implementation.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i3097804">
    <title>Extending a Persistence Bundle</title>

    <para>A Persistence Bundle is identified by its Meta-Persistence manifest
    header that references a number of Persistence Descriptor resources.
    Persistence bundles must be detected by a JPA Provider. The JPA Provider
    must parse any Persistence Descriptors in these bundles and detect the
    assigned Persistence Units. For each assigned Persistence Unit, the JPA
    Provider must register an Entity Manager Factory Builder service when the
    Persistence Bundle is ready, see <xref linkend="i3100956"/>.</para>

    <para>For complete and assigned Persistence Units, the JPA Provider must
    find the required Data Source Factory service based on the driver name.
    When the Persistence Bundle is ready and the selected Data Source Factory
    is available, the JPA Provider must have an Entity Manager Factory service
    registered that is linked to that Data Source Factory.</para>

    <para>When the Persistence Bundle is stopped (or the JPA Provider stops),
    the JPA Provider must close all connections and cleanup any resources
    associated with the Persistence Bundle.</para>

    <para>This process is outlined in detail in the following sections.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Class Space Consistency</title>

      <para>A JPA Provider must ignore Persistence Bundles that are in another
      class space for the <code>javax.persistence.*</code> packages. Such a
      JPA Provider cannot create JPA Services that would be visible and usable
      by the Client Bundles.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3088219">
      <title>Meta Persistence Header</title>

      <para>A <emphasis>Persistence Bundle</emphasis> is a bundle that
      contains the Meta-Persistence header. If this header is not present,
      then this specification does not apply and a JPA Provider should ignore
      the corresponding bundle.</para>

      <para>The persistence root of a Persistence Unit is the root of the
      Persistence Bundle's JAR</para>

      <para>The Meta-Persistence header has a syntax of:</para>

      <programlisting>Meta-Persistence ::= ( jar-path ( ',' jar-path)* )?
jar-path         ::= path ( '!/' spath )? 
spath            ::= path   // must not start with solidus ('/' \u002F)</programlisting>

      <para>The header may include zero or more comma-separated
      <code>jar-paths</code>, each a path to a Persistence Descriptor resource
      in the bundle. Paths may optionally be prefixed with the solidus
      (<code>'/' \u002F</code>) character. The JPA Provider must always
      include the <code>META-INF/persistence.xml</code> first if it is not one
      of the listed paths. Wildcards in directories are not supported. The
      <code>META-INF/persistence.xml</code> is therefore the default location
      for an empty header.</para>

      <para>For example:</para>

      <programlisting>Meta-Persistence: META-INF/jpa.xml, persistence/jpa.xml</programlisting>

      <para>The previous example will instruct the JPA Provider to process the
      <code>META-INF/persistence.xml</code> resource first, even though it is
      not explicitly listed. The JPA Provider must then subsequently process
      <code>META-INF/jpa.xml</code> and the <code>persistence/jpa.xml</code>
      resources.</para>

      <para>The paths in the Meta-Persistence header must be used with the
      <code>Bundle.getEntry()</code> method, or a mechanism with similar
      semantics, to obtain the corresponding resource. The
      <code>getEntry</code> method does not force the bundle to resolve when
      still unresolved; resolving might interfere with the efficiency of any
      required entity class enhancements. However, the use of the
      <code>getEntry</code> method implies that fragment bundles cannot be
      used to contain Persistence Descriptors nor entity classes.</para>

      <para>Paths in the Meta-Persistence header can reference JAR files that
      are nested in the bundle by using the <code>!/ jar:</code> URL syntax to
      separate the JAR file from the path within the JAR, for example:</para>

      <programlisting>Meta-Persistence: embedded.jar!/META-INF/persistence.xml</programlisting>

      <para>This example refers to a resource in the <code>embedded.jar</code>
      resource, located in the <code>META-INF</code> directory of
      <code>embedded.jar</code>.</para>

      <para>The <code>!/</code> splits the <code>jar-path</code> in a prefix
      and a suffix:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Prefix</emphasis> - The prefix is a path to a JAR
          resource in the bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Suffix</emphasis> - The suffix is a path to a
          resource in the JAR identified by the prefix.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For example:</para>

      <programlisting>embedded.jar!/META-INF/persistence.xml
prefix:     embedded.jar
suffix:     META-INF/persistence.xml</programlisting>

      <para>It is not required that all listed or implied resources are
      present in the bundle's JAR. For example, it is valid that the default
      <code>META-INF/persistence.xml</code> resource is absent. However, if no
      Persistence Units are found at all then the absence of any Persistence
      Unit is regarded as an error that should be logged. In this case, the
      Persistence Bundle is further ignored.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Processing</title>

      <para>A JPA Provider can detect a Persistence Bundle as early as its
      installation time. This early detection allows the JPA Provider to
      validate the Persistence Bundle as well as prepare any mechanisms to
      enhance the classes for better performance. However, this process can
      also be delayed until the bundle is started.</para>

      <para>The JPA Provider must validate the Persistence Bundle. A valid
      Persistence Bundle must:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Have no parsing errors of the Persistence Descriptors</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Validate all Persistence Descriptors against their
          schemas</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Have at least one assigned Persistence Unit</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Have all entity classes mentioned in the assigned Persistence
          Units on the Persistence Bundle's JAR.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A Persistence Bundle that uses multiple providers for its
      Persistence Units could become incompatible with future versions of this
      specification.</para>

      <para>If any validation fails, then this is an error and should be
      logged. Such a bundle is ignored completely even if it also contains
      valid assigned Persistence Units. Only a bundle update can recover from
      this state.</para>

      <para>Persistence Units can restrict JPA Providers by specifying a
      provider dependency. JPA Providers that do not own this JPA Provider
      implementation class must ignore such a Persistence Unit completely.
      Otherwise, if the JPA Provider can service a Persistence Unit, it
      assigns itself to this Persistence Unit.</para>

      <para>If after the processing of all Persistence Descriptors, the JPA
      Provider has no assigned Persistence Units, then the JPA Provider must
      further ignore the Persistence Bundle.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3100956">
      <title>Ready Phase</title>

      <para>A Persistence Bundle is <emphasis>ready</emphasis> when its state
      is <code>ACTIVE</code> or, when a <code>lazy</code> activation policy is
      used, <code>STARTING</code>. A JPA Provider must track the ready state
      of Persistence Bundles that contain assigned Persistence Units.</para>

      <para>While a Persistence Bundle is ready, the JPA Provider must have,
      for each assigned Persistence Unit, an Entity Manager Factory Builder
      service registered to allow Client Bundles to create new
      <code>EntityManagerFactory</code> objects. The JPA Provider must also
      register an Entity Manager Factory for each assigned and complete
      Persistence Unit that has its corresponding Data Source available in the
      service registry.</para>

      <para>The service registration process is asynchronous with the
      Persistence Bundle start because a JPA Provider could start after a
      Persistence Bundle became ready.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3087143">
      <title>Service Registrations</title>

      <para>The JPA Services must be registered through the Bundle Context of
      the corresponding Persistence Bundle to ensure proper class space
      consistency checks by the OSGi Framework.</para>

      <para>JPA Services are always related to an assigned Persistence Unit.
      To identify this Persistence Unit and the assigned JPA Provider, each
      JPA Service must have the following service properties:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>osgi.unit.name</code> - (<code>String</code>) The name
          of the Persistence Unit. This property corresponds to the
          <code>name</code> attribute of the <code>persistence-unit</code>
          element in the Persistence Descriptor. It is used by Client Bundles
          as the primary filter criterion to obtain a JPA Service for a
          required Persistence Unit. There can be multiple JPA Services
          registered under the same <code>osgi.unit.name</code>, each
          representing a different version of the Persistence Unit.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>osgi.unit.version</code> - (<code>String</code>) The
          version of the Persistence Bundle, as specified in Bundle-Version
          header, that provides the corresponding Persistence Unit. Client
          Bundles can filter their required JPA Services based on a particular
          Persistence Unit version.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>osgi.unit.provider</code> - (<code>String</code>) The
          JPA Provider implementation class name that registered the service.
          The <code>osgi.unit.provider</code> property allows Client Bundles
          to know the JPA Provider that is servicing the Persistence Unit.
          Client Bundles should be careful when filtering on this property,
          however, since the JPA Provider that is assigned a Persistence Unit
          may not be known by the Client Bundle ahead of time. If there is a
          JPA Provider dependency, it is better to specify this dependency in
          the Persistence Unit because other JPA Providers are then not
          allowed to assign such a Persistence Unit and will therefore not
          register a service.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3083073">
      <title>Registering the Entity Manager Factory Builder Service</title>

      <para>Once the Persistence Bundle is ready, a JPA Provider must register
      an Entity Manager Factory Builder service for each assigned Persistence
      Unit from that Persistence Bundle.</para>

      <para>The Entity Manager Factory Builder service must be registered with
      the service properties listed in <xref linkend="i3087143"/>. The Entity
      Manager Factory Builder service is registered under the
      <code>org.osgi.service.jpa.EntityManagerFactoryBuilder</code> name. This
      interface is using the JPA packages and is therefore bound to one of the
      two supported versions, see <xref linkend="i3113425"/>.</para>

      <para>The Entity Manager Factory Builder service enables the creation of
      a parameterized version of an Entity Factory Manager by allowing the
      caller to specify configuration properties. This approach is necessary
      if, for example, the Persistence Unit is not complete.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3097403">
      <title>Registering the Entity Manager Factory</title>

      <para>A complete Persistence Unit is configured with a specific
      relational database driver, see <xref linkend="i3112211"/>. A JPA
      Provider must have an Entity Manager Factory service registered for each
      assigned and complete Persistence Unit when:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The originating Persistence Bundle is ready, and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <emphasis>matching</emphasis> Data Source Factory service is
          available. Matching a Data Source Factory service to a Persistence
          Unit is discussed in <xref linkend="i3097361"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A JPA Provider must track the life cycle of the matching Data
      Source Factory service; while this service is unavailable the Entity
      Manager Factory service must also be unavailable. Any active Entity
      Managers created by the Entity Manager Factory service become invalid to
      use at that time.</para>

      <para>The Entity Manager Factory service must be registered with the
      same service properties as described for the Entity Manager Factory
      Builder service, see <xref linkend="i3087143"/>. It should be registered
      under the following name:</para>

      <programlisting> <code>javax.persistence.EntityManagerFactory</code></programlisting>

      <para>The <code>EntityManagerFactory</code> interface is from the JPA
      packages and is therefore bound to one of the two supported versions,
      see <xref linkend="i3113425"/>.</para>

      <para>An Entity Manager Factory is bound to a Data Source Factory
      service because its assigned Persistence Unit was complete. However, a
      Client Bundle could still provide JDBC configuration properties for the
      <code>createEntityManager(Map)</code> method. This not always possible,
      see <xref linkend="i3115644"/>.</para>

      <para>In the case of an incomplete Persistence Unit no Entity Manager
      Factory can be initially registered, however once configured using an
      Entity Manager Factory Builder service the JPA Service must register the
      created Entity Manager Factory as a service. The registered service must
      include any supplied configuration properties that match the recommended
      OSGi service property types as service properties. The
      <code>javax.persistence.jdbc.password</code> property must be omitted
      from these service properties.</para>

      <para>If the Entity Manager Factory Builder service is later used to
      change the configuration being used by the Entity Manager Factory
      Service then the registered Entity Manager Factory service must be
      unregistered and closed. The newly created Entity Manager Factory object
      must then be registered as a service.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Stopping</title>

      <para>If a Persistence Bundle is being stopped, then the JPA Provider
      must ensure that any resources allocated on behalf of the Persistence
      Bundle are cleaned up and all open connections are closed. This cleanup
      must happen synchronously with the <code>STOPPING</code> event. Any
      Exceptions being thrown while cleaning up should be logged but must not
      stop any further clean up.</para>

      <para>If the JPA Provider is being stopped, the JPA Provider must
      unregister all JPA Services that it registered through the Persistence
      Bundles and clean up as if those bundles were stopped.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entity Manager Factory Life Cycle</title>

      <para>The Entity Manager Factory object has a <code>close</code> method.
      This method closes the EntityManagerFactory and all associated Entity
      Manager instances. As an OSGi framework is a multi-tenant environment it
      should not be possible for one user of an Entity Manager Factory service
      to break the valid usage of another. Therefore calls to the
      <code>close</code> method of the EntityManagerFactory registered in the
      service registry <emphasis>must not</emphasis> close the Entity Manager
      Factory.</para>

      <para>When an Entity Manager Factory Builder service is used to create
      an Entity Manager Factory the same rules apply to the resulting Entity
      Manager Factory service, however the object returned by the Entity
      Manager Factory Builder behaves differently. This object has a working
      close method which must unregister the Entity Manager Factory service
      and close the Entity Manager Factory. This allows callers of the Entity
      Manager Factory Builder to invalidate the Entity Manager Factories that
      they create if, for example, a configuration changes, or a Data Source
      becomes invalid.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>JPA Provider</title>

    <para>JPA Providers supply the implementation of the JPA Services and the
    Persistence Provider service. It is the responsibility of a JPA Provider
    to store and retrieve the entity classes from a relational database. It is
    the responsibility of the JPA Provider to register a Persistence Provider
    and start tracking Persistence Bundles, see <xref
    linkend="i3097804"/>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Managed Model</title>

      <para>A JPA Provider that supports running in managed mode should
      register a specific service for the Java EE Containers: the Persistence
      Provider service. The interface is the standard JPA
      <code>PersistenceProvider</code> interface. See <xref
      linkend="i3113425"/> for the issues around the multiple versions that
      this specification supports.</para>

      <para>The service must be registered with the following service
      property:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.persistence.provider</code> - The JPA Provider
          implementation class name, a documented name for all JPA
          Providers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Persistence Provider service enables a Java EE Container to
      find a particular JPA Provider. This service is intended for containers
      only, not for Client Bundles because there are implicit assumptions in
      the JPA Providers about the Java EE environment. A Java EE Container
      must obey the life cycle of the Persistence Provider service. If this
      service is unregistered then it must close all connections and clean up
      the corresponding resources.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3097361">
      <title>Database Access</title>

      <para>A Persistence Unit is configured to work with a relational
      database. JPA Providers must communicate with a relational database
      through a compliant JDBC database driver. The database and driver
      parameters are specified with properties in the Persistence Unit or the
      configuration properties when a Entity Manager Factory Builder is used
      to build an Entity Manager Factory. All JPA Providers, regardless of
      version, in an OSGi environment must support the following properties
      for database access:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.persistence.jdbc.driver</code> - Fully-qualified
          name of the driver class.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.persistence.jdbc.url</code> - Driver-specific URL
          to indicate database information</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.persistence.jdbc.user</code> - User name to use
          when obtaining connections</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.persistence.jdbc.password</code> - Password to use
          when obtaining connections</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>There are severe limitations in specifying these properties after
      the Entity Manager Factory is created for the first time, see <xref
      linkend="i3115644"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Data Source Factory Service Matching</title>

      <para>Providers must use the <code>javax.persistence.jdbc.driver</code>
      property, as defined in <xref linkend="i3112211"/>, to obtain a Data
      Source Factory service. The Data Source Factory is specified in <xref
      linkend="service.jdbc"/>. The <code>javax.persistence.jdbc.driver</code>
      property must be matched with the value of the Data Source Factory
      service property named <code>osgi.jdbc.driver.class</code>.</para>

      <para>The Data Source Factory service is registered with the
      <code>osgi.jdbc.driver.class</code> service property that holds the
      class name of the driver. This property must match the
      <code>javax.persistence.jdbc.driver</code> service property of the
      Persistence Unit.</para>

      <para>For example, if the Persistence Unit specifies the
      <code>com.acme.db.Driver</code> database driver in the
      <code>javax.persistence.jdbc.driver property</code> (or in the
      Persistence Descriptor <code>property</code> element), then the
      following filter would select an appropriate <code>Data Source
      Factory:</code></para>

      <programlisting>(&amp;(objectClass=org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory)
   (<code>osgi.jdbc.driver.class=com.acme.db.Driver))</code></programlisting>

      <para>Once the Data Source Factory is obtained, the JPA Provider must
      obtain a <code>DataSource</code> object. This Data Source object must
      then be used for all relational database access.</para>

      <para>In <xref linkend="i3075794"/> the JPA JDBC properties were not
      standardized. JPA Providers typically defined a set of JDBC properties,
      similar to those defined in JPA 2.0, to configure JDBC driver access.
      JPA 1.0 JPA Providers must look up the Data Source Factory service first
      using the JPA 2.0 JDBC properties. If these properties are not defined
      then they should fall back to their proprietary driver
      properties.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3115644">
      <title>Rebinding</title>

      <para>In this specification, the Entity Manager Factory service is only
      registered when the Persistence Unit is complete and a matching Data
      Source Factory service is available. However, the API of the Entity
      Manager Factory Builder allows the creation of an Entity Manager Factory
      with configuration properties. Those configuration properties could
      contain the JDBC properties to bind to another Data Source Factory
      service than it had already selected.</para>

      <para>This case must not be supported by a JPA Provider, an Illegal
      Argument Exception must be thrown. If such a case would be supported
      then the life cycle of the Entity Manager Factory service would still be
      bound to the first Data Source Factory. There would be no way for the
      JPA Provider to signal to the Client Bundle that the returned Entity
      Manager Factory is no longer valid because the rebound Data Source
      Factory was unregistered.</para>

      <para>Therefore, when an Entity Manager Factory is being created using
      the Entity Manager Factory Builder, a JPA Provider must verify that the
      new properties are compatible with the properties of the already created
      Entity Manager Factory. If no, then an Exception must be thrown. If they
      are compatible, then an instance of the previous Entity Manager Factory
      should be returned.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Enhancing Entity Classes</title>

      <para>JPA Providers may choose to implement the JPA specifications using
      various implementation approaches and techniques. This promotes
      innovation in the area, but also opens the door to limitations and
      constraints arising due to implementation choices. For example, there
      are JPA Providers that perform byte code weaving during the entity class
      loading. Dynamic byte code weaving requires that the entity classes are
      not loaded until the JPA Provider is first able to intercept the loading
      of the entity class and be given an opportunity to do its weaving. It
      also implies that the Persistence Bundle and any other bundles that
      import packages from that bundle must be refreshed if the JPA Provider
      needs to be changed.</para>

      <para>This is necessary because the JPA Services are registered against
      the Bundle Contexts of the Persistence Bundles and not the Bundle
      Context of the JPA Providers. Client Bundles must then unget the service
      to unbind themselves from the uninstalled JPA Provider. However, since
      most JPA Providers perform some kind of weaving or class transformation
      on the entity classes, the Persistence Bundle will likely need to be
      refreshed. This will cause the Client Bundles to be refreshed also
      because they depend on the packages of the entity classes.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Class Loading</title>

      <para>JPA Providers cannot have package dependencies on entity classes
      in Persistence Bundles because they cannot know at install time what
      Persistence Bundles they will be servicing. However, when a JPA Provider
      is servicing a Persistence Bundle, it must be able to load classes and
      resources from that Persistence Bundle according to the OSGi bundle
      rules. To do this class loading it must obtain a class loader that has
      the same visibility as the Persistence Bundle's bundle class loader.
      This will also allow it to load and manage metadata for the entity
      classes and resources for that Persistence Bundle's assigned Persistence
      Units. These resources and entity classes must reside directly in the
      Persistence Bundle, they must be accessed using the
      <code>getEntry</code> method. Entity classes and resources must not
      reside in fragments.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Validation</title>

      <para>There is not yet an OSGi service specification defined for
      validation providers. If validation is required, the validation
      implementation will need to be included with the JPA Provider
      bundle.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Static Access</title>

    <para>Non-managed client usage of JPA has traditionally been achieved
    through the <code>Persistence</code> class. Invoking a static method on
    the <code>Persistence</code> class is a dependency on the returned JPA
    Provider that cannot be managed by the OSGi framework.</para>

    <para>However, such an unmanaged dependency is supported in this
    specification by the Static Persistence bundle. This bundle provides
    backwards compatibility for programs that use existing JPA access
    patterns. However, usage of this static model requires that the deployer
    ensures that the actors needed are in place at the appropriate times by
    controlling the life cycles of all participating bundles. The normal OSGi
    safe-guards and dependency handling do not work in the case of static
    access.</para>

    <para>A Static Persistence Bundle must provide static access from the
    <code>Persistence</code> class to the JPA Services.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Access</title>

      <para>There are two methods on the <code>Persistence</code>
      class:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>createEntityManagerFactory(String)</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>createEntityManagerFactory(String,Map)</code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Both methods take the name of a Persistence Unit. The last method
      also takes a map that contains extra configuration properties. To
      support the usage of the static methods on the <code>Persistence</code>
      class, the implementation of the
      <code>Persistence.createEntityManagerFactory</code> method family must
      do a lookup of one of the JPA Services associated with the selected
      Persistence Unit.</para>

      <para>If no configuration properties are specified, the Static
      Persistence Bundle must look for an Entity Manager Factory service with
      the <code>osgi.unit.name</code> property set to the given name. The
      default service should be used because no selector for a version is
      provided. If no such service is available, <code>null</code> must be
      returned. Provisioning of multiple versioned Persistence Units is not
      supported. Deployers should ensure only a single version of a
      Persistence Unit with the same name is present in an OSGi framework at
      any moment in time.</para>

      <para>Otherwise, if configuration properties are provided, the Static
      Access implementation must look for an Entity Manager Factory Builder
      service with the <code>osgi.unit.name</code> property set to the given
      Persistence Unit name. If no such service exists, <code>null</code> must
      be returned. Otherwise, the default service must be used to create an
      Entity Manager Factory with the given configuration properties. The
      result must be returned to the caller.</para>

      <para>For service lookups, the Static Persistence Bundle must use its
      own Bundle Context, it must not attempt to use the Bundle Context of the
      caller. All exceptions should be passed to the caller.</para>

      <para>The class space of the Entity Manager Factory and the class space
      of the client cannot be enforced to be consistent by the framework
      because it is the <code>Persistence</code> class that is doing the
      lookup of the service, and not the actual calling Client Bundle that
      will be using the Entity Manager Factory. The framework cannot make the
      connection and therefore cannot enforce that the class spaces
      correspond. Deployers should therefore ensure that the involved class
      spaces are correctly wired.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.jpa-capabilities">
    <title>Capabilities</title>

    <para>The JPA Service Implementation must supply a number of capabilities
    for use by client bundles and Deployers.</para>

    <section>
      <title>The Extender Capability</title>

      <para>A JPA Service implementation must provide an extender which finds
      and extends persistence bundles. The bundle providing this extender must
      provide a capability in the <link
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.extender.namespace">
      <code>osgi.extender</code></link> namespace declaring an extender with
      the name <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa.EntityManagerFactoryBuilder.JPA_CAPABILITY_NAME"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This capability must also declare a uses
      constraint for the <code>org.osgi.service.jpa</code> and
      <code>javax.persistence</code> packages. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.extender;
    osgi.extender="osgi.jpa";
    version:Version="<xref endterm="org.osgi.service.jpa-version.number"
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa"/>";
    uses:="org.osgi.service.jpa,javax.persistence"</programlisting>

      <para>This capability must follow the rules defined for the <xref
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.extender.namespace"/>.</para>

      <para>All persistence bundles should require the
      <code>osgi.extender</code> capability from the JPA Service. This
      requirement will wire the persistence bundle to the JPA Service
      implementation and ensure that the JPA service is using the same API
      packages as the persistence bundle.</para>

      <programlisting>Require-Capability: osgi.extender;
  filter:="(&amp;(osgi.extender=osgi.jpa)(version&gt;=<xref
          endterm="org.osgi.service.jpa-version.number"
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa"/>)(!(version&gt;=2.0)))"</programlisting>

      <para>This requirement can be easily generated using the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa.annotations.RequireJPAExtender"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> annotation.</para>

      <para>The JPA extender must only process a persistence bundle's
      persistence units if the following is true:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The bundle's wiring has a required wire for at least one
          <code>osgi.extender</code> capability with the name
          <code>osgi.jpa</code> and the first of these required wires is wired
          to the JPA extender.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The bundle's wiring has no required wire for an
          <code>osgi.extender</code> capability with the name
          <code>osgi.jpa</code>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Otherwise, the JPA Service extender must not process the
      persistence bundle</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The JPA Contract Capability</title>

      <para>Previous versions of this specification recommended that the JPA
      API packages were versioned using the OSGi recommended semantic
      versioning policy. Whilst this would have been an excellent way to
      ensure compatibility between JPA persistence bundles, client bundles,
      and JPA providers, in practice few bundles followed this versioning
      policy. As a result the various actors in the JPA service can easily be
      created with have clashing version ranges.</para>

      <para>This problem is not isolated to JPA, and so a general solution was
      created called <xref
      linkend="service.jpa-portable.java.contracts.ref"/>. These define a
      capability namespace called <link
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.contract.namespace"><code>osgi.contract</code></link></para>

      <para>In order to permit JPA clients to reliably work when paired with
      newer versions of JPA there needs to be a defined contract upon which
      the clients and persistence units can rely, otherwise a JPA 1.0
      compatible client cannot declare a dependency which also accepts the
      backward compatible JPA 2.0 API. For JPA the following three contracts
      exist:</para>

      <programlisting>osgi.contract;osgi.contract=JavaJPA;version:Version=1;
    uses:="javax.persistence,javax.persistence.spi"
      </programlisting>

      <programlisting>osgi.contract;osgi.contract=JavaJPA;version:Version=2;
    uses:="javax.persistence,javax.persistence.criteria,
    javax.persistence.metamodel,javax.persistence.spi"
      </programlisting>

      <programlisting>osgi.contract;osgi.contract=JavaJPA;version:Version=2.1;
          uses:="javax.persistence,javax.persistence.criteria,
          javax.persistence.metamodel,javax.persistence.spi"
      </programlisting>

      <para>JPA API providers must declare the full set of API contract
      versions with which they are compatible. As JPA API versions are
      backward compatible this will typically result in the provider exposing
      all versions of a contract. Note that when a provider offers multiple
      versions of a contract then all of the contract versions must be offered
      by a single capability. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>Export-Package: javax.persistence,javax.persistence.criteria,
 javax.persistence.metamodel,javax.persistence.spi
Provide-Capability: osgi.contract;osgi.contract=JavaJPA;
 version:List&gt;Version&lt;="2.1,2,1"; uses:="javax.persistence,
 javax.persistence.criteria,javax.persistence.metamodel,javax.persistence.spi"</programlisting>

      <para>The contract capability means that clients can safely import the
      API using the contract and no import version. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>Import-Package: javax.persistence,javax.persistence.criteria
Require-Capability: osgi.contract;
 filter:="(&amp;(osgi.contract=JavaJPA)(version=2.1))"</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Service capabilities</title>

      <para>The JPA Service implementation is responsible for registering both
      an <code>EntityManagerFactoryBuilder</code> service and a
      <code>EntityManagerFactory</code> service on behalf of the persistence
      bundle. The persistence bundle should therefore provide two capabilities
      in the <link
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"><code>osgi.service</code></link>
      namespace, one representing the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.jpa.EntityManagerFactoryBuilder"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service, and another representing the
      <code>javax.persistence.EntityManagerFactory</code> service. These
      capabilities must also declare uses constraints for the packages that
      they expose. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.service;
    objectClass:List&lt;String&gt;=
      "org.osgi.service.jpa.EntityManagerFactoryBuilder";
    uses:="org.osgi.service.jpa",
    osgi.service;objectClass:List&lt;String&gt;=
      "javax.persistence.EntityManagerFactory";
    uses:="javax.persistence"</programlisting>

      <para>This capability must follow the rules defined for the <xref
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>When Java permissions are enabled, the JPA service must perform the
    following security procedures.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Service Permissions</title>

      <para>The JPA service is built upon the existing OSGi service
      infrastructure. This means that Service Permission applies regarding the
      ability to publish services. A persistence bundle therefore must have
      <code>ServicePermission[&lt;interface&gt;, REGISTER]</code> for both the
      <code>EntityManagerFactory</code> and
      <code>EntityManagerFactoryBuilder</code> services.</para>

      <para>If a persistence bundle specifies a complete persistence unit then
      the persistence bundle must either have
      <code>ServicePermission[&lt;org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory&gt;,
      GET]</code>, or be able to directly load the configured database
      driver.</para>

      <para>Client bundles that wish to configure a persistence unit using the
      <code>EntityManagerFactoryBuilder</code> service must have
      <code>ServicePermission[&lt;org.osgi.service.jpa.EntityManagerFactoryBuilder&gt;,
      GET]</code>. Furthermore, if this service is used to configure an
      incomplete persistence unit with a database driver name then it is the
      getter of the <code>EntityManagerFactoryBuilder</code> service whose
      permissions must be checked when obtaining the
      <code>DataSourceFactory</code> service. If the caller of the
      EntityManagerFactory Builder passes a ready constructed database
      <code>Driver</code> or <code>DataSource</code> then no permission check
      is required.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Required Admin Permission</title>

      <para>The JPA service implementation requires
      <code>AdminPermission[*,CONTEXT]</code> because it needs access to the
      bundle's Bundle Context object with the
      <code>Bundle.getBundleContext()</code> method.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.jpa.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.jpa.annotations.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3075794"><title>JPA 1.0</title><biblioid
      class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/summary?id=220"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3075842"><title>JPA 2.0</title><biblioid
      class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/summary?id=317"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3075842.1"><title>JPA 2.1</title><biblioid
      class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/summary?id=317"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3091015"><title>Java EE 5</title><biblioid
      class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javaee/tech/index.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.jpa-portable.java.contracts.ref"><title>Portable Java
      Contract Definitions</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://docs.osgi.org/reference/portable-java-contracts.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
