<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="57" revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="framework.dto"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Data Transfer Objects Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.dto-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.dto"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The OSGi API is rich and introspective supporting the local
    management of bundles, services and other items. Since the API has a lot
    of behavior and is not designed for serialization, any management model
    must design its own representation of the relevant OSGi objects for
    communication with remote management systems. We see this in the
    Management Model Specification for JMX™ Technology, the Dmt Admin Service
    Specification and Residential Device Management Tree Specification: the
    Management Model Specification for JMX™ Technology must define the MBeans
    and the Residential Device Management Tree Specification must define the
    tree representation.</para>

    <para>The OSGi API continues to evolve and at each update of the OSGi API,
    the management models will all need to update their representations of the
    OSGi objects. Having standard, simple, easy to serialize and deserialize
    objects which represent the relevant OSGi objects will make it easier for
    the management model to keep up with changes in the OSGi API. Therefore,
    this specification defines Data Transfer Objects for OSGi in general and
    well as specific Data Transfer Objects for the Core specification. Other
    OSGi specifications may be updated over time to define Data Transfer
    Objects specific to their domain.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Easy Serialization/Deserialization</emphasis> - Must
          be easily serializable. That is, no special
          serialization/deserialization logic must be required. Serialization
          must be possible simply by introspection and object graphs must be a
          tree.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>No Behavior</emphasis> - Must have no behavior. That
          is, no methods other than the default public constructor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Public</emphasis> - Must have only public fields.
          That is, no private implementation detail.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Limited Field Types</emphasis> - Must only use a
          limited selection of field types.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Extendable</emphasis> - May extend other Data
          Transfer Object types.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Snapshot</emphasis> - Does not track changes to
          represented runtime object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Not Thread Safe</emphasis> - External
          synchronization is needed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Instantiation</emphasis> - A means is provided to
          create Data Transfer Objects for the runtime objects they
          represent.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Data Transfer Object (DTO)</emphasis> - An object
          for carrying data between processes. A Data Transfer Object does not
          have any behavior. See <xref
          linkend="framework.dto.references-dto"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Runtime Object</emphasis> - A runtime object being
          represented by a Data Transfer Object. The runtime object can have
          complex behavior.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Data Transfer Object</title>

    <para>A Data Transfer Object is used to represent the state of a related
    runtime object in a form suitable for easy transfer to some receiver. The
    receiver can be in the same Java VM but is more likely in another process
    or on another system that is remote. All Data Transfer Objects are easily
    serializable having only public fields of a limited set of type. These
    types are:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Primitive types</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Wrapper classes for the primitive types</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>String</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>enum</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Version"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Data Transfer Objects</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>List</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>Set</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>Map</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>array</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The List, Set, Map and array aggregates must only hold objects of
    the listed types. The types for Map keys are limited to primitive wrapper
    classes, <code>String</code>, enums, and <code>Version</code>.</para>

    <para>Data Transfer Objects are public classes with no methods, other than
    the compiler supplied default constructor, having only public fields
    limited to the easily serializable types mentioned above. The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.dto" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> package defines the basic
    rules and the abstract base <xref linkend="org.osgi.dto.DTO"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> class which Data Transfer Objects must
    extend.</para>

    <para>A Data Transfer Object is a representation of a runtime object at
    the point in time the Data Transfer Object was created. Data Transfer
    Objects do not track state changes in the represented runtime object.
    Since Data Transfer Objects are simply fields with no method behavior,
    modifications to Data Transfer Object are inherently not thread safe. Care
    must be taken to safely publish Data Transfer Objects for use by other
    threads as well as proper synchronization if a Data Transfer Object is
    mutated by one of the threads.</para>

    <para>The object graph from a Data Transfer Object must be a tree to
    simplify serialization and deserialization.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Naming Conventions</title>

      <para>Data Transfer Objects should follow a naming convention for the
      package containing the Data Transfer Object as well as the Data Transfer
      Object type. For the package name, we start with the package name
      containing the runtime type for which the Data Transfer Object is a
      representation. A <code>dto</code> segment is suffixed to the package
      name. For example, a Data Transfer Object representing a runtime type in
      the <code>org.osgi.service.foo</code> package will be in the Data
      Transfer Object package name is
      <code>org.osgi.service.foo.dto</code>.</para>

      <para>The name of the Data Transfer Object type should be the name of
      the runtime type for which the Data Transfer Object is a representation
      followed by <code>DTO</code>. So for a type <code>Widget</code>, the
      Data Transfer Object for that type should be <code>WidgetDTO</code>.
      Sometimes the entity for which the Data Transfer Object provides a
      representation does not exists as a runtime type. In this case, the name
      of entity with a <code>DTO</code> suffix should be used. For example,
      <code>EntityDTO</code>.</para>

      <para>Putting both the package and type Data Transfer Object naming
      conventions together, the fully qualified name for the Data Transfer
      Object representing the runtime type
      <code>org.osgi.service.foo.Widget</code> would be
      <code>org.osgi.service.foo.dto.WidgetDTO</code>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Core Data Transfer Objects</title>

    <para>Data Transfer Objects are defined for several important Core
    specification objects including <code>Bundle</code>, the Framework, and
    <code>ServiceReference</code> as well as the Resource API types, Start
    Level API types and Bundle Wiring API types.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Framework Data Transfer Objects</title>

      <para>A <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.dto.BundleDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> represents information about a single bundle
      such as the id of the bundle, the current state of the bundle and the
      symbolic name and version of the bundle.</para>

      <para>A <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.dto.ServiceReferenceDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> represents information about a single registered
      service such as the service properties, the bundle which registered the
      service and the bundles using the service.</para>

      <para>A <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.dto.FrameworkDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> represents information about the Framework such
      as the list of installed bundles, the registered services and the launch
      properties of the framework.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Resource API Data Transfer Objects</title>

      <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.dto.CapabilityDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.resource.dto.RequirementDTO" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>,
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.dto.ResourceDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, <xref linkend="org.osgi.resource.dto.WiringDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.resource.dto.WireDTO" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      represent the capabilities and requirements wiring information of the
      Resource API. The following figure shows the effective relationship
      between these Data Transfer Object types. Since the graph of Data
      Transfer Objects must be a tree, some references are indirect.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Resource API Data Transfer Objects</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.437in"
                       contentwidth="4.959in"
                       fileref="resourcedto-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bundle Wiring API Data Transfer Objects</title>

      <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.BundleRevisionDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.BundleWiringDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, and <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.BundleWireDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> represent the capabilities and requirements
      wiring information of the Bundle Wiring API. The following figure shows
      the effective relationship between these Data Transfer Object types.
      Since the graph of Data Transfer Objects must be a tree, some references
      are indirect.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Bundle Wiring API Data Transfer Objects</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="5.437in"
                       contentwidth="4.959in" fileref="wiringdto-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.FrameworkWiringDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> represents the complete capabilities and
      requirements wiring information for all the bundles in the
      framework.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Start Level API Data Transfer Objects</title>

      <para>A <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.dto.BundleStartLevelDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> represents information about the start level
      information of a bundle such as the assigned start level, the activation
      policy used and the whether the bundle is persistently started.</para>

      <para>A <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.dto.FrameworkStartLevelDTO"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> provides the start level information about the
      Framework such as the active start level and the initial bundle start
      level assigned to newly installed bundles.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="framework.dto-obtaining-dtos">
    <title>Obtaining Core Data Transfer Objects</title>

    <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.adapt-Class-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method allows the Bundle to be adapted to
    different types. The <code>adapt</code> method is used to obtain the Core
    Data Transfer Objects. For example, the <code>adapt</code> method can be
    used to adapt a Bundle object to the current <code>BundleDTO</code>
    object. The adapt method can be used as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>// DTO for the bundle
BundleDTO bundleDTO = bundle.adapt(BundleDTO.class);

// DTO for the current bundle wiring
BundleWiringDTO bundleWiringDTO = bundle.adapt(BundleWiringDTO.class);

// DTO for the current bundle revision
BundleRevisionDTO bundleRevisionDTO = bundle.adapt(BundleRevisionDTO.class);</programlisting>

    <para>The following table shows the Core Data Transfer Objects that can be
    obtained from a Bundle via the <code>adapt</code> method.</para>

    <table>
      <title>Data Transfer Objects that can be adapted from Bundle</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1"/>

        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Class</entry>

            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.dto.BundleDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The Bundle Data Transfer Object for the
            bundle.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.dto.ServiceReferenceDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/><code>[]</code></para></entry>

            <entry><para>An array of Service Reference Data Transfer Objects
            for the registered services of the bundle. If the bundle has no
            registered services, the result is an empty array. If the bundle
            does not have a valid bundle context, the result is
            <code>null</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.BundleRevisionDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The Bundle Revision Data Transfer Object for the
            bundle. If the bundle is uninstalled or otherwise does not have a
            bundle revision, the result is <code>null</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.BundleRevisionDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/><code>[]</code></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The Bundle Revision Data Transfer Objects for the
            bundle. The first revision is the current revision. If the bundle
            is uninstalled, the result is <code>null</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.BundleWiringDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The Bundle Wiring Data Transfer Object for the
            bundle. If the bundle is unresolved or otherwise does not have a
            bundle wiring, the result is <code>null</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.BundleWiringDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/><code>[]</code></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The Bundle Wiring Data Transfer Objects for the
            bundle. The first wiring is the current wiring. If the bundle is
            uninstalled, the result is <code>null</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.dto.BundleStartLevelDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The Bundle Start Level Data Transfer Object for the
            bundle. If the bundle is uninstalled, the result is
            <code>null</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.dto.FrameworkStartLevelDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The Framework Start Level Data Transfer Object if the
            bundle is the System Bundle. If the bundle is not the System
            Bundle, the result is <code>null</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.dto.FrameworkDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The Framework Data Transfer Object if the bundle is
            the System Bundle. If the bundle is not the System Bundle, the
            result is <code>null</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.FrameworkWiringDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>The Framework Wiring Data Transfer Object if the
            bundle is the System Bundle. If the bundle is not the System
            Bundle, the result is <code>null</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.ServiceReference.adapt-Class-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method allows the Service Reference to be adapted
    to different types. The <code>adapt</code> method is used to obtain the
    Core Data Transfer Objects. For example, the <code>adapt</code> method can
    be used to adapt a Service Reference object to the current
    <code>ServiceReferenceDTO</code> object. The adapt method can be used as
    follows:</para>

    <programlisting>// DTO for the service reference
ServiceReferenceDTO referenceDTO = reference.adapt(ServiceReferenceDTO.class);</programlisting>

    <para>The following table shows the Core Data Transfer Objects that can be
    obtained from a Service Reference via the <code>adapt</code>
    method.</para>

    <table>
      <title>Data Transfer Objects that can be adapted from
      ServiceReference</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1"/>

        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Class</entry>

            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.dto.ServiceReferenceDTO"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

            <entry><para>A Service Reference Data Transfer Object for the
            Service Reference.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>Data Transfer Objects have no behavior by definition and thus no
    permissions are applicable to their use. To obtain Data Transfer Objects
    from a Bundle or ServiceReference object via the <code>adapt</code>
    method, <code>AdaptPermission[&lt;dtotype&gt;,ADAPT]</code> is required
    for the desired Data Transfer Object type.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.dto.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.framework.dto.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.framework.startlevel.dto.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.framework.wiring.dto.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.resource.dto.xml"/>

  <section xml:id="framework.dto.references">
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="framework.dto.references-dto"><title>Data Transfer
      Object</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_transfer_object"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Updated <xref linkend="framework.dto-obtaining-dtos"/> to
        reflect that ServiceReference can now be adapted to
        ServiceReferenceDTO.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Clarified that the allowed key types for Map values in DTOs are
        limited to primitive wrapper classes, <code>String</code>, enums, and
        <code>Version</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
