<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="701"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="util.tracker"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Tracker Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.util.tracker-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para xml:id="i1708332">The Framework provides a powerful and very dynamic
    programming environment: Bundles are installed, started, stopped, updated,
    and uninstalled without shutting down the Framework. Dependencies between
    bundles are monitored by the Framework, but bundles
    <emphasis>must</emphasis> cooperate in handling these dependencies
    correctly. Two important <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis> aspects of the
    Framework are the service registry and the set of installed
    bundles.</para>

    <para xml:id="i1708335">Bundle developers must be careful not to use
    service objects that have been unregistered and are therefore stale. The
    dynamic nature of the Framework service registry makes it necessary to
    track the service objects as they are registered and unregistered to
    prevent problems. It is easy to overlook race conditions or boundary
    conditions that will lead to random errors. Similar problems exist when
    tracking the set of installed bundles and their state.</para>

    <para xml:id="i1718746">This specification defines two utility classes,
    <code>ServiceTracker</code> and <code>BundleTracker</code>, that make
    tracking services and bundles easier. A <code>ServiceTracker</code> class
    can be customized by implementing the
    <code>ServiceTrackerCustomizer</code> interface or by sub-classing the
    <code>ServiceTracker</code> class. Similarly, a <code>BundleTracker</code>
    class can be customized by sub-classing or implementing the
    <code>BundleTrackerCustomizer</code> interface.</para>

    <para>These utility classes significantly reduce the complexity of
    tracking services in the service registry and the set of installed
    bundles.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Simplify</emphasis> - Make it simple to tracking
          services or bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Customizable</emphasis> - Allow a default
          implementation to be customized so that bundle developers can start
          simply and later extend the implementation to meet their
          needs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Small</emphasis> - Every Framework implementation
          should have this utility implemented. It should therefore be very
          small because some Framework implementations target minimal OSGi
          frameworks.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Services</emphasis> - Track a set of services,
          optionally filtered, or track a single service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundles</emphasis> - Track bundles based on their
          state.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Cleanup</emphasis> - Properly clean up when tracking
          is no longer necessary</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Generified</emphasis> - Generics are used to promote
          type safety.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Operation</title>

      <para>The fundamental tasks of a tracker are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To create an initial list of <emphasis>targets</emphasis>
          (service or bundle).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To listen to the appropriate events so that the targets are
          properly tracked.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To allow the client to customize the tracking process through
          programmatic selection of the services/bundles to be tracked, as
          well as to perform client code when a service/bundle is added or
          removed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A <code>ServiceTracker</code> object is populated with a set of
      services that match given search criteria, and then listens to
      <code>ServiceEvent</code> objects which correspond to those services. A
      Bundle Tracker is populated with the set of installed bundles and then
      listens to <code>BundleEvent</code> objects to notify the customizer of
      changes in the state of the bundles.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <figure>
        <title>Class diagram of org.osgi.util.tracker</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.227in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="tracker-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tracking</title>

    <para>The OSGi Framework is a dynamic multi-threaded environment. In such
    an environments callbacks can occur on different threads at the same time.
    This dynamism causes many complexities. One of the surprisingly hard
    aspects of this environment is to reliably track services and bundles
    (called <emphasis>targets</emphasis> from now on).</para>

    <para>The complexity is caused by the fact that the
    <code>BundleListener</code> and <code>ServiceListener</code> interfaces
    are only providing access to the <emphasis>changed</emphasis> state, not
    to the existing state when the listener is registered. This leaves the
    programmer with the problem to merge the set of existing targets with the
    changes to the state as signified by the events, without unwantedly
    duplicating a target or missing a remove event that would leave a target
    in the tracked map while it is in reality gone. These problems are caused
    by the multi-threaded nature of OSGi.</para>

    <para>The problem is illustrated with the following (quite popular)
    code:</para>

    <programlisting>// Bad Example! Do not do this!
Bundle[] bundles = context.getBundles();
for ( Bundle bundle : bundles ) {
    map.put(bundle.getLocation(), bundle );
}

context.addBundleListener( new BundleListener() {
    public void bundleChanged(BundleEvent event) {
        Bundle bundle = event.getBundle();
        switch(event.getType()) {
        case BundleEvent.INSTALLED:
            map.put(bundle.getLocation(), bundle );
            break;

        case BundleEvent.UNINSTALLED:
            map.remove(bundle.getLocation());
            break;

        default:
            // ignore
        }
    }
});</programlisting>

    <para>Assume the code runs the first part, getting the existing targets.
    If during this time a targets state changes, for example bundle is
    installed or uninstalled, then the event is missed and the map will miss a
    bundle or it will contain a bundle that is already gone. An easy solution
    seems to be to first register the listener and then get the existing
    targets. This solves the earlier problem but will be introduce other
    problems. In this case, an uninstall event can occur before the bundle has
    been discovered.</para>

    <para>Proper locking can alleviate the problem but it turns out that this
    easily create solutions that are very prone to deadlocks. Solving this
    tracking problem is surprisingly hard. For this reason, the OSGi
    specifications contain a <emphasis>bundle tracker</emphasis> and a
    <emphasis>service tracker</emphasis> that are properly implemented. These
    classes significantly reduce the complexity of the dynamics in an OSGi
    framework.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Usage</title>

      <para>Trackers can be used with the following patterns:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>As-is</emphasis> - Each tracker can be used without
          further customizing. A tracker actively tracks a map of targets and
          this map can be consulted with a number of methods when the
          information is needed. This is especially useful for the Service
          Tracker because it provides convenience methods to wait for services
          to arrive.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Callback object</emphasis> - Each tracker provides a
          call back interface that can be implemented by the client
          code.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Sub-classing</emphasis> - The trackers are designed
          to be sub-classed. Sub-classes have access to the bundle context and
          only have to override the callback methods they need.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>General API</title>

      <para>A tracker hides the mechanisms in the way the targets are stored
      and evented. From a high level, a tracker maintains a
      <emphasis>map</emphasis> of targets to <emphasis>wrapper</emphasis>
      objects. The wrapper object can be defined by the client, though the
      Bundle Tracker uses the <code>Bundle</code> object and the Service
      Tracker uses the service object as default wrapper. The tracker notifies
      the client of any changes in the state of the target.</para>

      <para>A tracker must be constructed with a Bundle Context. This context
      is used to register listeners and obtain the initial list of targets
      during the call to the <code>open</code> method. At the end of the life
      of a tracker it must be closed to release any remaining objects. It is
      advised to properly close all trackers in the bundle activator's stop
      method.</para>

      <para>A tracker provides a uniform callback interface, which has 3
      different methods.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Adding</emphasis> - Provide a new object, obtained
          from the store or from an event and return the wrapper or a related
          object. The adding method can decide not to track the target by
          returning a <code>null</code> object. When null is returned, no
          modified or remove methods are further called. However, it is
          possible that the adding method is called again for the same
          target.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Modified</emphasis> - The target is modified. For
          example, the service properties have changed or the bundle has
          changed state. This callback provides a mechanism for the client to
          update its internal structures. The callback provides the wrapper
          object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Removing</emphasis> - The target is no longer
          tracked. This callback is provided the wrapper object returned from
          the adding method. This allows for simplified cleanup if the client
          maintains state about the target.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Each tracker is associated with a callback interface, which it
      implements itself. That is, a Service Tracker implements the
      <code>ServiceTrackerCustomizer</code> interface. By implementing this
      customizer, the tracker can also be sub-classed, this can be quite
      useful in many cases. Sub-classing can override only one or two of the
      methods instead of having to implement all methods. When overriding the
      callback methods, it must be ensured that the wrapper object is treated
      accordingly to the base implementation in all methods. For example, the
      Service Tracker's default implementation for the adding method checks
      out the service and therefore the remove method must unget this same
      service. Changing the wrapper object type to something else can
      therefore clash with the default implementations.</para>

      <para>Trackers can provide all the objects that are tracked, return the
      mapped wrapper from the target, and deliver the number of tracked
      targets.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tracking Count</title>

      <para>The tracker also maintains a count that is updated each time that
      an object is added, modified, or removed, that is any change to the
      implied map. This tracking count makes it straightforward to verify that
      a tracker has changed; just store the tracking count and compare it
      later to see if it has changed.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Multi Threading</title>

      <para>The dynamic environment of OSGi requires that tracker are thread
      safe. However, the tracker closely interacts with the client through a
      callback interface. The tracker implementation must provide the
      following guarantees:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The tracker code calling a callback must not hold any
          locks</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Clients must be aware that their callbacks are reentrant though
      the tracker implementations guarantee that the add/modified/remove
      methods can only called in this order for a specific target. A tracker
      must not call these methods out of order.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Synchronous</title>

      <para>Trackers use <emphasis>synchronous</emphasis> listeners; the
      callbacks are called on the same thread as that of the initiating event.
      Care should be taken to not linger in the callback and perform
      non-trivial work. Callbacks should return immediately and move
      substantial work to other threads.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Service Tracker</title>

    <para>The purpose of a Service Tracker is to track <emphasis>service
    references</emphasis>, that is, the target is the
    <code>ServiceReference</code> object. The Service Tracker uses generics to
    provide a type safe interface. It has two type arguments:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>S</code> - The service type.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>T</code> - The type used by the program. <code>T</code>
        can differ from S if the program creates a wrapper around the service
        object, a common pattern.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para xml:id="i1582460">The <code>ServiceTracker</code> interface defines
    three constructors to create <code>ServiceTracker</code> objects, each
    providing different search criteria:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.ServiceTracker-BundleContext-String-ServiceTrackerCustomizer-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This constructor takes a service interface
        name as the search criterion. The <code>ServiceTracker</code> object
        must then track all services that are registered under the specified
        service interface name.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.ServiceTracker-BundleContext-Filter-ServiceTrackerCustomizer-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This constructor uses a <code>Filter</code>
        object to specify the services to be tracked. The
        <code>ServiceTracker</code> must then track all services that match
        the specified filter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem xml:id="i1582462">
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.ServiceTracker-BundleContext-ServiceReference-ServiceTrackerCustomizer-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This constructor takes a
        <code>ServiceReference</code> object as the search criterion. The
        <code>ServiceTracker</code> must then track only the service that
        corresponds to the specified <code>ServiceReference</code>. Using this
        constructor, no more than one service must ever be tracked, because a
        <code>ServiceReference</code> refers to a specific service.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.ServiceTracker-BundleContext-Class-ServiceTrackerCustomizer-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This constructor takes a class as argument.
        The tracker must only track services registered with this name. This
        is in general the most convenient way to use the Service
        Tracker.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Each of the <code>ServiceTracker</code> constructors takes a
    <code>BundleContext</code> object as a parameter. This
    <code>BundleContext</code> object must be used by a
    <code>ServiceTracker</code> object to track, get, and unget
    services.</para>

    <para>A new <code>ServiceTracker</code> object must not begin tracking
    services until its <code>open</code> method is called. There are 2
    versions of the open method:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.open--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This method is identical to
        <code>open(false)</code>. It is provided for backward compatibility
        reasons.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.open-boolean-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The tracker must start tracking the services
        as were specified in its constructor. If the boolean parameter is
        <code>true</code>, it must track all services, regardless if they are
        compatible with the bundle that created the Service Tracker or not.
        See <xref
        linkend="framework.service.multipleversionexportconsiderations"/> for
        a description of the compatibility issues when multiple variations of
        the same package can exist. If the parameter is <code>false</code>,
        the Service Tracker must only track compatible versions.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Using a Service Tracker</title>

      <para>Once a <code>ServiceTracker</code> object is opened, it begins
      tracking services immediately. A number of methods are available to the
      bundle developer to monitor the services that are being tracked,
      including the ones that are in the service registry at that time. The
      <code>ServiceTracker</code> class defines these methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.getService--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns one of the services being tracked
          or <code>null</code> if there are no active services being
          tracked.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.getServices--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns an array of all the tracked
          services. The number of tracked services is returned by the
          <code>size</code> method.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.getServices-T---"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Like <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.getServices--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> but provides a convenient way to get these
          services into a correctly typed array.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.getServiceReference--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns a <code>ServiceReference</code>
          object for one of the services being tracked. The service object for
          this service may be returned by calling the
          <code>ServiceTracker</code> object's <code>getService()</code>
          method.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.getServiceReferences--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns a list of the
          <code>ServiceReference</code> objects for services being tracked.
          The service object for a specific tracked service may be returned by
          calling the <code>ServiceTracker</code> object's
          <code>getService(ServiceReference)</code> method.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.waitForService-long-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Allows the caller to wait until at least
          one instance of a service is tracked or until the time-out expires.
          If the time-out is zero, the caller must wait until at least one
          instance of a service is tracked. <code>waitForService</code> must
          not used within the <code>BundleActivator</code> methods, as these
          methods are expected to complete in a short period of time. A
          Framework could wait for the start method to complete before
          starting the bundle that registers the service for which the caller
          is waiting, creating a deadlock situation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.remove-ServiceReference-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This method may be used to remove a
          specific service from being tracked by the
          <code>ServiceTracker</code> object, causing
          <code>removedService</code> to be called for that service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.close--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This method must remove all services being
          tracked by the <code>ServiceTracker</code> object, causing
          <code>removedService</code> to be called for all tracked
          services.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem xml:id="i1582472">
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.getTrackingCount--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A Service Tracker can have services added,
          modified, or removed at any moment in time. The
          <code>getTrackingCount</code> method is intended to efficiently
          detect changes in a Service Tracker. Every time the Service Tracker
          is changed, it must increase the tracking count.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.isEmpty--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - To detect that the tracker has no tracked
          services.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTracker.getTracked--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Return the tracked objects.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Customizing the Service Tracker class</title>

      <para>The behavior of the <code>ServiceTracker</code> class can be
      customized either by providing a <code>ServiceTrackerCustomizer</code>
      object, implementing the desired behavior when the
      <code>ServiceTracker</code> object is constructed, or by sub-classing
      the <code>ServiceTracker</code> class and overriding the
      <code>ServiceTrackerCustomizer</code> methods.</para>

      <para>The <code>ServiceTrackerCustomizer</code> interface defines these
      methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTrackerCustomizer.addingService-ServiceReference-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Called whenever a service is being added
          to the <code>ServiceTracker</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTrackerCustomizer.modifiedService-ServiceReference-T-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Called whenever a tracked service is
          modified.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.ServiceTrackerCustomizer.removedService-ServiceReference-T-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Called whenever a tracked service is
          removed from the <code>ServiceTracker</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>When a service is being added to the <code>ServiceTracker</code>
      object or when a tracked service is modified or removed from the
      <code>ServiceTracker</code> object, it must call
      <code>addingService</code>, <code>modifiedService</code>, or
      <code>removedService</code>, respectively, on the
      <code>ServiceTrackerCustomizer</code> object (if specified when the
      <code>ServiceTracker</code> object was created); otherwise it must call
      these methods on itself.</para>

      <para>A bundle developer may customize the action when a service is
      tracked. Another reason for customizing the <code>ServiceTracker</code>
      class is to programmatically select which services are tracked. A filter
      may not sufficiently specify the services that the bundle developer is
      interested in tracking. By implementing <code>addingService</code>, the
      bundle developer can use additional runtime information to determine if
      the service should be tracked. If <code>null</code> is returned by the
      <code>addingService</code> method, the service must not be
      tracked.</para>

      <para>Finally, the bundle developer can return a specialized object from
      <code>addingService</code> that differs from the service object. This
      specialized object could contain the service object and any associated
      information. This returned object is then tracked instead of the service
      object. When the <code>removedService</code> method is called, the
      object that is passed along with the <code>ServiceReference</code>
      object is the one that was returned from the earlier call to the
      <code>addingService</code> method.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Customizing Example</title>

      <para>An example of customizing the action taken when a service is
      tracked might be registering a <code>MyServlet</code> object with each
      Http Service that is tracked. This customization could be done by
      sub-classing the <code>ServiceTracker</code> class and overriding the
      <code>addingService</code> and <code>removedService</code> methods as
      follows:</para>

      <programlisting>new ServiceTracker&lt;HttpService,MyServlet&gt;(context,HttpService.class,null){
  public MyServlet addingService( ServiceReference&lt;HttpService&gt;reference) {
     HttpService svc = context.getService(reference);
     MyServlet ms = new MyServlet(scv);   return ms;
  }
  public void removedService( ServiceReference&lt;HttpService&gt;reference,
     MyServlet ms) {
     ms.close();
     context.ungetService(reference);
  }
}</programlisting>

      <para>In this example, the service type is the <code>HttpService</code>
      class and the wrapper type is the servlet.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Bundle Tracker</title>

    <para>The purpose of the Bundle Tracker is to simplify tracking bundles. A
    popular example where bundles need to be tracked is the
    <emphasis>extender</emphasis> pattern. An extender uses information in
    other bundles to provide its function. For example, a Declarative Services
    implementation reads the component XML file from the bundle to learn of
    the presence of any components in that bundle.</para>

    <para>There are, however, other places where it is necessary to track
    bundles. The Bundle Tracker significantly simplifies this task.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Bundle States</title>

      <para>The state diagram of a Bundle is significantly more complex than
      that of a service. However, the interface is simpler because there is
      only a need to specify for which states the bundle tracker should track
      a service.</para>

      <para>Bundle states are defined as a bit in an integer, allowing the
      specifications of multiple states by setting multiple bits. The Bundle
      Tracker therefore uses a <emphasis>bit mask</emphasis> to specify which
      states are of interest. For example, if a client is interested in active
      and resolved bundles, it is possible to specify the <code>Bundle</code>
      <code>ACTIVE | RESOLVED | STARTING</code> states in the mask.</para>

      <para>The Bundle Tracker tracks bundles whose state matches the mask.
      That is, when a bundle is not tracked it adds that bundle to the tracked
      map when its state matches the mask. If the bundle reaches a new state
      that is not listed in the mask, the bundle will be removed from the
      tracked map. If the state changes but the bundle should still be
      tracked, then the bundle is considered to be modified.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Constructor</title>

      <para>The <code>BundleTracker</code> interface defines the following
      constructors to create <code>BundleTracker</code> objects:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTracker.BundleTracker-BundleContext-int-BundleTrackerCustomizer-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Create a Bundle Tracker that tracks the
          bundles which state is listed in the mask. The customizer may be
          <code>null</code>, in that case the callbacks can be implemented in
          a subclass.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A new <code>BundleTracker</code> object must not begin tracking
      services until its <code>open</code> method is called.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTracker.open--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Start tracking the bundles, callbacks can
          occur before this method is called.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using a Bundle Tracker</title>

      <para>Once a <code>BundleTracker</code> object is opened, it begins
      tracking bundles immediately. A number of methods are available to the
      bundle developer to monitor the bundles that are being tracked. The
      <code>BundleTracker</code> class defines the following methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTracker.getBundles--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns an array of all the tracked
          bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTracker.getObject-Bundle-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns the wrapper object that was
          returned from the <code>addingBundle</code> method.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTracker.remove-Bundle-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Removes the bundle from the tracked
          bundles. The <code>removedBundle</code> method is called when the
          bundle is not in the tracked map.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTracker.size--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns the number of bundles being
          tracked.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTracker.getTrackingCount--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A Bundle Tracker can have bundles added,
          modified, or removed at any moment in time. The
          <code>getTrackingCount</code> method is intended to efficiently
          detect changes in a Bundle Tracker. Every time the Bundle Tracker is
          changed, it must increase the tracking count.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTracker.isEmpty--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - To detect that the tracker has no tracked
          bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTracker.getTracked--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Return the tracked objects.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Customizing the Bundle Tracker class</title>

      <para>The behavior of the <code>BundleTracker</code> class can be
      customized either by providing a <code>BundleTrackerCustomizer</code>
      object when the <code>BundleTracker</code> object is constructed, or by
      sub-classing the <code>BundleTracker</code> class and overriding the
      <code>BundleTrackerCustomizer</code> methods on the
      <code>BundleTracker</code> class.</para>

      <para>The <code>BundleTrackerCustomizer</code> interface defines these
      methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTrackerCustomizer.addingBundle-Bundle-BundleEvent-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Called whenever a bundle is being added to
          the <code>BundleTracker</code> object. This method should return a
          wrapper object, which can be the <code>Bundle</code> object itself.
          If <code>null</code> is returned, the Bundle must not be further
          tracked.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTrackerCustomizer.modifiedBundle-Bundle-BundleEvent-T-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Called whenever a tracked bundle is
          modified. The object that is passed is the object returned from the
          <code>addingBundle</code> method, the wrapper object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker.BundleTrackerCustomizer.removedBundle-Bundle-BundleEvent-T-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Called whenever a tracked bundle is
          removed from the <code>BundleTracker</code> object. The passed
          object is the wrapper returned from the <code>addingBundle</code>
          method.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The <code>BundleEvent</code> object in the previous methods can be
      <code>null</code>.</para>

      <para>When a bundle is being added the OSGi Framework, or when a tracked
      bundle is modified or uninstalled from the OSGi Framework, the Bundle
      Tracker must call <code>addingBundle</code>,
      <code>modifiedBundle</code>, or <code>removedBundle</code>,
      respectively, on the <code>BundleTrackerCustomizer</code> object (if
      specified when the <code>BundleTracker</code> object was created);
      otherwise it must call these methods on itself, allowing them to be
      overridden in a subclass.</para>

      <para>The bundle developer can return a specialized object from
      <code>addingBundle</code> that differs from the <code>Bundle</code>
      object. This wrapper object could contain the <code>Bundle</code> object
      and any associated client specific information. This returned object is
      then used as the wrapper instead of the <code>Bundle</code> object. When
      the <code>removedBundle</code> method is called, the wrapper is passed
      as an argument.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Extender Model</title>

      <para>The Bundle Tracker allows the implementation of extenders with
      surprisingly little effort. The following example checks a manifest
      header (Http-Mapper) in all active bundles to see if the bundle has
      resources that need to be mapped to the HTTP service. This extender
      enables bundles that have no code, just content.</para>

      <para>This example is implemented with a
      <code>BundleTrackerCustomizer</code> implementation, though sub-classing
      the <code>BundleTracker</code> class is slightly simpler because the
      open/close methods would be inherited, the tracker field is not
      necessary and it is not necessary to provide a dummy implementation of
      <code>modifiedBundle</code> method. However, the Service Tracker example
      already showed how to use inheritance.</para>

      <para>The Extender class must implement the customizer and declare
      fields for the Http Service and a Bundle Tracker.</para>

      <programlisting>public class Extender implements BundleTrackerCustomizer&lt;ExtenderContext&gt;{
    final HttpService                    http;
    final BundleTracker&lt;ExtenderContext&gt; tracker;</programlisting>

      <para>It is necessary to parse the Http-Mapper header. Regular
      expression allow this to be done very concise.</para>

      <programlisting>final static Pattern     HTTPMAPPER = 
    Pattern.compile(
        "\\s*([-/\\w.]+)\\s*=\\s*([-/\\w.]+)\\s*");</programlisting>

      <para>The Bundle Tracker requires a specialized constructor. This
      example only works for <emphasis>active</emphasis> bundles. This implies
      that a bundle only provides contents when it is started, enabling an
      administrator to control the availability.</para>

      <programlisting>Extender(BundleContext context, HttpServicehttp) {
    tracker = new BundleTracker&lt;ExtenderContext&gt;(
        context,Bundle.ACTIVE, this );
    this.http = http;
}</programlisting>

      <para>The following method implements the callback from the Bundle
      Tracker when a new bundle is discovered. In this method a specialized
      <code>HttpContext</code> object is created that knows how to retrieve
      its resources from the bundle that was just discovered. This context is
      registered with the Http Service. If no header is found
      <code>null</code> is returned so that non-participating bundles are no
      longer tracked.</para>

      <programlisting>public ExtenderContext addingBundle(Bundlebundle, 
    BundleEvent event) {
    String header = bundle.getHeaders()
        .get("Http-Mapper") + "";
    Matcher match = HTTPMAPPER.matcher(header);
    if (match.matches()) {
        try {
            ExtenderContext wrapper = 
                new ExtenderContext(bundle, match.group(1));
            http.registerResources(
                match.group(1), // alias
                match.group(2), // resource path
                wrapper         // the http context
            );
            return wrapper;
        } catch (NamespaceException nspe) {
            // error is handled in the fall through
        }
    }
   System.err.println(
      "Invalid header for Http-Mapper: " + header);
   return null;
}</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>modifiedBundle</code> method does not have to be
      implemented because this example is not interested in state changes
      because the only state of interest is the <code>ACTIVE</code> state.
      Therefore, the remaining method left to implement is the
      <code>removedBundle</code> method. If the wrapper object is non-null
      then we need to unregister the alias to prevent collisions in the http
      namespace when the bundle is reinstalled or updated.</para>

      <programlisting>public void removedBundle(
    Bundle bundle, BundleEvent event, 
    ExtenderContext wrapper) {
        http.unregister(wrapper.alias);
}</programlisting>

      <para>The remaining methods would be unnecessary if the
      <code>Extender</code> class had extended the <code>BundleTracker</code>
      class. The <code>BundleTrackerCustomizer</code> interface requires a
      dummy implementation of the <code>modifiedBundle</code> method:</para>

      <programlisting>public void modifiedBundle(
    Bundle bundle, BundleEvent event, ExtenderContext object){
    // Nothing to do
}</programlisting>

      <para>It is usually not a good idea to start a tracker in a constructor
      because opening a service tracker will immediately cause a number of
      callbacks for the existing bundles. If the <code>Extender</code> class
      was sub-classed, then this could call back the uninitialized sub class
      methods. It is therefore better to separate the initialization from the
      opening. There is therefore a need for an <code>open</code> and
      <code>close</code> method.</para>

      <programlisting>    public void close() {
        tracker.close();
    }
    public void open() {
        tracker.open();
    }
}</programlisting>

      <para>The previous example uses an <code>HttpContext</code> subclass
      that can retrieve resources from the target bundle:</para>

      <programlisting>public class ExtenderContext implements HttpContext{
    final Bundle bundle;
    final String alias;

    ExtenderContext(Bundle bundle, String alias) {
        this.bundle = bundle;
        this.alias = alias;
    }
    public boolean handleSecurity(
        HttpServletRequest rq, HttpServletResponse rsp) {
        return true;
    }
    public String getMimeType(String name) {
        return null;
    }
    public URL getResource(String name) {
        return bundle.getResource(name);
    }
}</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>A tracker contains a <code>BundleContext</code> instance variable
    that is accessible to the methods in a subclass. A
    <code>BundleContext</code> object should never be given to other bundles
    because it is a <emphasis>capability</emphasis>. The framework makes
    allocations based on the bundle context with respect to security and
    resource management.</para>

    <para>The tracker implementations do not have a method to get the
    <code>BundleContext</code> object, however, subclasses should be careful
    not to provide such a method if the tracker is given to other
    bundles.</para>

    <para>The services that are being tracked are available via a
    <code>ServiceTracker</code>. These services are dependent on the
    <code>BundleContext</code> as well. It is therefore necessary to do a
    careful security analysis when <code>ServiceTracker</code> objects are
    given to other bundles. The same counts for the Bundle Tracker. It is
    strongly advised to not pass trackers to other bundles.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Synchronous Bundle Listener</title>

      <para>The Bundle Tracker uses the synchronous bundle listener because it
      is impossible to provide some of the guarantees the Bundle Tracker
      provides without handling the events synchronously. Synchronous events
      can block the complete system, therefore Synchronous Bundle Listeners
      require <code>AdminPermission[*,LISTENER]</code>. The wildcard * can be
      replaced with a specifier for the bundles that should be visible to the
      Bundle Tracker. See <xref
      linkend="framework.lifecycle.adminpermission"/> for more
      information.</para>

      <para>Code that calls the <code>open</code> and <code>close</code>
      methods of Bundle Trackers must therefore have the appropriate Admin
      Permission.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.util.tracker.xml"/>
</chapter>
