<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="59" revision="$Id$" version="5.0" xml:id="service.condition"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Condition Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.condition-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.condition"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="service.condition.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>In dynamic systems, such as OSGi, one of the more challenging problems can be to define when a System or part 
    of it is ready to do work. The answer can change depending on the individual perspective. The developer of a Webserver 
    might say, the System is ready when the server starts listening to port 80. An Application developer however would 
    define the system as ready, when the database connection is up and all Servlets are registered. Taking the Application 
    developers view, the Server should start Listening on Port 80 when the System is ready and not beforehand.</para>
    
    <para>The OSGi <xref linkend="framework.service" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> already provides all necessary tools to register any 
    service as a Marker, for when a System is ready. The Condition Service Specification simply provides a specified 
    method to signal such states. With this, other specifications and users have a known method to listen for such signals.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Condition</emphasis> - Represents a particular state of the runtime.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Target</emphasis> - A filter used to match a required condition.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="service.condition.entities">
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Condition</emphasis> - A service interface used to represent a state at runtime.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>True Condition</emphasis> - A condition registered by the Framework which is always available from the moment ofFramework initialization.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  	</section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="service.condition.operation">
    <title>Condition Service</title>
    
    <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
    can be used to control the order in which bundles are activated when the
    Framework is launched. In some scenarios it can be helpful to have lower level bundles activate before higher
    level ones so that the necessary services provided by the lower levels are ready before the higher levels start.
    However, such solutions have drawbacks in a dynamic system because any dependency can appear and disappear
    at any time. There is no guarantee that when a bundle finishes activation that it has registered all the services
    that it ever will for the lifetime of its active state.</para>
    
    <para>A better solution is to model ordering as a dependency. Once something is a service dependency, an
    injection framework, such as Declarative Services or OSGi CDI integration, can defer component activation
    until the dependency is available. With a proper dependency, when the dependency disappears any components
    that depend on it will be deactivated automatically. Such a system will tend to automatically initialize
    and tear down components in the correct order. EXPLICITLY NAME (what was it? I stopped writing mid note.)</para>

    <para>The OSGi service layer provides a very expressive tool for describing the aspects of a service
    through its service properties (see <xref linkend="framework.service.serviceproperties"/>) and for
    selecting and matching available services with the service filter
    (see <xref linkend="i2671413"/>). Dependency injection frameworks such as Declarative Services and OSGi CDI integration use
    the expressive nature of the service layer by allowing a target option for dependencies. The target
    specifies a filter that is used to assert the properties provided by a specific dependency.</para>

    <para>The notion of a target for a dependency is very powerful and allows for additional control
    over when a component can be activated. With Declarative Services and OSGi CDI integration
    a dependency target can be overwritten with configuration. This gives the deployer of the system
    power to select specific services for dependencies and therefore power over what conditions
    are necessary for a component to be activated.</para>

    <para>Translating ordering dependencies to service dependencies is often straightforward to do, but 
    some scenarios make it more challenging. For example, if a component depends on a system wide state
    in order to be fully functional. This type of problem can be common when using the whiteboard pattern.
    An example of a whiteboard pattern is above mentioned Webserver. As a Servlet implementation it is only required to register a Servlet
    service and that servlet will automatically get used to dispatch requests to by the Webserver implementation.
    However, in some scenarios a deployer may want to ensure that one or more specific Servlets are
    registered before allowing the Webserver to be active. By default the webserver
    does not need any servlets to be active, but a deployer may want to ensure at least one listener
    is available. For this example a deployer wants a Servlet 1 and Servlet 2 to be available.</para>

 	<figure pgwide="1">
        <title>Service Activation without Condition</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" 
                       fileref="without-condition-sequence.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

    <para>With Declarative Services one could incorrectly try the following to achieve this:</para>

    <programlisting>// THIS WILL NEVER WORK
@Reference(target= "(&amp;(servlet=1)(servlet=2))")
volatile List&lt;Servlet&gt; servlets;</programlisting>

    <para>This does not work because no single Servlet will satisfy both properties. 
    The result is that the list of servlets will remain empty for the system and the webserver will not start.
    Condition services provide a mechanism for declaring and controlling what conditions
    are necessary to enable a component. For example, with the listener whiteboard implementation
    the following condition service requirement could be specified:</para>

    <programlisting>@Reference(target= "(osgi.condition.id=true)")
Condition requiredCondition;</programlisting>

    <para>By default this component requires the <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.condition.Condition.CONDITION_ID_TRUE" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> condition which is always available
    at runtime. This allows the component to activate as soon as all of its other
    requirements are met. In addition a deployer can now use configuration to change the target
    of the required condition. For example, the target could be changed to a condition that represents
    when all the required listeners the deployer requires are available at runtime. For
    example, the following condition target could be used:</para>

    <programlisting xml:id="service.condition.into.example">target= "(&amp;(osgi.condition.id=listeners)(servlet=1)(servlet=2))"</programlisting>

    <figure pgwide="1">
       <title>Service Activation with Condition</title>

       <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
           <imagedata align="center"
                      fileref="condition-sequence.svg"/>
         </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    
    <para>By declaring a requirement on the invariably available true condition a developer can open
    up a component to be configured for activation based on a condition that can be
    controlled at runtime with configuration. Conditions can also be enabled based on the availability of
    other conditions. This allows for more powerful layering of conditions for a system.</para>
    
    <para>The Condition that provides the servlets are ready state can then look as follows:</para>
   <programlisting>@Component(property = {
   	"osgi.condition.id=application", 
   	"servlet=1", 
   	"servlet=2"})
public class ApplicationCondition implements Condition{
	@Reference(target = "(servlet=1)")
	private Servlet servlet1;
	@Reference(target = "(servlet=2)")
	private Servlet servlet2;
}</programlisting>
      <section>
        <title>The Default True Condition</title>
        <para>The Framework will always register a default Condition everybody can rely on. The Condition will be registered during Framework <code>INIT</code> as the Framework registers framework services. It is registered with the <code>org.osgi.service.Condition.CONDITION_ID</code> property set to <code>org.osgi.service.Condition.CONDITION_ID_TRUE</code></para>
      </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.condition.security">
    <title>Security</title>
    <section>
        <title>Conditions</title>
        <para>A Condition service has no function outside of providing a marker service to indicate a particular state and
        is therefore not required to be a trusted service.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Minimum Implementation Permissions</title>
        <programlisting>PackagePermission[org.osgi.service.condition,IMPORT]
ServicePermission[org.osgi.service.condition.Condition, REGISTER ]</programlisting>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Minumum Using Permissions</title>
        <para>No permissions are necessary to get a Condition service. 
        The Service Permission <code>GET</code> must be implied by the framework to get Condition services
        (see <xref linkend="framework.security.impliedpermissions"/>).
        Note that the <code>org.osgi.service.condition</code> package does
        not need to be imported for a bundle to be able to get a Condition service.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.condition.xml"/>

</chapter>
