<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="705"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="util.pushstream"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Promises Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.util.pushstream-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>In large-scale distributed systems <emphasis>events</emphasis> are
    a commonly used communication mechanism for passing data and triggering
    behaviours. Events are typically generated 
    <emphasis>asynchronously</emphasis> rather than at the request of the
    processing system, and once received an event usually undergoes some
    level of transformation before being stored, acted upon, or forwarded to
    another consumer.</para>
    
    <para>Pipelines and streams are a popular and effective model for consuming
    and processing events, with numerous APIs providing this sort of model.
    One of the most well-known processing pipeline APIs is the Java 8 Streams
    API, which provides a functional pipleline for operating on Collections. 
    The Streams API is inherently <emphasis>pull based</emphasis>” as it relies 
    on iterators and spliterators to <emphasis>pull</emphasis> the next entry 
    from the stream. This is the primary difference between synchronous and 
    asynchronous models. In an asynchronous world events are pushed into the 
    pipeline as they are received.</para>

    <para>This specification defines a PushStream API which can be used on
    devices which support the Java 8 compact1 profile. The PushStream API
    defined by this specification depends on OSGi Promises but is 
    independent of all other OSGi specifications, including the OSGi 
    Framework, and thus can be easily used outside of the OSGi environment.</para>

    <para>A PushStream object encapsulates a pipeline of a potentially 
    asynchronous tasks which will be performed when an event arrives. The 
    result of the processing pipeline is represented using a Promise object
    which will resolve when the result has been calculated.</para>

    <para>PushStream capture the effects of errors, finite streams and back 
    pressure by making these explicit in the API signatures. Errors and End 
    of Stream conditions are represented by specific events which are pushed 
    into the stream. Back pressure is represented by a delay value returned
    from the event pipeline stages.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Common concepts</emphasis> - The API is inspired by
          the Streams API in Java 8 and uses the same basic concepts.
          See ## TODO.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Independent</emphasis> - The design is independent
          of all other OSGi specifications (except for OSGi Promises) and 
          can be used outside of an OSGi environment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Asynchronous</emphasis> - The design is built
          to handle asynchronously produced events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Back Pressure</emphasis> - The design provides
          a means for event pipelines to communicate back-pressure to
          the Event Source.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Complete</emphasis> - The design provides a very
          complete set of operations for PushStreams which are primitives 
          that can be used to address most use cases.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Generified</emphasis> - Generics are used to promote
          type safety.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Push Event Source</emphasis> - A PushEventSource
          object represents a source of asynchronous events, and can
          be used to create a PushStream.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Push Event Consumer</emphasis> - A Push Event Consumer
          object represents a sink for asynchronous events, and can be
          attached to a PushEventSource or a PushStream.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Push Stream</emphasis> - A PushStream object 
          represents a pipeline for processing asynchronous events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Terminal Operation</emphasis> - The final operation
          of a PushStream pipeline results in a Promise which represents the
          completion state of the pipeline. The operation also begins the
          processing of events.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asynchronous Eventing Streams</title>
    
    <para>The Push Stream API is built upon the principals of Asynchronous
    Event streams, and therefore requires three basic primitives:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>An event object</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>A source of event objects</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>A consumer of event objects</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  
    <section>
      <title>The Push Event</title>
      
      <para>The Push Event is an object representing an event. Every
      Push Event has an event type, which has one of three values:</para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>DATA</code> - A data event encapsulates a
          typed object</para></listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>ERROR</code> - An error event encapsulates
          an exception and indicates a failure in the event stream.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>CLOSE</code> - A close event represents
          the end of the stream of events.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>An event stream consists of zero or more data events
      followed by a <emphasis>terminal event</emphasis>. A terminal
      event is either an error or a failure, and it indicates that
      there will be no more events in this stream. Depending on the
      reason for the terminal event it may be possible to re-attach
      to the event source and consume more events.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>The Push Event Source</title>
  
      <para>A Push Event Source object represents a source of asynchronous
      Push Events. The event source defines a single method <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEventSource.open--" 
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> which can be used to connect to the source
      and begin receiving a stream of events.</para>
      
      <para>The <code>open</code> method of the Push Event Source returns 
      an <code>AutoCloseable</code> which can be used to close the event 
      stream. If the <code>close</code> method is called on this object then 
      the stream is terminated by sending a close event. If additional calls 
      are made to the close method then they return without further action. 
      </para>
      
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Push Event Consumer</title>
  
      <para>A Push Event Consumer object represents a sink for 
      asynchronous Push Events. The event consumer defines a single method 
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEventConsumer.accept--" 
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> which can be used to receive a stream of 
      events.</para>
      
      <para>The <code>accept</code> method of the Push Event Consumer 
      returns a <code>long</code> representing 
      <emphasis>back pressure</emphasis>. Back pressure is described in
      detail in <xref linkend="util.pushstream.back-pressure" 
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. If the returned long is negative then
      the event stream should be closed by the event source. 
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>Closing the Event Stream</title>
      
      <para>There are three ways in which a stream can be closed:</para>
      
      <para>The Push Event Source may close the stream at any time by
      sending a terminal event to the consumer. Upon receiving a terminal
      event the consumer should clean up any resources and not expect
      to receive further messages. Note that in a multi-threaded system
      the consumer may receive events out of order, and in this case data 
      events may be received after a terminal event. Event processors 
      should be careful to ignore data events that occur after terminal
      events, and to ensure that any downstream consumers receive any
      pending data events before forwarding the terminal event.</para>
        
      <para>The <code>open</code> method of the Push Event Source returns 
      an <code>AutoCloseable</code> which can be used to close the event 
      stream. If the <code>close</code> method is called on this object then 
      the stream is terminated by sending a close event. If additional calls 
      are made to the close method then they return without action. If the 
      close method is called after a terminal event has been sent for any
      other reason then it should return without action.</para>
       
      <para>The <code>accept</code> method of the Push Event Consumer
      returns a long indicating back pressure. If the long is negative
      then the event source should immediately close the stream by sending
      a close event.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Buffering, Back pressure and Circuit Breakers</title>
  
    <para>TODO</para>
  
    <section xml:id="util.pushstream.back-pressure">
      <title>Back pressure</title>
      <para>TODO</para>
    </section>
  
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>The Push Stream API does not define any OSGi services nor does the 
    API perform any privileged actions. Therefore, it has no security
    considerations.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.util.pushstream.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>
      <para>TODO</para>

  </section>

</chapter>
