<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="706"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="util.pushstream"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Push Stream Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.util.pushstream-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>In large-scale distributed systems <emphasis>events</emphasis> are a
    commonly used communication mechanism for passing data and triggering
    behaviors. Events are typically generated
    <emphasis>asynchronously</emphasis> rather than at the request of the
    processing system, and once received an event usually undergoes some level
    of transformation before being stored, acted upon, or forwarded to another
    consumer.</para>

    <para>Pipelines and streams are a popular and effective model for
    consuming and processing events, with numerous APIs providing this sort of
    model. One of the most well-known processing pipeline APIs is the Java 8
    Streams API, which provides a functional pipeline for operating on
    Collections. The Streams API is inherently <emphasis>pull
    based</emphasis>” as it relies on iterators and spliterators to
    <emphasis>pull</emphasis> the next entry from the stream. This is the
    primary difference between synchronous and asynchronous models. In an
    asynchronous world events are pushed into the pipeline as they are
    received.</para>

    <para>This specification defines a PushStream API which can be used on
    devices which support the Java 8 compact1 profile. The PushStream API
    defined by this specification depends on OSGi Promises but is independent
    of all other OSGi specifications, including the OSGi Framework, and thus
    can be easily used outside of the OSGi environment.</para>

    <para>A PushStream object encapsulates a pipeline of a potentially
    asynchronous tasks which will be performed when an event arrives. The
    result of the processing pipeline is represented using a Promise object
    which will resolve when the result has been calculated.</para>

    <para>PushStream capture the effects of errors, finite streams and back
    pressure by making these explicit in the API signatures. Errors and End of
    Stream conditions are represented by specific events which are pushed into
    the stream. Back pressure is represented by a delay value returned from
    the event pipeline stages.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Common concepts</emphasis> - The API is inspired by
          the Streams API in Java 8 and uses the same basic concepts. See
          <xref linkend="util.pushstream-ref.java8stream"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Independent</emphasis> - The design is independent
          of all other OSGi specifications (except for OSGi Promises) and can
          be used outside of an OSGi environment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Asynchronous</emphasis> - The design is built to
          handle asynchronously produced events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Back Pressure</emphasis> - The design provides a
          means for event pipelines to communicate back-pressure to the Event
          Source.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Complete</emphasis> - The design provides a very
          complete set of operations for PushStreams which are primitives that
          can be used to address most use cases.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Generified</emphasis> - Generics are used to promote
          type safety.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Push Event Source</emphasis> - A PushEventSource
          object represents a source of asynchronous events, and can be used
          to create a PushStream.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Push Event Consumer</emphasis> - A Push Event
          Consumer object represents a sink for asynchronous events, and can
          be attached to a PushEventSource or a PushStream.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Push Stream</emphasis> - A PushStream object
          represents a pipeline for processing asynchronous events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Terminal Operation</emphasis> - The final operation
          of a PushStream pipeline results in a Promise which represents the
          completion state of the pipeline. The operation also begins the
          processing of events.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asynchronous Event Streams</title>

    <para>The Push Stream API is built upon the principals of Asynchronous
    Event streams, and therefore requires three basic primitives:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An event object</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A source of event objects</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A consumer of event objects</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>The Push Event</title>

      <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEvent"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> is an object representing an event. Every Push
      Event has an event type, which has one of three values:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEvent.EventType.DATA"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A data event encapsulates a typed
          object</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEvent.EventType.ERROR"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - An error event encapsulates an exception
          and indicates a failure in the event stream.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEvent.EventType.CLOSE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A close event represents the end of the
          stream of events.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>An event stream consists of zero or more data events followed by a
      <emphasis>terminal event</emphasis>. A terminal event is either an error
      or a close, and it indicates that there will be no more events in this
      stream. Depending on the reason for the terminal event it may be
      possible to re-attach to the event source and consume more
      events.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Push Event Source</title>

      <para>A Push Event Source object represents a source of asynchronous
      Push Events. The event source defines a single method <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEventSource.open-PushEventConsumer-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> which can be used to connect to the source and
      begin receiving a stream of events.</para>

      <para>The <code>open</code> method of the Push Event Source returns an
      <code>AutoCloseable</code> which can be used to close the event stream.
      If the <code>close</code> method is called on this object then the
      stream is terminated by sending a close event. If additional calls are
      made to the close method then they return without further action.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Push Event Consumer</title>

      <para>A Push Event Consumer object represents a sink for asynchronous
      Push Events. The event consumer defines a single method <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEventConsumer.accept-PushEvent-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> which can be used to receive a stream of
      events.</para>

      <para>The <code>accept</code> method of the Push Event Consumer returns
      a <code>long</code> representing <emphasis>back pressure</emphasis>.
      Back pressure is described in detail in <xref
      linkend="util.pushstream.back-pressure"/>. If the returned long is
      negative then the event stream should be closed by the event
      source.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Closing the Event Stream</title>

      <para>There are three ways in which a stream of events can complete
      normally.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Push Event Source may close the stream at any time by
          sending a terminal event to the consumer. Upon receiving a terminal
          event the consumer should clean up any resources and not expect to
          receive further messages. Note that in a multi-threaded system the
          consumer may receive events out of order, and in this case data
          events may be received after a terminal event. Event processors
          should be careful to ignore data events that occur after terminal
          events, and to ensure that any downstream consumers receive any
          pending data events before forwarding the terminal event.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <code>open</code> method of the Push Event Source returns
          an <code>AutoCloseable</code> which can be used to close the event
          stream. If the <code>close</code> method is called on this object
          then the stream is terminated by sending a close event. If
          additional calls are made to the close method then they return
          without action. If the close method is called after a terminal event
          has been sent for any other reason then it must return without
          action.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <code>accept</code> method of the Push Event Consumer
          returns a long indicating back pressure. If the long is negative
          then the event source must close the stream by sending a close
          event.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Push Stream</title>

    <para>Simple event passing can be achieved by connecting a Push Event
    Consumer directly to a Push Event Source, however this model forces a
    large amount of flow-control and resource management into a single
    location. Furthermore it is difficult to reuse business logic across
    different event streams.</para>

    <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> provides a powerful, flexible pipeline for event
    processing. The Push Stream API shares many concepts with the Java 8
    Streams API, in particular Push Streams are lazy, they may not consume the
    entire event stream, and they can be composed from functional
    steps.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Simple Pipelines</title>

      <para>A Push Stream can be created from a Push Event Source by using a
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStreamProvider"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. A Push Stream represents a stage in an event
      processing pipeline. The overall pipeline is constructed from zero or
      more <emphasis>intermediate operations</emphasis>, and completed with a
      single <emphasis>terminal operation</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Each intermediate operation returns a new Push Stream object
      chained to the previous pipeline step. Once a Push Stream object has had
      an intermediate operation invoked on it then it may not have any other
      operations chained to it. Terminal operations are either void, or return
      a <code>Promise</code> representing the future result of the pipeline.
      These API patterns allow Push Streams to be built using a fluent
      API.</para>

      <para>Push Stream instances are lazy, and so the Push Stream will not be
      connected to the Push Event Source until a <code>terminal
      operation</code> is invoked on the Push Stream. This means that a push
      stream object can be safely built without events being received when the
      pipeline is partially initialized.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Mapping, Flat Mapping and Filtering</title>

        <para>The simplest intermediate operations on a Push Stream are
        <emphasis>mapping</emphasis> and <emphasis>filtering</emphasis>. These
        operations use stateless, non-interfering functions to alter the data
        received by the next stage in the pipeline.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Mapping</title>

          <para>Mapping is the act of transforming an event from one type into
          another. This may involve taking a field from the object, or
          performing some simple processing on it. When mapping there is an
          <emphasis>one to one</emphasis> relationship between input and
          output events, that is, each input event is mapped to exactly one
          output event.</para>

          <programlisting>    PushStream&lt;String&gt; streamOfStrings = getStreamOfStrings();
    
    PushStream&lt;Integer&gt; streamOfLengths = 
            streamOfStrings.map(String::length);</programlisting>

          <para>If the mapping function throws an Exception then an Error
          Event is propagated down the stream to the next pipeline step. The
          failure in the error event is set to the Exception thrown by the
          mapping function. The current pipeline step is also closed, and the
          close operation is propagated back upstream to the event source by
          closing previous pipeline stages. Any subsequently received events
          must not be propagated and must return negative back
          pressure.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Flat Mapping</title>

          <para>Flat Mapping is the act of transforming an event from one type
          into multiple events of another type. This may involve taking fields
          from an object, or performing some simple processing on it. When
          flat mapping there is a <emphasis>one to many</emphasis>
          relationship between input and output events, that is, each input
          event is mapped to zero or more output events.</para>

          <para>A flat mapping function should asynchronously consume the
          event data and return a Push Stream containing the flow of
          subsequent events.</para>

          <programlisting>    PushStream&lt;String&gt; streamOfStrings = getStreamOfStrings();
    
    PushStream&lt;Character&gt; streamOfCharacters = 
            streamOfStrings.flatMap(s -&gt; {
                    SimplePushEventSource&lt;Character&gt; spes = 
                            getSimplePushEventSource();
                    
                    spes.connectPromise()
                        .onResolve(() -&gt;
                            executor.execute(() -&gt; {
                                    for(int i = 0; i &lt; s.length; i++) {
                                        spes.publish(s.charAt(i));
                                    }
                                });
                    return pushStreamProvider.createStream(spes);
                });</programlisting>

          <para>If the flat mapping function throws an Exception then an Error
          Event is propagated down the stream to the next pipeline step. The
          failure in the error event is set to the Exception thrown by the
          mapping function. The current pipeline step is also closed, and the
          close operation is propagated back upstream to the event source by
          closing previous pipeline stages. Any subsequently received events
          must not be propagated and must return negative back
          pressure.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Filtering</title>

          <para>Filtering is the act of removing events from the stream based
          on some characteristic of the event data. This may involve
          inspecting the fields of the data object, or performing some simple
          processing on it. If the filter function returns true for an event
          then it will be passed to the next stage of the pipeline. If the
          filter function returns false then it will be discarded, and not
          passed to the next pipeline stage.</para>

          <programlisting>    PushStream&lt;String&gt; streamOfStrings = getStreamOfStrings();
    
    PushStream&lt;String&gt; filteredStrings = 
            streamOfStrings.filter(s -&gt; s.length() == 42);</programlisting>

          <para>If the filtering function throws an Exception then an Error
          Event is propagated down the stream to the next pipeline step. The
          failure in the error event is set to the Exception thrown by the
          filter function. The current pipeline step is also closed, and the
          close operation is propagated back upstream to the event source by
          closing previous pipeline stages. Any subsequently received events
          must not be propagated and must return negative back
          pressure.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Asynchronous Mapping</title>

          <para>Mapping operations may sometimes take time to calculate their
          results. PushStream operations should, in general be fast and
          non-blocking and so long-running mapping operations should be run on
          a separate thread. The <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.asyncMap-int-int-Function-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> operation allows the mapping function to
          return a Promise representing the ongoing calculation of the mapped
          value. When this promise resolves then its value will be passed to
          the next pipeline stage.</para>

          <para>As asynchronous mapping operations are long-running they
          require back pressure to be generated as the number of running
          operations increases. The amount of back pressure returned is equal
          to the number of pending promises (aside from the mapping operation
          that has just started) plus the number of waiting threads if the
          maximum number of concurrent promises has been reached. The returned
          back pressure when only a single promise is running is therefore
          always zero.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Stateless and Stateful Intermediate Operations</title>

        <para>Intermediate operations are either
        <emphasis>stateless</emphasis> or <emphasis>stateful</emphasis>.
        Stateless operations are ones where the pipeline stage does not need
        to remember the previous data from the stream. Mapping, Flat Mapping
        and Filtering are all stateless operations. The following table lists
        the stateless operations on the Push Stream.</para>

        <table pgwide="1">
          <title>Stateless Intermediate Operations on the Push Stream</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="3.0*"/>

            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3.8*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Intermediate Operation</entry>

                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.adjustBackPressure-LongUnaryOperator-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.adjustBackPressure-ToLongBiFunction-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Register a transformation function to adjust the
                back pressure returned by the previous entry in the stream.
                The result of this function will be returned as back
                pressure.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.asyncMap-int-int-Function-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Register a mapping function which will
                asynchronously calculate the value to be passed to the next
                stage of the stream. The returned back pressure is equal to
                one less than the number of outstanding promises, plus the
                number of queued threads, multiplied by the delay
                value.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.filter-Predicate-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Register a selection function to be called with
                each data event in the stream. If the function returns
                <code>true</code> then the event will propagated, if
                <code>false</code> then the event will dropped from the
                stream.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.flatMap-Function-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Register a transformation function to be called
                with each data event in the stream. Each incoming data element
                is converted into a stream of elements. The transformed data
                is then propagated to the next stage of the
                stream.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.fork-int-int-Executor-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Pushes event processing onto one or more threads
                in the supplied <code>Executor</code> returning a fixed back
                pressure</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.map-Function-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Register a transformation function to be called
                with each data event in the stream. The transformed data is
                propagated to the next stage of the stream.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.merge-PushStream-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Merges <code>this</code> stream and another
                stream into a single stream. The returned stream will not
                close until both parent streams are closed.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.sequential--"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Forces data events to be delivered sequentially
                to the next stage of the stream. Events may be delivered on
                multiple threads, but will not arrive concurrently at the next
                stage of the pipeline.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.split-Predicate...-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Register a set of filter functions to select
                elements that should be forwarded downstream. The returned
                streams correspond to the supplied filter
                functions.</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>Stateful operations differ from stateless operations in that
        they must remember items from the stream. Sometimes stateful
        operations must remember large numbers of events, or even the entire
        stream. For example the <code>distinct</code> operation remembers the
        identity of each entry in the stream, and filters out duplicate
        events.</para>

        <para>Care should be taken when using Stateful operations with large
        or infinite streams. For example the <code>sorted</code> operation
        must process the <emphasis>entire</emphasis> stream until it receives
        a close event. At this point the events can be sorted and delivered in
        order. It is usually a good idea to use the <code>limit</code>
        operation to restrict the length of the stream before performing a
        stateful operation which must remember many elements.</para>

        <para>The following table lists all of the stateful operations of the
        PushStream.</para>

        <table pgwide="1">
          <title>Stateful Intermediate Operations on the Push Stream</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="3.0*"/>

            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3.8*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Intermediate Operation</entry>

                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.buffer--"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Introduces a buffer before the next stage of the
                stream. The buffer can be used to provide a circuit breaker,
                or to allow a switch of consumer thread(s).</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.buildBuffer--"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Introduces a configurable buffer before the next
                stage of the stream. The buffer can be used to provide a
                circuit breaker, or to allow a switch of consumer
                thread(s).</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.coalesce-Function-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.coalesce-int-Function-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.coalesce-IntSupplier-Function-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Register a coalescing function which aggregates
                one or more data events into a single data event which will be
                passed to the next stage of the stream.</para> <para>The
                number of events to be accumulated is either provided as a
                fixed number, or as the result of a function</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.distinct--"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>A variation of <xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.filter-Predicate-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> which drops data from the stream that
                has already been seen. Specifically if a data element
                <code>equals</code> an element which has previously been seen
                then it will be dropped. This stateful operation must remember
                all data that has been seen.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.limit-long-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Limits the length of the stream to the defined
                number of elements. Once that number of elements are received
                then a close event is propagated to the next stage of the
                stream.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.limit-Duration-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Limits the time that the stream will remain open
                to the supplied <code>Duration</code>. Once that time has
                elapsed then a close event is propagated to the next stage of
                the stream.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.skip-long-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Drops the supplied number of data events from the
                stream and then forwards any further data
                events.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.sorted--"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.sorted-Comparator-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Remembers all items in the stream until the
                stream ends. At this point the data in the stream will be
                propagated to the next stage of the stream, either in the
                Natural Ordering of the elements, or in the order defined by
                the supplied Comparator.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.timeout-Duration-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Tracks the time since the last event was
                received. If no event is received within the supplied Duration
                then an error event is propagated to the next stage of the
                stream. The exception in the event will be an
                <code>org.osgi.util.promise.TimeoutException</code>.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.window-Duration-Function-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.window-Duration-Executor-Function-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.window-Supplier-IntSupplier-BiFunction-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.window-Supplier-IntSupplier-Executor-BiFunction-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Collects events over the specified time-limit,
                passing them to the registered handler function. If no events
                occur during the time limit then a Collection containing no
                events is passed to the handler function.</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Terminal Operations</title>

        <para>Terminal operations mark the end of a processing pipeline.
        Invoking a terminal operation causes the PushStream to connect to its
        underlying event source and begin processing.</para>

        <para>The simplest terminal operation is the <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.count--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> operation. This method returns a promise that
        will resolve when the stream finishes. If the stream finishes with a
        close event then the promise will resolve with a Long representing the
        number of events that reached the end of the pipeline. If the stream
        finishes with an error then the promise will fail with that
        error.</para>

        <para>Terminal operations such as <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.forEachEvent-PushEventConsumer-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> are passed a handler function which will be
        called for each piece of data that reaches the end of the stream. If
        the handler function throws an Exception then the Promise returned by
        the terminal operation must fail with the Exception thrown by the
        handler function.</para>

        <para>Some terminal operations, like <code>count</code> require the
        full stream to be processed, others are able to finish before the end
        of the stream. These are known as <emphasis>short
        circuiting</emphasis> operations. An example of a short-circuiting
        operation is <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.findFirst--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This operation resolves the promise with the
        first event that is received by the end of the pipeline. Once a
        short-circuiting operation has completed it propagates negative
        back-pressure through the pipeline to close the source of events. Any
        subsequently received events must not affect the result and must
        return negative back pressure. If an asynchronous pipeline step is
        encountered, such as a buffer, the close operation is propagated back
        upstream to the event source by closing previous pipeline
        stages.</para>

        <table pgwide="1">
          <title>Non Short Circuiting Terminal Operations on the Push
          Stream</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="3.0*"/>

            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3.8*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Terminal Operation</entry>

                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.collect-Collector-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Uses the Java Collector API to collect the data
                from events into a single Collection, Map, or other
                type.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.count--"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Counts the number of events that reach the end of
                the stream pipeline.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.forEach-Consumer-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Register a function to be called back with the
                data from each event in the stream</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.forEachEvent-PushEventConsumer-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Register a <code>PushEventConsumer</code> to be
                called back with each event in the stream. If negative
                back-pressure is returned then the stream will be
                closed.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.max-Comparator-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Uses a Comparator to find the largest data
                element in the stream of data. The promise is resolved with
                the final result when the stream finishes.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.min-Comparator-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Uses a Comparator to find the smallest data
                element in the stream of data. The promise is resolved with
                the final result when the stream finishes.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.reduce-BinaryOperator-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.reduce-T-BinaryOperator-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.reduce-U-BiFunction-BinaryOperator-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Uses a Binary Operator function to combine event
                data into a single object. The promise is resolved with the
                final result when the stream finishes.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.toArray--"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.toArray-IntFunction-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Collects together all of the event data in a
                single array which is used to resolve the returned
                promise.</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table pgwide="1">
          <title>Short Circuiting Terminal Operations on the Push
          Stream</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="3.0*"/>

            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3.8*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Terminal Operation</entry>

                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.allMatch-Predicate-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Resolves with <code>false</code> if any event
                reaches the end of the stream pipeline that does not match the
                predicate. If the stream ends without any data matching the
                predicate then the promise resolves with
                <code>true</code></para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.anyMatch-Predicate-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Resolves with <code>true</code> if any data event
                reaches the end of the stream pipeline and matches the
                supplied predicate. If the stream ends without any data
                matching the predicate then the promise resolves with
                <code>false</code></para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.findAny--"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Resolves with an Optional representing the data
                from the first event that reaches the end of the pipeline. If
                the stream ends without any data reaching the end of the
                pipeline then the promise resolves with an empty
                Optional.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.findFirst--"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Resolves with an Optional representing the data
                from the first event that reaches the end of the pipeline. If
                the stream ends without any data reaching the end of the
                pipeline then the promise resolves with an empty
                Optional.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para><xref
                linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.noneMatch-Predicate-"
                xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

                <entry><para>Resolves with <code>false</code> if any data
                event reaches the end of the stream pipeline and matches the
                supplied predicate. If the stream ends without any data
                matching the predicate then the promise resolves with
                <code>true</code></para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Buffering, Back pressure and Circuit Breakers</title>

      <para>Buffering and Back Pressure are an important part of asynchronous
      stream processing. Back pressure and buffering are therefore an
      important part of the push stream API.</para>

      <section xml:id="util.pushstream.back-pressure">
        <title>Back pressure</title>

        <para>In a synchronous model the producer's thread is held by the
        consumer until the consumer has finished processing the data. This is
        not true for asynchronous systems, and so a producer can easily
        overwhelm a consumer with data. Back pressure is therefore used in
        asynchronous systems to allow consumers to control the speed at which
        producers provide data.</para>

        <para>Back pressure in the asynchronous event processing model is
        provided by the PushEventConsumer. The value returned by the
        <code>accept</code> method of the PushEventConsumer is an indication
        of the requested back pressure. A return of zero indicates that event
        delivery may continue immediately. A positive return value indicates
        that the source should delay sending any further events for the
        requested number of milliseconds. A negative return value indicates
        that no further events should be sent and that the stream can be
        closed.</para>

        <para>Back pressure in a Push Stream can also be applied mid-way
        through the processing pipeline through the use of the <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.adjustBackPressure-LongUnaryOperator-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.adjustBackPressure-ToLongBiFunction-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods. These methods can be used to increase
        or decrease the back pressure requested by later stages of the
        pipeline.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Buffering</title>

        <para>In asynchronous systems events may be produced and consumed at
        different rates. If the consumer is faster than the producer then
        there is no issue, however if the producer is faster than the consumer
        then events must be held somewhere. Back pressure provides some
        assistance here, however some sources do not have control over when
        events are produced. In these cases the data must be buffered until it
        can be processed.</para>

        <para>As well as providing a queue for pending work, introducing
        buffers allows event processing to be moved onto a different thread,
        and for the number of processing threads to be changed part way
        through the pipeline. Buffering can therefore protect an
        PushEventSource from having its event generation thread “stolen” by a
        consumer which executes a long running operation. As a result the
        PushEventSource can be written more simply, without a thread switch,
        if a buffer is used.</para>

        <para>Buffering also provides a “fire break” for back-pressure.
        Back-pressure return values propagate back along a PushStream until
        they reach a part of the stream that is able to respond. For some
        PushEventSource implementations it is not possible to slow or delay
        event generation, however a buffer can always respond to back pressure
        by not releasing events from the buffer. Buffers can therefore be used
        to “smooth out” sources that produce bursts of events more quickly
        than they can be immediately processed. This simplifies the creation
        of PushEventConsumer instances, which can rely on their back-pressure
        requests being honored.</para>

        <para>Buffering is provided by the Push Stream using default
        configuration values, either when creating the Push Stream from the
        Push Stream Provider, or using the <code>buffer</code> method. These
        defaults are described in <xref
        linkend="util.pushstream.building-a-stream"/>.</para>

        <para>The default configuration values can be overridden by using a
        <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.BufferBuilder"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> to explicitly provide the buffering
        parameters. If no Executor is provided then the PushStream will create
        its own internal Executor with the same number of threads as the
        defined parallelism. An internally created Executor will be shut down
        when the PushStream is closed.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Buffering policies</title>

        <para>Buffering policies govern the behavior of a buffer as it becomes
        full.</para>

        <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.QueuePolicy"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> of the buffer determines what happens when the
        queue becomes full. Different policies may discard incoming data,
        evict data from the buffer, block, or throw an exception.</para>

        <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.QueuePolicyOption"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> provides basic implementations of the queue
        policies, but custom polices can be implemented to provide more
        complex behaviors.</para>

        <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushbackPolicy"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> of the buffer determines how much back
        pressure is requested by the buffer. Different policies may return a
        constant value, slowly increase the back pressure as the buffer fills,
        or return an exponentially increasing value when the buffer is
        full.</para>

        <para>The <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushbackPolicyOption"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> provides basic implementations of the push
        back policies, but custom polices can be implemented to provide more
        complex behaviors.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="util.pushstream.building-a-stream">
        <title>Building a Buffer or Push Stream</title>

        <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStreamBuilder"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> can be obtained from a Push Stream Provider
        and used to customize the buffer at the start of the PushStream, or it
        can be used to create an unbuffered PushStream. An unbuffered
        PushStream uses the incoming event delivery thread to process the
        events, and therefore users must be careful not to block the thread,
        or perform long-running tasks. The default configuration building a
        Push Stream is as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A parallelism of one</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.QueuePolicyOption.FAIL"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> queue policy</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushbackPolicyOption.LINEAR"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> push back policy with a maximum push back
            of one second</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A Buffer with a capacity of 32 elements</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>A Push Stream also requires a timer and an executor. For a new
        Push Stream the Push Stream Provider must create a new fixed pool of
        worker threads with the same size as the parallelism. The Push Stream
        Provider may create a new <code>ScheduledExecutorService</code> for
        each new Push Stream, or reuse a common Scheduler. When adding a
        buffer to an existing Push Stream the existing executor and timer used
        by the Push Stream are reused by default. The builder of the
        Buffer/Push Stream may provide their own executor and timer using the
        <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStreamBuilder.withExecutor-Executor-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStreamBuilder.withScheduler-ScheduledExecutorService-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Circuit Breakers</title>

        <para>Buffering is a powerful tool in event processing pipelines,
        however it cannot help in the situation where the average event
        production rate is higher than the average processing rate. Rather
        than having an infinitely growing buffer a circuit breaker is used. A
        circuit breaker is a buffer which fails the stream when the buffer is
        full. This halts event processing and prevents the consuming system
        from being overwhelmed.</para>

        <para>The default policy for push stream buffers is the FAIL policy,
        which means that push stream buffers are all circuit breakers by
        default.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Forking</title>

      <para>Sometimes the processing that needs to be performed on an event is
      long-running. An important part of the asynchronous eventing model is
      that callbacks are short and non-blocking, which means that these
      callbacks should not run using the primary event thread. One solution to
      this is to buffer the stream, allowing a thread handoff at the buffer
      and limiting the impact of the long-running task. Buffering, however,
      has other consequences, and so it may be the case that a simple thread
      hand-off is preferable.</para>

      <para>Forking allows users to specify a maximum number of concurrent
      downstream operations. Incoming events will block if this limit has been
      reached. If there are blocked threads then the returned back pressure
      for an event will be equal to the number of queued threads multiplied by
      the supplied timeout value. If there are no blocked threads then the
      back pressure will be zero.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Coalescing and Windowing</title>

      <para>Coalescing and windowing are both processes by which multiple
      incoming data events are collapsed into a single outgoing event.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Coalescing</title>

        <para>There are two main ways to coalesce a stream.</para>

        <para>The first mechanism delegates all responsibility to the
        coalescing function, which returns an <code>Optional</code>. The
        coalescing function is called for every data event, and returns an
        optional which either has a value, or is empty. If the optional has a
        value then this value is passed to the next stage of the processing
        pipeline. If the optional is empty then no data event is passed to the
        next stage.</para>

        <para>The second mechanism allows the stream to be configured with a
        (potentially variable) buffer size. The stream then stores values into
        this buffer. When the buffer is full then the stream passes the buffer
        to the handler function, which returns data to be passed to the next
        stage. If the stream finishes when a buffer is partially filled then
        the partially filled buffer will be passed to the handler
        function.</para>

        <para>When coalescing events there is no opportunity for feedback from
        the event handler while the events are being buffered. As a result
        back pressure from the handler is zero except when the event triggers
        a call to the next stage. When the next stage is triggered the back
        pressure from that stage is returned.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Windowing</title>

        <para>Windowing is similar to coalescing, the primary difference
        between coalescing and windowing is the way in which the next stage of
        processing is triggered. A coalescing stage collects events until it
        has the correct number and then passes them to the handler function,
        regardless of how long this takes. A windowing stage collects events
        for a given amount of time, and then passes the collected events to
        the handler function, regardless of how many events are
        collected.</para>

        <para>To avoid the need for a potentially infinite buffer a windowing
        stage may also place a limit on the number of events to be buffered.
        If this limit is reached then the window finishes early and the buffer
        is passed to the client, just like a coalescing stage. In this mode of
        operation the handler function is also passed the length of time for
        which the window lasted.</para>

        <para>As windowing requires the collected events to be delivered
        asynchronously there is no opportunity for back-pressure from the
        previous stage to be applied upstream. Windowing therefore returns
        zero back-pressure in all cases except when a buffer size limit has
        been declared and is reached. If a window size limit is reached then
        the windowing stage returns the remaining window time as back
        pressure. Applying back pressure in this way means that the event
        source will tend not to repeatedly over saturate the window.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Merging and Splitting</title>

      <para>Merging and Splitting are actions that can be used to combine push
      streams, or to convert one stream into many streams.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Merging</title>

        <para>A client may need to consume data from more than one Event
        Sources. In this case the PushStream may be used to merge two event
        streams. The returned stream will receive events from both parent
        streams, but will only close when <emphasis>both</emphasis> parent
        streams have delivered terminal events.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Splitting</title>

        <para>Sometimes it is desirable to split a stream into multiple
        parallel pipelines. These pipelines are independent from the point at
        which they are split, but share the same source and upstream
        pipeline.</para>

        <para>Splitting a stream is possible using the
        <code>split(Predicate&lt;? super T &gt;... predicates)</code> method.
        For each predicate a PushStream will be returned that receives the
        events accepted by the predicate.</para>

        <para>The lifecycle of a split stream differs from that of a normal
        stream in two key ways:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The stream will begin event delivery when any of the
            downstream handlers encounters a terminal operation</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The stream will only close when all of the downstream
            handlers are closed</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Time Limited Streams</title>

      <para>An important difference between Push Streams and Java 8 Streams is
      that events occur over time, there are therefore some operations that do
      not apply to Java 8 Streams which are relevant to Push Streams.</para>

      <para>The <code>limit()</code> operation on a Stream can be used to
      limit the number of elements that are processed, however on a Push
      Stream that number of events may never be reached, even though the
      stream has not closed. Push Streams therefore also have a
      <code>limit</code> method which takes a <code>Duration</code>. This
      duration limits the time for which the stream is open, closing it after
      the duration has elapsed.</para>

      <para>The <code>timeout</code> operation of a Push Stream can be used to
      end a stream if no events are received for the given amount of time. If
      an event is received then this resets the timeout counter. The timeout
      operation is therefore a useful mechanism for identifying pipelines
      which have stalled in their processing. If the timeout expires then it
      propagates an error event to the next stage of the pipeline. The
      Exception in the error event is an
      <code>org.osgi.util.promise.TimeoutException</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Closing Streams</title>

      <para>A <xref linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> represents a stage in the processing pipeline
      and is <code>AutoCloseable</code>. When the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.close--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is invoked it will not, in general,
      coincide with the processing of an event. The closing of a stream in
      this way must therefore do the following things:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Send a close event downstream to close the stream</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Discard events subsequently received by this pipeline stage,
          and return negative backpressure for any that do arrive at this
          pipeline stage.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Propagate the close operation upstream until the
          <code>AutoCloseable</code> returned by the <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEventSource.open-PushEventConsumer-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is closed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The result of this set of operations must be that all stages of
      the pipeline, including the connection to the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushEventSource"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, are eagerly closed. This may be as a result of
      receiving a close event, negative back pressure, or the close call being
      propagated back up the pipeline, but it must not wait for the next
      event. For example, if an event is produced every ten minutes and the
      stream is closed one minute after an event is created then it must not
      take a further nine minutes to close the connection to the Push Event
      Source.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Push Stream Provider</title>

    <para>The <code>PushStreamProvider</code> can be used to assist with a
    variety of asynchronous event handling use cases. A Push Stream Provider
    can create Push Stream instances from a Push Event Source, it can buffer
    an Push Event Consumer, or it can turn a Push Stream into a reusable Push
    Event Source.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Building Buffers</title>

      <para>The Push Stream Provider allows several types of buffered objects
      to be created. By default all Push Streams are created with a buffer,
      but other objects can also be wrapped in a buffer. For example a Push
      Event Consumer can be wrapped in a buffer to isolate it from a Push
      Event Source. The <code>SimplePushEventSource</code> also has a buffer,
      which is used to isolate the event producing thread from event
      consumers.</para>

      <para>In all cases buffers are configured using a
      <code>BufferBuilder</code> with the following defaults:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A parallelism of one</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <code>FAIL</code> QueuePolicy</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <code>LINEAR</code> PushbackPolicy with a maximum pushback
          of one second</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A Buffer with a capacity of 32 elements</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A Buffer requires a timer and an executor. If no Executor is
      provided when creating a buffer then the buffer will have its own
      internal Executor with the same number of threads as the defined
      parallelism. The Push Stream Provider may create a new
      <code>ScheduledExecutorService</code> for each buffer, or reuse a common
      Scheduler. The builder of the Buffer may provide their own executor and
      timer using the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStreamBuilder.withExecutor-Executor-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStreamBuilder.withScheduler-ScheduledExecutorService-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods</para>

      <para>Any internally created Executor will be shut down after the buffer
      has processed a terminal event.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Mapping between Java 8 Streams and Push Streams</title>

      <para>There are a number of scenarios where an application developer may
      wish to convert between a Java 8 Stream and a PushStream. In particular,
      the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStream.flatMap-Function-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> operation of a Push Stream takes a single event
      and converts it into many events in a Push Stream. Common operations,
      such as splitting the event into child events will result in a Java
      Collection, or a Java 8 Stream. These need to be converted into a Push
      Stream before they can be returned from the flatMap operation.</para>

      <para>To assist this model the PushStreamProvider provides two
      <code>streamOf</code> methods. These convert a Java 8 Stream into a Push
      Stream, changing the pull-based model of Java 8 Streams into the
      asynchronous model of the Push Stream.</para>

      <para>The first <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStreamProvider.streamOf-Stream-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method takes a Java 8 Stream. The PushStream
      created by this method is not fully asynchronous, it uses the connecting
      thread to consume the Java 8 Stream. As a result the streams created
      using this method will block terminal operations. This method should
      therefore not normally be used for infinite event streams, but instead
      for short, finite streams of data that can be processed rapidly, for
      example as the result of a flatmapping operation. In this scenario
      reusing the incoming thread improves performance. In the following
      example an incoming list of URLs is registered for download.</para>

      <programlisting>PushStreamProvider psp = new PushStreamProvider();

PushStream&lt;List&lt;URL&gt;&gt; urls = getURLStream();

urls.flatMap(l -&gt; psp.streamOf(l.stream()))
    .forEach(url -&gt; registerDownload(url));</programlisting>

      <para>For larger Streams of data, or when truly asynchronous operation
      is required, there is a second <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.PushStreamProvider.streamOf-Executor-ScheduledExecutorService-Stream-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method which allows for asynchronous consumption
      of the stream. The Executor is used to consume elements from the Java 8
      Stream using a single task. This mode of operation is suitable for use
      with infinite data streams, or for streams which require a truly
      asynchronous mode of operation, and does not require the stream to be
      parallel. If <code>null</code> is passed for the <code>Executor</code>
      then the PushStreamProvider will create a fixed thread pool of size 2.
      This allows for work to continue in the Push Stream even if the
      passed-in Stream blocks the consuming thread. If <code>null</code> is
      passed for the <code>ScheduledExecutor</code> then the Push Stream
      Provider may create a new scheduler or use a shared default.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Simple Push Event Sources</title>

    <para>The PushEventSource and PushEventConsumer are both functional
    interfaces, however it is noticeably harder to implement a PushEventSource
    than a PushEventConsumer. A PushEventSource must be able to support
    multiple independently closeable consumer registrations, all of which are
    providing potentially different amounts of back pressure.</para>

    <para>To simplify the case where a user wishes to write a basic event
    source the PushStreamProvider is able to create a SimplePushEventSource.
    The SimplePushEventSource handles the details of implementing
    PushEventSource, providing a simplified API for the event producing code
    to use.</para>

    <para>Events can be sent via the Simple Push Event Source <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.SimplePushEventSource.publish-T-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method at any time until it is closed. These
    events may be silently ignored if no consumer is connected, but if one or
    more consumers are connected then the event will be asynchronously
    delivered to them.</para>

    <para>Close or error events can be sent equally easily using the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.SimplePushEventSource.endOfStream--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.util.pushstream.SimplePushEventSource.error-Throwable-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods. These will send disconnection events to
    all of the currently connected consumers and remove them from the Simple
    Push Event Source. Note that sending these events does not close the
    Simple Push Event Source. Subsequent connection attempts will succeed, and
    events can still be published.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Optimizing Event Creation</title>

      <para>In addition to the publication methods the Simple Push Event
      Source provides <code>isConnected()</code> and
      <code>connectPromise()</code> methods. The isConnected method gives a
      point-in-time snapshot of whether there are any connections to the
      Simple Push Event Source. If this method returns false then the event
      producer may wish to avoid creating the event, particularly if it is
      computationally expensive to do so. The connectPromise method returns a
      Promise representing the current connection state. This Promise resolves
      when there is a client connected (which means it may be resolved
      immediately as it is created). If the Simple Push Event Source is closed
      before the Promise resolves then the Promise is failed with an
      IllegalStateException. The connect Promise can be used to trigger the
      initialization of an event thread, allowing lazier startup.</para>

      <programlisting>PushStreamProvider psp = new PushStreamProvider();

SimplePushEventSource&lt;Long&gt; ses = psp.createSimpleEventSource(Long.class))

Success&lt;Void,Void&gt; onConnect = p -&gt; {
    new Thread(() -&gt; {
        long counter = 0;
        // Keep going as long as someone is listening
        while (ses.isConnected()) {
          ses.publish(++counter);
          Thread.sleep(100);
          System.out.println("Published: " + counter);
        }
        // Restart delivery when a new listener connects
        ses.connectPromise().then(onConnect);
      }).start();
    return null;
  };

// Begin delivery when someone is listening
ses.connectPromise().then(onConnect);

// Create a listener which prints out even numbers
psp.createStream(ses).
  filter(l -&gt; l % 2L == 0).
  limit(5000L).
  forEach(f -&gt; System.out.println("Consumed event: " + f));</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>The Push Stream API does not define any OSGi services nor does the
    API perform any privileged actions. Therefore, it has no security
    considerations.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.util.pushstream.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="util.pushstream-ref.java8stream"><title>Java 8
      Stream API</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/stream/package-summary.html#package.description"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
