<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="138" revision="$Id:" version="5" xml:id="service.async"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Asynchronous Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.async-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>OSGi Bundles collaborate using loosely coupled services registered
    in the OSGi service registry. This is a powerful and flexible model, and
    allows for the dynamic replacement of services at runtime. OSGi services
    are therefore a very common interaction pattern within OSGi.</para>

    <para>As with most Java APIs and Objects, OSGi services are primarily
    synchronous in operation. This has several benefits; synchronous APIs are
    typically easier to write and to use than asynchronous ones; synchronous
    APIs provide immediate feedback; synchronous implementations typically
    have a less complex threading model.</para>

    <para>Asynchronous APIs, however, have different advantages. Asynchronous
    APIs can reduce bottlenecks by encouraging more effective use of
    parallelism, improving the responsiveness of the application. In many
    cases high throughput systems can be written more simply and elegantly
    using asynchronous programming techniques.</para>

    <para>The <xref linkend="util.promise"/> provides powerful primitives for
    asynchronous programming, including the ability to compose flows in a
    functional style. There are, however, many existing services that do not
    use the Promise API. The purpose of the Asynchronous Service is to bridge
    the gap between these existing, primarily synchronous, services in the
    OSGi service registry, and asynchronous programming. The Asynchronous
    Service therefore provides a way to invoke arbitrary OSGi services
    asynchronously, providing results and failure notifications through the
    Promise API.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Async Invocation</emphasis> - A single method call
          that is to be executed without blocking the requesting
          thread.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Client</emphasis> - Application code that wishes to
          invoke one or more OSGi services asynchronously.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Async Service</emphasis> - The OSGi service
          representing the Asynchronous Services implementation. Used by the
          Client to make one or more Async Invocations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Async Mediator</emphasis> - A mediator object
          created by the Async Service which represents the target service.
          Used by the Client to register Async Invocations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Success Callback</emphasis> - A callback made when
          an Async Invocation completes with a normal return value.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Failure Callback</emphasis> - A callback made when
          an Async Invocation completes with an exception.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Async Service</emphasis> - A service that can create
          Async Mediators and run Async Invocations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Target Service</emphasis> - A service that is to be
          called asynchronously by the Client.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Client</emphasis> - The code that makes Async
          Invocations using the Async Service</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Promise</emphasis> - A promise, representing the
          result of the Async Invocation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Class and Service overview</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.100in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="async-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>This section is an introduction in the usage of the Async Service.
    It is not the formal specification, the normative part starts at <xref
    linkend="service.async-main.body"/>. This section leaves out some of the
    details for clarity.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>The Async Service provides a mechanism for a client to
      <emphasis>asynchronously</emphasis> invoke methods on a target service.
      The service may be aware of the asynchronous nature of the call and
      actively participate in it, or be unaware and execute normally. In
      either case the client's thread will not block, and will continue
      executing its next instructions. Clients are notified of the completion
      of their task, and whether it was successful or not, through the use of
      the Promise API.</para>

      <para>Each async invocation is registered by the client making a method
      call on an <emphasis>Async Mediator</emphasis>, and then started by
      making a call to the Async Service that created the mediator. This call
      returns a Promise that will eventually be resolved with the return value
      from the async invocation.</para>

      <para>An Async Mediator can be created by the client, either from an
      Object, or directly from a Service Reference. Using a service reference
      has the advantage that the mediator will track the underlying service.
      This means that if the service is unregistered before the asynchronous
      call begins then the Promise will resolve with a failure, rather than
      continuing using an invalid service object.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Making Async Invocations</title>

      <para>The general pattern for a client is to obtain the Async Service,
      and a service reference for the target service. The client then creates
      an Async Mediator for the target service, invokes a method on the
      mediator, then starts the asynchronous call. This is demonstrated in the
      following example:</para>

      <programlisting>
      
private Async asyncService;
private ServiceReference&lt;Foo&gt; fooRef;
private Foo mediated;

@Reference
void setAsync(Async async) {
    asyncService = async;
}

@Reference(service = Foo.class)
void setList(ServiceReference&lt;Foo&gt; foo) {
    fooRef = foo;
}

@Activate
void start() {
    mediated = asyncService.mediate(fooRef, Foo.class);
}

public synchronized void doStuff() {
    Promise&lt;Boolean&gt; promise = asyncService
           .call(mediated.booleanMethod(“aValue”));
    ...
}

      </programlisting>

      <para>This example demonstrates how simply clients can make asynchronous
      calls using the Async Service. The eventual result can be obtained from
      the promise using one of the relevant callbacks.</para>

      <para>One important thing to note is that whilst the call to <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> causes the async invocation to begin, the actual
      execution of the underlying task may be queued until a thread is
      available to run it. If the service has been unregistered before the
      execution actually begins then the promise will be resolved with a
      Service Exception. The type of the Service Exception will be
      <code>ASYNC_ERROR</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Async Invocations of Void Methods</title>

      <para>The return value of the mediator method call is used to provide
      type information to the Async Service. This, however, does not work for
      <code>void</code> methods that have no return value. In this case the
      client can either pass an arbitrary object to the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      method, or use the zero argument <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      method. In either case the returned promise will eventually resolve with
      a value of <code>null</code>. This is demonstrated in the following
      example.</para>

      <programlisting>
private Async asyncService;
private ServiceReference&lt;Foo&gt; fooRef;
private Foo mediated;

@Reference
void setAsync(Async async) {
    asyncService = async;
}

@Reference(service = Foo.class)
void setList(ServiceReference&lt;Foo&gt; foo) {
    fooRef = foo;
}

@Activate
void start() {
    mediated = asyncService.mediate(fooRef, Foo.class);
}

public synchronized void doStuff() {
    mediated.voidMethod();
    Promise&lt;?&gt; promise = asyncService
           .call();
    ...
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fire and Forget Calls</title>

      <para>Sometimes a client does not require any notification that an async
      invocation has completed. In this case the client could use one of the
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      methods and simply discard the returned Promise object. This, however,
      can be wasteful of resources. The act of resolving the Promise object
      may be expensive, for example it may involve serializing the return
      value over a network if the remote call was asynchronous.</para>

      <para>If the client knows that no Promise object representing the result
      of the asynchronous task is needed then it can signal this to the Async
      Service. This allows the Async Service to better optimize the async
      invocation by not providing a result.</para>

      <para>To indicate that the client wants to make a fire-and-forget style
      call the client invokes the mediator as normal, but then begins the
      asynchronous invocation using the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.execute--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      method as show below.</para>

      <programlisting>
private Async asyncService;
private ServiceReference&lt;Foo&gt; fooRef;

private Foo mediated;

@Reference
void setAsync(Async async) {
    asyncService = async;
}

@Reference(service = Foo.class)
void setList(ServiceReference&lt;Foo&gt; foo) {
    fooRef = foo;
}

@Activate
void start() {
    mediated = asyncService.mediate(fooRef, Foo.class);
}

public synchronized void doStuff() {
    mediated.someMethod();
    asyncService.execute();
    ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>Note that the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.execute--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      method does still return a Promise. This Promise is not the same as the
      ones returned by <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>,
      its resolution value does not provide access to the result, but instead
      indicates whether the fire-and-forget call could be successfully
      started. If there is a failure which prevents the task from being
      executed then this is used to fail the returned promise.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Multi Threading</title>

      <para>By their very definition asynchronous tasks do not run inline, and
      typically they will not run on the same thread as the caller. This is
      not, however, a guarantee. A valid implementation of the Async Service
      may have only one worker thread, which may be the thread currently
      running in the client code. Async invocations also have the same
      threading model as the Promise API. This means that callbacks may run on
      arbitrary threads, which may, or may not, be the same as the client
      thread, or the thread which executed the asynchronous work.</para>

      <para>It is important for multi-threaded clients to note that calls to
      the mediator and Async Service must occur on the same thread. For
      example it is not supported to invoke a mediator using one thread, and
      then to begin the async invocation by calling the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>,
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.execute--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      method on a different thread.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.async-main.body">
    <title>Async Service</title>

    <para>The Async Service is the primary interaction point between a client
    and the Async Service implementation. An Async Service implementation must
    expose a service implementing the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface.
    Clients obtain an instance of the Async Service using the normal OSGi
    service registry mechanisms, either directly using the OSGi framework API,
    or using dependency injection.</para>

    <para>The Async Service is used to:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create async mediators</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Begin async invocations</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Obtain Promise objects representing the result of the async
        invocation</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Using the Async Service</title>

      <para>The first action that a client wishing to make an async invocation
      must take is to create an async mediator using one of the
      <code>mediate</code> methods. Once created the client invokes the method
      that should be run asynchronously, supplying the arguments that should
      be used. This call records the invocation, but does not start the
      asynchronous task. The asynchronous task begins when the client invokes
      one of the <code>call</code> or <code>execute</code> methods on the
      Async Service. The <code>call</code> methods must return a Promise
      representing the async invocation. The promise must resolve with the
      value returned by the async invocation, or fail with the failure thrown
      by the async invocation.</para>

      <para>If the client attempts to begin an async invocation without first
      having called a method on the mediator object then the Async Service
      must detect this usage error and throw an
      <code>IllegalStateException</code> to the client. This applies to all
      methods that begin an async invocation.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="service.async-main.failures">
      <title>Asynchronous Failures</title>

      <para>There are a variety of reasons that async invocations may be
      started correctly by the client, but then fail without running the
      asynchronous task. In any of these cases the Promise representing the
      async invocation must fail with a Service Exception. This Service
      Exception must be initialized with a type of <code>ASYNC_ERROR</code>.
      If there is no promise representing the async invocation then there is
      no way to notify the client of the failure, therefore the Service
      Exception must be logged by the Async Service using all available Log
      Service implementations.</para>

      <para>The following list of scenarios is not exhaustive, but indicates
      failure scenarios that must result in a Service Exception with a type of
      async</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the client is using a service reference backed mediator and
          the client bundle's bundle context becomes invalid before looking up
          the target service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the client is using a service reference backed mediator and
          the service is unregistered before making the async
          invocation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the client is using a service reference backed mediator and
          the service lookup returns <code>null</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the Async Service is unable to accept new work, for example
          it is in the process of being shut down.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the type of the mediator object does not match the type of
          the service object to be invoked.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Thread Safety and Instance Sharing</title>

      <para>Implementations of the Async Service must be thread safe and may
      be used simultaneously across multiple clients and from multiple threads
      within the same client. Whilst the Async Service is able to be used
      across multiple threads, if a client wishes to make an async invocation
      then the call to the mediator and the call to begin the async invocation
      must occur on the same thread. The returned Promise may then be shared
      between threads if required.</para>

      <para>It is expected, although not required, that the Async Service
      implementation will use a Service Factory to create customized
      implementations for each client bundle. This simplifies the tracking of
      the relevant client bundle context to use when performing service
      lookups on the client bundle's behalf. Clients should therefore not
      share instances of the Async Service with other bundles. Instead both
      bundles should obtain their own instances from the service
      registry.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Service Object Lifecycle Management</title>

      <para>If the Async Service is being used to call an OSGi service object
      and the service reference is available then the service object should be
      looked up immediately before the asynchronous task begins executing.
      This ensures that the service is still available at the point it is
      eventually called. Any call to <code>getService</code> must have a
      corresponding call to <code>ungetService</code> after the mediated
      method invoked has returned and, if available, the promise is resolved,
      but before the asynchronous task releases its thread of
      execution.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Async Mediator</title>

    <para>Async mediators are dynamically created objects that have the same
    type or interface as the object being mediated, and are used to record
    method invocations and arguments. Mediator objects are specific to an
    Async Service implementation, and must only be used in conjunction with
    the Async Service object that they were created by.</para>

    <para>Mediators may be created either from a <code>ServiceReference</code>
    or from a service object. The actions and overall result are similar for
    both the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.mediate-ServiceReference-Class-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.mediate-T-Class-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods, with the primary difference being that
    mediated objects created from a <code>ServiceReference</code> will
    validate whether the service object is still available immediately before
    the asynchronous task is executed.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Building the Mediator Object</title>

      <para>The client passes in a <code>Class</code> indicating the type that
      should be mediated. If the class object represents an interface type
      then the generated mediator object must implement that interface. If the
      class object represents a Java class type then the mediator object must
      either be an instance of that type or extend it.</para>

      <para>When building a mediator object the Async Service has the
      opportunity to detect numerous problems, for example if the referenced
      service to be mediated has been unregistered. Although fail-fast
      behavior is usually preferable, in this case it would force the client
      to handle errors in two places; both when creating the mediator, and for
      the returned Promise. To simplify client usage, error cases detected
      when creating a mediator must not prevent the mediator from being
      created and must not result in an exception being thrown. The only
      reason that the Async Service may fail to create a mediator is if the
      class object passed in cannot be mediated.</para>

      <para>There are three reasons why the Async Service may not be able to
      mediate a class type:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The class object passed in represents a final type.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The class object passed in represents a type that has no
          zero-argument constructor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The class object passed in represents a type which has one or
          more public final methods present in its type hierarchy (other than
          those declared by <code>java.lang.Object</code>).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If any of these constraints are violated and prevent the Async
      Service from creating a mediator then the Async Service must throw an
      IllegalArgumentException.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Async Mediator Behaviors</title>

      <para>When invoked, the Async mediator must record the method call, and
      its arguments, and then return rapidly and should avoid performing
      blocking operations. The values returned by the mediator object are
      opaque, and the client should not attempt to interpret the returned
      value. The value may be null (or null-like in the case of primitives) or
      contain implementation specific information. If the mediated method call
      has a return type, specifically it is non-void, then this object must be
      passed to the Async Service's <code>call</code> method when beginning
      the async invocation</para>

      <para>Async mediators should make a best-effort attempt to detect
      incorrect API usage from the client. If this incorrect usage is detected
      then the mediator object must throw an IllegalStateException when
      invoked. An example of incorrect usage that must be detected is when a
      client makes multiple invocations on a single mediator object from the
      same thread without making any calls to the Async Service.</para>

      <para>After a usage error has been detected and an IllegalStateException
      has been thrown the mediator object must be reset so that a subsequent
      invocation from the client thread can proceed normally.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Thread Safety and Instance Sharing</title>

      <para>Async mediators, like instances of the Async Service, are required
      to be thread safe. Clients may therefore share mediator objects across
      threads, and can safely store them as instance fields. Whilst mediators
      are thread safe, if a client wishes to make an async invocation then the
      call to the mediator and the call to <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> must occur on the same thread. The returned
      Promise may then be shared between threads if required.</para>

      <para>Async mediators created from <code>ServiceReference</code> objects
      remain directly associated with the service reference and client bundle
      after creation. Clients should therefore not share mediator objects with
      other bundles. Instead each bundle should create its own
      mediator.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Fire and Forget Invocations</title>

    <para>The Async Service provides <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods for clients to use when they wish to
    receive results from asynchronous tasks. Clients that do not need the
    result can simply discard the returned Promise object. This, however, can
    be wasteful of resources. The act of resolving the Promise object may be
    expensive, for example it may involve serializing the return value over a
    network.</para>

    <para>To address this use case the Async Service provides the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.execute--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
    method, which behaves similarly to <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, but does not provide access to the eventual
    result. Instead the <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.execute--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method returns a <code>Promise</code> that
    indicates whether the fire-and-forget call is able to be successfully
    started.</para>

    <para>The returned Promise must be resolved with <code>null</code> if the
    asynchronous task begins executing successfully. There is no
    <emphasis>happens-before</emphasis> relationship required, meaning that if
    the Promise resolves successfully then the task may, or may not, have
    started or finished. The primary usage of the Promise is actually to
    detect failures. If the fire-and-forget task cannot be executed for some
    reason, for example the backing service has been unregistered, then the
    returned promise must be failed appropriately using the same rules as
    defined in <xref linkend="service.async-main.failures"/>. If the returned
    Promise is failed then the fire-and-forget task has not executed and will
    not execute in the future.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Delegating to Asynchronous Implementations</title>

    <para>Some service APIs are already asynchronous in operation, and others
    are partly asynchronous, in that some methods run asynchronously and
    others do not. There are also services which have a synchronous API, but
    could run asynchronously because they are a proxy to another service. A
    good example of this kind of service is a remote service. Remote services
    are local views of a remote endpoint, and depending upon the
    implementation of the endpoint it may be possible to make the remote call
    asynchronously, optimizing the thread usage of any local asynchronous
    call.</para>

    <para>Services that already have some level of asynchronous support may
    advertise this to clients and to the Async Service by having their service
    object be an <code>instanceof</code> <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The service object can be cast to <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> to be used by the Async Service implementation, or
    by the client directly, to make an asynchronous call on the
    service.</para>

    <para>Because the Async Delegate behavior is transparently handled by the
    Async Service, clients of the Async Service do not need to know whether
    the service object is an <code>instanceof</code> <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or not. Their usage pattern can remain
    unchanged.</para>

    <para>When making an async invocation, the Async Service must check to see
    whether the service object is an <code>instanceof</code> <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. If the service object is an
    <code>instanceof</code> <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, then the Async Service must attempt to delegate
    the asynchronous call. The exact delegation operation depends on whether a
    Promise result is required.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Obtaining a Promise from an Async Delegate</title>

      <para>If the result of the method invocation is needed by the client,
      then the Async Service must attempt to delegate to the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate.async-Method-Object---"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The delegation proceeds as
      follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the call to the Async Delegate returns a Promise, then the
          Promise returned by the Async Service must be resolved with that
          Promise.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the call to the Async Delegate throws an exception, then
          the Promise returned by the Async Service must be failed with the
          exception.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the Async Delegate is unable to optimize the call and
          returns <code>null</code> from the <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate.async-Method-Object---"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, the Async Service must continue
          processing the async invocation, treating the service as a normal
          service object.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Delegating Fire and Forget Calls to an Async Delegate</title>

      <para>If the result of the method invocation is not needed by the
      client, then the Async Service must attempt to delegate to the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate.execute-Method-Object---"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This gives the Async Delegate
      implementation the opportunity to further optimize its processing. The
      delegation proceeds as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the call to the Async Delegate returns <code>true</code>,
          then the Promise returned by the Async Service must be resolved with
          <code>null</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the call to the Async Delegate throws an exception, then
          the Promise returned by the Async Service must be failed with the
          exception.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the Async Delegate is unable to optimize the call and
          returns <code>false</code> from the <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate.execute-Method-Object---"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, the Async Service must continue
          processing the async invocation, treating the service as a normal
          service object.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Lifecycle for Service Objects When Delegating</title>

      <para>If an Async Delegate implementation accepts an asynchronous task,
      via a call to either <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate.execute-Method-Object---"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.async.delegate.AsyncDelegate.async-Method-Object---"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, then it is responsible for continuing to
      process the work until completion. This means that if the service
      implementing Async Delegate is unregistered for some reason, then the
      task must be properly cleaned up and succeed or fail as
      appropriate.</para>

      <para>If the Async Service implementation used a service reference to
      obtain the service, then it must release the service object after the
      task has been accepted. This means that if the service object is
      provided by a service factory, then the service object should take extra
      care not to destroy its internal state when released. The service object
      must remain valid until all executing asynchronous tasks associated with
      the service object are either completed or failed.</para>

      <para>If an Async Delegate implementation rejects an asynchronous task,
      by returning <code>false</code> or <code>null</code>, the Async Service
      implementation must take over the asynchronous invocation of the method.
      In this case, if the Async Service implementation used a service
      reference to obtain the service, the Async Service must not release the
      service object until the asynchronous task is completed.</para>

      <para>If an Async Delegate implementation throws an exception and the
      Async Service implementation used a service reference to obtain the
      service, then the service object must be released immediately.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.async-capabilities">
    <title>Capabilities</title>

    <para>Implementations of the Asynchronous Service specification must
    provide the following capabilities.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A capability in the <link
        linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.implementation.namespace"><code>osgi.implementation</code></link>
        namespace declaring the implemented specification to be
        <code>osgi.async</code>. This capability must also declare a uses
        constraint for the <code>org.osgi.service.async</code> and
        <code>org.osgi.service.async.delegate</code> packages. For
        example:</para>

        <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.implementation;
    osgi.implementation="osgi.async";
    version:Version="<xref endterm="org.osgi.service.async-version.number"
            linkend="org.osgi.service.async"/>";
    uses:="org.osgi.service.async,org.osgi.service.async.delegate"</programlisting>

        <para>This capability must follow the rules defined for the <xref
        linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.implementation.namespace"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A capability in the <link
        linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"><code>osgi.service</code></link>
        namespace representing the <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        service. This capability must also declare a uses constraint for the
        <code>org.osgi.service.async</code> package. For example:</para>

        <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.service;
    objectClass:List&lt;String&gt;="org.osgi.service.async.Async";
    uses:="org.osgi.service.async"</programlisting>

        <para>This capability must follow the rules defined for the <xref
        linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.async-security">
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>Asynchronous Services implementations must be careful to avoid
    elevating the privileges of client bundles when calling services
    asynchronously, and also to avoid restricting the privileges of clients
    that are permitted to make a call. This means that the implementation
    must:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Be granted <code>AllPermission</code>. As the Async Service will
        always be on the stack when invoking a service object asynchronously
        it must be granted <code>AllPermission</code> so that it does not
        interfere with security any checks made by the service object.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Establish the caller's <code>AccessControlContext</code> in a
        worker thread before starting to call the service object. This
        prevents a bundle from being able to call a service asynchronously
        that it would not normally be able to call. The
        <code>AccessControlContext</code> must be collected during any call to
        <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        or <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.execute--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Use a <code>doPrivileged</code> block when mediating a concrete
        type. A no-args constructor in a concrete type may perform actions
        that the client may not have permission to perform. This should not
        prevent the client from mediating the object, as the client is not
        directly performing these actions.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If the mediator object was created using a service reference,
        then the Async Services implementation must use the client's bundle
        context when retrieving the target service. If the service lookup
        occurs on a worker thread, then the lookup must use the
        <code>AccessControlContext</code> collected during the call to <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call--" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>,
        <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.call-R-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.async.Async.execute--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This prevents the client bundle from being
        able to make calls on a service object that they do not have
        permission to obtain, and ensures that an appropriately customized
        object is returned if the service is implemented using a service
        factory.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Further security considerations can be addressed using normal OSGi
    security rules. For example access to the Async Service can be controlled
    using <code>ServicePermission[...Async, GET]</code>.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.async.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.async.delegate.xml"/>
</chapter>
