<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="53" revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="framework.resolverhooks"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Resolver Hook Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The module layer is responsible for the resolve operation that wires
    requirements (Import-Package, Require-Bundle etc.) to capabilities
    (Export-Package, Bundle-SymbolicName/Bundle-Version etc.). The resolve
    operation is designed to work stand-alone but in certain use cases it is
    important to be able to influence the resolver's decisions. This
    specification defines a Resolver Hook Factory service that allows third
    party bundles to influence the resolve operation. Primary use cases for
    this hook are scoping of groups of bundles. However, the hooks also allows
    bundle to find out about, and control, the resolve operation for other
    purposes.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Reduction</emphasis> - Allow third party bundles to
          remove capabilities from a set of capabilities that matches a
          requirement.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Complete</emphasis> - Support all built-in
          namespaces as well as the generic capability and requirement
          headers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Singletons</emphasis> - Allow third party bundles to
          remove candidates from a set of singleton capabilities before the
          resolver selects one.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Secure</emphasis> - Support full security but allow
          operation without security present.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Resolver Hook Factory</emphasis> - The service
          registered by a bundle that wants to control the resolve operation.
          This service is used to create an instance of the Resolver Hook for
          each resolve operation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Resolver Hook</emphasis> - Is created by the
          Resolver Hook Factory service for each resolver process. Is
          consulted to reduce candidate capabilities for resolving and
          selecting singletons.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Client</emphasis> - A bundle that is considered
          during the resolve operation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Handler</emphasis> - A bundle that registers a
          Resolver Hook Factory service for influencing the resolve
          operation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Capability</emphasis> - A capability
          represents a feature of a bundle described with attributes and
          directives defined in a namespace. Some namespaces are built-in to
          the OSGi framework, others are generic.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Requirement</emphasis> - A requirement
          represents a need from a bundle described as a filter on the
          attributes of a Bundle Capability.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Provider</emphasis> - A bundle that provides a
          Bundle Capability.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Consumer</emphasis> - A bundle that requires a
          Bundle Capability</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Resolver</emphasis> - The internal framework
          machinery that resolves requirements to providers with matching
          capabilities.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Resolver Hooks Entities</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.865in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in"
                       fileref="resolverhook-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>A handler bundle that needs to manage the wiring between bundles
      must register a Resolver Hook Factory service. For each resolve
      operation the Resolver needs to perform, the framework asks each
      Resolver Hook Factory service for a new Resolver Hook specific for the
      operation. During the resolve operation, the Resolver will allow the
      Resolver Hooks to remove candidate solutions and assist in selecting
      singletons.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resolve Operation</title>

    <section>
      <title>Trigger Bundles</title>

      <para>The Resolver is triggered by activity in the OSGi framework.
      Calling certain methods on a bundle when a bundle is in the
      <code>INSTALLED</code> state will cause the framework to begin a
      <emphasis>resolve operation</emphasis> in order to resolve the bundle.
      Other API can also trigger a resolver. Frameworks can resolve on a per
      bundle basis or they can resolve a number of bundles atomically in one
      operation. The bundles that trigger a resolve operation are called the
      <emphasis>trigger bundle</emphasis>s. The trigger bundles can be defined
      by the following cases:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Root Bundle</emphasis> - Calling certain methods on
          a bundle when a bundle is in the <code>INSTALLED</code> state will
          cause the framework to begin a <emphasis>resolve
          operation</emphasis> in order to resolve the bundle. In general, a
          bundle needs to be resolved when its class loader is needed. The
          following Bundle methods will start a resolve operation when the
          subject is not yet resolved:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><code>start</code></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><code>loadClass</code></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><code>findEntries</code></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><code>getResource</code></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><code>getResources</code></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Resolve Bundles</emphasis> - The set of bundle
          revisions of the unresolved bundles given as argument, or their
          default when <code>null</code> is used, to the Framework Wiring
          <code>resolveBundles</code> method. See <xref
          linkend="framework.wiring.usingthewiringapi"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Refresh Bundles</emphasis> - A refresh operation
          will have to re-resolve the bundles that will be unresolved in the
          refresh. The trigger bundles are then the bundle revisions of the
          dependency closure, which is described in <xref
          linkend="framework.wiring.refreshing"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dynamic Import</emphasis> - A Dynamic Import can
          require the framework to start a resolve operation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Other</emphasis> - The Resolver Hook is a service so
          other parties can to start a resolver operation to run what-if
          scenarios or for other purposes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Resolving Types</title>

      <para>Various types of resolve operations can be initiated:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Static</emphasis> - A static bundle resolve
          operation. This resolve operation is necessary any time one or more
          bundles transitions from the <code>INSTALLED</code> state to the
          <code>RESOLVED</code> state. During this resolve operation the
          framework attempts to resolve static requirements specified by the
          bundles being resolved.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dynamic</emphasis> - A dynamic import must be
          resolved.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The resolve operation is not limited to the trigger bundles only,
      they just provide the root bundles that must be resolved. The Resolver
      is free to consider any present bundle to provide the required
      capabilities. If such bundles are in the <code>INSTALLED</code> state
      then they can also become a candidate to be resolved. The resolver is
      also free to use bundles that are actually not installed in the
      framework, for example for what-if scenarios.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Preparing Handlers</title>

      <para>Once the resolver is triggered, it must prepare the
      <emphasis>Handlers</emphasis> to participate in the resolve operation. A
      Handler is an active bundle that needs to participate in the resolve
      operation, there can be multiple Handlers in a framework. A Handler must
      register a Resolver Hook Factory service. This service is the interface
      between a <emphasis>Handler</emphasis> bundle, a bundle that will handle
      some aspects of the resolve operation, and the Resolver.</para>

      <para>To prepare the Handlers, the Resolver must request a new Resolver
      Hook from each of the registered Resolver Hook Factory services with the
      <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHookFactory.begin-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The parameter is the set of trigger
      bundles. The Handler is expected to create a new <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object for each call. If <code>null</code> is
      returned then the Handler abstains from participation. A Resolver Hook
      Factory must be thread-safe and allow the creation of independent
      Resolver Hook objects that can be active on multiple threads.</para>

      <para>A Resolver Hook is created for a single atomic resolve operation
      and does not have to be thread safe. The Resolver must ensure that
      access to the Resolver Hook is serialized, that is, the can only be
      active from a single thread. The <code>ResolverHook</code> object is
      called multiple times during a resolve operation to influence the
      outcome of a resolve operation. The following operations are
      provided:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterResolvable-Collection-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Removes bundles that are candidates for
          resolving so they do not resolve in the current operation. Provides
          an easy way to exclude bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterMatches-BundleRequirement-Collection-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Remove matching capabilities from the
          candidate capabilities. This effectively hides capabilities for
          certain requirers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterSingletonCollisions-BundleCapability-Collection-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Remove potentially conflicting singletons
          from the collection. This provides the possibility to resolve a
          singleton multiple times in different groups.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A Resolver Hook can influence the outcome of a resolve operation
      by removing entries from <emphasis>shrinkable</emphasis> collections. A
      shrinkable collection is a collection that can only shrink. The Handler
      can remove entries from the collection but it cannot add an entry to it.
      Any attempt to add to the collection must result in throwing an
      Unsupported Operation Exception. All collections in the Resolver Hook
      API are shrinkable collections.</para>

      <para>The Resolver Hook Factory services <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHookFactory.begin-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is called in the ranking order, see <xref
      linkend="framework.service.servicerankingorder"/>. This is the same
      order used for calling the resulting Resolver Hooks. The Resolver Hook
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method notifies the Handler that the resolve
      operation has finished. The framework must not hold on to this Resolver
      Hook instance after the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method has been called.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Limiting the Set of Resolvable Bundles</title>

      <para>There are use cases where a bundle that is being installed should
      not be allowed to resolve until some activity has taken place. Sometimes
      certain bundles should never resolve. For example, there are byte code
      weaving scenarios where a bundle is used as the source but a synthetic
      bundle with the woven code provides the actual classes. The source
      bundle should then not resolve. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterResolvable-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method can be used to ensure that certain
      bundles are never resolved. All the given Bundle Revisions are
      unresolved. The Handler can look at the given collection and remove any
      bundles it wants to prevent being resolved in this resolve
      operation.</para>

      <para>The set of bundles passed will contain the trigger bundles. If a
      Handler removes one of the trigger bundles the resolve of the removed
      bundle will not succeed and fail the call to the method that triggered
      the resolve operation.</para>

      <para>The framework can pass an empty collection of resolvable bundle
      revisions, this could for example happen while resolving a dynamic
      import. An empty collection indicates that the framework will not cause
      any bundles to transition from <code>INSTALLED</code> to
      <code>RESOLVED</code> during a dynamic import package resolving.</para>

      <para>For example, a Handler wants to ensure certain bundles are not
      resolved, then it can do:</para>

      <programlisting>public class UnresolveHandler implements ResolverHook{
    Set&lt;BundleRevision&gt; neverResolve = ... ;

    public void filterResolvable(
        Collection&lt;BundleRevision&gt; toBeResolved ) {
        toBeResolved.removeAll( neverResolve );
    }

   ... other methods
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Hiding Capabilities</title>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterMatches-BundleRequirement-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is used to remove capabilities for
      consideration for a specific requirer. The Handler receives the Bundle
      Requirement and the set of candidates that already match the
      requirement. The Handler can now remove any candidates that are not
      suitable. Removing the capability will prevent the requirement from
      getting wired to the capability. If the Bundle Requirement is declared
      in a fragment then the host is not knowable.</para>

      <para>For example, a Handler wants to ensure that a set of bundles in a
      group are only wired to a limited set of infra-structure bundles and
      each other. This could be implemented as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>public class GroupHandler implements ResolverHook{
    Map&lt;Bundle,Set&lt;Bundle&gt;&gt; groups = ...;
    Set&lt;Bundle&gt; system = ... ;

    public void filterMatches( BundleRequirement r,
        Collection&lt;BundleCapability&gt; candidates ) {
        Set&lt;Bundle&gt; group = groups.get(r.getRevision().getBundle());
        if ( group == null )
            return; // not in a group

        for ( Iterator&lt;BundleCapability&gt; i = candidates.iterator();
            i.hasNext(); ) {
            BundleCapability candidate = i.next();
            Bundle other = candidate.getRevision().getBundle();

            if ( group.contains(other) || 
                system.contains(other) )
                continue;

            i.remove(); // not system, not in the same group
        }
    }

   ... other methods
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Effect of Singleton Capabilities</title>

      <para>Certain namespaces provide a <code>singleton</code> directive. For
      example, the <code>osgi.wiring.bundle</code> namespace defines that a
      bundle can be singleton, meaning that only one such bundle with a given
      symbolic name can be resolved. The purpose is to ensure that a bundle
      that needs exclusiveness gets this.</para>

      <para>In certain scenarios it is necessary to limit the singleton
      constraint to a group of bundles instead of the whole framework. One of
      the primary use cases of the Resolver Hooks is to allow scoping of
      bundles. Some Handlers can interpret the singleton constraints as to
      apply to the group, not the whole framework. For this purpose, the
      Resolver Hook API allows the Handler to influence which bundle revision
      is selected for the singleton with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterSingletonCollisions-BundleCapability-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

      <para>The first parameter is the capability that is under consideration
      by the resolver, called the <emphasis>viewpoint</emphasis> capability.
      The resolver needs to find out what other capabilities can
      <emphasis>collide</emphasis> with the viewpoint. A collision takes place
      when multiple bundles with the same symbolic name and singleton
      directive set to <code>true</code> can potentially be resolved at the
      same time. For example, a Handler implements a grouping model. A
      singleton is therefore only valid for the bundles in this group. A
      Handler must therefore be able to indicate which bundles can collide.
      This model is asymmetric. If a group has for example outer and inner
      bundles, then inner bundles can collide with outer bundles but not vice
      versa.</para>

      <para>The second parameters of the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterSingletonCollisions-BundleCapability-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is a set of capabilities called the
      <emphasis>candidates</emphasis>. The Handler can shrink this collection
      by removing capabilities. Removing a capability from the list of
      collision candidates will effectively hide the collision candidate from
      the target singleton bundle. This will allow the target singleton bundle
      to resolve regardless of the resolving state of the collision
      candidate.</para>

      <para>If <code>S</code> is the group of infrastructure bundles (acting
      as an outer bundles) and a non-infrastructure group is <code>A</code>,
      then the following cases exist:</para>

      <programlisting>S S     collide, leave in set
A A     collide, leave in set
A !A    remove from set, not visible
A S     collide, leave in set
S A     do not collide, remove from set</programlisting>

      <para>The following example implements this strategy:</para>

      <programlisting>public class GroupHandler implements ResolverHook{
    Map&lt;Bundle,Set&lt;Bundle&gt;&gt; groups = ...;

    public void filterSingletonCollisions( BundleCapability c,
        Collection&lt;BundleCapability&gt; candidates ) {
        Set&lt;Bundle&gt; group = groups.get(c.getRevision().getBundle());

        for ( Iterator&lt;BundleCapability&gt; i = candidates.iterator();
            i.hasNext(); ) {
            BundleCapability candidate = i.next();
            Bundle other = candidate.getRevision().getBundle();
            Set&lt;Bundle&gt; otherGroup = groups.get(other);

            if ( group == otherGroup || otherGroup == null ) // Samegroup
                continue;

            i.remove(); // not system, not in the same group
        }
    }

   ... other methods
}</programlisting>

      <para>The framework can call this method multiple times for the same
      singleton capability. For example, as a first pass a framework may want
      to determine if a singleton bundle is resolvable first based on the
      presence of other already resolved singleton capabilities. Later the
      framework may call this method again to determine which singleton
      capabilities from unresolved bundles to allow to resolve.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Resolve Operation</title>

    <para>The following steps outline the way a framework uses the resolver
    hooks during a resolve operation. Any callbacks to the hook services must
    be done in a privileged block, see <xref
    linkend="framework.lifecycle.privilegedcallbacks"/>.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Collect a snapshot of registered Resolver Hook Factory services
        that will be called during the current resolve operation. If a
        Resolver Hook Factory contained in the snapshot unregisters then the
        resolve must fail, see <xref linkend="i1703638"/>. Each registered
        Resolver Hook Factory service in the snapshot will be obtained by the
        framework through the system's bundle context.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For each Resolver Hook Factory in the snapshot, in ranking
        order, call the <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHookFactory.begin-Collection-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method to inform the Handler about the begin
        of a new resolve operation. This method must return a Resolver Hook.
        If this hook is not null, must be added to list <code>H</code>. If a
        corresponding Resolver Hook Factory service is unregistered then the
        Resolver Hook must be removed from <code>H</code>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Determine the collection of unresolved bundle revisions that may
        be considered for resolving during the current resolve operation and
        place each of the bundle revisions in a shrinkable collection
        <code>U(nresolved)</code>.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>For each active Resolver Hook in <code>H(ooks)</code>, call
            the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterResolvable-Collection-"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method with <code>U</code>. The Handler
            can remove any candidate that should not be resolved.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><code>U</code> now contains all the unresolved bundle revisions
        that potentially could be resolved during this resolve operation. Any
        bundle revisions that were removed by Handlers must not resolve in
        this operation.</para>

        <para>This step can be repeated multiple times interspersed with other
        calls except to the <code>begin</code> and <code>end</code>
        methods.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>S = {}</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For each bundle revision <code>B</code> in <code>U</code> that
        represents a singleton capability:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Determine the collection of available capabilities that have
            a namespace of <code>osgi.wiring.bundle</code>, are singletons,
            and have the same symbolic name as the singleton bundle revision
            <code>B</code> and place each of the matching capabilities into a
            shrinkable collection <code>S</code>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Remove the <code>osgi.wiring.bundle</code> capability
            provided by the bundle revision B from <code>S</code>. A singleton
            bundle cannot collide with itself.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For each resolver hook call the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterSingletonCollisions-BundleCapability-Collection-"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method with the
            <code>osgi.wiring.bundle</code> capability provided by bundle
            revision <code>B</code> and <code>S</code>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><code>S</code> now contains all the singleton
        <code>osgi.wiring.bundle</code> capabilities that can influence the
        ability of bundle revision <code>B</code> to resolve.</para>

        <para>This step can be repeated multiple times interspersed with other
        calls except to the <code>begin</code> and <code>end</code>
        methods.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>During a resolve operation the Resolver can resolve any or all
        bundles contained in <code>U</code>. For each bundle revision
        <code>B</code> in <code>U</code> which the Resolver attempts to
        resolve the following steps must be followed:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>For each requirement <code>R(equirement)</code> specified by
            bundle revision <code>B</code>, determine the collection of
            capabilities that satisfy the requirement <code>R</code> and place
            each matching capability into a shrinkable collection
            <code>C(apabilities)</code>. A capability is considered to satisfy
            a particular requirement if its attributes match the requirement's
            filter and the requirer bundle has permission to access the
            capability.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For each Resolver Hook in <code>H</code>, call the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.filterMatches-BundleRequirement-Collection-"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method with the Bundle Requirement
            <code>R</code> and the shrinkable collection
            <code>C</code>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><code>C</code> now contains all the capabilities that can be
        used to satisfy the requirement <code>R</code>. Any other capabilities
        that got removed from <code>C</code> must not be used to satisfy
        requirement R.</para>

        <para>This step can be repeated multiple times interspersed with other
        calls except <code>begin</code> and <code>end</code>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For each Resolver Hook in <code>H</code></para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Call the <code>end</code> method to inform the Handler about
            a resolve operation ending.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For each Resolve Hook still in <code>H</code>, ensure that the
        Resolver Hook is no longer referenced.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>In cases where the a shrinkable collection becomes empty the
    framework must continue calling the remaining hooks because these hooks
    can also be used to trace progress.</para>

    <para>The above steps are meant to illustrate how the Resolve Hooks are
    used by the Resolver, they are not normative. The nature of the resolve
    operation and the Resolver algorithm can require back tracking by the
    Resolver implementation. It is therefore acceptable for the Resolver to
    call the Resolver Hook multiple times with similar or identical parameters
    during a single resolve operation. This is true for all methods except the
    <code>begin</code> and <code>end</code> methods that are only called once
    during a resolve operation.</para>

    <para>A Resolver Hook must always return the same answer for the same set
    of inputs, that is, it must be <emphasis>stable</emphasis>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Resolver Hook Limitations</title>

      <para>Resolver hooks are system level components. Handlers must be
      careful not to create an unresolvable state which is very hard for a
      developer or a provisioner to diagnose. Resolver Hooks also must not be
      allowed to start another resolve operation, for example by starting a
      bundle or resolving bundles. The framework must detect this and throw an
      Illegal State Exception.</para>

      <para>In cases where a Bundle Exception can be thrown, such as the
      Bundle <code>start</code> method, the Illegal State Exception must be
      the cause of the Bundle Exception and the Bundle Exception must be of
      type <code>RESOLVE_ERROR</code>. In cases where an exception cannot be
      propagated to a caller, for example during dynamic import resolving, a
      Framework Event of type <code>ERROR</code> must be published.</para>

      <para>All hooks are treated as ordinary services, they can be used by
      the system bundle or other bundles.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1703638">
      <title>Failures</title>

      <para>If during the resolving anything goes wrong then the Resolver must
      abort the resolve operation, clean up and report an error.</para>

      <para>If the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHookFactory.begin-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method successfully returns a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, then the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method must be called on that hook if it is
      still valid (its <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHookFactory"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> is still registered) at the end of the Resolve.
      A <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> can therefore safely allocate resources in the
      <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHookFactory.begin-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method because it is guaranteed that it can
      deallocate them in the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.ResolverHook.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

      <para>The following are potential failures:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A Resolver Hook Factory used in a resolve operation is
          unregistered</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A Resolver Hook throws an exception.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the Resolver fails, it must throw a Bundle Exception to the
      caller if possible. Otherwise it must publish a Framework Event of type
      <code>ERROR</code>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>The Resolver Hook Factory service described in this specification is
    a highly complex facility that requires great care in their implementation
    to maintain the Framework invariants. It is therefore important that in a
    secure system the permission to register these hooks is only given to
    privileged bundles.</para>

    <para>In this case, the user of the Resolver Hook Factory service is the
    framework. Therefore, there is never a need to provide this service.
    Implementers of these hooks must have:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>ServicePermission[..ResolverHookFactory,REGISTER]</code>
        for Event Listener Hook services.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver.xml"/>
</chapter>
