<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="111"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="service.upnp"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Device Service Specification for UPnP™ Technology</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.upnp-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The UPnP Device Architecture specification provides the protocols
    for a peer-to-peer network. It specifies how to join a network and how
    devices can be controlled using XML messages sent over HTTP. The OSGi
    specifications address how code can be download and managed in a remote
    system. Both standards are therefore fully complimentary. Using an OSGi
    Framework to work with UPnP enabled devices is therefore a very successful
    combination.</para>

    <para>This specification specifies how OSGi bundles can be developed that
    interoperate with UPnP™ (Universal Plug and Play) devices and UPnP control
    points. The specification is based on the UPnP Device Architecture and
    does not further explain the UPnP specifications. The UPnP specifications
    are maintained by <xref linkend="i1586441"/>.</para>

    <para>UPnP™ is a trademark of the UPnP Implementers Corporation.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Scope - </emphasis>This specification is limited to
          device control aspects of the UPnP specifications. Aspects
          concerning the TCP/IP layer, like DHCP and limited TTL, are not
          addressed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Transparency</emphasis> - OSGi services should be
          made available to networks with UPnP enabled devices in a
          transparent way.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Network Selection</emphasis> - It must be possible
          to restrict the use of the UPnP protocols to a selection of the
          connected networks. For example, in certain cases OSGi services that
          are UPnP enabled should not be published to the Wide Area Network
          side of a gateway, nor should UPnP devices be detected on this
          WAN.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event handling</emphasis> - Bundles must be able to
          listen to UPnP events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Export OSGi services as UPnP devices</emphasis> -
          Enable bundles that make a service available to UPnP control
          points.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Implement UPnP Control Points</emphasis> - Enable
          bundles that control UPnP devices.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1527768">
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Base Driver</emphasis> - The bundle that
          implements the bridge between OSGi and UPnP networks. This entity is
          not represented as a service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Root Device</emphasis> -A physical device can
          contain one or more root devices. Root devices contain one ore more
          devices. A root device is modeled with a <code>UPnPDevice</code>
          object, there is no separate interface defined for root
          devices.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Device</emphasis> - The representation of a
          UPnP device. A UPnP device may contain other UPnP devices and UPnP
          services. This entity is represented by a <code>UPnPDevice</code>
          object. A device can be local (implemented in the Framework) or
          external (implemented by another device on the net).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Service</emphasis> -A UPnP device consists of a
          number of services. A UPnP service has a number of UPnP state
          variables that can be queried and modified with actions. This
          concept is represented by a <code>UPnPService</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Action</emphasis> - A UPnP service is
          associated with a number of actions that can be performed on that
          service and that may modify the UPnP state variables. This entity is
          represented by a <code>UPnPAction</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP State Variable</emphasis> - A variable
          associated with a UPnP service, represented by a
          <code>UPnPStateVariable</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Local State Variable</emphasis> - Extends the
          <code>UPnPStateVariable</code> interface when the state variable is
          implemented locally. This interface provides access to the actual
          value.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Event Listener Service</emphasis> - A listener
          to events coming from UPnP devices.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Host</emphasis> - The machine that hosts the
          code to run a UPnP device or control point.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Control Point</emphasis> - A UPnP device that
          is intended to control UPnP devices over a network. For example, a
          UPnP remote controller.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Icon</emphasis> - A representation class for an
          icon associated with a UPnP device.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UPnP Exception</emphasis> - An exception that
          delivers errors that were discovered in the UPnP layer.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>UDN</emphasis> - Unique Device Name, a name that
          uniquely identifies the a specific device.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure pgwide="1">
        <title>UPnP Service Specification class Diagram org.osgi.service.upnp
        package</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="4.243in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="upnp-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Operation Summary</title>

      <para>To make a UPnP service available to UPnP control points on a
      network, an OSGi service object must be registered under the
      <code>UPnPDevice</code> interface with the Framework. The UPnP driver
      bundle must detect these UPnP Device services and must make them
      available to the network as UPnP devices using the UPnP protocol.</para>

      <para>UPnP devices detected on the local network must be detected and
      automatically registered under the <code>UPnPDevice</code> interface
      with the Framework by the UPnP driver implementation bundle.</para>

      <para>A bundle that wants to control UPnP devices, for example to
      implement a UPnP control point, should track UPnP Device services in the
      OSGi service registry and control them appropriately. Such bundles
      should not distinguish between resident or remote UPnP Device
      services.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>UPnP Specifications</title>

    <para>The UPnP DA is intended to be used in a broad range of device from
    the computing (PCs printers), consumer electronics (DVD, TV, radio),
    communication (phones) to home automation (lighting control, security) and
    home appliances (refrigerators, coffee makers) domains.</para>

    <para>For example, a UPnP TV might announce its existence on a network by
    broadcasting a message. A UPnP control point on that network can then
    discover this TV by listening to those announce messages. The UPnP
    specifications allow the control point to retrieve information about the
    user interface of the TV. This information can then be used to allow the
    end user to control the remote TV from the control point, for example turn
    it on or change the channels.</para>

    <para>The UPnP specification supports the following features:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Detect and control a UPnP standardized
        device</emphasis>. In this case the control point and the remote
        device share a priori knowledge about how the device should be
        controlled. The UPnP Forum intends to define a large number of these
        standardized devices.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Use a user interface description</emphasis>. A UPnP
        control point receives enough information about a device and its
        services to automatically build a user interface for it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Programmatic Control</emphasis>. A program can
        directly control a UPnP device without a user interface. This control
        can be based on detected information about the device or through a
        priori knowledge of the device type.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Allows the user to browse a web page supplied by the
        device</emphasis>. This web page contains a user interface for the
        device that be directly manipulated by the user. However, this option
        is not well defined in the UPnP Device Architecture specification and
        is not tested for compliance.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The UPnP Device Architecture specification and the OSGi Framework
    provide <emphasis>complementary</emphasis> functionality. The UPnP Device
    Architecture specification is a data communication protocol that does not
    specify where and how programs execute. That choice is made by the
    implementations. In contrast, the OSGi Framework specifies a (managed)
    execution point and does not define what protocols or media are supported.
    The UPnP specification and the OSGi specifications are fully complementary
    and do not overlap.</para>

    <para>From the OSGi perspective, the UPnP specification is a communication
    protocol that can be implemented by one or more bundles. This
    specification therefore defines the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>How an OSGi bundle can implement a service that is exported to
        the network via the UPnP protocols.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>How to find and control services that are available on the local
        network.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The UPnP specifications related to the assignment of IP addresses to
    new devices on the network or auto-IP self configuration should be handled
    at the operating system level. Such functions are outside the scope of
    this specification.</para>

    <section>
      <title>UPnP Base Driver</title>

      <para>The functionality of the UPnP service is implemented in a UPnP
      <emphasis>base driver</emphasis>. This is a bundle that implements the
      UPnP protocols and handles the interaction with bundles that use the
      UPnP devices. A UPnP base driver bundle must provide the following
      functions:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Discover UPnP devices on the network and map each discovered
          device into an OSGi registered UPnP Device service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Present UPnP marked services that are registered with the OSGi
          Framework on one or more networks to be used by other
          computers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>UPnP Device</title>

    <para xml:id="i1365305">The principle entity of the UPnP specification is
    the UPnP device. There is a UPnP <emphasis>root device</emphasis> that
    represents a physical appliance, such as a complete TV. The root device
    contains a number of sub-devices. These might be the tuner, the monitor,
    and the sound system. Each sub-device is further composed of a number of
    UPnP services. A UPnP service represents some functional unit in a device.
    For example, in a TV tuner it can represent the TV channel selector. <xref
    linkend="i1264660" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/> illustrates
    this hierarchy.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1264660">
      <title>UPnP device hierarchy</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.134in"
                     contentwidth="4.850in" fileref="device-hierarchy.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Each UPnP service can be manipulated with a number of UPnP actions.
    UPnP actions can modify the state of a UPnP state variable that is
    associated with a service. For example, in a TV there might be a state
    variable <emphasis>volume</emphasis>. There are then actions to set the
    volume, to increase the volume, and to decrease the volume.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Root Device</title>

      <para>The UPnP root device is registered as a UPnP Device service with
      the Framework, as well as all its sub-devices. Most applications will
      work with sub-devices, and, as a result, the children of the root device
      are registered under the <code>UPnPDevice</code> interface.</para>

      <para>UPnP device properties are defined per sub-device in the UPnP
      specification. These properties must be registered with the OSGi
      Framework service registry so they are searchable.</para>

      <para>Bundles that want to handle the UPnP device hierarchy can use the
      registered service properties to find the parent of a device (which is
      another registered <code>UPnPDevice</code>).</para>

      <para>The following service registration properties can be used to
      discover this hierarchy:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.PARENT_UDN"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>String</code>) The Universal Device
          Name (UDN) of the parent device. A root device most not have this
          property registered. Type is a <code>String</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.CHILDREN_UDN"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - <code>(String[])</code> An array of UDNs
          of this device's children.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Exported Versus Imported Devices</title>

      <para>Both imported (from the network to the OSGi service registry) and
      exported (from the service registry to the network)
      <code>UPnPDevice</code> services must have the same representation in
      the OSGi Framework for identical devices. For example, if an OSGi UPnP
      Device service is exported as a UPnP device from an OSGi Framework to
      the network, and it is imported into another OSGi Framework, the object
      representation should be equal. Application bundles should therefore be
      able to interact with imported and exported forms of the UPnP device in
      the same manner.</para>

      <para>Imported and exported UPnP devices differ only by two marker
      properties that can be added to the service registration. One marker,
      <code>DEVICE_CATEGORY</code>, should typically be set only on imported
      devices. By not setting <code>DEVICE_CATEGORY</code> on internal UPnP
      devices, the Device Manager does not try to refine these devices (See
      the <xref linkend="service.device"/> for more information about the
      Device Manager). If the device service does not implement the
      <code>Device</code> interface and does not have the
      <code>DEVICE_CATEGORY</code> property set, it is not considered a
      <emphasis>device</emphasis> according to the Device Access
      Specification.</para>

      <para>The other marker, <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.UPNP_EXPORT"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, should only be set on internally created
      devices that the bundle developer wants to export. By not setting <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.UPNP_EXPORT"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> on registered UPnP Device services, the UPnP
      Device service can be used by internally created devices that should not
      be exported to the network. This allows UPnP devices to be simulated
      within an OSGi Framework without announcing all of these devices to any
      networks.</para>

      <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.UPNP_EXPORT"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service property has no defined type, any value
      is correct.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Icons</title>

      <para>A UPnP device can optionally support an icon. The purpose of this
      icon is to identify the device on a UPnP control point. UPnP control
      points can be implemented in large computers like PC's or simple devices
      like a remote control. However, the graphic requirements for these UPnP
      devices differ tremendously. The device can, therefore, export a number
      of icons of different size and depth.</para>

      <para>In the UPnP specifications, an icon is represented by a URL that
      typically refers to the device itself. In this specification, a list of
      icons is available from the UPnP Device service.</para>

      <para>In order to obtain localized icons, the method <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.getIcons-String-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> can be used to obtain different versions. If the
      locale specified is a <code>null</code> argument, then the call returns
      the icons of the default locale of the called device (not the default
      locale of the UPnP control point).When a bundle wants to access the icon
      of an imported UPnP device, the UPnP driver gets the data and presents
      it to the application through an input stream.</para>

      <para>A bundle that needs to export a UPnP Device service with one or
      more icons must provide an implementation of the <code>UPnPIcon</code>
      interface. This implementation must provide an <code>InputStream</code>
      object to the actual icon data. The UPnP driver bundle must then
      register this icon with an HTTP server and include the URL to the icon
      with the UPnP device data at the appropriate place.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Device Category</title>

    <para>UPnP Device services are devices in the context of the Device
    Manager. This means that these services need to register with a number of
    properties to participate in driver refinement. The value for UPnP devices
    is defined in the <code>UPnPDevice</code> constant <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.DEVICE_CATEGORY"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The value is <code>UPnP</code>. The
    <code>UPnPDevice</code> interface contains a number of constants for
    matching values. Refer to <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.MATCH_GENERIC"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> for further information.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1527770">
    <title>UPnPService</title>

    <para>A UPnP Device contains a number of <code>UPnPService</code> objects.
    <code>UPnPService</code> objects combine zero or more actions and one or
    more state variables.</para>

    <section xml:id="i1487511">
      <title>State Variables</title>

      <para>The <code>UPnPStateVariable</code> interface encapsulates the
      properties of a UPnP state variable. In addition to the properties
      defined by the UPnP specification, a state variable is also mapped to a
      Java data type. The Java data type is used when an event is generated
      for this state variable and when an action is performed containing
      arguments related to this state variable. There must be a strict
      correspondence between the UPnP data type and the Java data type so that
      bundles using a particular UPnP device profile can predict the precise
      Java data type.</para>

      <para>The function <code>QueryStateVariable</code> defined in the UPnP
      specification has been deprecated and is therefore not implemented. It
      is recommended to use the UPnP event mechanism to track UPnP state
      variables.</para>

      <para>Additionally, a <code>UPnPStateVariable</code>object can also
      implement the <code>UPnPLocalStateVariable</code> interface if the
      device is implemented locally. That is, the device is not imported from
      the network. The <code>UPnPLocalStateVariable</code> interface provides
      a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPLocalStateVariable.getCurrentValue--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method that provides direct access to the actual
      value of the state variable.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Working With a UPnP Device</title>

    <para>The UPnP driver must register all discovered UPnP devices in the
    local networks. These devices are registered under a
    <code>UPnPDevice</code> interface with the OSGi Framework.</para>

    <para>Using a remote UPnP device thus involves tracking UPnP Device
    services in the OSGi service registry. The following code illustrates how
    this can be done. The sample <code>Controller</code> class extends the
    <code>ServiceTracker</code> class so that it can track all UPnP Device
    services and add them to a user interface, such as a remote controller
    application.</para>

    <programlisting>class Controller extends ServiceTracker {
    UI ui;
    
    Controller( BundleContext context ) {
        super( context, UPnPDevice.class.getName(), null );
    }
    public Object addingService( ServiceReference ref ) {
        UPnPDevice dev = (UPnPDevice)super.addingService(ref);
        ui.addDevice( dev ); 
        return dev;
    }
    public void removedService( ServiceReference ref,
        Object dev ) {
        ui.removeDevice( (UPnPDevice) dev );
    }
    ...
}</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Implementing a UPnP Device</title>

    <para>OSGi services can also be exported as UPnP devices to the local
    networks, in a way that is transparent to typical UPnP devices. This
    allows developers to bridge legacy devices to UPnP networks. A bundle
    should perform the following to export an OSGi service as a UPnP
    device:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Register an UPnP Device service with the registration property
        <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.UPNP_EXPORT"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Use the registration property <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.PRESENTATION_URL"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> to provide the presentation page. The service
        implementer must register its own servlet with the Http Service to
        serve out this interface. This URL must point to that servlet.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>There can be multiple UPnP root devices hosted by one OSGi platform.
    The relationship between the UPnP devices and the OSGi platform is defined
    by the <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.PARENT_UDN"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.CHILDREN_UDN"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service properties. The bundle registering those
    device services must make sure these properties are set
    accordingly.</para>

    <para>Devices that are implemented on the OSGi Framework (in contrast with
    devices that are imported from the network) should use the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPLocalStateVariable"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface for their state variables instead of the
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPStateVariable"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface. This interface provides programmatic
    access to the actual value of the state variable as maintained by the
    device specific code.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1527771">
    <title>Event API</title>

    <para>There are two distinct event directions for the UPnP Service
    specification.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>External events from the network must be dispatched to listeners
        inside the OSGi Frameworks. The UPnP Base driver is responsible for
        mapping the network events to internal listener events.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Implementations of UPnP devices must send out events to local
        listeners as well as cause the transmission of the UPnP network
        events.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>UPnP events are sent using the whiteboard model, in which a bundle
    interested in receiving the UPnP events registers an object implementing
    the <code>UPnPEventListener</code> interface. A filter can be set to limit
    the events for which a bundle is notified. The UPnP Base driver must
    register a UPnP Event Lister without filter that receives all
    events.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Event Dispatching for Local and External Devices</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.697in"
                     contentwidth="4.102in" fileref="event-dispatching.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If a service is registered with a property named
    <code>upnp.filter</code> with the value of an instance of an
    <code>Filter</code> object, the listener is only notified for matching
    events (This is a <code>Filter</code> object and not a <code>String</code>
    object because it allows the <code>InvalidSyntaxException</code> to be
    thrown in the client and not the UPnP driver bundle).</para>

    <para>The filter might refer to any valid combination of the following
    pseudo properties for event filtering:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>UPnPDevice.</code><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.UDN" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        - (<code>UPnP.device.UDN/String</code>) Only events generated by
        services contained in the specific device are delivered. For example:
        <code>(UPnP.device.UDN=uuid:Upnp-TVEmulator-1_0-1234567890001)</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>UPnPDevice.</code><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.TYPE"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>UPnP.device.type/String or
        String[]</code>) Only events generated by services contained in a
        device of the given type are delivered. For example:
        <code>(UPnP.device.type=urn:schemas-upnp-org:device:tvdevice:1)</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>UPnPService.</code><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPService.ID" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        - (<code>UPnP.service.id/String</code>) Service identity. Only events
        generated by services matching the given service ID are
        delivered.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>UPnPService.</code><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPService.TYPE"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>UPnP.service.type/String or
        String[]</code>) Only events generated by services of the given type
        are delivered.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If an event is generated by either a local device or via the base
    driver for an external device, the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPEventListener.notifyUPnPEvent-String-String-Dictionary-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is called on all registered <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPEventListener" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
    services for which the optional filter matches for that event. If no
    filter is specified, all events must be delivered. If the filter does not
    match, the UPnP Driver must not call the UPnP Event Listener service. The
    way events must be delivered is the same as described in
    <emphasis>Delivering Events</emphasis> of <xref
    linkend="intro.core.release" xrefstyle="template:%t"/>.</para>

    <para>One or multiple events are passed as parameters to the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPEventListener.notifyUPnPEvent-String-String-Dictionary-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The <code>Dictionary</code> object holds a
    pair of <code>UpnPStateVariable</code> objects that triggered the event
    and an Object for the new value of the state variable.</para>

    <section xml:id="i1527773">
      <title>Initial Event Delivery</title>

      <para>Special care must be taken with the initial subscription to
      events. According to the UPnP specification, when a client subscribes
      for notification of events for the first time, the device sends out a
      number of events for each state variable, indicating the current value
      of each state variable. This behavior simplifies the synchronization of
      a device and an event-driven client.</para>

      <para>The UPnP Base Driver must mimic this event distribution on behalf
      of external devices. It must therefore remember the values of the state
      variables of external devices. A UPnP Device implementation must send
      out these initial events for each state variable they have a value
      for.</para>

      <para>The UPnP Base Driver must have stored the last event from the
      device and retransmit the value over the multicast network. The UPnP
      Driver must register an event listener without any filter for this
      purpose.</para>

      <para>The call to the listener's notification method must be done
      asynchronously.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1527772">
    <title>UPnP Events and Event Admin service</title>

    <para>UPnP events must be delivered asynchronously to the Event Admin
    service by the UPnP implementation, if present. UPnP events have the
    following topic:</para>

    <programlisting>org/osgi/service/upnp/UPnPEvent</programlisting>

    <para>The properties of a UPnP event are the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>upnp.deviceId</code> - (<code>String</code>) The identity
        as defined by <code>UPnPDevice.</code><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.UDN" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        of the device sending the event.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>upnp.serviceId</code> - (<code>String)</code> The identity
        of the service sending the events.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>upnp.events - (Dictionary)</code> A
        <code>Dictionary</code> object containing the new values for the state
        variables that have changed.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Localization</title>

    <para>All values of the UPnP properties are obtained from the device using
    the device's default locale. If an application wants to query a set of
    localized property values, it has to use the method <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.getDescriptions-String-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. For localized versions of the icons, the method
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPDevice.getIcons-String-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> is to be used.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Dates and Times</title>

    <para>The UPnP specification uses different types for date and time
    concepts. An overview of these types is given in the following
    table.</para>

    <table>
      <title>Mapping UPnP Date/Time types to Java</title>

      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1.5*"/>

        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

        <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="3*"/>

        <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="3.5*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>UPnP Type</entry>

            <entry>Class</entry>

            <entry>Example</entry>

            <entry>Value (TZ=CEST=UTC+0200)</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><code>date</code></entry>

            <entry><code>Date</code></entry>

            <entry><code>1985-04-12</code></entry>

            <entry><code>Sun April 12 00:00:00 CEST 1985</code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>dateTime</code></entry>

            <entry><code>Date</code></entry>

            <entry><code>1985-04-12T10:15:30</code></entry>

            <entry><code>Sun April 12 10:15:30 CEST 1985</code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>dateTime.tz</code></entry>

            <entry><code>Date</code></entry>

            <entry><code>1985-04-12T10:15:30+0400</code></entry>

            <entry><code>Sun April 12 08:15:30 CEST 1985</code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>time</code></entry>

            <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

            <entry><code>23:20:50</code></entry>

            <entry><code>84.050.000 (ms)</code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>time.tz</code></entry>

            <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

            <entry><code>23:20:50+0100</code></entry>

            <entry><code>1.250.000 (ms)</code></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The UPnP specification points to <xref linkend="i1325817"/>. In this
    standard, <xref linkend="i1325829"/> are referenced. The mapping is not
    completely defined which means that this OSGi UPnP specification defines a
    complete mapping to Java classes. The UPnP types <code>date</code>,
    <code>dateTime</code> and <code>dateTime.tz</code> are represented as a
    <code>Date</code> object. For the <code>date</code> type, the hours,
    minutes and seconds must all be zero.</para>

    <para>The UPnP types <code>time</code> and <code>time.tz</code> are
    represented as a <code>Long</code> object that represents the number of ms
    since midnight. If the time wraps to the next day due to a time zone
    value, then the final value must be truncated modulo 86.400.000.</para>

    <para>See also <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPStateVariable.TYPE_DATE"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>UPnP Exception</title>

    <para>The UPnP Exception can be thrown when a <code>UPnPAction</code> is
    invoked. This exception contains information about the different UPnP
    layers. The following errors are defined:</para>

    <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPException.INVALID_ACTION"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>401</code>) No such action could be
    found.</para>

    <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPException.INVALID_ARGS"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>402</code>) Invalid argument.</para>

    <para><xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPException.INVALID_SEQUENCE_NUMBER"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>403</code>) Out of
    synchronization.</para>

    <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPException.INVALID_VARIABLE"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>404</code>) State variable not
    found.</para>

    <para><xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.upnp.UPnPException.DEVICE_INTERNAL_ERROR"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>501</code>) Internal error.</para>

    <para>Further errors are categorized as follows:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Common Action Errors</emphasis> - In the range of
        <code>600-69</code>, defined by the UPnP Forum Technical
        Committee.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Action Specific Errors</emphasis> - In the range of
        700-799, defined by the UPnP Forum Working Committee.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Non-Standard Action Specific Errors</emphasis> - In
        the range of 800-899. Defined by vendors.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>

    <para>In order to provide a standardized way to configure a UPnP driver
    bundle, the Configuration Admin property <code>upnp.ssdp.address</code> is
    defined.</para>

    <para>The value is a <code>String[]</code> with a list of IP addresses,
    optionally followed with a colon (<code>':' \u003A</code>) and a port
    number. For example:</para>

    <programlisting>239.255.255.250:1900</programlisting>

    <para>Those addresses define the interfaces which the UPnP driver is
    operating on. If no SSDP address is specified, the default assumed will be
    239.255.255.250:1900. If no port is specified, port 1900 is assumed as
    default.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Networking considerations</title>

    <section>
      <title>The UPnP Multicasts</title>

      <para>The operating system must support multicasting on the selected
      network device. In certain cases, a multicasting route has to be set in
      the operating system routing table.</para>

      <para>These configurations are highly dependent on the underlying
      operating system and beyond the scope of this specification.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>The UPnP specification is based on HTTP and uses plain text SOAP
    (XML) messages to control devices. For this reason, it does not provide
    any inherent security mechanisms. However, the UPnP specification is based
    on the exchange of XML files and not code. This means that at least worms
    and viruses cannot be implemented using the UPnP protocols.</para>

    <para>However, a bundle registering a UPnP Device service is represented
    on the outside network and has the ability to communicate. The same is
    true for getting a UPnP Device service. It is therefore recommended that
    <code>ServicePermission[UPnPDevice|UPnPEventListener, REGISTER|GET]</code>
    be used sparingly and only for bundles that are trusted.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.upnp.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1586441"><title>UPnP
      Forum</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.upnp.org"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1325817"><title>XML
      Schema</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1325829"><title>ISO 8601 Date And Time
      formats</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.iso.ch"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
