<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="130"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="service.coordinator"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Coordinator Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.coordinator-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The OSGi programming model is based on the collaboration of standard
    and custom components. In such a model there is no central authority that
    has global knowledge of the complete application. Though this lack of
    authority can significantly increase reusability (and robustness) there
    are times when the activities of the collaborators must be coordinated.
    For example, a service that is repeatedly called in a task could optimize
    performance by caching intermediate results until it
    <emphasis>knew</emphasis> the task was ended.</para>

    <para>To know when a task involving multiple collaborators has ended is
    the primary purpose of the Coordinator service specification. The
    Coordinator service provides a rendezvous for an initiator to create a
    Coordination where collaborators can decide to participate. When the
    Coordination has ended, all participants are informed.</para>

    <para>This Coordinator service provides an explicit Coordination model,
    the Coordination is explicitly passed as a parameter, and an implicit
    model where the Coordination is associated with the current thread.
    Implicit Coordinations can be nested.</para>

    <para>Coordinators share the coordination aspects of the resource model of
    transactions. However, the model is much lighter-weight because it does
    not support any of the ACID properties.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Coordination</emphasis> - Provide a solution to
          allow multiple collaborators to coordinate the outcome of a task
          initiated by an initiator.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Initiator</emphasis> - An initiator must be able to
          initiate a coordination and control the final outcome.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Participants</emphasis> - Participants in the task
          must be informed when the coordination has ended or failed as well
          as being able to terminate the Coordination.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Time-out</emphasis> - A Coordination should fail
          after a given time-out.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Blocking</emphasis> - Provide support for blocking
          and serializing access to Participants.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Nesting</emphasis> - It must be possible to nest
          Coordinations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Per Thread Model</emphasis> - Provide a per-thread
          current Coordination model.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Variables</emphasis> - Provide a variable space per
          Coordination</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Coordinator</emphasis> - A service that can create
          and enumerate Coordinations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Coordination</emphasis> - Represents the ongoing
          Coordination.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Initiator</emphasis> - The party that initiates a
          Coordination.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Participant</emphasis> - A party that wants to be
          informed of the outcome of a Coordination.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Collaborator</emphasis> - Either a participant or
          initiator.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Class and Service overview</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.100in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in"
                       fileref="coordinator-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>This section is an introduction in the usage of the Coordinator
    service. It is not the formal specification, the normative part starts at
    <xref linkend="i3151714"/>. This section leaves out some of the details
    for clarity.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>The Coordinator service provides a mechanism for multiple parties
      to <emphasis>collaborate</emphasis> on a common task without a priori
      knowledge of who will collaborate in that task. A collaborator can
      participate by adding a <emphasis>Participant</emphasis> to the
      Coordination. The Coordination will notify the Participants when the
      coordination is <emphasis>ended</emphasis> or when it is
      <emphasis>failed</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Each Coordination has an <emphasis>initiator</emphasis> that
      creates the <code>Coordination</code> object through the Coordinator
      service. The initiator can then push this object on a thread-local stack
      to make it an implicit Coordination or it can pass this object around as
      a parameter for <emphasis>explicit</emphasis> Coordinations.
      Collaborators can then use the <emphasis>current</emphasis> Coordination
      on the stack or get it from a parameter. Whenever a bundle wants to
      participate in the Coordination it adds itself to the Coordination as a
      participant. If necessary, a collaborator can initiate a new
      Coordination, which could be a nested Coordination for implicit
      Coordinations.</para>

      <para>A Coordination must be <emphasis>terminated</emphasis>.
      Termination is either a normal end when the initiator calls the
      <code>end</code> method or it is failed when the <code>fail</code>
      method is called. A Coordination can be failed by any of the
      collaborators. A Coordination can also fail independently due to a
      <emphasis>time-out</emphasis> or when the initiator releases its
      Coordinator service. All participants in the Coordination are informed
      in reverse participation order about the outcome in a callback for ended
      or failed Coordinations.</para>

      <para>A typical action diagram with a successful outcome is depicted in
      <xref linkend="service.coordinator-coordination-action"/>.</para>

      <figure xml:id="service.coordinator-coordination-action">
        <title>Action Diagram Implicit Coordination</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.700in"
                       contentwidth="6.241in"
                       fileref="coordination-action.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Explicit Coordination</title>

      <para>The general pattern for an initiator is to create a Coordination
      through the Coordinator service, perform the work in a try block, catch
      any exceptions and fail the Coordination in the catch block, and then
      ensure ending the Coordination in the finally block. The finally block
      can cause an exception. This is demonstrated in the following
      example:</para>

      <programlisting>Coordination c = coordinator.create("com.example.work",0);
try {
    doWork(c);
} catch( Exception e ) { 
    c.fail(e); 
} finally { 
    c.end();   
}</programlisting>

      <para>This deceptively small template is quite robust:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the <code>doWork</code> method throws an Exception then the
          template fails with a Coordination Exception because it is failed in
          the try block.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any exceptions thrown in the try block are automatically
          causing the Coordination to fail.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Coordination is always terminated and removed from the
          stack due to the finally block.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All failure paths, Coordinations that are failed by any of the
          collaborators, time-outs, or other problems are handled by the
          <code>end</code> method in the finally block. It will throw a <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.FAILED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.PARTIALLY_ENDED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception for any of the
          failures.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The different failure paths and their handling is pictured in
      <xref linkend="i3187111"/>.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i3187111">
        <title>Flow through the Coordination template</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.615in"
                       contentwidth="6.222in" fileref="coordination-flow.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The example shows an explicit Coordination because the
      <code>create</code> method is used, implicit Coordinations are used in
      <xref linkend="i3175342"/>. The parameters of the <code>create</code>
      method are the name of the Coordination and its time-out. The name is
      used for informational purposes as well as security. For security
      reasons, the name must follow the same syntax as the Bundle Symbolic
      Name. In a secure environment the name can be used to limit
      Coordinations to a limited set of bundles. For example, a set of bundles
      signed by a specific signer can use names like <code>com.acme.*</code>
      that are denied to all other bundles.</para>

      <para>The zero time-out specifies that the Coordination will not have a
      time-out. Otherwise it must be a positive long, indicating the number of
      milliseconds the Coordination may take. However, implementations should
      have a configurable time-out to ensure that the system remains
      alive.</para>

      <para>In the <code>doWork</code> method the real work is done in
      conjunction with the collaborators. Explicit Coordinations can be passed
      to other threads if needed. Collaborators can decide to add participants
      whenever they require a notification when the Coordination has been
      terminated. For example, the following code could be called from the
      <code>doWork</code> method:</para>

      <programlisting>void foo(Coordination c) {
  doPrepare();
  c.addParticipant(this);
}</programlisting>

      <para>This method does the preparation work but does not finalize it so
      that next time it can use some intermediate results. For example, the
      <code>prepare</code> method could cache a connection to a database that
      should be reused during the Coordination. The collaborator can assume
      that it will be called back on either the <code>failed</code> or
      <code>ended</code> method. These methods could look like:</para>

      <programlisting>public void ended(Coordination c)  { doFinish(); }
public void failed(Coordination c) { doFailed(); }</programlisting>

      <para>The Coordinator provides the guarantee that this code will always
      call the <code>doFinish</code> method when the Coordination succeeds and
      <code>doFailed</code> method when it failed.</para>

      <para>The Participant must be aware that the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Participant.ended-Coordination-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Participant.failed-Coordination-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods can be called on any thread.</para>

      <para>If the <code>doWork</code> method throws an exception it will end
      up in the catch block of the initiator. The catch block will then fail
      the Coordination by calling the <code>fail</code> method with the given
      exception. If the Coordination was already terminated because something
      else already had failed it then the method call is ignored, only the
      first fail is used, later fails are ignored.</para>

      <para>In all cases, the finally block is executed last. The finally
      block ends the Coordination. If this coordination was failed then it
      will throw a Coordination Exception detailing the reason of the failure.
      Otherwise it will terminate it and notify all the participants.</para>

      <para>The Coordination Exception is a Runtime Exception making it
      unnecessary to declare it.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Multi Threading</title>

      <para>Explicit Coordinations allow the Coordination objects to be passed
      to many different collaborators who can perform the work on different
      threads. Each collaborator can fail the Coordination at any moment in
      time or the time-out can occur on yet another thread. Participants must
      therefore be aware that the callbacks <code>ended</code> and
      <code>failed</code> can happen on any thread. The following example
      shows a typical case where a task is parallelized. If any thread fails
      the Coordination, all other threads could be notified before they're
      finished.</para>

      <programlisting>Executor executor = ...
final CountDownLatch latch = new CountdownLatch(10);
final Coordination c = coordinator.create("parallel", 0); 
for ( int i=0; i&lt;10; i++) {
  executor.execute(
    new Runnable() {
        public void run() { baz(c); latch.countDown(); }
      });
  }
  latch.await();
  c.end();</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>Coordination</code> object is thread safe so it can be
      freely passed around.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3175342">
      <title>Implicit Coordinations</title>

      <para>An explicit Coordination requires that the Coordination is passed
      as a parameter to the <code>doWork</code> method. The Coordinator also
      supports <emphasis>implicit</emphasis> Coordinations. With implicit
      Coordinations the Coordinator maintains a thread local stack of
      Coordinations where the top of this stack is the
      <emphasis>current</emphasis> Coordination for that thread. The usage of
      the implicit Coordination is almost identical to the explicit
      Coordinations except that all the work occurs on a single thread. The
      control flow is almost identical to explicit Coordinations:</para>

      <programlisting>Coordination c = coordinator.begin("com.example.work",0);
try {
    doWork();
} catch( Exception e ) { 
    c.fail(e); 
} finally { 
    c.end();   
}</programlisting>

      <para>See also <xref linkend="i3187111"/>. However, in this case the
      finally block with the call to the end method is even more important.
      With an implicit Coordination the Coordination is put on a thread local
      stack in the <code>begin</code> method and must therefore be popped when
      the Coordination is finished. The finally block ensures therefore the
      proper cleanup of this thread local stack.</para>

      <para>The difference between implicit and explicit Coordinations is that
      the implicit Coordination is not passed as a parameter, instead,
      collaborators use the current Coordination. With implicit Coordinations
      all method invocations in a thread can always access the current
      Coordination, even if they have many intermediates on the stack. The
      implicit model allows a collaborator many levels down the stack to
      detect a current Coordination and register itself without the need to
      modify all intermediate methods to contain a Coordination parameter. The
      explicit model has the advantage of explicitness but requires all APIs
      to be modified to hold the parameter. This model does not support
      passing the parameter through layers that are not aware of the
      Coordination. For example, OSGi services in general do not have a
      Coordination parameter in their methods making the use of explicit
      Coordinations impossible.</para>

      <para>Collaborators can act differently in the presence of a current
      Coordination. For example, a collaborator can optimize its work flow
      depending on the presence of a current Coordination.</para>

      <programlisting>Coordinator coordinator = ...
void foo() {
  doPrepare();
  if ( !coordinator.addParticipant(this))
      doFinish();
}</programlisting>

      <para>The Coordinator service has an <code>addParticipant</code> method
      that makes working with the current Coordination simple. If there is a
      current Coordination then the Coordinator service will add the
      participant and return <code>true</code>, otherwise it returns
      <code>false</code>. It is therefore easy to react differently in the
      presence of a current Coordination. In the previous example, the
      <code>doFinish</code> method will be called immediately if there was no
      current Coordination, otherwise it is delayed until the Coordination
      fails or succeeds. The participant callbacks look the same as in the
      previous section:</para>

      <programlisting>public void ended(Coordination c)  { doFinish(); }
public void failed(Coordination c) { doFailed(); }</programlisting>

      <para>Though the code looks very similar for the implicit and explicit
      Coordinations there are some additional rules for implicit
      Coordinations.</para>

      <para>The <code>end</code> method must be called on the same thread as
      the <code>begin</code> method, trying to end it on another thread
      results in a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.WRONG_THREAD"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception being thrown.</para>

      <para>Even though the <code>end</code> method must be called on the
      initiating thread, the callbacks to the Participants can be done on any
      thread as the specification allows the Coordinator to use multiple
      threads for all callbacks.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Partial Ending</title>

      <para>The Coordination is a best effort mechanism to coordinate, not a
      transaction model with integrity guarantees. This means that users of
      the Coordinator service must understand that there are cases where a
      Coordination ends in limbo. This happens when one of the Participants
      throws an Exception in the <code>ended</code> callback. This is similar
      to a transactional resource manager failing to commit in a 2-phase
      commit after it has voted yes in the prepare phase; a problem that is
      the cause of much of the complexity of a transaction manager. The
      Coordinator is limited to use cases that do not require full ACID
      properties and can therefore be much simpler. However, users of the
      Coordinator service must be aware of this limitation.</para>

      <para>If a Participant throws an exception in the ended method, the end
      method that terminated the Coordination must throw a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.PARTIALLY_ENDED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception. It is then up to the
      initiator to correct the situations. In most cases, this means allowing
      the exception to be re-thrown and handle the failure at the top level.
      Handling in those cases usually implies logging and continuing.</para>

      <para>The following code shows how the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.PARTIALLY_ENDED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> case can be handled more explicitly.</para>

      <programlisting>Coordination c = coordinator.begin("work",0);
try {
  doWork();
} catch( Excption e ) {
  c.fail(e);
} finally {
  try {
    c.end();
  } catch( CoordinationException e ) {
    if ( e.getType() == CoordinationException.PARTIALLY_ENDED) {
      // limbo!
      ...
    }
  }
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Locking</title>

      <para>To participate in a Coordination and receive callbacks a
      collaborator must add a <code>Participant</code> object to the
      Coordination. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.addParticipant-Participant-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method blocks if the given
      <code>Participant</code> object is already used in another Coordination.
      This blocking facility can be used to implement a number of simple
      locking schemes that can simplify maintaining state in a concurrent
      environment.</para>

      <para>Using the <code>Participant</code> object as the key for the lock
      makes it simple to do course grained locking. For example, a service
      implementation could use the service object as a lock, effectively
      serializing access to this service when it is used in a Coordination.
      Coarse grained locking allows all the state to be maintained in the
      coarse object and not having to worry about multiplexing simultaneous
      requests. The following code uses the coarse locking pattern because the
      collaborator implements the <code>Participant</code> interface
      itself:</para>

      <programlisting>public class Collaborator implements Participant{
  public void doWork(Coordination coordination ) {
    ...
    coordination.addParticipant(this);
  }

  public void ended(Coordination c) { ... }
  public void failed(Coordination c) { ... }
}</programlisting>

      <para>The simplicity of the coarse grained locking is at the expense of
      lower performance because tasks are serialized even if it would have no
      contention. Locks can therefore also be made more fine grained, allowing
      more concurrency. In the extreme case, creating a new object for each
      participation makes it possible to never lock. For example, the
      following code never locks because it always creates a new object for
      the Participant:</para>

      <programlisting>    public void doWork(Coordination coordination){
      final State state = ...
      coordination.addParticipant(
         new Participant() {
           public void ended(Coordination c) { state ... }
           public void failed(Coordination c) { state ...}
    } ); }</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Failing</title>

      <para>Any collaborator can fail an ongoing Coordination by calling the
      <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.fail-Throwable-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, the Throwable parameter must not be
      <code>null</code>. When the Coordination has already terminated then
      this is a no-op. The Coordinator service has a convenience method that
      fails the current Coordination if present. The <code>fail</code> methods
      return a boolean that is <code>true</code> when the method call causes
      the termination of the Coordination, in all other cases it is
      <code>false</code>.</para>

      <para>Failing a Coordination will immediately perform the callbacks and
      reject any additional Participants by throwing an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.ALREADY_ENDED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception. The asynchronous nature
      of the fail method implies that it is possible to have been called even
      before the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.addParticipant-Participant-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method has returned. Anybody that has the
      Coordination object can check the failed state with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getFailure--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

      <para>In general, the best and most robust strategy to handle failures
      is to throw an Exception from the collaborator, allowing the initiator
      to catch the exception and properly fail the Coordination.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Time-out</title>

      <para>The time-out is specified in the Coordinator <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.create-String-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.begin-String-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods. A time-out of zero is indefinite,
      otherwise the time-out specifies the number of milliseconds the
      Coordination can take to terminate. A given time-out can be extended
      with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.extendTimeout-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This method will add an additional
      time-out to the existing deadline if a prior deadline was set. For
      example, the following code extends the time-out with 5 seconds whenever
      a message must be sent to a remote address:</para>

      <programlisting>Object sendMessage(Message m) {
  Coordination c = coordinator.peek();
  Address a = m.getDestination();
  if ( c != null &amp;&amp; a.isRemote() ) {
    c.extendTimeout(5000);
  }
  return sendMessage0(m);
}</programlisting>

      <para>Applications should not rely on the exact time-out of the
      Coordination and only use it as a safety function against deadlocks and
      hanging collaborators.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Joining</title>

      <para>When a Coordination is terminated it is not yet completely
      finished, the callback to the Participants happens after the atomic
      termination. In certain cases it is necessary to ensure that a method
      does not progress until all the participants have been notified. It is
      therefore possible to wait for the Coordination to completely finish
      with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.join-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This method can have a time-out. For
      example:</para>

      <programlisting>void collaborate( final Coordination c ) {
  doWork();
  Thread t = new Thread() {
    public void run(){
      try {
          c.join(0);
          ... // really terminated here, all participantscalled back
      } catch( Exception e) { ... }
    }
  };
  t.start();
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Variables</title>

      <para>A Participant is likely to have to maintain state that is
      particular for the collaboration. This state is usually needed in the
      <code>ended</code> method to properly finalize the work. In general, the
      best place to store this state is in the <code>Participant</code> object
      itself, inner classes and final variables are a good technique for
      storing the state. However, the state can also be stored in a
      Coordination <emphasis>variable</emphasis>. Each Coordination has a
      private set of variables that can be obtained with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getVariables--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The resulting map takes a class as the
      key and returns an Object. The map is not synchronized, any changes to
      the map must be synchronized on the returned Map object to ensure the
      visibility of the changes to other threads. The class used for the key
      is not related to the returned type, it is a <code>Class</code> object
      to provide a convenient namespace.</para>

      <para>The following example shows how the state can be stored with
      variables.</para>

      <programlisting>public void doWork(Coordination coordination){
  Map&lt;Class&lt;?&gt;,Object&gt; map = coordination.getVariables();
  synchronized(map) {
    State state = (State) map.get( SharedWorker.class );
    if ( state == null ) {
      state = new State(this);
      map.put( state );
      ... do initial work
    }
  }
  ... do other work
  coordination.addParticipant( this );
}
public void ended(Coordination c) {
  Map&lt;Class&lt;?&gt;,Object&gt; map = coordination.getVariables();
  synchronized(map) {
    State state = (State) map.get( SharedWorker.class );
    .. finalize
  }  
}
public void failed(Coordination c) {
  Map&lt;Class&lt;?&gt;,Object&gt; map = coordination.getVariables();
  synchronized(map) {
    State state = (State) map.get( SharedWorker.class );
    .. finalize
  }
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Optimizing Example</title>

      <para>For example, a web based system has a charge service:</para>

      <programlisting>public interface Charge {
  void charge( String reason, int amount );
}</programlisting>

      <para>This service is used throughout the system for charging the tasks
      the system performs. Each servlet request can actually create multiple
      Charge Data Records (CDR). For this reason, a Coordination is started
      before the page is constructed. Each part of the page that has an
      associated cost must create a CDR. There are the following issues at
      stake:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Charging should not take place when failing, and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Performance can be optimized to only persist the CDRs once,
          and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The user must be passed to the Charge service.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To begin with the request code:</para>

      <programlisting>public void doGet(HttpServletRequest rq, HttpServletResponsersp) {
  Coordination c = coordinator.begin("com.acme.request", 30000);
  try {
    Principal p = rq.getUserPrincipal();
    Map&lt;Class&lt;?&gt;,Object&gt; map = c.getVariables();
    map.put( Principal.class, p );
    buildPage(rq,rsp);
  } catch( Exception e  ) { c.fail(e); } 
    finally               { c.end(); }
}</programlisting>

      <para>Each method that has a charge will call the Charge service. The
      following code shows an implementation of this Charge service.</para>

      <programlisting>public class ChargeImpl implements Charge,Participant {
  final List&lt;CDR&gt; records = new ArrayList&lt;CDR&gt;();

  public void charge( String reason, int amount ) {
    Coordination c = coordinator.peek();
    if ( c == null ) {
       save( Arrays.asList( new CDR(null, reason, amount)));
    } else {
      Principal p = getPrincipal(c);
      records.add( new CDR(p, reason, amount ) );
      c.addParticipant( this );
    }
  }

  Principal getPrincipal(Coordination c) {
    if ( c == null )
      return null;

    Map&lt;Class&lt;?&gt;,Object&gt; map = c.getVariables();
    synchronized(map) {
      Principal p = (Principal) map.get( Principal.class );
      return p != null ? p : getPrincipal(c.getEnclosingCoordination());
    }
  }

  public void ended(Coordination c) {
    save(records);
    records.clear();
  }
  public void failed(Coordination c) {
    records.clear();
  }

  void save(List&lt;CDR&gt; records) { ... }
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Security Example</title>

      <para>The Coordination Permission is a filter based permission that is
      asserted for many of the methods in the API, the bundle that is checked
      is always the bundle that created the corresponding Coordination. For
      example:</para>

      <programlisting>ALLOW {
     [ BundleSignerCondition "cn=ACME" ]
    ( CoordinationPermission "(signer=cn=ACME)" "*" )
}</programlisting>

      <para>This example allows bundles signed by ACME to perform all
      Coordination actions on Coordinations created by bundles signed by
      ACME.</para>

      <para>The filter can also assert the name of the Coordination:</para>

      <programlisting>coordination.name</programlisting>

      <para>It is therefore possible to create a name based protection scheme.
      By denying all bundles except a select group through the use of a name
      prefix, the use of Coordinations can be restricted to this select
      group:</para>

      <programlisting>DENY {
     [ BundleSignerCondition "cn=ACME" "!" ]
    ( CoordinationPermission "(coordination.name=com.acme.*)""*" )
}
ALLOW {
    ( CoordinationPermission "(coordination.name=*)" "*" )
}</programlisting>

      <para>If a bundle is not signed by ACME it will be denied the use of
      Coordination names starting with <code>com.acme.</code> though it will
      be allowed to use any other name. This effectively enables only bundles
      signed by ACME to create Coordinations with this name prefix.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i3151714">
    <title>Coordinator Service</title>

    <para>The Coordinator service is the entry point for the Coordination. It
    provides the following functions:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Coordination creation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Life cycle management of a Coordination</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Thread based Coordinations</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Introspection</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Coordination Creation</title>

      <para>A <code>Coordination</code> object is created by an
      <emphasis>initiator</emphasis>. An initiator can create a
      <code>Coordination</code> object with the Coordinator <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.create-String-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.begin-String-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. Each Coordination when created gets a
      positive long identity that is available with <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getId--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. Ids are a unique identifier for a specific
      Coordinator service. The id is always increasing, that is, a
      Coordination with a higher id is created later.</para>

      <para>The create methods specify the name of the Coordination. This name
      is a security concept, see <xref
      linkend="service.coordinator.security"/>, as well as used for debugging.
      The coordination name must therefore conform to the same syntax as a
      bundle symbolic name:</para>

      <programlisting>coordination-name ::= symbolic-name   // see <xref
          linkend="intro.core.release" xrefstyle="template:%t"/></programlisting>

      <para>Passing a name that does not conform to this syntax must throw an
      Illegal Argument Exception. There are no constraints on duplicates,
      multiple different Coordinations can use the same name. The name of the
      Coordination is available with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getName--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding Participants</title>

      <para>The <code>Coordination</code> object can be passed to
      <emphasis>collaborators</emphasis> as a parameter in a method call. Some
      of these collaborators might be interested in
      <emphasis>participating</emphasis> in the given Coordination, they can
      achieve this by adding a <code>Participant</code> object to the
      Coordination.</para>

      <para>A Participant is a collaborator that requires a callback after the
      Coordination has been terminated, either when it ended or when it
      failed. To participate, it must add a <code>Participant</code> object to
      a Coordination with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.addParticipant-Participant-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method on Coordination. This method throws an
      <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.ALREADY_ENDED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.FAILED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception when the Coordination has
      been terminated.</para>

      <para>When a Participant is:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Not in any Coordination</emphasis> - Add it to the
          given Coordination and return.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>In target Coordination</emphasis> - Ignore,
          participant is already present. A Participant can participate in the
          same Coordination multiple times by calling <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.addParticipant-Participant-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> but will only be called back once when the
          Coordination is terminated. Its order must be defined by the first
          addition.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>In another Coordination</emphasis> - Lock until
          after the other Coordination has notified all the Participants.
          Implementations can detect deadlocks in certain cases and throw a
          Coordination Exception if a dead lock exist, otherwise the deadlock
          is solved when the Coordination times out.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Verifying if a Participant object is already in another
      Coordination must use identity and not equality.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Active</title>

      <para>A Coordination is active until it is
      <emphasis>terminated</emphasis>. A Coordination can terminate because it
      is <emphasis>ended</emphasis>, or it is <emphasis>failed</emphasis>. The
      following methods cause a termination:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A normal end. All participants that were
          added before the end call are called back on their <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Participant.ended-Coordination-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.fail-Throwable-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Coordination has failed, this will
          call back the <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Participant.failed-Coordination-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method on the participants. This method can
          be called by the Coordinator, the initiator, or any of the
          collaborators. There are a number of failures that are built in to
          the Coordinator. These failures use singleton Exception instances
          defined in the <code>Coordination</code> interface:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.TIMEOUT"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - If the Coordination times out the
              Coordination is failed with the <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.TIMEOUT"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> exception instance in
              Coordination.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.RELEASED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - If the Coordinator that created the
              Coordination was unget, all Coordinations created by it will
              fail with the <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.RELEASED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> exception.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The state diagram for the Coordination is pictured in <xref
      linkend="i3136697"/>.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i3136697">
        <title>Coordination state diagram</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.550in"
                       contentwidth="6.207in" fileref="state-diagram.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Explicit and Implicit Models</title>

      <para>The Coordinator supports two very different models of usage:
      <emphasis>explicit</emphasis> and <emphasis>implicit</emphasis>. The
      explicit model is when a Coordination is created and passed around as a
      parameter. The second model is the implicit model where the Coordinator
      maintains a thread local stack of Coordinations. Any collaborator can
      then decide to use the top of the stack as the
      <emphasis>current</emphasis> Coordination. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.peek--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method provides access to the current
      Coordination.</para>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.begin-String-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method creates a new Coordination and pushes
      this on the stack, beginning an implicit Coordination. This is identical
      to:</para>

      <programlisting>coordinator.create("work",0).push();</programlisting>

      <para>Once a Coordination is pushed on a stack it is from that moment on
      associated with the current thread. A Coordination can only be pushed
      once, the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.ALREADY_PUSHED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception must be thrown when the
      Coordination is already associated with one of the thread local stacks
      maintained by the Coordinator service.</para>

      <para>The Coordination is removed from the stack in the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method must not only terminate itself but it
      must also terminate all nested Coordinations.</para>

      <para>The current Coordination can also be explicitly removed with the
      Coordinator <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.pop--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

      <para>A Coordination that is pushed on a thread local stack returns the
      associated thread on the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getThread--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This method returns <code>null</code>
      for Coordinations not on any stack, that is, explicit
      Coordinations.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Termination</title>

      <para>Both the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.fail-Throwable-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods terminate the Coordination if it was not
      already terminated. Termination is atomic, only the <code>end</code> or
      the <code>fail</code> method can terminate the Coordination. Though this
      happens on different threads, a Coordination can never both end and fail
      from any perspective. That is, if a fail races with end then only one of
      them can win and the other provides the feedback that the Coordination
      was already terminated.</para>

      <para>Terminating a Coordination has the following effects:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>It is atomic, it can only happen once in a Coordination</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It freezes the set of participants, no more participants can
          be added</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Ending</title>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method should always be called at the end of a
      Coordination to ensure proper termination, notification, and cleanup.
      The end method throws a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.FAILED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.PARTIALLY_ENDED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception if the Coordination was
      failed before.</para>

      <para>If the Coordination had already been ended before then this is a
      programming error and an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.ALREADY_ENDED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Configuration Exception is thrown. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method should never be called twice on the same
      Coordination.</para>

      <para>If the termination succeeds then the participants must be notified
      by calling the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Participant.ended-Coordination-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method on each Participant that had been
      successfully added to the Coordination. This callback can take place on
      any thread but must be in reverse order of adding. That is, the last
      added Participant is called back first.</para>

      <para>Participants must never make any assumptions about the current
      Coordination in the callback. The Coordination it was added to is
      therefore given as an explicit parameter in the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Participant.ended-Coordination-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

      <para>If a Participant throws an Exception then this must not prevent
      the calling of the remaining participants. The Exception should be
      logged. If a Participant has thrown an Exception then the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method must throw a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.PARTIALLY_ENDED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception after the last
      Participant has returned from its callback, otherwise the method returns
      normally. Participants should normally not throw Exceptions in their
      callbacks.</para>

      <para>If the Coordination is implicit (it is pushed on a stack) then the
      Coordination must be removed from its stack after the participants have
      been called back. This requires that the ending thread is the same as
      the thread of the Coordination. The end thread is the thread of the
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method call. If the Coordination's thread is not
      the same as the ending thread then a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.WRONG_THREAD"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception is thrown.</para>

      <para>If the ending Coordination is on the stack but it is not the
      current Coordination then each nested Coordination must be ended before
      the current Coordination, see <xref linkend="i3202535"/> for more
      information.</para>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.fail-Throwable-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method must not remove the current Coordination,
      it must remain on the stack. The initiator must always call the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. Always calling <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> in a <code>finally</code> block is therefore
      paramount.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3142795">
      <title>Failing, TIMEOUT, ORPHANED, and RELEASED</title>

      <para><emphasis>Failing</emphasis> can happen asynchronously during the
      time a Coordination is active. A Coordination is failed by calling <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.fail-Throwable-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The Throwable argument must not be
      <code>null</code>, it is the cause of the failure.</para>

      <para>Failing a Coordination must first terminate it. If the
      Coordination was already terminated the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.fail-Throwable-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method has no effect. Otherwise, it must
      callback all its added Participants on the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Participant.failed-Coordination-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> callback method. Exceptions thrown from this
      method should be logged and further ignored. The callback can occur on
      any thread, including the caller's.</para>

      <para>Implicit Coordinations must not be popped from its stack in a fail
      nor is it necessary to call the <code>fail</code> method from any
      particular thread. The removal of the Coordination from the stack must
      happen in the <code>end</code> method.</para>

      <para>There are two asynchronous events that can also fail the
      Coordination. If the Coordination times out, it will be treated as a
      <code>fail(</code> <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.TIMEOUT"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> <code>)</code> and if the Coordinator is
      ungotten with active Coordinations then each of those Coordinations must
      fail as if <code>fail(</code> <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.RELEASED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> <code>)</code> is called.</para>

      <para>A Coordination can also be <emphasis>orphaned</emphasis>. An
      orphaned Coordination has no longer any outside references. This means
      that the Coordination can no longer be ended or failed. Such
      Coordinations must fail with an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.ORPHANED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Exception.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3202535">
      <title>Nesting Implicit Coordinations</title>

      <para>Implicit Coordinations can be nested. For this reason, the
      Coordinator maintains a thread local stack of Coordinations where the
      top, accessible with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.peek--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, is the current Coordination. Each time a
      new Coordination is begun with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.begin-String-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, the current Coordination is replaced
      with the newly created Coordination. When that Coordination is ended,
      the previous current Coordination is restored. Nesting is always on the
      same thread, implicit Coordinations are always associated with a single
      thread, available through its <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getThread--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The end method must be called on the
      same thread as the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.begin-String-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or last <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.push--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>

      <para>Using the standard model for implicit Coordinations, where the
      initiator always ends the Coordination on the same thread as it begun,
      ensures that nesting is properly handled. However, in certain cases it
      is necessary to manipulate the stack or make implicit Coordinations
      explicit or vice versa. For this reason, it is possible to pop
      Coordinations from the stack with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.pop--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. This method disassociates the
      Coordination from the current thread and restores the previous (if any)
      Coordination as the current Thread. A Coordination can then be made the
      current Coordination for a thread by calling the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.push--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. However, a Coordination can be pushed on
      the stack at most once. If a Coordination is pushed a second time, in
      any thread, the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.ALREADY_PUSHED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> Coordination Exception must be thrown.</para>

      <para>The Coordination is removed from its stack when the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is called. It is therefore highly
      recommended to always end a Coordination in the nesting order. However,
      it is possible that a Coordination is ended that is not the current
      Coordination, it has nested Coordinations that were not properly ended.
      In that case all nested Coordinations must be ended in reverse creation
      order, that is, the current Coordination first, by calling the
      <code>end</code> method on it.</para>

      <para>If any Coordination fails to end properly (including <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.PARTIALLY_ENDED"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> ) then the remaining Coordinations on the stack
      must fail and chain the exceptions. In pseudo code:</para>

      <programlisting>while (coordinator.peek() != this) {
 try {
     coordinator.peek().end();
 } catch (CoordinationException e) {
      coordinator.peek().fail(e);
 }
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Time-outs</title>

      <para>When a Coordination is created it will receive a time-out. A
      time-out is a positive value or zero. A zero value indicates that the
      Coordination should have no time-out. This does not imply that a
      Coordination will never time-out, implementations are allowed to be
      configured with a limit to the maximum active time for a
      Coordination.</para>

      <para>Collaborators can extend the time out with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.extendTimeout-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. If no time-out was set (0), this method
      will be ignored. Otherwise the given amount (which must be positive) is
      added to the existing deadline. A Coordinator implementation can fail
      the Coordination earlier, however, when configured to do so.</para>

      <para>If a Coordination is timed out, the Coordination is failed with a
      <code>fail(TIMEOUT)</code> method call from an unspecified thread, see
      <xref linkend="i3142795"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Released</title>

      <para>The Coordination's life cycle is bound to the Coordinator service
      that created it. If the initiator's bundle ungets this service then the
      Coordinator must fail all the Coordinations created by this Coordinator
      by calling the <code>fail(RELEASED)</code> method.</para>

      <para>Participants from bundles that are stopped are not taken into
      account. This means that it is possible that a participant is called
      while its bundle is stopped. Stopped Participants should fail any
      Coordinations that they participate in.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Coordinator Convenience Methods</title>

      <para>The Coordinator contains a number of convenience methods that can
      be used by collaborators to interact with the current
      Coordination.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.begin-String-long-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Is logically the same as <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.create-String-long-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.push--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.addParticipant-Participant-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This method makes it easy to react
          differently to the presence of a current implicit Coordination. If a
          current Coordination exists, the participant is added and
          <code>true</code> is returned (or an exception thrown if the
          Coordination is already terminated), otherwise <code>false</code> is
          returned.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.fail-Throwable-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - If there is no current Coordination, this
          method returns false. Otherwise it returns the result of calling
          <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.fail-Throwable-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> on the current Coordination. This method
          therefore only returns <code>true</code> when a current Coordination
          was actually terminated due to this call.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Administrative Access</title>

      <para>The <code>Coordination</code> objects provide a number of methods
      that are used for administrating the Coordinations and the
      Coordinator.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getBundle--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Provide the bundle that created the
          Coordination. This bundle is the bundle belonging to the Bundle
          Context used to get the Coordinator service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getFailure--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Exception that caused this
          Coordination to fail or <code>null</code>. There are two fixed
          exception instances for a time out ( <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.TIMEOUT"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> ), when the Coordination is orphaned ( <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.ORPHANED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> ), and when the Coordinator service is
          released ( <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.RELEASED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> ).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getId--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Coordination's id.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getName--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The name of the Coordination.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getParticipants--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The current list of participants. This is
          a mutable snapshot of the added participants. Changing the snapshot
          has no effect on the Coordination.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getThread--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Answer the thread associated with an
          implicit Coordination. If the Coordination is not implicit then the
          answer is <code>null</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.getEnclosingCoordination--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Return the enclosing Coordination.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>And for the Coordinator:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.getCoordination-long-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Retrieve a Coordination by its id.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordinator.getCoordinations--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get a list of active Coordinations</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Summary</title>

      <para>A Coordination can exist in three different states
      <emphasis>ACTIVE</emphasis>, <emphasis>END</emphasis>, and
      <emphasis>FAIL</emphasis>. During its life it will transition from
      ACTIVE to either END or FAIL. The entry (when the state is entered) and
      exit (when the state is left) actions when this transition takes place
      and the effect on the different methods are summarized in the following
      table.</para>

      <table pgwide="1">
        <title>States and transitions</title>

        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="0.8*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="0.8*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1.2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="1.2*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>State/Method</entry>

              <entry>ACTIVE</entry>

              <entry>END</entry>

              <entry>FAIL</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para><emphasis role="strong">entry
              action</emphasis></para></entry>

              <entry><para/></entry>

              <entry><para>Notify all the participants by calling the <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Participant.ended-Coordination-"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Notify all the participants by calling the <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Participant.failed-Coordination-"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><emphasis role="strong">exit
              action</emphasis></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Terminate</para></entry>

              <entry><para/></entry>

              <entry><para/></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.end--"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>-&gt; <code>END</code>.</para><para>Can throw <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.PARTIALLY_ENDED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>throws <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.ALREADY_ENDED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>throws <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationException.FAILED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.Coordination.fail-Throwable-"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>-&gt; <code>FAIL</code>, return
              <code>true</code>.</para></entry>

              <entry><para>return <code>false</code>.</para></entry>

              <entry><para>return <code>false</code>.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.coordinator.security">
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>This specification provides a Coordination Permission. This
    permission can enforce the name of the coordination as well as assert the
    properties of the initiating bundle, like for example the signer or bundle
    symbolic name. The permission therefore uses a filter as name, as defined
    in the filter based permissions section in <xref
    linkend="intro.core.release" xrefstyle="template:%t"/>, see <xref
    linkend="intro.core.release" xrefstyle="template:%t"/>. There is one
    additional parameter for the filter:</para>

    <programlisting>coordination.name</programlisting>

    <para>The value is the given name of the Coordination. Restricting the
    name of a Coordination allows the deployer to limit the use of this name
    to a restricted set of bundles.</para>

    <para>The following actions are defined:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationPermission.INITIATE"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Required to initiate and control a
        Coordination.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationPermission.PARTICIPATE"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Required to participate in a
        Coordination.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationPermission.ADMIN"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Required to administrate a
        Coordinator.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The target bundle of the Coordination Permission is the initiator's
    bundle. This is the bundle that got the Coordinator service to create the
    Coordination. An initiator must therefore have permission to create
    Coordinations for itself.</para>

    <para>There are two constructors available:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationPermission.CoordinationPermission-String-String-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The constructor for the granted permission.
        It is given a filter expression and the actions that the permission
        applies to.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.coordinator.CoordinationPermission.CoordinationPermission-String-Bundle-String-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The constructor for the requested
        permission. It is given the name of the permission, the bundle that
        created the corresponding coordination, and the requested
        actions.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.coordinator.xml"/>
</chapter>
