<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright (c) Contributors to the Eclipse Foundation
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
   
    SPDX-License-Identifier: Apache-2.0 
 -->

<chapter label="155" revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="tr157softwaremodules"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>TR-157 Amendment 3 Software Module Guidelines</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo xml:id="tr157softwaremodules-version">Version
    1.0</releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <para><xref linkend="i747111"/> (BBF) has defined an object model for
  managing the software modules in a CPE. The BBF Software Modules object
  defines Execution Environments, Deployment Units, and Execution Units. These
  concepts are mapped in the following table.</para>

  <table>
    <title>Mapping of concepts</title>

    <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>

      <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>

      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Software Modules Concept</entry>

          <entry>OSGi Concept</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>

      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><code>Execution Environment</code></entry>

          <entry><code>OSGi Framework</code></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><code>Deployment Unit</code></entry>

          <entry><code>Bundle</code></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><code>Execution Unit</code></entry>

          <entry><code>Bundle</code></entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>There can be multiple Execution Environments of the same or different
  types. The parent Execution Environment is either the native environment,
  for example Linux, or it can be another Framework. A BBF Deployment Unit and
  Execution Unit both map to a bundle since there is no need to separate those
  concepts in OSGi. An implementation of this object model should have access
  to all the Execution Environments as the Deployment Units and Execution
  Units are represented in a single table.</para>

  <para>This section is not a specification in the normal sense. The intention
  of this chapter is to provide guidelines for implementers of the <xref
  linkend="i751018"/> on an OSGi Framework.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Management Agent</title>

    <para>The Broadband Forum TR-157 Software Modules standard provides a
    uniform view of the different execution environments that are available in
    a device. Execution Environments can model the underlying operating
    system, an OSGi framework, or other environments that support managing the
    execution of code.</para>

    <para>Most parameters in the Software Modules object model map very well
    to their OSGi counter parts. However, there are a number of issues that
    require support from a <emphasis>management agent</emphasis>. This
    management agent must maintain state to implement the contract implied by
    the Software Modules standard. For example, the OSGi Framework does not
    have an Initial Start Level, an OSGi Framework always starts at an
    environment property defined start level. However, the standard requires
    that a Framework must start at a given level after it is launched.</para>

    <para>There are many other actions that require a management agent to
    provide the functionality required by TR-157 that is not build into the
    OSGi Framework since the standard requires a view that covers the whole
    device, not just the OSGi environment. The assumed architecture is
    depicted in <xref linkend="i751444"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i751444">
      <title>Management Agent Architecture</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.025in"
                     contentwidth="5.261in"
                     fileref="management-agent-architecture.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Parameter Mapping</title>

    <para>The following table provides OSGi specific information for the
    different parameters in the Software Modules object model.</para>

    <table pgwide="1">
      <title>OSGi Specific Information for the BBF Software Modules object
      model</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>

        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry><para>TR-069 Software Module</para><para>Object
            Parameter</para></entry>

            <entry>Mapping in case of OSGi</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><code>Device.SoftwareModules.</code></entry>

            <entry><para/></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ExecEnvNumberOfEntries</code></entry>

            <entry><para/></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;DeploymentUnitNumberOfEntries</code></entry>

            <entry><para/></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ExecutionUnitNumberOfEntries</code></entry>

            <entry><para/></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>Device.SoftwareModules.ExecEnv.{i}.</code></entry>

            <entry><para/></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Enable</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Indicates whether or not this OSGi Framework is
            enabled. Disabling an enabled OSGi Framework must stop it, while
            enabling a disabled OSGi Framework must launch it. When an
            Execution Environment is disabled, Bundles installed in that OSGi
            Framework will be unaffected, but any Bundles on that OSGi
            Framework are automatically made inactive. When an OSGi Framework
            is disabled it is impossible to make changes to the installed
            bundles, install new bundles, or query any information about the
            bundles. Disabling the OSGi Framework could place the device in a
            non-manageable state. For example, if the OSGi Framework runs the
            Protocol Adapter or has a management agent then it is possible
            that the device can no longer be restarted.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Status</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Indicates the status of the OSGi Framework.
            Enumeration of:</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Up</code> - The OSGi Framework is up and
                  running.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Error</code> - The OSGi Framework could not be
                  launched.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Disabled</code> - The OSGi Framework is not
                  enabled</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Reset</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Setting this parameter to <code>true</code> causes
            this OSGi Framework to revert back to the state it was in when the
            device last issued a <code>0 BOOTSTRAP Inform</code> event
            (bootstrap). The following requirements dictate what must happen
            for the reset to be complete:</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The system must restore the set of bundles that were
                  present at the last bootstrap event. That means that
                  installed bundles since that moment must be uninstalled,
                  updated bundles rolled back, and uninstalled bundles
                  re-installed.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The OSGi Framework must roll back to the version it
                  had during the previous rollback.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The OSGi Framework must be restarted after the
                  previous requirements have been met.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist><para>The value of this parameter is not part of
            the device configuration and is always <code>false</code> when
            read.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Alias</code></entry>

            <entry><para>A non-volatile handle used to reference this instance
            for alias based addressing.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Name</code></entry>

            <entry><para>A Name that adequately distinguishes this OSGi
            Framework from all other OSGi Frameworks. This must be the OSGi
            Framework UUID as stored in the
            <code>org.osgi.framework.uuid</code> property. </para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Type</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Indicates the complete type and specification version
            of this <code>ExecEnv</code>. For an OSGi Framework it must
            be:</para><programlisting>OSGi &lt;version&gt;</programlisting><para>Where
            the <code>&lt;version&gt;</code> is the value of the framework
            property <code>org.osgi.framework.version</code></para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;InitialRunLevel</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The run level that this <code>ExecEnv</code> will be
            in upon startup (whether that is caused by a CPE Boot or the
            Execution Environment starting). Run levels map to directly OSGi
            start levels. However, the OSGi Framework has no concept of an
            initial start level, it can use the
            <code>org.osgi.framework.startlevel.beginning</code> environment
            property but this requires a management to control it. A
            management agent must therefore handle this value and instruct the
            OSGi Framework to move to this start level after a
            reboot.</para><para>If the value of <code>CurrentRunLevel</code>
            is set to -1, then the value of this parameter is irrelevant when
            read. Setting its value to -1 must have no impact on the start
            level of this OSGi Framework.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;RequestedRunLevel</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Sets the start level of this OSGi Framework, meaning
            that altering this parameter's value will change the value of the
            <code>CurrentRunLevel</code> asynchronously. Start levels dictate
            which Bundles will be started. Setting this value when
            <code>CurrentRunLevel</code> is -1 must have no impact on the
            start Level of this OSGi Framework. The value of this parameter is
            not part of the device configuration and must always be -1 when
            read.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;CurrentRunLevel</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The start level that this OSGi Framework is currently
            operating in. This value is altered by changing the
            <code>RequestedRunLevel</code> parameter. Upon startup (whether
            that is caused by a CPE Boot or the Execution Environment
            starting) <code>CurrentRunLevel</code> must be set equal to
            <code>InitialRunLevel</code> by some management agent.
            </para><para>If Run Levels are not supported by this OSGi
            Framework then <code>CurrentRunLevel</code> must be
            -1.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Version</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The Version of this OSGi Framework as specified by
            its Vendor. This is not the version of its specification. Must be
            the value of the System Bundle's <code>getVersion()</code>
            method.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Vendor</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The vendor that produced this OSGi Framework, the
            value of the <code>org.osgi.framework.vendor</code> Framework
            property.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ParentExecEnv</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The value must be the path name of a row in the
            <code>ExecEnv</code> table, it can either be the operating system
            or another OSGi Framework if the framework is nested. If the
            referenced object is deleted, the parameter value must be set to
            an empty string. If this value is an empty string then this is
            the <emphasis>Primary Execution
            Environment</emphasis>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;AllocatedDiskSpace</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Implementation specific.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;AvailableDiskSpace</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Implementation specific.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;AllocatedMemory</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Implementation specific.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;AvailableMemory</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Implementation specific.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ProcessorRefList</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Comma-separated list of paths into the
            <code>DeviceInfo.Processor</code> table. If the referenced object
            is deleted, the corresponding item must be removed from the list.
            Represents the processors that this OSGi Framework has available
            to it.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ActiveExecutionUnits</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Comma-separated list of paths into the
            <code>ExecutionUnit</code> table. If the referenced object is
            deleted, the corresponding item must be removed from the list.
            Represents the Bundles currently active on this OSGi
            Framework.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><code>Device.SoftwareModules.</code></para><para><code>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;DeploymentUnit.{i}.</code></para></entry>

            <entry><para>This table serves as the Bundles inventory and
            contains status information about each Bundle. A new instance of
            this table gets created during the installation of a
            Bundle.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;UUID</code></entry>

            <entry><para>A Universally Unique Identifier either provided by
            the ACS, or generated by the CPE, at the time of Deployment Unit
            Installation. The format of this value is defined by <xref
            linkend="i749662"/> Version 3 (Name-Based) and <xref
            linkend="i749742"/>. This value must not be altered when the
            Bundle is updated. A management agent should use the UUID as the
            bundle location since the location plays the same
            role.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;DUID</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The Bundle id from the <code>getBundleId()</code>
            method.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Alias</code></entry>

            <entry><para>A non-volatile handle used to reference this
            instance.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Name</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Indicates the Bundle Symbolic Name of this Bundle.
            The value of this parameter is used in the generation of the UUID
            based on the rules defined in <xref
            linkend="i749742"/>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Status</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Indicates the status of this Bundle. Enumeration
            of:</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Installing</code> - This bundle is in the
                  process of being Installed and should transition to the
                  Installed state. This state will never be visible in an OSGi
                  Framework.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Installed</code> - This bundle has been
                  successfully installed.This maps to the Bundle
                  <code>INSTALLED</code> or <code>RESOLVED</code>
                  state.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Updating</code> - This bundle is in the process
                  of being updated and should transition to the Installed
                  state. This state will never be visible in an OSGi
                  Framework.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Uninstalling</code> - This bundle is in the
                  process of being uninstalled and should transition to the
                  uninstalled state.This state will never be visible in an
                  OSGi Framework.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Uninstalled</code> - This bundle has been
                  successfully uninstalled. This state will never be visible
                  in an OSGi Framework.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Resolved</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Indicates whether or not this
            <code>DeploymentUnit</code> has resolved all of its dependencies.
            Must be true if this Bundle's state is <code>ACTIVE</code>,
            <code>STARTING</code>, <code>STOPPING</code>, or
            <code>RESOLVED</code>. Otherwise it must be
            <code>false</code>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;URL</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Contains the URL used by the most recent
            <code>ChangeDUState</code> RPC to either Install or Update this
            Bundle. This must be remembered by a management agent since this
            information is not available in a Bundle.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Description</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Textual description of this Bundle, must be the value
            of the Bundle-Description manifest header or an empty string if
            not present.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Vendor</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The author of this <code>DeploymentUnit</code>
            formatted as a domain name. The value of this parameter is used in
            the generation of the UUID based on the rules defined in <xref
            linkend="i749742"/>. The recommended value is the value of the
            Bundle-Vendor header.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Version</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Version of this Bundle, it mist be he value of the
            <code>geVersion()</code> method.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;VendorLogList</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Empty String</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;VendorConfigList</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Empty String</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ExecutionUnitList</code></entry>

            <entry><para>A path into the <code>ExecutionUnit</code> table for
            the corresponding <code>ExecutionUnit</code> for this Bundle,
            which is also the bundle since the relation is 1:1.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ExecutionEnvRef</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The value must be the path name of a row in the
            <code>ExecEnv</code> table of the corresponding OSGi
            Framework.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><code>Device.SoftwareModules.</code></para><para><code>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;ExecutionUnit.{i}.</code></para></entry>

            <entry><para>This table serves as the Execution Unit inventory and
            contains both status information about each Execution Unit as well
            as configurable parameters for each Execution Unit. This list
            contains all the bundles since in an OSGi Framework Deployment
            Unit and Execution Unit are mapped to Bundles.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;EUID</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Table wide identifier for a bundle chosen by the OSGi
            Framework during installation of the associated
            <code>DeploymentUnit</code>. The value must be unique across
            <code>ExecEnv</code> instances. It is recommended that this be a
            combination of the <code>ExecEnv.{i}.Name</code> and an OSGi
            Framework local unique value. The unique value for an OSGi
            framework should be the Bundle Location.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Alias</code></entry>

            <entry><para>A non-volatile handle used to reference this
            instance.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Name</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The name should be unique across all Bundles
            instances contained within its associated
            <code>DeploymentUnit</code>. As the Deployment Unit and the
            Execution Unit are the same the value must be the Bundle Symbolic
            Name.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ExecEnvLabel</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The name must be unique across all Bundles contained
            within a specific OSGi Framework. This must therefore be the
            Bundle Id.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;AutoStart</code></entry>

            <entry><para>If <code>true</code> and the proper start level is
            met, then this Bundle will be automatically started by the device
            after its OSGi Framework's start level is met. If
            <code>false</code> this Bundle must not be started after launch
            until it is explicitly commanded to do so.</para><para>An OSGi
            bundle is persistently started or transiently started. It is not
            possible to change this state without affecting the active state
            of the bundle. Therefore, if the <code>AutoStart</code> is set to
            <code>true</code>, the bundle must be started persistently, even
            if it is already started. This will record the persistent start
            state. If the <code>AutoStart</code> is set to <code>false</code>,
            the bundle must be stopped. Therefore, in an OSGi Framework
            setting the <code>AutoStart</code> flag to <code>true</code> has
            the side effect that the bundle is started if it was not active;
            setting it to <code>false</code> will stop the
            bundle.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;RunLevel</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Determines when this Bundle will be started. If
            <code>AutoStart</code> is <code>true</code> and the <code>
            CurrentRunLevel</code> is greater than or equal to this
            <code>RunLevel</code>, then this <code>ExecutionUnit</code> must
            be started, if run levels are enabled. This maps directly to the
            Bundles start level.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Status</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Indicates the status of this
            <code>ExecutionUnit</code>. Enumeration of:</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Idle</code> - This Bundle is in an Idle state
                  and not running. This maps to the Bundle
                  <code>INSTALLED</code> or Bundle <code>RESOLVED</code>
                  state.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Starting</code> - This Bundle is in the process
                  of starting and should transition to the Active state. This
                  maps to the <code>STARTING</code> state in OSGi. In an OSGi
                  Framework, lazily activated bundles can remain in the
                  <code>STARTING</code> state for a long time.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Active</code> - This instance is currently
                  running. This maps to the Bundle <code>ACTIVE</code>
                  state.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Stopping</code> - This instance is in the
                  process of stopping and should transition to the Idle
                  state.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;RequestedState</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Indicates the state transition that the ACS is
            requesting for this Bundle. Enumeration of:</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Idle</code> - If this Bundle is currently in
                  <code>STARTING</code> or <code>ACTIVE</code> state then the
                  CPE must attempt to stop the Bundle; otherwise this
                  requested state is ignored.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>Active</code> - If this Bundle is currently in
                  the <code>INSTALLED</code> or <code>RESOLVED</code> state
                  the management agent must attempt to start the Bundle. If
                  this ExecutionUnit is in the <code>STOPPING</code> state the
                  request is rejected and a fault raised. Otherwise this
                  requested state is ignored.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist><para>If this Bundle is disabled and an attempt
            is made to alter this value, then a CWMP Fault must be generated.
            The value of this parameter is not part of the device
            configuration and is always an empty string when read. Bundles
            must be started transiently when the <code>AutoStart</code> is
            <code>false</code>, otherwise persistently.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ExecutionFaultCode</code></entry>

            <entry><para>If while running or transitioning between states this
            Bundle raises an Exception then this parameter embodies the
            problem. Enumeration of:</para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><code>NoFault</code> - No fault, default value.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>FailureOnStart</code> - Threw an exception when
                  started.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>FailureOnAutoStart</code> - Failed to be started
                  by the framework, this must be intercepted by the management
                  agent because this is a Framework Error event.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>FailureOnStop</code> - Raised an exception while
                  stopping</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>FailureWhileActive</code> - Raised when a bundle
                  cannot be restarted after a background operation of the
                  Framework, for example refreshing.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>DependencyFailure</code> - Failed to
                  resolve</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><code>UnStartable</code> - Cannot be raised in OSGi
                  since this is the same error as
                  <code>FailureOnStart</code>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist><para>For fault codes not included in this list,
            the vendor can include vendor-specific values, which must use the
            format defined in Section 3.3 of <xref
            linkend="i749746"/>.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ExecutionFaultMessage</code></entry>

            <entry><para>If while running or transitioning between states this
            Bundle identifies a fault this parameter provides a more detailed
            explanation of the problem enumerated in the
            <code>ExecutionFaultCode</code>.</para><para>If
            <code>ExecutionFaultCode</code> has the value of
            <code>NoFault</code> then the value of this parameter must be an
            empty string and ignored. This message must be the message value
            of the exception thrown by the Bundle.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Vendor</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Vendor of this Bundle. The value of the Bundle-Vendor
            manifest header</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Description</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Textual description of this Bundle. The value of the
            Bundle-Description manifest header</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;Version</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Version of the Bundle. The value of the
            <code>getVersion()</code> method.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;VendorLogList</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Empty string.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;VendorConfigList</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Empty string.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;DiskSpaceInUse</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Implementation defined</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;MemoryInUse</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Implementation defined</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;References</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Empty String</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;AssociatedProcessList</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Empty String as an OSGi bundle reuses the process of
            the VM.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;SupportedDataModelList</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Comma-separated list of strings. Each list item must
            be the path name of a row in the DeviceInfo.SupportedDataModel
            table. If the referenced object is deleted, the corresponding item
            must be removed from the list. Represents the CWMP-DT schema
            instances that have been introduced to this device because of the
            existence of this <code>ExecutionUnit</code>. In OSGi this is
            implementation defined.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>&#160;ExecutionEnvRef</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The path to the OSGi Framework that hosts this bundle
            in the <code>ExecEnv</code> table.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para><code>Device.SoftwareModules.</code></para><para><code>&#160;ExecutionUnit.{i}.Extensions.</code></para></entry>

            <entry><para>This object proposes a general location for vendor
            extensions specific to this Execution Unit, which allows multiple
            Execution Units to expose parameters without the concern of
            conflicting parameter names. This part is not used in
            OSGi.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i747111"><title>Broadband
      Forum</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.broadband-forum.org"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i749662"><title>RFC 4122 A Universally Unique
      IDentifier (UUID) URN
      Namespace</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4122"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed><title>TR-157a3 Component Objects for
      CWMP</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.broadband-forum.org/technical/download/TR-157_Amendment-3.pdf"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i751018"><title>TR-157a3 Internet Gateway Device
      Software
      Modules</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.broadband-forum.org/cwmp/tr-157-1-3-0-igd.html#D.InternetGatewayDevice.SoftwareModules"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i749742"><title>TR-069a3 CPE WAN Management
      Protocol</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.broadband-forum.org/technical/download/TR-069_Amendment-3.pdf"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i749746"><title>TR-106a4 Data Model Template for
      TR-069-Enabled
      Devices</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.broadband-forum.org/technical/download/TR-106_Amendment-4.pdf"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
