<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="9" revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="framework.startlevel"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Start Level API Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework.startlevel-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This specification describes how to enable a management agent to
    control the relative starting and stopping order of bundles in an OSGi
    framework.</para>

    <para>The management agent can set the start levels for bundles and set
    the active start level of the Framework, which will start and stop the
    appropriate bundles. Only bundles that have a start level less or equal to
    this active start level must be active. The purpose of the Start Level API
    is to allow the management agent to control, in detail, what bundles will
    be started and stopped and when this occurs.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Ordering</emphasis> - A management agent should be
          able to order the startup and shutdown sequences of bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Levels</emphasis> - The management agent should
          support a virtually unlimited number of levels.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Start Level</emphasis> - The adapter on a
          bundle that is used by a management agent to order the startup and
          shutdown sequences of bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Framework Start Level</emphasis> - The adapter that
          is used to set the framework start levels.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Management Agent</emphasis> - A bundle that is
          provided by the Operator to implement an Operator specific
          policy.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Framework Event</emphasis> - See <xref
          linkend="i3032483"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Framework Listener</emphasis> - See <xref
          linkend="i3032481"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Class Diagram org.osgi.framework.startlevel package</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.586in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="startlevel-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Start Level API</title>

    <para>The Start Level API provides the following functions:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Controls the beginning start level of the OSGi Framework.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Is used to modify the active start level of the
        Framework.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Can be used to assign a specific start level to a bundle.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Can set the initial start level for newly installed
        bundles.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Defining the order in which bundles are started and stopped is
    useful for the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Safe mode</emphasis> - The management agent can
        implement a <emphasis>safe mode</emphasis>. In this mode, only fully
        trusted bundles are started. Safe mode might be necessary when a
        bundle causes a failure at startup that disrupts normal operation and
        prevents correction of the problem.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Splash screen</emphasis> - If the total startup time
        is long, it might be desirable to show a splash screen during
        initialization. This improves the user's perception of the boot time
        of the device. The startup ordering can ensure that the right bundle
        is started first.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Handling erratic bundles</emphasis> - Problems can
        occur because bundles require services to be available when they are
        activated (this is a programming error). By controlling the start
        order, the management agent can prevent these problems.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>High priority bundles</emphasis> - Certain tasks such
        as metering need to run as quickly as possible and cannot have a long
        startup delay. These bundles can be started first.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Start levels are not intended to be used for ensuring that
    dependencies are met when a bundle is started. Any of the life cycle
    actions (install/update/uninstall) can cause a dependency to become
    unavailable regardless of start levels.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Adaptations</title>

      <para>This specification provides two adaptations of a
      <code>Bundle</code> object to a:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Used to get and set the start level on a
          specific bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Used to get and control the framework
          start level. This adaptation must return null for any other bundle
          than the system bundle (bundle 0).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bundle Start Level Bundle Adaptation</title>

      <para>The adaptation provides the following methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel.setStartLevel-int-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sets the current start level for the
          adapted bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel.getStartLevel--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Gets the current start level for the
          adapted bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel.isActivationPolicyUsed--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Answer if the activation policy is
          used.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel.isPersistentlyStarted--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Answer if this bundle as persistently
          started.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Framework Start Level Bundle Adaptation</title>

      <para>The Framework Start Level adaptation is only possible for the
      system bundle. Other bundles must return <code>null</code> for this
      adaptation. The adaptation provides the following methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel.getInitialBundleStartLevel--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Return the start level to assign for newly
          installed bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel.setInitialBundleStartLevel-int-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Set the initial start level.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel.getStartLevel--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Get the current framework start
          level.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel.setStartLevel-int-FrameworkListener...-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Set the current framework start level and
          provide an optional callback Framework Listener. This listener is
          called back when the set start level has been reached.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Concept of a Start Level</title>

    <para>A <emphasis>start level</emphasis> is defined as a non-negative
    integer. A start level of 0 (zero) is the state in which the Framework has
    either not been launched or has completed shutdown (these two states are
    considered equivalent). In this state, no bundles are running.
    Progressively higher integral values represent progressively higher start
    levels. For example, 2 is a higher start level than 1. The Framework must
    support all positive <code>int</code> values
    (<code>Integer.MAX_VALUE</code>) for start levels.</para>

    <para>The Framework has an <emphasis>active start level</emphasis> that is
    used to decide which bundles can be started. All bundles must be assigned
    a <emphasis>bundle start level.</emphasis> This is the minimum start level
    to start a bundle. The bundle start level can be set with the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel.setStartLevel-int-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method on the <code>BundleStartLevel</code>
    object. When a bundle is installed, it is initially assigned the bundle
    start level returned by <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel.getInitialBundleStartLevel--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> on a <code>FrameworkStartLevel</code> object. The
    initial bundle start level to be used when bundles are installed can be
    set with <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel.setInitialBundleStartLevel-int-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>

    <para>In addition, a bundle can be persistently marked as
    <emphasis>started</emphasis> or <emphasis>stopped</emphasis> with the
    <code>Bundle</code> <code>start</code> and <code>stop</code> methods. A
    bundle cannot run unless it is marked started, regardless of the bundle's
    start level.</para>

    <section xml:id="i1300852">
      <title>Changing the Active Start Level</title>

      <para>A management agent can influence the active start level with the
      <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel.setStartLevel-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The Framework must then increase or
      decrease the active start level by 1 until the requested start level is
      reached. The process of starting or stopping bundles, which is initiated
      by the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel.setStartLevel-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, must take place asynchronously.</para>

      <para>This means that the <emphasis>active start level</emphasis> (the
      one that is active at a certain moment in time) must be changed to a new
      start level, called the <emphasis>requested start level</emphasis>. The
      active and requested levels differ during a certain period when the
      Framework starts and stops the appropriate bundles. Moving from the
      active start level to the requested start level must take place in
      increments of one (1).</para>

      <para>If the requested start level is higher than the active start
      level, the Framework must increase the start level by one and then start
      all bundles that meet the following criteria:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Bundles that are persistently marked started, and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Bundles that have a bundle start level equal to the new active
          start level.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Framework continues increasing the active start level and
      starting the appropriate bundles until it has started all bundles with a
      bundle start level that equals the requested start level.</para>

      <para>The Framework must not increase to the next active start level
      until all started bundles have returned from their
      <code>BundleActivator.start</code> method normally or with an exception.
      A <code>FrameworkEvent.ERROR</code> must be broadcast when the
      <code>BundleActivator.start</code> method throws an exception.</para>

      <para>If the requested start level is lower than the active start level,
      the Framework must stop all bundles that have a bundle start level that
      is equal to the active start level. The Framework must then decrease the
      active start level by 1. If the active start level is still higher than
      the requested start level, it should continue stopping the appropriate
      bundles and decreasing the active start level until the requested start
      level is reached. A <code>FrameworkEvent.ERROR</code> must be broadcast
      when the <code>BundleActivator.stop</code> method throws an
      exception.</para>

      <para>If the requested start level is the active start level, the
      Framework will not start or stop any bundles.</para>

      <para>When the requested start level is reached and all bundles satisfy
      the condition that their bundle start level &lt;= active start level in
      order to be started, then the
      <code>FrameworkEvent.STARTLEVEL_CHANGED</code> event must be sent to all
      registered <code>FrameworkListener</code> objects. If the requested
      start level and active start level are equal, then this event may arrive
      before the <code>setStartLevel</code> method has returned.</para>

      <para>It must therefore always be true that:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A bundle is started, or will be started soon, if the start
          level is less or equal to the active start level.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A bundle is stopped, or will be stopped soon, when it has a
          start level more than the active start level.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>These steps are depicted in the flow chart in <xref
      linkend="i1300675"/>.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i1300675">
        <title>Move to requested start level R, active level is A, B is a
        bundle's start level</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.882in"
                       contentwidth="4.917in" fileref="startlevel-example.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If the Framework is currently involved in changing the active
      start level, it must first reach the previously requested start level
      before it is allowed to continue with a newly requested start level. For
      example, assume the active start level is 5 and the Framework is
      requested to transition to start level 3. Before start level 3 is
      reached, another request is made to transition to start level 7. In this
      case, the OSGi Framework must first complete the transition to start
      level 3 before it transitions to start level 7.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1334328">
      <title>Startup Sequence</title>

      <para>At startup, the Framework must have an active start level of zero.
      It must then move the active start level to the <emphasis>beginning
      start level</emphasis>. The beginning start level is specified with an
      argument when starting the Framework or through some other means, which
      is left undefined here. If no beginning start level is given, the
      Framework must assume a beginning start level of one (1).</para>

      <para>The Framework must launch and then set the requested start level
      to the beginning start level. It must then follow the procedure
      described in <xref linkend="i1300852"/> to make the active start level
      equal the beginning start level, with the exception of the
      <code>FrameworkEvent.START_LEVEL_CHANGED</code> event broadcast. During
      launching, the Framework must broadcast a
      <code>FrameworkEvent.STARTED</code> event when the beginning start level
      is reached.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1277583">
      <title>Shutdown Sequence</title>

      <para>When the Framework shuts down, the requested start level must be
      set to zero. The Framework must then follow the process described in
      <xref linkend="i1300852"/> to make the active start level equal to
      zero.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Changing a Bundle's Start Level</title>

      <para>Bundles are assigned an initial start level when they are
      installed. The default value for the initial start level is set to one,
      but can be changed with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel.setInitialBundleStartLevel-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method on the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object. A bundle's start level will not change
      when the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel.setInitialBundleStartLevel-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method later modifies the default initial start
      level.</para>

      <para>Once installed, the start level of a bundle can be changed with
      <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel.setStartLevel-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. When a bundle's start level is changed and the
      bundle is marked persistently to be started, then the OSGi Framework
      must compare the new bundle start level to the active start level. For
      example, assume that the active start level is 5 and a bundle with start
      level 5 is started. If the bundle's start level subsequently is changed
      to 6 then this bundle must be stopped by the OSGi Framework but it must
      still be marked persistently to be started.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Starting a Bundle</title>

      <para>If a bundle is started by calling the
      <code>Bundle.start</code> method, then the OSGi Framework must mark the
      bundle as persistently started. The OSGi Framework must not actually
      start a bundle when the active start level is less than the bundle's
      start level. In that case, the state must not change.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Exceptions in the Bundle Activator</title>

      <para>If the <code>BundleActivator.start</code> or <code>stop</code>
      method throws an <code>Exception</code>, then the handling of this
      <code>Exception</code> is different depending who invoked the
      <code>start</code> or <code>stop</code> method.</para>

      <para>If the bundle is started/stopped due to a change in the active
      start level or the bundle's start level, then the <code>Exception</code>
      must be wrapped in a <code>BundleException</code> and broadcast as a
      <code>FrameworkEvent.ERROR</code> event. Otherwise, a new
      <code>BundleException</code> must be created containing the exception
      and this <code>BundleException</code> is then thrown to the
      caller.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>System Bundle</title>

      <para>The System Bundle is defined to have a start level of zero. The
      start level of the System Bundle cannot be changed.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Example Applications</title>

    <para>The Start Level API allows a management agent to implement many
    different startup schemes. The following sections show some
    examples.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Safe Mode Startup Scheme</title>

      <para>A management agent can implement a <emphasis>safe mode</emphasis>
      in which it runs trusted bundles at level 1 and runs itself on level 2.
      When the management agent gets control, it constructs a list of all
      applications to be started. This list can be constructed from
      <code>BundleContext.getBundles()</code>. The management agent checks
      each bundle to determine if it is not started but is marked to be
      started persistently by calling the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel.isPersistentlyStarted--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method of the Start Level API.</para>

      <para>Before it starts each bundle, the management agent persistently
      records the bundle to be started and then starts the bundle. This
      continues until all bundles are started. When all bundles are
      successfully started, the management agent persistently records that all
      bundles started without problems.</para>

      <para>If the OSGi framework is restarted, the management agent should
      inspect the persistently recorded information. If the persistently
      recorded information indicates a bundle failure, the management agent
      should try to restart the system without that application bundle since
      that bundle failed. Alternatively, it could contact its Remote Manager
      and ask for assistance.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Splash Screen Startup Scheme</title>

      <para>A splash screen is a popup containing startup information about an
      application. The popup provides feedback to the end user indicating that
      the system is still initializing. The Start Level API can be used by a
      bundle to pop-up a splash screen before any other bundle is started, and
      remove it once all bundles have been started. The splash-screen bundle
      would start at start level 1 and all other bundles would start at start
      level 2 or higher.</para>

      <programlisting>class SplashScreen implements 
    BundleActivator, FrameworkListener {
    Screen         screen;
    public void start(BundleContext context) {
        context.addFrameworkListener( this );
        screen = createSplash();
        screen.open();
    }
    public void stop(BundleContext context) {
        screen.close();
    }
    public void frameworkEvent( FrameworkEvent event ) {
        if ( event.getType() == FrameworkEvent.STARTED )
            screen.close();
    }
    Screen createSplash() { ... }
}</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>The Start Level API requires Adapt Permission with action
    <code>ADAPT</code> for the following type:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel</code></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Start Level methods that mutate state require an additional
    Admin Permission with the action:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>EXECUTE</code> - For bundles that must be able to modify a
        bundle's start level</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>STARTLEVEL</code> - For modifying the Framework's active
        start level.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
