<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="55" revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="framework.servicehooks"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Service Hook Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The OSGi framework has built-in support for the normal service
    primitives: <emphasis>publish</emphasis>, <emphasis>find</emphasis>, and
    <emphasis>bind</emphasis>. Despite their simplicity, these primitives are
    surprisingly powerful and have become quite popular. However, these
    primitives operate on information that is not completely visible to the
    bundles. For example, it is impossible to find out what services are being
    waited upon by other bundles. This information can be useful to provide a
    service just in time to that bundle. Additionally, it is also not possible
    to allow bundles functionality that interacts with the service engine. For
    example, a bundle could proxy another service but to do this
    transparently, it is required to hide the original service and offer the
    proxy only to a specific bundle. With the current primitives this is also
    not possible.</para>

    <para>Therefore, this service hook specification provides a number of new
    mechanisms that closely interact with the service engine. These
    interactions are <emphasis>not</emphasis> intended for use by application
    bundles. The service primitives appear simple but require surprisingly
    complex code to make them appear simple to the bundle developer. Modifying
    the behavior of the service engine requires developers to closely follow
    the semantics of the OSGi service model and this is often hard, requiring
    a significant amount of code.</para>

    <para>However, the service hooks provide a more symmetric model for
    service based programming that can act as a multiplier for the framework.
    The basic framework provides a powerful service engine and this
    specification allows a bundle to interact with this service engine</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Robust</emphasis> - The service primitives are very
          simple and work reliably in many scenarios. The specified hooks
          interact with this robust service engine. This interaction must not
          cause disruption of the normal operations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Find listeners</emphasis> - Provide information
          about the services specific bundles are interested in.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Control visibility</emphasis> - Provide a mechanism
          to hide the visibility of a service to one or more bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Intercept finds</emphasis> - Provide a mechanism to
          detect the searches of a bundle in the service registry and restrict
          the set of found service references.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Whiteboard based</emphasis> - Use the <xref
          linkend="framework.servicehooks-whiteboard.pattern.ref"/> to
          simplify the writing of the interceptors.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Client</emphasis> - The bundle that finds services,
          gets services, and/or receives events about services.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Handler</emphasis> - The bundle that registers a
          hook service and uses this to view or modify the state.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Target</emphasis> - A client bundle being targeted
          by a Handler.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Publisher</emphasis> - A client bundle that
          publishes services.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Consumer</emphasis> - A client bundle that consumes
          services.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Service Engine</emphasis> - The internal framework
          machinery that makes the service registry work.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Listener Hook</emphasis> - An Event Listener
          Hook intercepts service events before they are delivered to the
          client. The hook can select to remove events for specific bundles,
          which effective allows the hook to hide service events from a
          bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Find Hook</emphasis> - A find hook intercepts the
          <code>getServiceReference(s)</code> call just before it is returns
          the result to the client. The result can be influenced by removing
          service entries. The find hook can be used to hide specific services
          for specific bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Listener Hook</emphasis> - The listener hook
          provides insight into what services are being waited for in the
          system. It gets updated as service listeners are added and removed
          from the service registry.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Service Hooks, org.osgi.framework.hooks.service package</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.865in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in"
                       fileref="servicehooks-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>A bundle that needs to hide service references from other bundles,
      or wants to be informed about the service events another bundle sees,
      can register a <emphasis>Find</emphasis> and <emphasis>Event
      Listener</emphasis> hook by registering a Find Hook service and an Event
      Listener Hook service with the framework. If a service event is
      generated, it will pass this event to the hook. The Event Listener Hook
      method can then inspect the arguments and optionally remove bundles from
      the event delivery list.</para>

      <para>When a bundle uses the Bundle Context getServiceReference or
      <code>getServiceReferences</code> method, the Find Hook is notified with
      the list of discovered services. The hook can then remove any service
      references it wants to hide for the target bundle.</para>

      <para>A bundle that wants to be aware of the services bundles are
      waiting for to be registered can register a Listener Hook. The framework
      will notify such hooks of all existing listeners as well as any changes
      in this list. The interceptor can use the filter information registered
      with the listener to detect the services that are being listened
      for.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Service Hooks</title>

    <para>Service hooks provide an interaction with the service engine. This
    service engine provides the following primitives to the bundle:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Register a service under an interface/class name with a set of
        properties</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Modify the set of properties of a service</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Unregister a service</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Find services based on their interface class name and/or
        property values</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Listen for the life cycle events of a service</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Service Primitives</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="0.954in"
                     contentwidth="4.951in" fileref="service-primitives.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>These primitives provide the cornerstone for <emphasis>service
    oriented programming</emphasis>. Service oriented programming consists of
    a code base that is de-coupled from the outside world through
    <emphasis>services</emphasis>. It can provide services to other bundles
    and it can consume services from other bundles. In the OSGi variation of
    service oriented programming, a service is a plain Java object that can be
    registered and unregistered at runtime.</para>

    <para>The dynamics of OSGi services forces bundles to consider the
    absence, presence, and arrival of services. The cause of these dynamics
    can be external events, the result of an update, a bundle that is stopped,
    or the disappearance of a dependent service. A number of support libraries
    have been developed to minimize the amount of work for the developer that
    these dynamics can bring. The dynamic nature of services have made them an
    excellent tool to handle a wide array of dependency scenarios. Services
    can easily model a real world concept that a bundle depends upon. The
    features of the service model combined with support libraries like iPOJO,
    Declarative Services, Spring DM, and others have made the OSGi service
    model easy to use and very powerful.</para>

    <para>A key aspect of the service model is the centrality of the OSGi
    framework. The service model acts as a guard between bundles. All service
    primitives pass through the framework and bundles can not intercept the
    result of other bundles interacting with the service registry. This design
    was intentional because it creates a boundary between bundles that
    increases robustness and security. However, the success of the service
    model also means that it becomes very attractive to interact with the
    service engine because all inter-bundle communication runs through this
    engine.</para>

    <para>For complexity reasons, this specification does not introduce any
    ordering dependencies between the handlers and the client bundles.</para>

    <para>All Service Hooks must be called in a privileged block, see <xref
    linkend="framework.lifecycle.privilegedcallbacks"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Usage Scenarios</title>

    <para>The service hooks are general mechanisms but they were designed for
    some specific use cases. The following sections detail some of those use
    cases.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Proxying</title>

      <para>In an OSGi system, all communication is normally tunneled through
      services. This makes it a very interesting place for a handler to
      intercept the service communications. These handlers can provide
      facilities like proxying, extra security, authentication, and other
      functions completely transparent to the parties that interact through
      services.</para>

      <para>Proxying an existing service for a specific bundle requires the
      following steps:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Hide the existing service X</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Register a proxy X' with the same properties as X</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Registering a proxy service X' is trivial with the OSGi API, there
      are no special requirements on the service. As long as it implements the
      listed interfaces and provides the same attributes then it can pose as
      service X.</para>

      <para>Hiding service X can be implemented with a combination of the
      Event Listener Hook and the Find Hook. The Event Listener Hook can be
      used to hide any service events from the target bundle and the Find Hook
      can be used to remove X from the delivered results of the
      <code>getServiceReference(s)</code> methods.</para>

      <para>In the following figure the difference between a normal service
      interaction and a proxied interaction is depicted. In the normal case,
      Bundle A directly uses Service X, in the proxying case, the Proxy Bundle
      hides the original and provides an alternative.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Normal and proxied service interaction</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.289in"
                       contentwidth="4.918in"
                       fileref="normal-proxied-interaction.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>However, there is one complication with the service hiding: what
      is the observing state of the target bundle when proxying begins? The
      Event Listener Hook must be registered to act as a filter on the service
      events. Just after this registration it can not determine what events
      have been seen by the target bundle. If it has already checked out X,
      the hook has no possibility to make the target bundle unget the service.
      A solution is to transiently stop the target bundle before the hook is
      registered and then transiently started it again, if the bundle is
      active. It is usually not advised to start/stop other bundles but this
      seems to be the only reliable solution. The problem can be alleviated
      when the start level is used to start the proxying handler bundle before
      the target bundles, in that case the target bundle is not started when
      the proxy is created. Though this optimizes the normal case, stopping
      the target bundle remains necessary because any of the bundles can be
      updated or stopped at any moment in time.</para>

      <para>The following example shows how to hide a specific Service
      Reference from a specific bundle.</para>

      <programlisting>public class Hide implementsEventListenerHook, FindHook {
    final Bundle           bundle;
    final ServiceReference reference;
    final BundleContext    context;
    ServiceRegistration    reg;

    Hide(BundleContext context, 
        ServiceReference reference, 
        Bundle bundle) {
        this.context = context;
        this.bundle = bundle;
        this.reference = reference;
    }

    void open() {
        boolean active = 
            bundle.getBundleState() == Bundle.ACTIVE;
        if ( active )
            bundle.stop(Bundle.STOP_TRANSIENTLY);
        reg = context.registerService(
            new String[] {
                FindHook.class.getName(),
                EventListenerHook.class.getName() }, this, null);
        if ( active )
            bundle.start(Bundle.START_TRANSIENTLY);
    }

    public void close() { reg.unregister();}</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>Hide</code> class registers a Event Listener Hook and
      Find Hook service in the open method. Once registered, these services
      will receive their event callbacks. In the find hook, the target Service
      Reference is removed from the results if the bundle that called the
      <code>getServiceReference(s)</code> method is the target bundle.</para>

      <programlisting>    public void find(BundleContext ctx, 
        String name, String filter,
        boolean allServices, Collection refs) {
        if (ctx.getBundle() == bundle) {
            refs.remove(reference);
        }
    }</programlisting>

      <para>The event method is the opposite of the find method. In this
      method, the target bundle is removed from the event destinations if the
      related Service Reference is the target Service Reference.</para>

      <programlisting>    public void event(ServiceEvent event, 
        Collection bundles) {
        if (event.getServiceReference().equals(
            reference)) 
            bundles.remove(bundle);
    }
}</programlisting>

      <para>Once the Hide class is working, a proxy can be registered. For
      example:</para>

      <programlisting>void startProxy(ServiceReference ref,Bundlefor,
        Object proxy ) {
    Hide hide = new Hide(ctx, ref, for);
    hide.open();
    ServiceRegistration reg = ctx.registerService(
        (String[]) ref.getProperty("objectClass"),
        proxy,
        makeProperties(ref)  // copy the properties
    );
}
...</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Providing a Service on Demand</title>

      <para>The Listener Hook provides information about services that bundles
      are listening for. This makes it possible to look outside the OSGi
      framework to see if a listened for service could be provided in another
      way. For example, this service could come from Jini, SLP, or through
      some other means.</para>

      <para>A Listener Hook receives events every time a bundle adds or
      removes a Service Listener. The Listener Hook is called with an
      <code>added</code> and <code>removed</code> method that take a
      collection of <code>ListenerInfo</code> objects. These objects provide
      the identity of the bundle that added a Service Listener and the
      optional filter string. The Listener Hook can use this filter string to
      look for specific properties, for example the <code>objectClass</code>
      property to determine the type that is being sought. Extracting the
      property from this filter string is non-trivial though regular
      expressions can in general be used to extract the needed
      information.</para>

      <para>The following class uses an unexplained Track object to do the low
      level details. The example only shows how the Listener Hook can interact
      with these track objects.</para>

      <programlisting>public class OnDemand implements ListenerHook{
    final BundleContext context;
    final Map           tracked = HashMap();
    ServiceRegistration reg;</programlisting>

      <para>The constructor saves the Bundle Context. The registration is done
      in an open method.</para>

      <programlisting>    public OnDemand(BundleContext context) {
        this.context = context; }
    public void open() {
        reg = context.registerService(
            ListenerHook.class.getName(), this, null); }</programlisting>

      <para>The Listener Hook has added and removed methods that take
      collections. It is easier to handle the concurrency per object.</para>

      <programlisting>    public void added(Collection listeners) {
        for (Iterator i=listeners.iterator(); i.hasNext();) {
            add((ListenerHook.ListenerInfo) i.next());
    } }
    public void removed(Collection listeners) {
        for (Iterator i=listeners.iterator(); i.hasNext();) {
            remove((ListenerHook.ListenerInfo) i.next());
    } }</programlisting>

      <para>In the add hook, a <code>ListenerInfo</code> object provides the
      information about the Service Listener. In this example, a
      <code>Track</code> object is created for each active listener and
      associated with the given info object. This requires proper
      synchronization and should handle the rare case that the events are
      delivered out of order. The <code>ListenerInfo</code> object contains an
      <code>isRemoved</code> method that provides this information. If it is
      true, the corresponding removed event has already been called or will be
      called very soon. In that case, it is safe to discard the added event.
      For proper cleanup, the reg field is tested to see if it is set, if not,
      this call is during closing and should be ignored.</para>

      <programlisting>    synchronized void add(ListenerHook.ListenerInfoinfo) {
        if ( reg == null || info.isRemoved() )
            return;

        Track t = new Track(info);
        tracked.put(info, t);
        t.open();
    }</programlisting>

      <para>To remove a Track object it is necessary to consult the tracked
      map. If the track object is in the map, it must be closed. If not, there
      is an out of order delivery and this event can be ignored, the add
      method will ignore the corresponding <code>ListenerInfo</code> object
      because the <code>isRemoved</code> flag will be set. For proper closing,
      the reg field is tested for <code>null</code>.</para>

      <programlisting>    synchronized void remove(ListenerHook.ListenerInfoinfo){
        if ( reg == null )
            return;
        Track t = tracked.remove(info);
        if ( t != null ) 
            t.close();
    }</programlisting>

      <para>The close method is straightforward. The hook services are
      unregistered and all the remaining <code>Track</code> objects are
      closed. The reg field is used to make sure the event methods are
      ignoring any outstanding calls by setting it to <code>null</code>. After
      the synchronized block, any incoming event is ignored.</para>

      <programlisting>    public void close() {
        reg.unregister();
        synchronized(this) { reg = null; }
        for ( Track t : tracked.values() ) { t.close(); }
        tracked.clear();    }  }</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Event Listener Hook</title>

    <para>To intercept events being delivered to bundles, a handler must
    register an <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.EventListenerHook"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object as a service with the framework. The
    framework must then send a service events to all the registered hooks. The
    calling order of the hooks is defined by the reversed
    <code>compareTo</code> ordering of their Service Reference objects. That
    is, the service with the highest ranking number is called first. Event
    Listener Hooks are called <emphasis>after</emphasis> the event is
    generated but <emphasis>before</emphasis> they are filtered by the
    optional filter expressions of the service listeners. Before the return,
    the handler can remove bundles from the given list. This allows an Event
    Listener Hook to hide service events for specific bundles.</para>

    <para>The model is depicted in the <xref linkend="i1664951"/>. A target
    bundle listens for service events but these events can be filtered by the
    handler because it has registered an Event Listener Hook service that is
    accepted by the Framework.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1664951">
      <title>Event Listener Hook Interaction</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.881in"
                     contentwidth="4.976in" fileref="eventlistenerhook.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>An Event Listener Hook receives all events, <code>REGISTERED</code>,
    <code>MODIFIED</code>, <code>UNREGISTERING</code>, and
    <code>MODIFIED_ENDMATCH</code>, that are to be delivered to all Service
    Listener objects registered with the framework, regardless of the presence
    of a service listener filter.</para>

    <para>The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.EventListenerHook"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> class has a single method:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.EventListenerHook.event-ServiceEvent-Map-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A service event has been generated. The
        implementer of this method can optionally shrink the given map of
        target bundles to service listeners.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>One of the parameters of the <code>event</code> method is a map of
    target bundles to a collection of <code>ListenerInfo</code> objects. The
    handler can shrink this map by removing bundles as well as specific
    service listeners from the collection of <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.ListenerHook.ListenerInfo"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> objects. Both the map and the collection must
    therefore implement the appropriate remove methods.</para>

    <para>Removing a bundle from the list of target bundles will effectively
    hide the service event from the target bundle. The target bundle can still
    get the service, though the Find Hook can be used to block this access to
    the service.</para>

    <para>Implementers of the Event Listener Hook must ensure that target
    bundles continue to see a consistent set of service events. Service events
    are normally used in a state machine. Such state machines can get confused
    if some events are missed. For example, if a Service Tracker sees a
    <code>REGISTERED</code> event but is hidden from the corresponding
    <code>UNREGISTERING</code> event then the service will never be released.
    A simple solution is to stop the target bundle when the filter is put in
    place. However, when the bundle that implements the Event Listener Hook is
    stopped, it will of course no longer be able to filter events and the
    target bundle might see an service events for services it was not aware
    of.</para>

    <section>
      <title>System Service Listeners</title>

      <para>Service Listeners may be registered with the system bundle's
      <code>BundleContext</code>. If at least one Service Listener is
      registered with the system bundle's <code>BundleContext</code> then the
      system bundle's <code>BundleContext</code> must be contained in the keys
      of the shrinkable map passed to the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.EventListenerHook.event-ServiceEvent-Map-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. Just like other
      <code>BundleContext</code> keys contained in the shrinkable map, the
      system bundle's <code>BundleContext</code> may be removed. If the system
      bundle's <code>BundleContext</code> is removed by a service Event
      Listener Hook then the <code>BundleContext</code> will not be contained
      in the map for the remaining service Event Listener Hooks called. Unlike
      other <code>BundleContext</code> objects, if the system bundle's
      <code>BundleContext</code> is removed from the shrinkable map then the
      service event is still delivered to the Service Listeners added to the
      system bundle's <code>BundleContext</code>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Find Hook</title>

    <para>The Find Hook is called when a target bundle searches the service
    registry with the <code>getServiceReference</code> or
    <code>getServiceReferences</code> methods. A registered Find Hook service
    gets a chance to inspect the returned set of service references and can
    optionally shrink the set of returned services. The order in which the
    find hooks are called is the reverse <code>compareTo</code> ordering of
    their Service References. That is, the service with the highest ranking
    number must be called first.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.FindHook.find-BundleContext-String-String-boolean-Collection-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The callback when a bundle calls the
        <code>getServiceReference</code>, <code>getServiceReferences</code>,
        or <code>getAllServiceReferences</code> method. As parameters, it gets
        the bundle context of the calling bundle, the service name, the filter
        name, the flag that indicates that all services are considered or only
        the ones that are class compatible with the target bundle. The last
        parameter is the set of service references that will be returned. This
        list can be shortened by removing service references form the given
        list.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The purpose of the Find Hook is to limit the visibility of services
    to selected target bundles. For this reason, the hook implementation can
    remove selected service references from the result collection.</para>

    <section>
      <title>System Bundle Context</title>

      <para>When one of the <code>getServiceReference</code> or
      <code>getServiceReferences</code> methods is called using the system
      bundle's <code>BundleContext</code> then the service Find Hooks are
      called in the same way the hooks are called when a normal
      <code>BundleContext</code> is used. The system bundle's
      <code>BundleContext</code> along with the shrinkable candidate service
      references collection is passed to the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.FindHook.find-BundleContext-String-String-boolean-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. Service Find Hooks may remove service
      references from the shrinkable collection. If a service reference is
      removed by a service Find Hook then the service reference will not be
      contained in the collection for the remaining service find hooks called.
      Unlike other <code>BundleContext</code> objects, if the system bundle's
      <code>BundleContext</code> is used to find services then the Framework
      ignores the service reference removals performed by the service Find
      Hooks and allows the service references removed to remain visible in the
      find results.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Listener Hook</title>

    <para>The Framework API provides extensive insight in the registration,
    modification, and unregistration of services. However, it does not provide
    the information about what services bundles are waiting for. It is a
    common pattern that a bundle waits for a service to arrive before it is
    able to perform its function, having the knowledge what bundles are
    waiting for, allows a number of interesting scenarios.</para>

    <para>The Listener Hook is a <xref
    linkend="framework.servicehooks-whiteboard.pattern.ref"/> service that is
    informed about the coming and going of all service listeners. When a
    Listener Hook service is registered with the Framework, the Framework will
    inform this service of all existing listeners and keep it updated of all
    removed and newly registered service listeners. The events are dispatched
    in order of the Listener Hook service registration.</para>

    <para>In the following figure, it is depicted how the interceptor can find
    out about target bundles listening for services. It
    <emphasis>listens</emphasis> to registration and unregistration of Service
    Listeners.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Listener Hook Interaction</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.129in"
                     contentwidth="4.976in" fileref="listenerhook.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The <code>ListenerHook</code> interface is composed of the following
    methods:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.ListenerHook.added-Collection-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Inform the hook of the registered listeners.
        The collection is immutable and contains <code>ListenerInfo</code>
        objects. These objects identify a unique <code>ServiceListener</code>
        object registration with the framework. They provide the registering
        bundle as well as the optional filter. The <code>ListenerInfo</code>
        class is nested class of the <code>ListenerHook</code> class.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.ListenerHook.removed-Collection-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> -Inform the hook of listeners that have been
        removed because the bundle is stopped or the bundle implementation has
        unregistered a listener. The <code>ListenerInfo</code> objects are
        equal to their corresponding Info Listener object during the
        addition.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The <code>ListenerHook.ListenerInfo</code> class provides the
    following methods:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.ListenerHook.ListenerInfo.getBundleContext--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Bundle Context of the bundle that
        registered the service listener.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.ListenerHook.ListenerInfo.getFilter--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The filter used in the registration.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.ListenerHook.ListenerInfo.isRemoved--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Provides information if this Listener Info
        is still valid.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A <code>ListenerInfo</code> object is related to the registration of
    a <code>ServiceListener</code> with the Framework. The Framework maintains
    only one registration for a specific, identity based, Service Listener
    object. That is, registering the same object again, even with a different
    filter, will automatically unregister the previous registration. This will
    be visible as a <code>removed</code> - <code>added</code> pair of
    calls.</para>

    <para>The <code>equality</code> and <code>hashCode</code> method of a
    <code>ListenerInfo</code> object must guarantee that the hook can place
    the Listener Info objects in hashed collections, such that an
    <code>ListenerInfo</code> object received in the <code>added</code>
    method's collection parameter matches its corresponding
    <code>ListenerInfo</code> object in the <code>removed</code> method's
    collection parameter. This is trivially met by the identity
    <code>equals</code> and <code>hashCode</code> methods if the same objects
    are used in both methods.</para>

    <para>The reason the Listener Hook provides methods that take collection
    instead of a single <code>ListenerInfo</code> object is because of
    performance optimization. When a Listener Hook service gets registered,
    there can already be a large number of Service Listeners available.
    Similarly, when a bundle gets stopped, it could have registered a number
    of service listeners that then need to be unregistered. Being able to
    provide all changes in a batch improves performance.</para>

    <para>The framework must report each registration of a Service Listener
    with the Bundle Context with a new <code>ListenerInfo</code> object that
    is unequal to any other <code>ListenerInfo</code> object. If the same
    Service Listener object is registered multiple times, each previous
    registration must be removed before the listener is added again.</para>

    <para>The <code>event</code> method in a Listener Hook is called
    synchronously with the registration of the Service Listener to minimize
    the overhead for the framework. However, this does not imply that delivery
    is always ordered. There are rare cases where a removal is reported before
    the corresponding addition. Handling this case is simplified by the
    <code>isRemoved</code> method. If the <code>removed</code> and
    <code>added</code> methods are synchronized, then the
    <code>isRemoved</code> method can be used in the <code>added</code> method
    to detect the out of order delivery. A simple strategy is to ignore
    removed events without corresponding added events and ignore added events
    where the <code>ListenerInfo</code> object is already removed.</para>

    <para>The following code shows a skeleton of how the Listener Hook methods
    can be implemented.</para>

    <programlisting>final HashMap tracked = new HashMap();

public void added( Collection lis ) {
    for ( Iterator li = lis.iterator(); li.hasNext(); ) {   
        ListenerHook.ListenerInfo li =
            (ListenerHook.ListenerInfo) li.next();
        synchronized(tracked) {
            if ( li.isRemoved() )
                return;
            ... create some object t
            tracked.put( li, t );
        }
  }
}
public void removed( Collection lis ) {
    for ( Iterator li = lis.iterator(); li.hasNext(); ) {   
        ListenerHook.ListenerInfo li =
            (ListenerHook.ListenerInfo) li.next();
        synchronized(tracked) {
            Object t =  tracked.remove( li );
            if ( t != null )
                ... dispose object t
        }
  }
}</programlisting>

    <section>
      <title>Filter</title>

      <para>A key concept in the Listener Hook is the filter. When a bundle is
      interested in a specific set of services, it registers a service
      listener with a filter. This filter is an indication of what services
      are interesting to the target bundle. The <code>objectclass</code>
      property holds the names of the interfaces and classes. However, just
      searching for this property with a regular expression is not guaranteed
      to return a usable value. The form of the sub-expressions can make the
      property part of an and or even negate. For example, looking for the
      <code>objectclass</code> in the following expression gives a result that
      is the opposite of what is searched.</para>

      <programlisting>(!(objectclass=org.osgi.service.cm.ConfigurationAdmin))</programlisting>

      <para>However, understanding a full filter expression is quite
      difficult. An acceptable strategy is to look for the object classes in
      the filter string with a regular expression but evaluate the filter
      against any conclusions that are being drawn. That is, testing a
      Configuration Admin service against the filter in the previous example
      will not match.</para>

      <para>Realistically, many scenarios that are enabled by the Listener
      Hook will require the filters to have a simple structure.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Architectural Notes</title>

    <section>
      <title>Remove Only</title>

      <para>The Event Listener Hook and Find Hook both allow the interceptor
      to remove elements from a collection and not add elements. The reason is
      that adding almost inevitably violates framework invariants that can
      trip the receivers. These invariants are very important to keep the
      programming model for the bundle developers simple.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Ordinary Services</title>

      <para>All service hooks are treated as ordinary services. If the
      framework uses them, their Service References will show that the system
      bundle is using them, and if a hook is a Service Factory, then the
      actual instance will be properly created.</para>

      <para>The only special treatment of the service hooks is that the
      framework must not use them for the hooks themselves. That is, the Event
      and Find Hooks can not be used to hide the services from the
      framework.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Ordering</title>

      <para>The hooks are very sensitive to ordering because they modify the
      basic behavior of the OSGi Framework. Before a hook is registered, a
      client bundle interacts with the framework directly. However, ordering
      in an OSGi Framework can never be relied upon from an programmer's
      perspective. It is bad practice to rely on start level ordering in a
      program because updates and other disturbances will inevitably break
      this ordering. Start level ordering is a tool for deployers to smoothen
      initialization problems, not to handle ordering dependencies.</para>

      <para>Implementers of the hooks must therefore be intricately aware that
      they can be started before or after their target bundles are
      started.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Providing the Service Object</title>

      <para>Many scenarios for the hooks specified here could be simplified by
      being able to intercept the <code>getService</code> call of the target
      bundle. This design was investigated and rejected because it created a
      dependency graph (registering bundle, proxying bundle, and target
      bundle) that could not be properly managed in a dynamic OSGi system. For
      example, if a proxying bundle provides an alternative implementation for
      a service, how does the receiving bundle know that it should stop using
      this service? It has no knowledge that the proxying bundle even exists.
      Instead of creating a much more complex service registry, it was decided
      to keep the model simple and reuse the existing primitives. This puts
      the complexity at implementing the hooks, but leaves the overall service
      model simple.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Multi Threading</title>

      <para>All hooks in this specification must be thread safe because the
      hooks can be called any time. All hook methods must be re-entrant, the
      framework can enter them at any time, and in rare cases in the wrong
      order. Most methods will be called synchronously with framework
      activities. It is fully allowed to call the framework from any of the
      hook methods. However, even more than usual, it is highly recommended to
      not hold any locks while calling the framework.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>All hooks described in this specification are highly complex
    facilities that require great care in their implementation to maintain the
    Framework invariants concerning the service registry. It is therefore
    important that in a secure system the permission to register these hooks
    is only given to privileged bundles.</para>

    <para>In this case, the user of the hook services is the framework.
    Therefore, there is never a need to provide:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>ServicePermission[..EventListenerHook,GET]</code>,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>ServicePermission[..FindHook,GET]</code>, or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>ServicePermission[..ListenerHook,GET]</code></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Implementers of these hooks must have:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>ServicePermission[..EventListenerHook,REGISTER]</code> for
        Event Listener Hook services.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>ServicePermission[..FindHook,REGISTER]</code> for Find
        Hook services</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>ServicePermission[..ListenerHook,REGISTER]</code> for
        Listener Hook services</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.framework.hooks.service.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="framework.servicehooks-whiteboard.pattern.ref"><title>Whiteboard
      Pattern</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://docs.osgi.org/whitepaper/whiteboard-pattern/"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
