<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright (c) Contributors to the Eclipse Foundation
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
   
    SPDX-License-Identifier: Apache-2.0 
 -->

<chapter label="133"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="service.loader"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Service Loader Mediator Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.serviceloader-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.serviceloader"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Java SE 6 introduced the <emphasis>Service Loader</emphasis>, a
    simple service-provider loading facility, that attempted to unify the
    different ad-hoc mechanisms used by Java's many factories and builders.
    The design allows a JAR to advertise the name of one or more embedded
    classes that implement a given interface and consumers to obtain instances
    of these implementation classes through the Service Loader API.</para>

    <para>Though the Service Loader is about extensibility, its own design is
    closed and therefore not extendable. It does not support a provider model
    that would allow different ways of finding interface implementations; its
    classes are final and its policy is fixed. Unfortunately, the Service
    Loader's fixed design uses a non-modular class loading policy; it defines
    its visibility scope with a class loader, which in general requires full
    visibility of the application's class path. The Service Loader can
    therefore in OSGi not find implementations from other bundles.
    Additionally, the Service Loader also does not enforce a life cycle;
    objects are handed out forever.</para>

    <para>Since the Service Loader is the only standardized plugin mechanism
    in the JRE it is necessary that the mechanism is supported in OSGi with as
    few changes as possible from the consumer's authors. This specification
    therefore defines a <emphasis>mediator</emphasis> that ensures that the
    Service Loader is useful in an OSGi Framework, allowing programs that
    leverage the Service Loader to be used in OSGi frameworks almost
    as-is.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Compatibility</emphasis> - Allow JARs that run in a
          classic Java SE environment that leverage the Service Loader to run
          in OSGi with only manifest modifications.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Services</emphasis> - Register services for Service
          Provider bundles that opt-in.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Security</emphasis> - Enforce service permissions
          for the Service Loader objects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Life Cycle</emphasis> - Manage the life cycle
          mismatch between OSGi bundles and the Service Loader's create only
          model.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Service Loader</emphasis> - An API in Java SE that
          allows a Consumer to find an implementation of a Service Type from a
          Service Provider by searching a class loader for Service
          Providers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Service Type</emphasis> - The interface or class
          that the Service Provider must implement/extend.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Provider Configuration File</emphasis> - A resource
          in the <code>META-INF/services</code> directory that has the fully
          qualified name of the Service Type and contains one ore more fully
          qualified names of Service Providers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Service Provider</emphasis> - An implementation
          class that implements or extends the Service Type.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Consumer</emphasis> - A class that uses the Java SE
          Service Loader inside an OSGi framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Mediator</emphasis> - An extender that mediates
          between Consumer bundles, the Service Loader API, and Service
          Provider bundles in an OSGi environment. It consists of a Processor
          and a Registrar.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Processor</emphasis> - Modifies a bundle that uses
          the Service Loader API so that it works in an OSGi
          environment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Registrar</emphasis> - Registers services on behalf
          of a bundle that contains Service Providers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure pgwide="1">
        <title>Entities</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.278in"
                       contentwidth="6.209in"
                       fileref="serviceloader-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>This specification defines two different functions that are
      provided by a Mediator extender:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Register OSGi services for each Service Provider.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allow Consumers that uses the Service Loader API to access
          Service Providers from other bundles that would normally not be
          visible from a bundle.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A Service Provider bundle can provide access to all its Service
      Providers through OSGi services by declaring a requirement on the
      <code>osgi.serviceloader.registrar</code> extender. This requirement
      activates a Mediator to inspect the <code>osgi.serviceloader</code>
      capabilities. If no <code>register</code> directive is used then all
      Service Providers for the given Service Type must be registered.
      Otherwise, each capability can select one Service Provider with the
      <code>register</code> directive. The fully qualified name selects a
      specific Service Provider, allowing different Service Providers to be
      registered with different service properties. The Mediator will then
      register an OSGi service factory for each selected capability. The
      <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capability's attributes are used to
      decorate the OSGi service registration with service properties. The
      service factory returns a new instance for each service get.</para>

      <para>Consumers are classes that use the Service Loader API to find
      Service Provider instances. Since the Service Loader API requires full
      visibility the Service API fails to work inside an OSGi bundle. A
      <code>osgi.serviceloader.processor</code> extender, which is the
      Mediator, processes bundles that require this capability by modifying
      calls to the Service Loader API to ensures that the Service Loader has
      visibility to published Service Providers.</para>

      <para>A Consumer's bundle by default receives visibility to all
      published Service Providers. Service Providers are published when a
      bundle declares one or more <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capabilities
      for a Service Type. If the Consumer has an
      <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> requirement for the given Service Type
      then the Mediator must only expose the bundles that are wired to those
      requirements and for each bundle provide all its Service
      Providers.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i3285425">
    <title>Java Service Loader API</title>

    <para>Java is quite unique with its focus on separation of
    <emphasis>specification</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>implementation</emphasis>. Virtually all Java Specification
    Requests (JSR) provide a specification that can be implemented
    independently by different parties. Though this is one of the industry's
    best practices it raises a new problem: how to find the implementation
    available in a Java environment from only the <emphasis>Service
    Type</emphasis>. A Service Type is usually an interface but a base class
    can also be used.</para>

    <para>Finding a Service Provider (the implementation class) from a Service
    Type is the so called <emphasis>instance coupling</emphasis> problem. The
    use of Service Types removed the type coupling between the Consumer of the
    contract and the <emphasis>Service Provider</emphasis> of the contract
    (the implementation) but to make things work there is a need of at least
    one place where the Service Provider is instantiated. The very large
    number of factories in Java reflects that this is a very common
    problem.</para>

    <para>The general pattern for factories to find Service Providers was to
    search the class loaders for classes with constant names, varying the
    package names, often using System properties to extend the different areas
    to be sought. Though a general pattern based on class loading tricks
    emerged in the Java VM and application programs, all these patterns
    differed in details and places where they looked. This became harder and
    harder to maintain and often caused unexpected instances to be
    found.</para>

    <para>The <code>java.util.ServiceLoader</code> class was therefore first
    introduced in Java SE 6 to provide a generic solution to this problem, see
    <xref linkend="i3255894"/>. With this API Service Providers of a
    specification can now <emphasis>advertise</emphasis> their availability by
    creating a <emphasis>Provider Configuration File</emphasis> in their JAR
    in the <code>META-INF/services</code> directory. The name of this resource
    is the fully qualified name of the Service Type, the Service Provider
    provides when instantiated.</para>

    <para>The Provider Configuration File contains a number of lines with
    comments or a class name that implements/extends the Service Type. For
    example:</para>

    <programlisting>org.example.Foo</programlisting>

    <para>A Service Provider must then advertise itself like:</para>

    <programlisting>META-INF/services/org.example.Foo:
    # Foo implementation
    org.acme.impl.FooImplementation</programlisting>

    <para>The Service Loader API finds all advertisers by constructing the
    name of the Provider Configuration File from the Service Type and then
    calling the <code>getResources</code> method on the provided class loader.
    This returns an enumeration of URLs to the advertisements. It then parses
    the contents of the resources; that will provide it with a list of Service
    Providers for the sought Service Type without duplicates. The API will
    return an iterator that will instantiate an object for the next available
    Service Provider.</para>

    <para>To find the Configuration files for a given Service Type, the
    Service Loader uses a class loader. The Consumer can select the following
    class loaders:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A given class loader as an argument in the call to the
        constructor</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Thread Context Class Loader (TCCL)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The system loader (when <code>null</code> is passed or no TCCL
        is set)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The class loader restricts the visibility of the Service Loader to
    only the resources to which the class loader has visibility. If the
    Service Loader has no access to the advertisement of a Service Provider
    then it cannot detect it and it will thus not be found.</para>

    <para>The Service Provider is loaded from the given class loader, however,
    the <code>Class.forName</code> method is used, which stores it in the
    cache of the initiating class loader. This means that Service Providers
    are not garbage collected as long as there is a resolved bundle that used
    the Service Loader to get that Service Provider.</para>

    <para>In the Service Loader API, the class does not have to originate from
    the same JAR file as the advertisement. In OSGi this is more restricted,
    the advertisement must come from the same bundle or must be explicitly
    imported.</para>

    <para>For example, to load a <code>Foo</code> instance the following code
    could be used:</para>

    <programlisting>ServiceLoader&lt;Foo&gt; sl =
    ServiceLoader.load( Foo.class );
Iterator&lt;Foo&gt; it = sl.iterator();
if ( it.hasNext() ) {
    Foo foo = it.next();
    ... 
}</programlisting>

    <para>Though the Service Loader API is about extensibility and contract
    based programming it is in itself not extendable nor replaceable. The
    <code>ServiceLoader</code> class is <code>final</code>, it comes from a
    sealed JAR, and is in a <code>java</code> package. It also does not
    provide an API to provide alternate means to find implementations for a
    Service Type.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Consumers</title>

    <para><emphasis>Consumers</emphasis> are classes that are not OSGi aware
    and directly use the <emphasis>Service Loader API</emphasis>. The Service
    Loader has a non-modular design and Consumers therefore run into many
    issues when running in an OSGi framework. Consumers should therefore in
    general be converted to use the OSGi service layer since this solves the
    visibility issues, life cycle impedance mismatch, and other problems. The
    Consumer part of this specification is therefore a last resort to use when
    existing code uses the Service Loader API and cannot be modified to
    leverage the OSGi service layer.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Processing</title>

      <para>The Service Loader Mediator can <emphasis>process</emphasis> the
      Consumer by modifying calls to the Service Loader API. This
      specification does not detail how the Mediator ensures that the Consumer
      has visibility to other Service Providers. However, a Mediator could for
      example set an appropriate Thread Context Class Loader during the call
      to the Service Loader's constructor by weaving the Consumer's byte
      codes.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Opting In</title>

      <para>Processing is an opt-in process, the Consumer bundle must declare
      that it is willing to be processed. The opt-in is handled by a
      requirement to the <code>osgi.serviceloader.processor</code> extender.
      This requirement must have a <code>single</code> cardinality (the
      default) since the Mediator uses the wiring to select the Consumer to
      process when multiple Mediators are present.</para>

      <para>For example, the following requirement in a manifest enables a
      bundle to be processed:</para>

      <programlisting>Require-Capability:
    osgi.extender;
        filter:="(&amp;(osgi.extender=osgi.serviceloader.processor)
                 (version&gt;=1.0)(!(version&gt;=2.0)))"</programlisting>

      <para>If the extender <code>osgi.serviceloader.processor</code>
      requirement is satisfied then the wired Mediator must process the
      Consumer.</para>

      <para>The Mediator must give visibility to all bundles with
      <emphasis>published</emphasis> Service Providers unless the Consumer
      restricts the visibility by having <code>osgi.serviceloader</code>
      requirements. Bundles publish a Service Type, meaning all their Service
      Providers for that type, by having at least one
      <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capability for that Service Type.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Restricting Visibility</title>

      <para>A Consumer's bundle can restrict its visibility to certain bundles
      by declaring an <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> requirement for each
      Service Type it wants to use. Only bundles wired from those requirement
      provide their advertised Service Providers. If no such requirements are
      declared then all bundles with the published Service Type become
      available.</para>

      <para>The cardinality can be used to select a single Service Provider's
      bundle or multiple bundles if it needs to see all Service Provider
      bundles. The requirement can be made optional if the Consumer's bundle
      can work also when no Service Provider bundle is available. See <xref
      linkend="i3280141"/> for more details.</para>

      <para>For example, a requirement that restricts visibility to the
      <code>org.example.Foo</code> Service Providers could look like:</para>

      <programlisting>Require-Capability:                             
    osgi.serviceloader;
    filter:="(osgi.serviceloader=org.example.Foo)";
    cardinality:=multiple</programlisting>

      <para>In this example, any bundle that publishes the
      <code>org.example.Foo</code> Service Type will contribute its Service
      Providers.</para>

      <para>Visibility can also be restricted to bundles that publish with
      capability's attributes. Any bundle that has at least one matching
      capability will then be able to contribute all its Service Providers.
      For example, the following example selects only bundles that have the
      <code>classified</code> property set:</para>

      <programlisting>osgi.serviceloader; filter:="(classified=*)"</programlisting>

      <para>With Service Registrations, see <xref linkend="i3280881"/>, the
      capability can discriminate between multiple Service Providers in the
      same bundle. The Service Loader API does not have this feature: any
      wired requirement has visibility to all Service Providers in the wired
      bundle, regardless of the <code>registered</code> directive.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Life Cycle Impedance Mismatch</title>

      <para>A Consumer can only see Service Provider instances of bundles that
      are active during the time the next instance is created. That is, the
      Mediator must treat the life cycle of the Service Provider as if it was
      a service. However, the Service Loader implementations perform extensive
      class loader techniques and cache results. The exact life cycle of the
      Service Provider bundle with respect to the Consumer is therefore
      impossible to enforce.</para>

      <para>The Service Loader API does not have a life cycle, objects are
      assumed to stay alive during the duration of the VM's process and due to
      the use of <code>Class.forName</code> in the Service Loader
      implementations. Therefore a Mediator should refresh a Consumer bundle
      when it is using a Service Provider and that Service Provider's bundle
      becomes stopped otherwise long running applications can run out of
      memory when bundles are regularly updated.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3252894">
      <title>Consumer Example</title>

      <para>A legacy JAR for which there is no more source code uses the
      Service Loader API to get access to <code>com.example.Codec</code>
      instances through the Service Loader API.</para>

      <para>It is wrapped in a bundle that then has the following
      manifest:</para>

      <programlisting>Manifest-Version:       1.0
Bundle-ManifestVersion: 2
Bundle-SymbolicName:    com.example.impl
Bundle-Version:         23.98.1.v199101232310.02011
Import-Package:         com.example; version=3.45
Bundle-ClassPath:       legacy.jar</programlisting>

      <para>The manifest must then declare that the bundle must be processed,
      this is triggered by requiring the
      <code>osgi.serviceloader.processor</code> extender:</para>

      <programlisting>Require-Capability:                                         
  osgi.extender;
    filter:="(&amp;(osgi.extender=osgi.serviceloader.processor)
             (version&gt;=1.0)(!(version&gt;=2.0)))"</programlisting>

      <para>With this manifest, the Consumer bundle has full visibility to all
      Service Provider bundles that are published. The following lines can be
      added to restrict the visibility to codecs that have support for
      <code>WAVE</code> formats (although all Service Providers in that bundle
      will be visible to the consumer).</para>

      <programlisting>,
    osgi.serviceloader;
     filter:="(&amp;(format=WAVE)(osgi.serviceloader=com.example.Codec))"</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Service Provider Bundles</title>

    <para>A <emphasis>Service Provider bundle</emphasis> is a bundle that
    contains one or more Service Providers that are usable by the Service
    Loader API. This section shows how Service Provider bundles should be
    constructed and what options they have.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Advertising</title>

      <para><emphasis>Service Providers</emphasis> are implementation classes
      that are <emphasis>advertised</emphasis> under a Service Type according
      to the rules in the Service Loader API. A Service Provider is advertised
      with a <emphasis>Provider Configuration File</emphasis> in a JAR. In an
      OSGi environment the Service Provider must reside in the same bundle as
      the advertisement or be imported. A single Provider Configuration File
      can contain multiple Service Providers. See <xref
      linkend="i3285425"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Publishing the Service Providers</title>

      <para>Service Providers can be used in two different scenarios:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A Service Provider can be used by a processed Consumer as a
          Service Type, or</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It can be registered as a service.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A Service Type must be <emphasis>published</emphasis> to allow its
      use it in these scenarios. Publishing a Service Type consists of
      providing one or more <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capabilities for
      an advertised Service Type, see <xref linkend="i3280141"/>. These
      <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capabilities must specify a fully
      qualified class name of the Service Type, there is no wildcarding
      allowed. Therefore, publishing a service implicitly makes all
      corresponding Service Providers available to Consumers.</para>

      <para>If a bundle does not provide <code>osgi.serviceloader</code>
      capabilities then it does not publish any Service Providers and its
      Service Providers can therefore not be used by Consumers. They can then
      also not be registered as OSGi services, see <xref linkend="i3285744"/>.
      Tools can use the advertisement of the Service Provider in the JAR to
      automatically generate the <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capabilities
      in the manifest.</para>

      <para>For example, the following capability publishes all the Service
      Providers in its bundle that advertise the
      <code>com.example.Codec</code> interface:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability:
  osgi.serviceloader;
    osgi.serviceloader=com.example.Codec;
    uses:="com.example"</programlisting>

      <para>A Service Provider bundle must not require the
      <code>osgi.serviceloader.processor</code> extender unless it needs to be
      processed; publishing a Service Type is sufficient to allow Consumers to
      use the published Service Types.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3285744">
      <title>OSGi Services</title>

      <para>The Service Provider can have its <code>osgi.serviceloader</code>
      capabilities be registered as services that provide instances from the
      Service Providers. For this, the Service Provider bundle must require
      the <code>osgi.serviceloader.registrar</code> extender, which is the
      Mediator. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>Require-Capability:
    osgi.extender;
        filter:="(&amp;(osgi.extender=osgi.serviceloader.registrar)
                 (version&gt;=1.0)(!(version&gt;=2.0)))"</programlisting>

      <para>The registrar must then inspect each
      <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capability and register an associated
      OSGi Service for each Service Provider <emphasis>selected</emphasis> by
      that capability. A Service Provider is selected when:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The capability has no <code>register</code> directive,
          or</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The register directive matches the fully qualified name of the
          Service Provider.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A <code>register</code> directive selects a Service Provider if it
      contains the fully qualified name of the Service Provider, that is, the
      implementation class. Selection only works for services, Consumer will
      always see all Service Providers regardless of the <code>register</code>
      directive due to limitations in the Service Loader API.</para>

      <para>For example, the following manifest selects all Service Providers
      of the <code>com.example.Foo</code> Service Type since no
      <code>register</code> directive is present:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability:
    osgi.serviceloader;
        uses:="com.example";
        osgi.serviceloader=com.example.Foo</programlisting>

      <para>Selected Service Providers must be registered as defined in <xref
      linkend="i3280881"/>, with the capability's attributes as
      <emphasis>decorating</emphasis> service properties. Private service
      properties (attributes that start with a full stop (<code>'.'
      \u002E</code>) and the defined capability attributes in the
      <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> namespace are not registered as service
      properties.</para>

      <para>The following example would register the <code>format</code>
      service property but not the <code>.hint</code> service property for the
      <code>com.acme.impl.WaveFoo</code> Service Provider.</para>

      <programlisting>    osgi.serviceloader;
        osgi.serviceloader=com.example.Foo;
        uses:="com.example";
        format=WAVE;
        .hint=E5437Qy7;
        register:="com.acme.impl.WaveFoo"</programlisting>

      <para>The Mediator must only register OSGi services for selected Service
      Providers; the Service Provider bundle can therefore decide not to
      register certain Service Providers and register them with another
      mechanism, for example Declarative Services or in a bundle
      activator.</para>

      <para>Since the Mediator must use the bundle context of the Service
      Provider to register the OSGi service the Service Provider bundle must
      have the proper Service Permission <code>REGISTER</code> for the Service
      Type.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Service Provider Example</title>

      <para>A Foo Codecs JAR needs to be ported to OSGi, it provides a Service
      Provider for the <code>org.example.Codec</code> Service Type. In this
      example the JAR is given a new manifest:</para>

      <programlisting>Manifest-Version:       1.0
Bundle-ManifestVersion: 2
Bundle-SymbolicName:    com.example.foo.codecs
Import-Package:         com.example; version=3.45</programlisting>

      <para>To ensure that the bundle opts in to registering its services it
      must require the <code>osgi.serviceloader.registrar</code>
      extender.</para>

      <programlisting>Require-Capability:                                         
    osgi.extender; 
        filter:="(&amp;(osgi.extender=osgi.serviceloader.registrar)
                 (version&gt;=1.0)(!(version&gt;=2.0)))"</programlisting>

      <para>To publish two Service Providers for the same type, two
      capabilities must be declared:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability:
    osgi.serviceloader;
        osgi.serviceloader="com.example.Codec";
        format:List&lt;String&gt;="WAVE,WMF";
      register:="com.acme.impl.FooWaveCodec";
      uses:="com.example,org.apache.common.codecs",
    osgi.serviceloader;
        osgi.serviceloader="com.example.Codec";
        format:List&lt;String&gt;=SINUS;
      register:="com.acme.impl.sinus.FooSinusCodec";
      uses:="com.example"</programlisting>

      <para>This example implicitly publishes the Service Type
      <code>com.example.Codec</code> multiple times with different attributes.
      Consumers that match any of these capabilities will however have
      visibility to all Service Providers since the Service Loader API cannot
      discriminate between different Service Providers from the same
      bundle.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Service Loader Mediator</title>

    <para>A Mediator is the <code>osgi.serviceloader.processor</code> and
    <code>osgi.serviceloader.registrar</code> extender bundle that has the
    following responsibilities:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>It registers selected Service Providers as OSGi services.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It processes any Consumers so that Service Loader API calls have
        proper visibility to published Service Provider bundles.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section xml:id="i3280881">
      <title>Registering Services</title>

      <para>The Mediator must track bundles that are wired to its
      <code>osgi.extender=osgi.serviceloader.registrar</code> capability.
      These are called the <emphasis>managed</emphasis> bundles. For all
      managed bundles the Mediator must enumerate all
      <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capabilities and register
      <emphasis>selected</emphasis> Service Providers as OSGi services. A
      Service Provider is selected by an <code>osgi.serviceloader</code>
      capability when:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The advertised Service Type matches the corresponding
          <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capability's Service Type,
          and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The register directive is absent, or</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The <code>register</code> directive contains the fully
              qualified name of the Service Provider.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>An <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capability that selects a
      Service Provider is said to <emphasis>decorate</emphasis> that Service
      Provider. A capability can decorate multiple Service Providers of the
      same Service Type and the same Service Provider can be decorated by
      different capabilities. <xref linkend="i3283346"/> depicts the resulting
      relations and their cardinalities since the relations are
      non-trivial.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i3283346">
        <title>Cardinality Service Type</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.565in"
                       contentwidth="6.237in"
                       fileref="cardinality-service-type.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The OSGi service for each selected Service Provider must be
      registered under the advertised Service Type of the Service Provider,
      which must match the Service Type specified in the capability.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>OSGi Service Factory</title>

      <para>The Mediator must register an OSGi service factory with the bundle
      context of the Service Provider's bundle. The OSGi service factory must
      be implemented such that it creates a new instance for each bundle that
      gets the service. This behavior is similar, though not quite identical,
      to the <code>ServiceLoader.load()</code> method that gives each consumer
      a separate instance of the service. The difference is that different
      users inside a bundle will share the same instance.</para>

      <para>Each service registration is controlled by a decorating
      <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capability. The attributes on this
      capability must be registered with the OSGi service as service
      properties, except for:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Private</emphasis> - Private properties, property
          names that start with a full stop (<code>'.' \u002E</code>) must not
          be registered.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following service property must be registered, overriding any
      identical named properties in the decorating capability:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>serviceloader.mediator</code> - (<code>Long</code>) The
          bundle id of the mediator.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Mediator should not verify class space consistency since the
      OSGi framework already enforces this as long as the publishing
      capability specifies the <code>uses</code> directive.</para>

      <para>Any services registered in the OSGi Service Registry must be
      unregistered when the Service Provider's bundle is stopped or the
      Mediator is stopped.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Service Loader and Modularity</title>

      <para>The Service Loader API causes issues in a modular environment
      because it requires a class loader that has wide visibility. In a
      modular environment like OSGi the Consumer, the Service Type, and the
      Service Provider can, and should, all reside in different modules
      because they represent different concerns. Best practice requires that
      only the Service Type is shared between these actors. However, for the
      Service Loader to work as it was designed the Consumer must provide a
      class loader that has visibility of the Service Provider. The Service
      Provider is an implementation class, exporting such classes is the
      anathema of modularity. However, since the standard JRE provides
      application wide visibility this was never a major concern.</para>

      <para>The simplest solution is to make the Service Loader aware of OSGi,
      its API clear is mappable to the OSGi service layer. However, the
      Service Loader is not extensible. The result is that using the Service
      Loader in OSGi fails in general because the Service Loader is unable to
      find the Service Providers. The issues are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The use of the Thread Context Class Loader (TCCL) is not
          defined in an OSGi environment. It should be set by the caller and
          this cannot be enforced. The multi threaded nature of OSGi makes it
          hard to predict what thread a Consumer will use, making it
          impossible to set an appropriate TCCL outside the Consumer.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A bundle cannot import <code>META-INF/services</code> since
          the name is not a package name. Even if it could, the OSGi framework
          can only bind a single exporter to an importer for a given package.
          The Service Loader API requires access to all these pseudo-packages
          via the Class Loader's <code>getResources</code> method, the
          technique used to find Service Providers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Instantiating a Service Provider requires access to internal
          implementation classes, by exporting these classes, an implementing
          bundle would break its encapsulation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If a Service Provider was exported then importing this class
          in a Consumer bundle would couple it to a specific implementation
          package; this also violates the principle of loose coupling.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Service Loader API does assume an eternal life cycle,
          there is no way to signal that a Service Provider is no longer
          available. This is at odds with the dynamic bundle life
          cycle.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Processing Consumers</title>

      <para>Consumers are not written for OSGi and require help to
      successfully use the Service Loader API. It is the Mediator's
      responsibility to ensure that bundles that are wired to published
      Service Types have access to these Service Provider's instances through
      the Service Loader API.</para>

      <para>This specification does not define how this is done. There are a
      number of possibilities and it is up to the Mediator to provide the
      guarantee to the Consumer that it has been properly processed.</para>

      <para>A Mediator must only process Consumer's bundles that are wired to
      the <code>osgi.extender</code> capability for the
      <code>osgi.serviceloader.processor</code> extender. Since Consumers must
      require this extender capability with the default cardinality of 1 there
      can at most be one extender wired to a Consumer.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Visibility</title>

      <para>The Mediator must process the Consumer bundle in such a way that
      when the Consumer uses the Service Loader API it receives all the
      Service Providers of bundles that:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Provide one or more <code>osgi.serviceloader</code>
          capabilities for the requested Service Type, and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Are not type space incompatible with the requester for the
          given Service Type, and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Either the Consumer has no <code>osgi.serviceloader</code>
          requirements or one of its requirements is wired to one of the
          <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> capabilities.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Mediator must verify that the Consumer has Service Permission
      <code>GET</code> for the given Service Type since the Consumer uses the
      Service Type as a service. This specification therefore reuses the
      Service Permission for this purpose. The check must be done with the
      <code>ServicePermission(String,String)</code> constructor using the
      bundle's Access Control Context or the bundle's
      <code>hasPermission</code> method.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Life Cycle</title>

      <para>There is a life cycle mismatch between the Service Loader API and
      the dynamic OSGi world. A Service Loader provides a Consumer with an
      object that could come from a bundle that is later stopped and/or
      refreshed. Such an object becomes <emphasis>stale</emphasis>. Mediators
      should attempt to refresh bundles that have access to these stale
      objects.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i3280141">
    <title>osgi.serviceloader Namespace</title>

    <para>The <code>osgi.serviceloader</code> Namespace:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Allows the Consumer's bundle to require the presence of a
        Service Provider for the required Service Type.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Provides the service properties for the service
        registration.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Indicates which Service Providers should be registered as an
        OSGi service.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The namespace is defined in the following table and <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.serviceloader.ServiceLoaderNamespace"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, see <xref linkend="service.namespaces"/> for the
    legend of this table.</para>

    <table pgwide="1">
      <title>osgi.serviceloader namespace definition</title>

      <tgroup cols="6">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="5*"/>

        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

        <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>

        <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="1.5*"/>

        <colspec colnum="5" colwidth="4*"/>

        <colspec colnum="6" colwidth="7*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Name</entry>

            <entry>Kind</entry>

            <entry>M/O</entry>

            <entry>Type</entry>

            <entry>Syntax</entry>

            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><code>osgi.serviceloader</code></entry>

            <entry><code>CA</code></entry>

            <entry><code>M</code></entry>

            <entry><code>String</code></entry>

            <entry><code>qname</code></entry>

            <entry><para>The Service Type's fully qualified
            name.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>*</code></entry>

            <entry><code>CA</code></entry>

            <entry><code>O</code></entry>

            <entry><code>*</code></entry>

            <entry><code>*</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Additional matching attributes are permitted. These
            attributes will be registered as custom service properties unless
            they are private (start with a full stop).</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><code>register</code></entry>

            <entry><code>CD</code></entry>

            <entry><code>O</code></entry>

            <entry><code>String</code></entry>

            <entry><code>qname</code></entry>

            <entry><para>Use this capability to register a different Service
            Factory under the Service Type for each selected Service Provider.
            </para><para>A Service Provider is selected if the Service Type is
            the advertising Service Type and the Service Provider's fully
            qualified name matches the given name. If no register directive is
            present all advertised Service Providers must be registered. To
            register no Service Providers, because the capability must only be
            used to publish, provide an empty string.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Use of the osgi.extender Namespace</title>

    <para>This section specifies the extender names for Mediators. They are
    used by both by Consumer and Service Provider bundles to ensure that a
    Mediator is present. Both names are defined for the general
    <code>osgi.extender</code> namespace in <emphasis>osgi.extender
    Namespace</emphasis> in <xref linkend="intro.core.release"
    xrefstyle="template:%t"/>.</para>

    <para>The <code>osgi.extender</code> namespace requires the use of an
    <emphasis>extender name</emphasis>, the name of the Mediator extenders
    is:</para>

    <programlisting>osgi.serviceloader.processor
osgi.serviceloader.registrar</programlisting>

    <para>The version is for this specification is in both cases:</para>

    <programlisting>1.0.0</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <section>
      <title>Mediator</title>

      <para>The Mediator will require significant permissions to perform its
      tasks. First, it will require access to the Bundle Context of the
      Service Provider bundle, which means it must have Admin
      Permission:</para>

      <programlisting>AdminPermission[&lt;Service Provider Bundles&gt;,CONTEXT|METADATA|CLASS]</programlisting>

      <para>Since it will have to register on behalf of the Service Provider
      bundle it must have complete liberty to register services:</para>

      <programlisting>ServicePermission[&lt;Service Type&gt;,REGISTER]</programlisting>

      <para>Depending on the way the Consumers are processed additional
      requirements may be necessary.</para>

      <para>The Mediator connects two parties; it must ensure that neither
      party will receive additional permissions.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Consumers</title>

      <para>Consumers must have:</para>

      <programlisting>ServicePermission[&lt;Service Type&gt;,GET] 
PackagePermission[&lt;Service Type's package&gt;,IMPORT]
CapabilityPermission["osgi.extender", REQUIRE]
CapabilityPermission["osgi.serviceloader", REQUIRE]
</programlisting>

      <para>The Mediator must ensure that the Consumer has the
      ServicePermission before it provides the instance. It must use the
      Bundle Context <code>hasPermission</code> method or the bundle's Access
      Control Context to verify this.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Service Providers</title>

      <para>Service Providers must have:</para>

      <programlisting>ServicePermission[&lt;Service Type&gt;,REGISTER] 
PackagePermission[&lt;Service Type's package&gt;,IMPORT]
CapabilityPermission["osgi.extender", REQUIRE]
CapabilityPermission["osgi.serviceloader", PROVIDE]
</programlisting>

      <para>The Mediator must ensure that the Service Provider has the
      ServicePermission before it provides the instance. It must use the
      Bundle Context <code>hasPermission</code> method or the bundle's Access
      Control Context to verify this.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.serviceloader.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3255894"><title>Java Service Loader
      API</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/util/ServiceLoader.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
