<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="4" revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="framework.lifecycle"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Life Cycle Layer</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.framework"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The Life Cycle Layer provides an API to control the security and
    life cycle operations of bundles. The layer is based on the module and
    security layer.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Complete</emphasis> - The Life Cycle layer must
          implement an API that fully covers the installation, starting,
          stopping, updating, uninstallation, and monitoring of
          bundles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Reflective</emphasis> - The API must provide full
          insight into the actual state of the Framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Secure</emphasis> - It must be possible to use the
          API in a secure environment using fine-grained permissions. However,
          security must be optional.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Manageable</emphasis> - It must be possible to
          manage a OSGi framework remotely.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Launching</emphasis> - It must be able to launch an
          implementation of a framework in a standardized way.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle</emphasis> - Represents an installed bundle
          in the Framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Context</emphasis> - A bundle's execution
          context within the Framework. The Framework passes this to a Bundle
          Activator when a bundle is started or stopped.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Activator</emphasis> - An interface
          implemented by a class in a bundle that is used to start and stop
          that bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Event</emphasis> - An event that signals a
          life cycle operation on a bundle. This event is received via a
          (Synchronous) Bundle Listener.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Framework Event</emphasis> - An event that signals
          an error or Framework state change. The event is received via a
          Framework Listener.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Listener</emphasis> - A listener to Bundle
          Events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Synchronous Bundle Listener</emphasis> - A listener
          to synchronously delivered Bundle Events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Framework Listener</emphasis> - A listener to
          Framework events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Exception</emphasis> - An Exception thrown
          when Framework operations fail.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>System Bundle</emphasis> - A bundle that represents
          the Framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Framework</emphasis> - An interface implemented by
          an object that represents the actual framework. It allows external
          management of a Framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Framework Factory</emphasis> - An interface
          implemented by Framework providers that allows the creation of a
          framework object.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Class diagram <code>org.osgi.framework</code> Life Cycle
        Layer</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="5.227in"
                       contentwidth="6.190in" fileref="lifecycle-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle-frameworks">
    <title>Frameworks</title>

    <para>This section outlines how a <emphasis>launcher</emphasis> can launch
    a framework implementation and then manage it, regardless of the
    implementation type of the framework. This allows a launcher to embed an
    OSGi framework without having to provide code that differs between
    different implementations.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Launching and Controlling a Framework</title>

      <para>Code that wants to use one of the OSGi Framework implementations
      must provide the chosen framework implementation on the class path, or
      create a special class loader that loads the code and resources from
      that implementation. How this is achieved, is outside this
      specification.</para>

      <para>A framework implementation must provide a
      <emphasis>factory</emphasis> class. A factory class is an indirection to
      create a framework implementation object. The implementation factory
      class must implement the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.launch.FrameworkFactory"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface. The launcher can use the following
      ways to get this class name:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Service Provider Configuration model, see <xref
          linkend="i3309166"/>,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Get it from some configuration and use
          <code>Class.forName</code>, or</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Hardcode the name.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.launch.FrameworkFactory"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface has a single method: <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.launch.FrameworkFactory.newFramework-Map-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The map provides the sole configuration
      properties for the framework object. The result of this method is a
      <emphasis>framework object</emphasis>, this object implements the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.launch.Framework" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      interface. The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.launch.Framework"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface extends the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface
      and adds methods to handle the issues unique to launching a framework.
      The framework object can be seen as the system bundle, though the
      framework object and the system bundle do not have to be identical,
      implementations are allowed to implement them in different
      objects.</para>

      <para>Before the framework object can be used, the launcher must first
      <emphasis>initialize</emphasis> it by calling the <code>init</code>
      method. After initialization, the framework object can provide a valid
      Bundle Context and has registered any framework services, but any
      installed bundles must be in the <code>INSTALLED</code> state. The
      launcher can then configure the framework object by installing bundles,
      interacting with the framework services, or registering launcher
      services. The launcher can also start bundles, but these bundles will
      not be started until the framework object becomes
      <code>ACTIVE</code>.</para>

      <para>After the framework object is properly configured, the launcher
      can <emphasis>start</emphasis> it by calling the <code>start</code>
      method. The framework object will become ACTIVE, and it will move the
      startlevel (if present) to the configured start level. This can then
      resolve and start any installed bundle. After a framework has become
      <code>ACTIVE</code>, it can be stopped from the framework object, or
      through the system bundle.</para>

      <para>The launcher can wait for a framework object to be stopped with
      the <code>waitForStop</code> method. This method will block until the
      framework is completely stopped and return a Framework event indicating
      the cause of the stop. After the framework object has been shutdown, and
      the <code>waitForStop</code> method has returned, all installed bundles
      will be in the <code>INSTALLED</code> state. The same framework object
      can be re-initialized, and started again, any number of times.</para>

      <para>The action diagram in <xref linkend="i3308801"/> shows a typical
      session. A new framework is created and initialized. The launcher then
      gets the Bundle Context, installs a bundle and starts the framework. It
      then gets a service, calls a method and then waits for the framework to
      stop. The service waits some time and calls stop on the System Bundle.
      The dotted lines indicate some non-specified interactions that are
      implementation dependent.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i3308801">
        <title>Action Diagram for Framework Launching</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.058in"
                       contentwidth="4.585in" fileref="launching-actions.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If security is enabled, then the launcher and the framework
      require All Permission. If All Permission is not available, then the
      framework must throw a Security Exception.</para>

      <para>The following code shows how a framework can be launched.</para>

      <programlisting>void launch( String factoryName, File[] bundles) 
            throws Exception {
    Map p = new HashMap();
    p.put( "org.osgi.framework.storage",    
            System.getProperty("user.home")
        +   File.separator+"osgi");

    FrameworkFactory factory = 
        (FrameworkFactory) Class.forName( factoryName )
                                            .newInstance();
    Framework framework = factory.newFramework(p);
    framework.init();

    BundleContext context = framework.getBundleContext();

    for ( File bundle : bundles )
        context.installBundle( bundle.toURL().toString() );
    
    framework.start();
    framework.waitForStop(0);
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle.launchingproperties">
      <title>Launching Properties</title>

      <para>The <code>Map</code> object given as a parameter to the
      <code>newFramework</code> method provides the <emphasis>configuration
      properties</emphasis> to the framework. This parameter may be
      <code>null</code>, in that case the framework must be started with
      reasonable defaults for the environment it is started in. For example,
      the framework should export the JRE packages as system packages and it
      should store its bundles in an appropriate place. The framework must not
      look in the System properties for configuration properties, the
      specified configuration properties are complete.</para>

      <para>The configuration properties may contain any implementation
      specific properties. The properties in <xref
      linkend="framework.lifecycle-framework.launching.properties"/> must be
      supported by all conformant frameworks.</para>

      <para>The configuration properties plus any defaults set by the
      framework and the fixed properties set by the framework all together
      form the <emphasis>launching properties</emphasis> for the
      framework.</para>

      <table xml:id="framework.lifecycle-framework.launching.properties">
        <title>Framework Launching Properties</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1.1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Property Name</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;bootdelegation</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Set the boot delegation mask, see <xref
              linkend="framework.module.parentdelegation"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;bsnversion</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Allow installation of multiple bundles with the
              same bundle symbolic name or restrict this. The property can
              have the following values:</para><itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>single</code> - A combination of equal bundle
                    symbolic name and equal version is unique in the
                    framework. Installing a second bundle with the same bundle
                    symbolic name and version is an error.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>multiple</code> - The combination of bundle
                    symbolic name and version is not unique in the
                    framework.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>managed</code> - (Default) Using a Bundle
                    Collision Hook to filter any non-colliding bundles, see
                    <xref linkend="framework.bundlehooks"/>.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;bundle.parent</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>This property is used to specify what class loader
              is used for boot delegation. That is, <code>java.*</code> and
              the packages specified on the
              <code>org.osgi.framework.bootdelegation</code>. All other
              packages must be accessed through a wire. </para><para>This
              property can have the following values:</para><itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>boot</code> - The boot class loader of the VM.
                    This is the default.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>app</code> - The application class
                    loader</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>ext</code> - The extension class loader</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>framework</code> - The class loader of the
                    framework</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;command.execpermission</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Specifies an optional OS specific command to set
              file permissions on a bundle's native code. This is required on
              some operating systems to use native libraries. For example, on
              a UNIX style OS you could have the following value:
              </para><programlisting>org.osgi.framework.command.execpermission=«
   "chmod +rx ${abspath}"</programlisting><para>The <code>${abspath}</code>
              macro will be substituted for the actual file
              path.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;executionenvironment</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>A comma-separated list of provided execution
              environments (EE). All methods of each listed EE must be present
              on the OSGi framework. For example, this property could
              contain:</para><programlisting>CDC-1.1/Foundation-1.1,OSGi/Minimum-1.2</programlisting><para>A
              OSGi framework implementation must provide
              <emphasis>all</emphasis> the signatures that are defined in the
              mentioned EEs. Thus, the execution environment for a specific
              OSGi framework Server must be the combined set of all signatures
              of all EEs in the
              <code>org.osgi.framework.executionenvironment</code>
              property.</para><para>This property is deprecated; its function
              is replaced with
              <code>org.osgi.framework.system.capabilities[.extra]</code>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>org.osgi.framework.language</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The language used by the framework for the
              selection of native code. If not set, the framework must provide
              a value. See <xref linkend="i1304871"/> for valid
              values.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.library.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;extensions</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>A comma separated list of additional library file
              extensions that must be used when searching for native code. If
              not set, then only the library name returned by
              <code>System.mapLibraryName(String)</code> will be used. This
              list of extensions is needed for certain operating systems which
              allow more than one extension for native libraries. For example,
              the AIX operating system allows library extensions of
              <code>.a</code> and <code>.so</code>, but
              <code>System.mapLibraryName(String)</code> will only return
              names with the <code>.a</code> extension. For
              example:</para><programlisting>org.osgi.framework.library.extensions= a,so,dll</programlisting></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>org.osgi.framework.os.name</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The name of the operating system as used in the
              native code clause. If not set, then the framework must provide
              a default value. <xref linkend="framework.module.os-names"/>
              defines a list of operating system names. New operating system
              names are made available on the OSGi web site, see <xref
              linkend="i3287541"/>. Names should be matched case
              insensitive.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>org.osgi.framework.os.version</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The version of the operating system as used in the
              native code clause. If not set, then the framework must provide
              a default value. If the operating system reported version does
              not fit the standard version syntax (<emphasis>e.g.</emphasis>
              <code>2.4.32-kwt</code>), then the launcher should define this
              launching property with a valid version value.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>org.osgi.framework.processor</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The name of the processor as used in the native
              code clause. If not set, then the framework must provide a
              value. <xref linkend="framework.module.processor-names"/>
              defines a list of processor names. New processors are made
              available on the OSGi web site, see <xref linkend="i3287541"/>.
              Names should be matched case insensitive.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>org.osgi.framework.security</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Specifies the type of security manager the
              framework must use. If not specified then the framework will not
              set the VM security manager. The following type is
              architected:</para><itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>osgi</code> - Enables a security manager that
                    supports all security aspects of the OSGi Core
                    specifications (including postponed conditions).</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist><para>If specified, and there is a security
              manager already installed, then a SecurityException must be
              thrown when the Framework is initialized. </para><para>For
              example:</para><programlisting>org.osgi.framework.security = osgi</programlisting></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.startlevel.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;beginning</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Specifies the beginning start level of the
              framework. See <xref linkend="framework.startlevel"/> for more
              information.</para><programlisting>org.osgi.framework.startlevel.beginning = 3</programlisting></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>org.osgi.framework.storage</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A valid file path in the file system to a
              directory. If the specified directory does not exist then the
              framework must create the directory. If the specified path
              exists, but is not a directory, or if the framework fails to
              create the storage directory, then the framework initialization
              must fail with an exception being thrown. The framework is free
              to use this directory as it sees fit, for example, completely
              erase all files and directories in it. If this property is not
              set, the framework must set this property to a reasonable
              platform default.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.storage.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;clean</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Specifies if and when the storage area for the
              framework should be cleaned. If no value is specified, the
              framework storage area will not be cleaned. The possible values
              is:</para><itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>onFirstInit</code> - The framework storage
                    area will be cleaned before the Framework bundle is
                    initialized for the first time. Subsequent inits, starts
                    or updates of the Framework bundle will not result in
                    cleaning the framework storage area.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist><para>For example:</para><programlisting>org.osgi.framework.storage.clean = onFirstInit</programlisting><para>It
              could seem logical to provide delete on exit and clean at
              initialization. However, restrictions in common Java VM
              implementations make it impossible to provide this functionality
              reliably.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.system.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;capabilities</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Specifies the capabilities of the environment in
              the grammar specified for the <code>Provide-Capability</code>
              header, see <xref linkend="framework.module.dependencies"/>.
              These capabilities must be provided from the system bundle. If
              this property is not set, the framework must calculate this
              header based on the environment. It should at least set the
              following namespaces:</para><itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>osgi.ee</code></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><code>osgi.native</code></para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist><para>Deployers should use the
              <code>org.osgi.framework.system.capabilities.extra</code>
              property.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.system.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;capabilities.extra</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Capabilities defined in this property are added to
              the <code>org.osgi.framework.system.capabilities</code>
              property. The purpose of the extra property is to be set by the
              deployer. The grammar for this property is identical to the
              other capabilities property.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.system.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;packages</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>The packages that must be exported from the System
              Bundle. If not set, the framework must provide a reasonable
              default for the current execution environment. See <xref
              linkend="framework.module-execution.environment"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.system.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;packages.extra</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Packages specified in this property are added to
              the <code>org.osgi.framework.system.packages</code> property and
              therefore have the same syntax. This allows the configurator to
              only define the additional packages and leave the standard
              execution environment packages to be defined by the framework.
              For example:</para><programlisting>org.osgi.framework.system.packages.extra=«
   org.acme.foo; version=1.2, org.acme.foo.impl</programlisting></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.trust.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;repositories</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>This property is used to configure trust
              repositories for the framework. The value is path of files. The
              file paths are separated by the <code>pathSeparator</code>
              defined in the <code>File</code> class. Each file path should
              point to a key store. The Framework must support the JKS type
              but can support other key store types. The framework will use
              the key stores as trust repositories to authenticate
              certificates of trusted signers. The key stores must only be
              used as read-only trust repositories to access public keys. The
              keystore must not have a password. For
              example:</para><programlisting>org.osgi.framework.trust.repositories = «
   /var/trust/keystore.jks:~/.cert/certs.jks</programlisting></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.framework.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;windowsystem</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Provide the name of the current window system. This
              can be used by the native code clause, <xref
              linkend="framework.module.nativecodealgorithm"/>. If not set,
              the framework should provide a value that depends on the current
              environment.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <table xml:id="framework.module.processor-names">
        <title>Processor Names</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="3*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Name</entry>

              <entry>Aliases</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>68k</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Motorola 68000</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>ARM</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para><emphasis>Intel Strong ARM. Deprecated because it
              does not specify the endianness. See the following two
              rows.</emphasis></para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>arm_le</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Intel Strong ARM Little Endian mode</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>arm_be</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Intel String ARM Big Endian mode</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Alpha</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Compaq (ex DEC)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>ia64n</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Hewlett Packard 32 bit</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>ia64w</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Hewlett Packard 64 bit mode</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Ignite</code></entry>

              <entry><code>psc1k</code></entry>

              <entry>PTSC</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Mips</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>SGI</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>PArisc</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Hewlett Packard</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>PowerPC</code></entry>

              <entry><code>power ppc</code></entry>

              <entry>Motorola/IBM Power PC</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>PowerPC-64</code></entry>

              <entry><code>ppc64</code></entry>

              <entry>IBM Power PC 64-bit Big Endian mode</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>PowerPC-64-LE</code></entry>

              <entry><code>ppc64le</code></entry>

              <entry>IBM Power PC 64-bit Little Endian mode</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Sh4</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Hitachi</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Sparc</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Sun Microsystems</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Sparcv9</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>Sun Microsystems</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>S390</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>IBM Mainframe 31 bit</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>S390x</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>IBM Mainframe 64-bit</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>V850E</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>NEC V850E</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>x86</code></entry>

              <entry><code>pentium i386 i486 i586 i686</code></entry>

              <entry>Intel &amp; AMD 32 bit</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>x86-64</code></entry>

              <entry><code>amd64 em64t x86_64</code></entry>

              <entry>AMD/Intel 64 bit x86 architecture</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <table xml:id="framework.module.os-names">
        <title>Operating System Names</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="3*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Name</entry>

              <entry>Aliases</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>AIX</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>IBM</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>DigitalUnix</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>Compaq</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Embos</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>Segger Embedded Software Solutions</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Epoc32</code></entry>

              <entry><code>SymbianOS</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Symbian OS</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>FreeBSD</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>Free BSD</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>HPUX</code></entry>

              <entry><code>hp-ux</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Hewlett Packard</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>IRIX</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>Silicon Graphics</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Linux</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>Open source</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>MacOS</code></entry>

              <entry><code>"Mac OS"</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Apple</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>MacOSX</code></entry>

              <entry><code>"Mac OS X"</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Apple</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>NetBSD</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>Open source</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Netware</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>Novell</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>OpenBSD</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>Open source</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>OS2</code></entry>

              <entry><code>OS/2</code></entry>

              <entry><para>IBM</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>QNX</code></entry>

              <entry><code>procnto</code></entry>

              <entry><para>QNX</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Solaris</code></entry>

              <entry><code>SunOS</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Sun Microsystems</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>VxWorks</code></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><para>WindRiver Systems</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Windows95</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Win95</code> <code>"Windows 95"</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Windows98</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Win98</code> <code>"Windows 98"</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsNT</code></entry>

              <entry><code>WinNT</code> <code>"Windows NT"</code>
              <code>"Windows NT (unknown)"</code> <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsCE</code></entry>

              <entry><code>WinCE</code> <code>"Windows CE"</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Windows2000</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Win2000</code> <code>"Windows 2000"</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Windows2003</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Win2003</code> <code>"Windows 2003"</code>
              <code>Win32</code> <code>"Windows Server 2003"</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsXP</code></entry>

              <entry><code>WinXP</code> <code>"Windows XP"</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsVista</code></entry>

              <entry><code>WinVista</code> <code>"Windows Vista"</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Windows7</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Win7</code> <code>"Windows 7"</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Windows8</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Win8</code> <code>"Windows 8"</code> <code>"Windows
              8.1"</code> <code>"Windows 8.2"</code> <code>"Windows
              8.3"</code> <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Windows10</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Win10</code> <code>"Windows 10"</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsServer2008</code></entry>

              <entry><code>"Windows Server 2008"</code> <code>"Windows
              2008"</code> <code>Windows2008</code> <code>Win2008</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsServer2008R2</code></entry>

              <entry><code>"Windows Server 2008 R2"</code> <code>"Windows 2008
              R2"</code> <code>Windows2008R2</code> <code>Win2008R2</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsServer2012</code></entry>

              <entry><code>"Windows Server 2012"</code> <code>"Windows
              2012"</code> <code>Windows2012</code> <code>Win2012</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsServer2012R2</code></entry>

              <entry><code>"Windows Server 2012 R2"</code> <code>"Windows 2012
              R2"</code> <code>Windows2012R2</code> <code>Win2012R2</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsServer2015</code></entry>

              <entry><code>"Windows Server 2015"</code> <code>"Windows
              2015"</code> <code>Windows2015</code> <code>Win2015</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsServer2015R2</code></entry>

              <entry><code>"Windows Server 2015 R2"</code> <code>"Windows 2015
              R2"</code> <code>Windows2015R2</code> <code>Win2015R2</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>WindowsServer2016</code></entry>

              <entry><code>"Windows Server 2016"</code> <code>"Windows
              2016"</code> <code>Windows2016</code> <code>Win2016</code>
              <code>Win32</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Microsoft</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>z/OS</code></entry>

              <entry><code/></entry>

              <entry><para>IBM</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>The properties in the following table are the fixed properties of
      the framework. The values of these properties are established by the
      framework implementation and added to the launching properties. If these
      properties are set in the configuration properties, the framework must
      ignore them.</para>

      <table xml:id="framework.lifecycle-fixed.property.names">
        <title>Fixed Framework Launching Properties</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Property name</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>org.osgi.framework.version</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The specification version number implemented by the
              Framework implementation. The specification version number of
              this specification is <xref
              endterm="org.osgi.framework-version.number"
              linkend="org.osgi.framework"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>org.osgi.framework.vendor</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The vendor of the Framework implementation.
              </para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>org.osgi.framework.uuid</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Unique id for the framework instance, see <xref
              linkend="i3324345"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.supports.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;framework.extension</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Support for framework extensions is mandatory, must
              therefore be set to <code>true</code>, see <xref
              linkend="framework.module.extensionbundles"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.supports.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;bootclasspath.extension</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Must be set to <code>true</code> or
              <code>false</code>, see <xref
              linkend="framework.module.requiringbundles"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.supports.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;framework.fragment</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Support for fragment bundles is mandatory, must
              therefore be set to <code>true</code>, see <xref
              linkend="framework.module.fragmentbundles"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>org.osgi.supports.«</code></para><para><code>&#160;framework.requirebundle</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Support for Require Bundle is mandatory, must
              therefore be set to <code>true</code>, see <xref
              linkend="framework.module.requiringbundles"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>All launching properties are available through the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleContext.getProperty-String-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. See <xref linkend="i2068690"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Life Cycle of a Framework</title>

      <para>Once the frameworks is created, it must be in the
      <code>INSTALLED</code> state. In this state, the framework is not active
      and there is no valid Bundle Context. From this point on, the framework
      object can go through its life cycle with the following methods.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>init</code> - If the framework object is not active,
          then this method moves the framework object into the
          <code>STARTING</code> state.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>start</code> - Ensure that the framework is in the
          <code>ACTIVE</code> state. This method can be called only on the
          framework because there are no bundles running yet.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>update</code> - Stop the framework. This returns the
          Framework event <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED_UPDATE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED_BOOTCLASSPATH_MODIFIED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> to the <code>waitForStop</code> method and
          then restarts the framework to its previous state. The launcher
          should then take the appropriate action and then call the
          <code>waitForStop</code> method again or reboot the VM. The
          <code>update</code> method can be called on the framework or on the
          system bundle. If the framework is not active, this has no
          effect.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>stop</code> - Move the framework into the
          <code>RESOLVED</code> state via the <code>STOPPING</code> state.
          This will return a Framework <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event from the <code>waitForStop</code>
          method. The Framework's Bundle Context is no longer valid. The
          framework must be initialized again to get a new, valid Bundle
          Context. The <code>stop</code> method can be called on the framework
          or on the system bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>uninstall</code> - Must not be called, will throw an
          Exception when called.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><xref linkend="i3309036"
      xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/> shows how the previous
      methods traverse the state diagram.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i3309036">
        <title>State diagram Framework</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.861in"
                       contentwidth="7.125in" fileref="framework-states.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle.initializing">
      <title>Initializing the Framework</title>

      <para>Before the framework can be used, it must be
      <emphasis>initialized</emphasis>. Initialization is caused by one of the
      <code>init</code> methods or implicitly by the <code>start</code>
      method. An initialized framework is operational, but none of its bundles
      are active. This is reflected in the <code>STARTING</code> state. As
      long as the framework is in this state, new bundles can be installed
      without any installed code interfering. Existing bundles must all be in
      the <code>INSTALLED</code> or <code>RESOLVED</code> state. In this
      state, the framework will run at start level 0.</para>

      <para>A framework object can be initialized multiple times. After
      initialization:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Event handling is enabled</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The security manager is configured</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Start level is set to 0</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The framework object has a valid Bundle Context</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any installed bundle is in the <code>INSTALLED</code> or
          <code>RESOLVED</code> state</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Framework services are available</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The framework state is <code>STARTING</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Has a valid UUID</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The system bundle can adapt to any of its defined types</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All resolved extension bundle activators <code>start</code>
          methods have been called</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section>
        <title>Start Extension Activators</title>

        <para>The Extension Bundle Activator <code>start</code> method is
        called to inform the framework extension that the
        <code>Framework</code> is initializing, see <xref
        linkend="framework.module.extensionActivator"/>.</para>

        <para>During the initialization process a framework must attempt to
        resolve all installed Framework Extensions. All resolve operations
        that occur during initialization must be scoped to only include the
        system bundle and the extension bundles. This is necessary to avoid
        resolution operations which change the wiring of normal bundles before
        all of the Extension Bundle Activators have been called.</para>

        <para>The last step during <code>Framework</code> initialization is to
        call the <code>start</code> method of each Extension Bundle Activator
        declared by resolved framework extensions. While calling Extension
        Bundle Activator <code>start</code> methods the framework must be in
        the <code>STARTING</code> state and have a valid bundle context. Any
        exception thrown by an Extension Bundle Activator <code>start</code>
        method must be wrapped in a <code>BundleException</code> and broadcast
        as an <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.ERROR"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Init Framework Listeners</title>

        <para>The <code>Framework</code> <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.launch.Framework.init-FrameworkListener...-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method may be called with a list of framework
        listeners. Any framework events broadcast during the initialization
        process must be delivered to the specified framework listeners in the
        order they are specified before returning from the <code>init</code>
        method. After returning from <code>init</code>, the specified
        listeners are no longer notified of framework events. This allows a
        launcher to initialize a <code>Framework</code> with an init framework
        listener in order to detect errors from framework extension
        activators.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Starting the Framework</title>

      <para>After the framework has been initialized, it can be started with
      the <code>start</code> method. This <code>start</code> method must be
      called on the framework object. The start method moves the framework
      into the <code>ACTIVE</code> state. If the framework was not
      initialized, it must be initialized first.</para>

      <para>In the active state, all installed bundles previously recorded as
      being started must be started as described in the
      <code>Bundle.start</code> method. Any exceptions that occur during
      startup must be wrapped in a <code>BundleException</code> and then
      published as a Framework <code>ERROR</code> event. Bundles, and their
      different states, are discussed in <xref linkend="i2030856"/>. If the
      Framework implements the optional Start Level specification, this
      behavior can be different. See <xref linkend="framework.startlevel"/>.
      Any bundles that specify an activation policy must be treated according
      to their activation policy, see <xref linkend="i3270439"/>.</para>

      <para>After the system bundle enters the <code>ACTIVE</code> state, a
      Framework <code>STARTED</code> event is broadcast.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle.stopping">
      <title>Stopping a Framework</title>

      <para>Shutdown can be initiated by stopping the system bundle, covered
      in <xref linkend="i3070515"/> or calling the <code>stop</code> method on
      the framework object. When the framework is shut down, it first enters
      the <code>STOPPING</code> state. All <code>ACTIVE</code> bundles are
      stopped as described in the <code>Bundle.stop</code> method, except that
      their persistently recorded start state is kept unchanged. Any
      exceptions that occur during shutdown must be wrapped in a
      <code>BundleException</code> and then published as a Framework event of
      type <code>FrameworkEvent.ERROR</code>. If the Framework implements the
      optional Start Level specification, this behavior can be different. See
      <xref linkend="framework.startlevel"/>. During the shutdown, bundles
      with a lazy policy must not be activated even when classes are loaded
      from them and they are not yet activated.</para>

      <para>The framework then moves to start level 0, calls <code>stop</code>
      on the Extension Bundle Activators (see <xref
      linkend="framework.lifecycle.stopExtension"/>), stops event handling and
      releases any resources (like threads, class loaders, etc.) it held. The
      framework then enters the <code>RESOLVED</code> state and destroys the
      Bundle Context. The last action is to notify any threads that are
      waiting in the <code>waitForStop</code> method. The Framework must be
      re-initialized if it needs to be used again.</para>

      <para>After a framework object is stopped and in the resolved state, it
      can be initialized and started again. Framework implementations must
      ensure that holding on to a framework object does not consume
      significant resources.</para>

      <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle.stopExtension">
        <title>Stop Extension Activators</title>

        <para>The Extension Bundle Activator <code>stop</code> method is
        called to inform the framework extension that the
        <code>Framework</code> is shutting down, see <xref
        linkend="framework.module.extensionActivator"/>. Before disabling
        event handling during the <code>Framework</code> shutdown process, the
        framework must call the <code>stop</code> method for each Extension
        Bundle Activator that was started successfully. While calling
        Extension Bundle Activator <code>stop</code> methods, the framework
        must be in the <code>STOPPING</code> state and have a valid bundle
        context. Any exception thrown by an Extension Bundle Activator
        <code>stop</code> method must be wrapped in a
        <code>BundleException</code> and broadcast as an <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.ERROR"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>

        <para>The framework must guarantee that if the <code>start</code>
        method has executed successfully for an Extension Bundle Activator,
        that same <code>BundleActivator</code> object must be called on its
        <code>stop</code> method when the framework is shutdown. After calling
        the <code>stop</code> method, that particular
        <code>BundleActivator</code> object must never be used again. An
        Extension Bundle Activators that threw an exception during
        <code>start</code> must not be called on shutdown.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Embedding a Framework</title>

      <para>The launcher is not running as an OSGi bundle, it is a plain Java
      application. However, often this launcher needs to communicate with the
      bundles inside the framework. The launcher can use the Bundle Context of
      the framework object to get and register services. However, it must
      ensure that there is class compatibility between its objects and objects
      from the bundle. A framework will not automatically share packages
      between the launcher code and the bundles. Packages must be explicitly
      exported from the parent class loader. The
      <code>org.osgi.framework.system.packages.extra</code> is specifically
      designed to hold any application packages that needs to be shared
      between the OSGi bundles and the application. Packages in that property
      are added to the system packages of the framework, which are packages
      exported by the system bundle from its parent loader. Care should be
      taken to ensure that all these system packages are visible to the class
      loader that loaded the framework.</para>

      <para>The OSGi Framework is running in a multi-threaded environment.
      After the framework is started, it will start bundles and these bundles
      will be activated. Activated bundles normally start background threads
      or react on events from other bundles. That is, after the
      <code>start</code> method returns, the framework has moved to the
      <code>ACTIVE</code> state and many bundles can be busy on different
      threads. At this point, the framework object can be stopped by the
      launcher through the framework object, or by a bundle through the System
      Bundle's <code>stop</code> method.</para>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.launch.Framework.waitForStop-long-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method on the framework object is included to
      handle any launcher cleanup that is required after the framework has
      completely stopped. It blocks until the framework has been completely
      shutdown. It returns one of the following Framework events to indicate
      the reason for stopping:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This framework object has been shutdown.
          It can be restarted.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED_UPDATE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This <code>Framework</code> object has
          been updated. The framework will begin to restart. The framework
          will return to its state before it was updated, either
          <code>ACTIVE</code> or <code>STARTING</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED_BOOTCLASSPATH_MODIFIED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This framework object has been stopped
          because a boot class path extension bundle has been installed or
          updated. The VM must be restarted in order for the changed boot
          class path to take affect.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.ERROR"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Framework encountered an error while
          shutting down or an error has occurred that forced the framework to
          shutdown.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.WAIT_TIMEDOUT"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This method has timed out and returned
          before this Framework has stopped.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3324345">
      <title>Framework UUID</title>

      <para>Each framework must have a unique identity every time before the
      framework is started. This identity is reflected in the framework
      property:</para>

      <programlisting>org.osgi.framework.uuid</programlisting>

      <para>The value of this property must reflect a string defined in <xref
      linkend="i3324333"/> with the <code>urn:uuid:</code> prefix. For
      example:</para>

      <programlisting>f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6</programlisting>

      <para>The Java UUID class is capable of generating such a UUID. However,
      as long as the external representation is maintained frameworks are free
      to create a unique global id in another way.</para>

      <para>Setting this property in the configuration properties has no
      effect, the framework must override it.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3321423">
      <title>Daemon Threads</title>

      <para>A Java VM will automatically exit when there are only daemon
      threads running. This can create the situation where the VM exits when
      the Framework uses only daemon threads and all threads created by
      bundles are also daemon threads. A Framework must therefore ensure that
      the VM does not exit when there are still active bundles. One way to
      achieve this, is to keep at least one non-daemon thread alive at all
      times.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3309166">
      <title>Java Service Provider Configuration Support</title>

      <para>The Java Service Provider Configuration model, as described in
      <xref linkend="i3300085"/>, provides a way to obtain the name of the
      framework factory by reading a resource in the JAR. In this
      specification, it is assumed that the framework implementation is on the
      class path. The name is obtained by reading the content of the
      configuration resource with the path
      <code>META-INF/services/org.osgi.framework.launch.FrameworkFactory</code>.</para>

      <para>For example, if the <code>com.acme.osgi</code> framework has a
      factory class <code>com.acme.osgi.Factory</code>, then it should have
      the following resource:</para>

      <programlisting>META-INF/services/org.osgi.framework.launch.FrameworkFactory</programlisting>

      <para>And the contents should be:</para>

      <programlisting># ACME Impl. for OSGi framework
com.acme.osgi.Factory</programlisting>

      <para>In contrast with the <xref linkend="i3300085"/>, there must only
      be one class name listed in the resource. However, launchers should be
      aware that the class path could contain multiple resources with the same
      name.</para>

      <para>Java 6 has introduced the <code>java.util.ServiceLoader</code>
      class that simplifies creating objects through these types of factories.
      The following code assumes there is a framework implementation JAR on
      the class path:</para>

      <programlisting>ServiceLoader&lt;FrameworkFactory&gt; sl =
    ServiceLoader.load(FrameworkFactory.class);

Iterator&lt;FrameworkFactory&gt; it = sl.iterator();
if ( it.hasNext() ) {
    Framework fw = it.next().newFramework(null);
    ...
}</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Bundles</title>

    <para>A bundle represents a JAR file that is executed in an OSGi
    Framework. The class loading aspects of this concept were specified in the
    Module Layer. However, the Module Layer does not define how a bundle is
    installed, updated, and uninstalled. These life cycle operations are
    defined here.</para>

    <para>The installation of a bundle can only be performed by another bundle
    or through implementation specific means (for example as a command line
    parameter of the Framework implementation).</para>

    <para>A Bundle is started through its Bundle Activator. Its Bundle
    Activator is identified by the Bundle-Activator manifest header. The given
    class must implement the <code>BundleActivator</code> interface. This
    interface has a <code>start</code> and <code>stop</code> method that is
    used by the bundle programmer to register itself as listener and start any
    necessary threads. The <code>stop</code> method must clean up and stop any
    running threads.</para>

    <para>Upon the activation of a bundle, it receives a Bundle Context. The
    Bundle Context interface's methods can roughly be divided in the following
    categories:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Information</emphasis> - Access to information about
        the rest of the Framework.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Life Cycle</emphasis> - The possibility to install
        other bundles.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Service Registry</emphasis> - The service registry is
        discussed in <xref linkend="framework.service"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i2030856">
    <title>The Bundle Object</title>

    <para>For each bundle installed in the OSGi framework, there is an
    associated <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object. The <code>Bundle</code> object for a
    bundle can be used to manage the bundle's life cycle. This is usually done
    with a Management Agent, which is also a Bundle.</para>

    <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle.bundleidentifiers">
      <title>Bundle Identifiers</title>

      <para>A bundle is identified by a number of names that vary in their
      scope:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle identifier</emphasis> - A <code>long</code>
          that is a Framework assigned unique identifier for the full lifetime
          of a bundle, even if it is updated or the Framework is restarted.
          Its purpose is to distinguish bundles in a Framework. Bundle
          identifiers are assigned in ascending order to bundles when they are
          installed. The method <code>getBundleId()</code> returns a bundle's
          identifier.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle location</emphasis> - A name assigned by the
          management agent (Operator) to a bundle during the installation.
          This string is normally interpreted as a URL to the JAR file but
          this is not mandatory. Within a particular Framework, a location
          must be unique. A location string uniquely identifies a bundle and
          must not change when a bundle is updated. The
          <code>getLocation()</code> method retrieves the location of a
          bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Symbolic Name and Bundle Version</emphasis> -
          A name and version assigned by the developer. The combination of
          Bundle Version and Bundle Symbolic Name is a globally unique
          identifier for a bundle. The <code>getSymbolicName()</code> method
          returns the assigned bundle name. The Bundle
          <code>getVersion()</code> method returns the version. Though the
          pair is unique, it is possible to install the same bundle multiple
          times if the <code>org.osgi.framework.bsnversion</code> framework
          launching property is set to <code>managed</code> or
          <code>multiple</code>, see also <xref
          linkend="framework.bundlehooks.collisionhook"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bundle State</title>

      <para>A bundle can be in one of the following states:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.INSTALLED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The bundle has been successfully
          installed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.RESOLVED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - All Java classes that the bundle needs are
          available. This state indicates that the bundle is either ready to
          be started or has stopped.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.STARTING"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The bundle is being started, the
          <code>BundleActivator.start</code> method will be called, and this
          method has not yet returned. When the bundle has a lazy activation
          policy, the bundle will remain in the <code>STARTING</code> state
          until the bundle is activated. See <xref linkend="i3270439"/> for
          more information.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.ACTIVE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The bundle has been successfully activated
          and is running; its Bundle Activator <code>start</code> method has
          been called and returned.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.STOPPING"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The bundle is being stopped. The
          <code>BundleActivator.stop</code> method has been called but the
          <code>stop</code> method has not yet returned.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.UNINSTALLED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The bundle has been uninstalled. It cannot
          move into another state.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure xml:id="i3320885">
        <title>State diagram Bundle</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.017in"
                       contentwidth="7.125in" fileref="bundle-states.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>When a bundle is installed, it is stored in the persistent storage
      of the Framework and remains there until it is explicitly uninstalled.
      Whether a bundle has been started or stopped must be recorded in the
      persistent storage of the Framework. A bundle that has been persistently
      recorded as started must be started whenever the Framework starts until
      the bundle is explicitly stopped. The Start Level API influences the
      actual starting and stopping of bundles. See <xref
      linkend="framework.startlevel"/>.</para>

      <para>The <code>Bundle</code> interface defines a
      <code>getState()</code> method for returning a bundle's state.</para>

      <para>If this specification uses the term <emphasis>active</emphasis> to
      describe a state, then this includes the <code>STARTING</code> and
      <code>STOPPING</code> states.</para>

      <para>Bundle states are expressed as a bit-mask though a bundle can only
      be in one state at any time. The following code sample can be used to
      determine if a bundle is in the <code>STARTING</code>,
      <code>ACTIVE</code>, or <code>STOPPING</code> state:</para>

      <programlisting>if ((b.getState() &amp; (STARTING | ACTIVE| STOPPING)) != 0)
    doActive()</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1314099">
      <title>Installing Bundles</title>

      <para>The <code>BundleContext</code> interface, which is given to the
      Bundle Activator of a bundle, defines the following methods for
      installing a bundle:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleContext.installBundle-String-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Installs a bundle from the specified
          location string (which should be a URL).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleContext.installBundle-String-InputStream-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Installs a bundle from the specified
          <code>InputStream</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A bundle must be valid before it is installed, otherwise the
      install must fail. The validity of a bundle is discussed in <xref
      linkend="framework.module.bundle.validity"/>.</para>

      <para>If the to be installed bundle has a bundle symbolic name and
      version pair that is already installed in the framework then the
      installation is only valid when the
      <code>org.osgi.framework.bsnversion</code> framework launching property
      is set to <code>multiple</code> or <code>managed</code>. See <xref
      linkend="framework.bundlehooks.collisionhook"/> for more
      information.</para>

      <para>Every bundle is uniquely identified by its location string. If an
      installed bundle is using the specified location, the
      <code>installBundle</code> methods must return the <code>Bundle</code>
      object for that installed bundle and not install a new bundle.</para>

      <para>The Framework must assign a unique bundle identifier that is
      higher than any previous bundle identifier.</para>

      <para>The installation of a bundle in the Framework must be:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Persistent</emphasis> - The bundle must remain
          installed across Framework and Java VM invocations until it is
          explicitly uninstalled.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Atomic</emphasis> - The install method must
          completely install the bundle or, if the installation fails, the
          OSGi framework must be left in the same state as it was in before
          the method was called.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Once a bundle has been installed, a <code>Bundle</code> object is
      created and all remaining life cycle operations must be performed upon
      this object. The returned <code>Bundle</code> object can be used to
      start, stop, update, and uninstall the bundle.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3270316">
      <title>Resolving Bundles</title>

      <para>A bundle can enter the <code>RESOLVED</code> state when the
      Framework has successfully resolved the bundle's dependencies as
      described in the manifest. These dependencies are described in <xref
      linkend="framework.module.resolvingprocess"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3270328">
      <title>Starting Bundles</title>

      <para>A bundle can be <emphasis>started</emphasis> by calling one of the
      <code>start</code> methods on its <code>Bundle</code> object or the
      Framework can automatically start the bundle if the bundle is
      <emphasis>ready</emphasis> and the <emphasis>autostart
      setting</emphasis> of the bundle indicates that it must be
      started.</para>

      <para>A bundle is <emphasis>ready</emphasis> if following conditions are
      all met:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The bundle can be resolved</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the optional Start Level API is used, then the bundle's
          start level is met.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Once a bundle is started, a bundle must be
      <emphasis>activated</emphasis>, see <xref linkend="i3270394"/>, to give
      control to the bundle so that it can initialize. This activation can
      take place immediately (<emphasis>eager activation</emphasis>), or upon
      the first class load from the bundle (<emphasis>lazy
      activation</emphasis>). A started bundle may need to be automatically
      started again by the framework after a restart or changes in the start
      level. The framework therefore maintains a persistent
      <emphasis>autostart setting</emphasis> for each bundle. This autostart
      setting can have the following values:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Stopped</emphasis> - The bundle should not be
          started.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Started with eager activation</emphasis> - The
          bundle must be started once it is ready and it must then be eagerly
          activated.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Started with declared activation</emphasis> - The
          bundle must be started once it is ready and it must then be
          activated according to its declared activation policy. See <xref
          linkend="i3270439"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The <code>Bundle</code> interface defines the
      <code>start(int)</code> method for starting a bundle and controlling the
      autostart setting. The <code>start(int)</code> method takes an integer
      option, the following values have been defined for this option:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>0</code> - Start the bundle with eager activation and
          set the autostart setting to <emphasis>Started with eager
          activation</emphasis>. If the bundle was already started with the
          lazy activation policy and is awaiting activation, then it must be
          activated immediately.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.START_TRANSIENT"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Identical to 0 in behavior, however, the
          autostart setting must <emphasis>not</emphasis> be altered. If the
          bundle can not be started, for example, the bundle is not ready,
          then a Bundle Exception must be thrown.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.START_ACTIVATION_POLICY"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Start the bundle using the activation
          policy declared in the manifest's Bundle-ActivationPolicy header and
          set the autostart setting to <emphasis>Started with declared
          activation</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>START_ACTIVATION_POLICY | START_TRANSIENT</code> - Start
          the bundle with the bundle's declared activation policy but do not
          alter the autostart setting.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Framework must attempt to resolve the bundle, if not already
      resolved, when trying to start the bundle. If the bundle fails to
      resolve, the start method must throw a <code>BundleException</code>. In
      this case, the bundle's autostart setting must still be set unless
      <code>START_TRANSIENT</code> is used.</para>

      <para>When the start method returns without an exception, the state of
      the bundle will either be <code>ACTIVE</code> or <code>STARTING</code>,
      depending on the declared activation policy and whether it was used. If
      the <code>start</code> method throws an exception, then the bundle will
      not be in either of these states and the <code>stop</code> method will
      not be called for this Bundle Activator instance.</para>

      <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.start--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method calls <code>start(0)</code>.</para>

      <para>The optional Start Level API influences the actual order of
      starting and stopping of bundles. See <xref
      linkend="framework.startlevel"/>. Fragment bundles can not be started
      and must cause a Bundle Exception when there is an attempt to start
      them.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3270394">
      <title>Activation</title>

      <para>A bundle is activated by calling its Bundle Activator object, if
      one exists. The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleActivator"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface defines methods that the Framework
      invokes when it starts and stops the bundle.</para>

      <para>To inform the OSGi environment of the fully qualified class name
      serving as its Bundle Activator, a bundle developer must declare a
      Bundle-Activator manifest header in the bundle's manifest file. The
      Framework must instantiate a new object of this class and cast it to a
      <code>BundleActivator</code> instance. It must then call the
      <code>BundleActivator.start</code> method to start the bundle.</para>

      <para>The following is an example of a Bundle-Activator manifest
      header:</para>

      <programlisting>Bundle-Activator: com.acme.Activator</programlisting>

      <para>A class acting as a Bundle Activator must implement the
      <code>BundleActivator</code> interface, be declared <code>public</code>,
      and have a public default constructor so an instance of it may be
      created with <code>Class.newInstance</code>.</para>

      <para>Supplying a Bundle Activator is optional. For example, a library
      bundle that only exports a number of packages does not need to define a
      Bundle Activator. In addition, other mechanism exists to obtain control
      and get a Bundle Context, like for example the Service Component
      Runtime.</para>

      <para>The <code>BundleActivator</code> interface defines these methods
      for starting and stopping a bundle:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleActivator.start-BundleContext-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This method can allocate resources that a
          bundle needs, start threads, register services, and more. If this
          method does not register any services, the bundle can register
          services it needs later: for example, in a callback or an external
          event, as long as it is in the <code>ACTIVE</code> state. If the
          <code>start(BundleContext)</code> method throws an exception, the
          Framework must mark the bundle as stopped and send out
          <code>STOPPING</code> and <code>STOPPED</code> events but it must
          not call the Bundle Activator <code>stop(BundleContext)</code>
          method. The start method must therefore be careful to clean up any
          resources it creates in the start method when it throws an
          exception.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleActivator.stop-BundleContext-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This method must undo all the actions of
          the <code>BundleActivator.start(BundleContext)</code> method.
          However, it is unnecessary to unregister services or Framework
          listeners, because they must be cleaned up by the Framework anyway.
          This method is only called when the bundle has reached the
          <code>ACTIVE</code> state. That is, when the start method has thrown
          exception, the <code>stop</code> method is never called for the same
          instance.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para xml:id="i3270437">A Bundle Activator must be created when a Bundle
      is started, implying the creation of a class loader. For larger systems,
      this greedy strategy can significantly increase startup times and
      unnecessarily increase the memory footprint. Mechanisms such as the
      Service Component Runtime and activation policies can mitigate these
      problems.</para>

      <para>Fragment bundles must not have a Bundle Activator
      specified.</para>

      <section xml:id="i3270439">
        <title>Activation Policies</title>

        <para>The activation of a bundle can also be deferred to a later time
        from its start using an <emphasis>activation policy</emphasis>. This
        policy is specified in the Bundle-ActivationPolicy header with the
        following syntax:</para>

        <programlisting>Bundle-ActivationPolicy ::= policy ( ';' directive )*
policy ::= 'lazy'</programlisting>

        <para>The only policy defined is the <code>lazy</code> activation
        policy. If no Bundle-ActivationPolicy header is specified, the bundle
        will use eager activation.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="i3270445">
        <title>Lazy Activation Policy</title>

        <para>A <code>lazy</code> activation policy indicates that the bundle,
        once started, must not be activated until it receives the first
        request to load a class. This request can originate either during
        normal class loading or via the Bundle <code>loadClass</code> method.
        Resource loading and a request for a class that is re-directed to
        another bundle must not trigger the activation. The first request is
        relative to the bundle class loader, a bundle will not be lazily
        started if it is stopped and then started again without being
        refreshed in the mean time.</para>

        <para>This change from the default eager activation policy is
        reflected in the state of the bundle and its events. When a bundle is
        started using a lazy activation policy, the following steps must be
        taken:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A Bundle Context is created for the bundle.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The bundle state is moved to the <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.STARTING"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.LAZY_ACTIVATION"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event is fired.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The system waits for a class load from the bundle to
            occur.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The normal <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.STARTING"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event is fired.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The bundle is activated.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The bundle state is moved to <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.ACTIVE"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.STARTED"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> event is fired.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If the activation fails because the Bundle Activator
        <code>start</code> method has thrown an exception, the bundle must be
        stopped without calling the Bundle Activator <code>stop</code> method.
        These steps are pictured in a flow chart in <xref
        linkend="i3270475"/>. This flow chart also shows the difference in
        activation policy of the normal eager activation and the lazy
        activation.</para>

        <figure xml:id="i3270475">
          <title>Starting with eager activation versus lazy activation</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="4.704in"
                         contentwidth="4.975in"
                         fileref="eager-lazy-activation.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The <code>lazy</code> activation policy allows a Framework
        implementation to defer the creation of the bundle class loader and
        activation of the bundle until the bundle is first used; potentially
        saving resources and initialization time during startup.</para>

        <para>By default, any class loaded from the bundle can trigger the
        lazy activation, however, resource loads must not trigger the
        activation. The <code>lazy</code> activation policy can define which
        classes cause the activation with the following directives:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>include</code> - A list of package names that must
            trigger the activation when a class is loaded from any of these
            packages. The default is all package names present in the
            bundle.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>exclude</code> - A list of package names that must not
            trigger the activation of the bundle when a class is loaded from
            any of these packages. The default is no package names.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>For example:</para>

        <programlisting>Bundle-ActivationPolicy: lazy; «
    include:="com.acme.service.base,com.acme.service.help"</programlisting>

        <para>When a class load triggers the lazy activation, the Framework
        must first define the triggering class. This definition can trigger
        additional lazy activations. These activations must be deferred until
        all transitive class loads and defines have finished. Thereafter, the
        activations must be executed in the reverse order of detection. That
        is, the last detected activation must be executed first. Only after
        all deferred activations are finished must the class load that
        triggered the activation return with the loaded class. If an error
        occurs during this process, it should be reported as a Framework
        <code>ERROR</code> event. However, the class load must succeed
        normally. A bundle that fails its lazy activation should not be
        activated again until the framework is restarted or the bundle is
        explicitly started by calling the <code>Bundle</code> start
        method.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="i3285256">
        <title>Restoring State After Refresh or Update</title>

        <para>The refresh operation, see <xref
        linkend="framework.wiring.refreshing"/>, and the <code>update</code>
        methods can cause other bundles to be stopped. Started bundles can be
        in the <code>ACTIVE</code> state or waiting to be activated, depending
        on their activation policy. The following rules must be applied when
        restoring the state after an update or refresh:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>An <code>ACTIVE</code> or <code>STARTING</code> bundle must
            be started <emphasis>transiently</emphasis> after an update or
            refresh operation to not change its persistent autostart
            state.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the bundle was in the <code>STARTING</code> state due to
            lazy activation, the bundle's activation policy should be used
            when starting the bundle.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Stopping Bundles</title>

      <para>The <code>Bundle</code> interface defines the
      <code>stop(int)</code> method for stopping a bundle. This calls the stop
      method when the bundle is in the <code>ACTIVE</code> state and sets the
      bundle's state to <code>RESOLVED</code>. The <code>stop(int)</code>
      takes an integer option. The following value has been defined for this
      option:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>0</code> - If the bundle was activated, then deactivate
          the bundle and sets the autostart setting for this bundle to
          <emphasis>Stopped</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.STOP_TRANSIENT"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - If the bundle was activated, then
          deactivate the bundle. Does not alter the autostart setting for this
          bundle.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The <code>stop()</code> method calls <code>stop(0)</code>.</para>

      <para>The optional Start Level API influences the actual order of
      starting and stopping of bundles. See <xref
      linkend="framework.startlevel"/>.</para>

      <para>Attempting to stop a Fragment bundle must result in a Bundle
      Exception.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Deactivation</title>

      <para>The <code>BundleActivator</code> interface defines a
      <code>stop(BundleContext)</code> method, which is invoked by the
      Framework to stop a bundle. This method must release any resources
      allocated since activation. All threads associated with the stopping
      bundle should be stopped immediately. The threaded code may no longer
      use Framework-related objects (such as services and
      <code>BundleContext</code> objects) once the stop method returns.</para>

      <para>If the stopping bundle had registered any services or Framework
      listeners during its lifetime, then the Framework must automatically
      unregister all registered services and Framework listeners when the
      bundle is stopped. It is therefore unnecessary from the Framework's
      point of view to unregister any services or Framework listeners in the
      <code>stop</code> method.</para>

      <para>The Framework must guarantee that if a
      <code>BundleActivator</code>. <code>start</code> method has executed
      successfully, that same <code>BundleActivator</code> object must be
      called with its <code>BundleActivator</code>.<code>stop</code> method
      when the bundle is deactivated. After calling the <code>stop</code>
      method, that particular <code>BundleActivator</code> object must never
      be used again.</para>

      <para>Packages exported by a stopped bundle continue to be available to
      other bundles. This continued export implies that other bundles can
      execute code from a stopped bundle, and the designer of a bundle should
      assure that this is not harmful. Exporting interfaces only is one way to
      prevent such unwanted execution when the bundle is not started.
      Generally, to ensure they cannot be executed, interfaces should not
      contain executable code.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3284680">
      <title>Updating Bundles</title>

      <para>The <code>Bundle</code> interface defines two methods for updating
      a bundle:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.update--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This method updates a bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.update-InputStream-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - This method updates a bundle from the
          specified <code>InputStream</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The update process supports migration from one revision of a
      bundle to a newer revision of the same bundle. The capabilities provided
      by the new revision must be immediately available to the Framework. If
      the old bundle revision has an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.isInUse--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> bundle wiring then all capabilities provided by
      the old bundle wiring must remain available for existing bundles and
      future resolves until the bundle is refreshed, see <xref
      linkend="framework.wiring.refreshing"/>, or the Framework is restarted.
      Otherwise the capabilities provided by the old revision must be
      removed.</para>

      <para>After the update operation is complete, the framework must attempt
      to move the bundle to the same state as it was before the operation
      taking the activation policy into account, without changing the
      autostart setting. This is described in more detail in <xref
      linkend="i3285256"/>.</para>

      <para>An updater of a bundle must have
      <code>AdminPermission[&lt;bundle&gt;,LIFECYCLE]</code> for both the
      installed bundle as well as the new bundle. The parameters of
      <code>AdminPermission</code> are explained in <xref
      linkend="framework.lifecycle.adminpermission"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Uninstalling Bundles</title>

      <para>The <code>Bundle</code> interface defines the
      <code>uninstall()</code> method for uninstalling a bundle from the
      Framework. This method causes the Framework to notify other bundles that
      the bundle is being uninstalled, and sets the bundle's state to
      <code>UNINSTALLED</code>. To whatever extent possible, the Framework
      must remove any resources related to the bundle. This method must always
      uninstall the bundle from the persistent storage of the
      Framework.</para>

      <para>If the uninstalled bundle has one or more revisions with <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.isInUse--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> bundle wirings then all capabilities provided by
      the old in use bundle wirings must remain available for existing bundles
      and future resolves until the bundle is refreshed, see <xref
      linkend="framework.wiring.refreshing"/>, or the Framework is restarted.
      Otherwise the capabilities provided by the old revision must be
      removed.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle-lastmodified">
      <title>Detecting Bundle Modifications</title>

      <para>The Bundle object provides a convenient way to detect
      modifications in a bundle. The Framework must keep the time that a
      bundle is modified by any of the life cycle operations or, in the case
      of multi-release JARs, by changing the version of Java platform being
      used. See <xref linkend="framework.module-multireleasejar"/>. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.getLastModified--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method will return the last time the bundle was
      effectively modified. This last modified time must be stored
      persistently.</para>

      <para>The method must return the number of milliseconds since midnight
      Jan. 1, 1970 UTC with the condition that a modification must always
      result in a higher value than the previous last modified time of any
      bundle.</para>

      <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.getLastModified--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is very useful when a bundle is caching
      resources from another bundle and needs to refresh the cache when the
      other bundle is effectively modified. A modification in the other bundle
      can happen while the caching bundle is not active. The last modified
      time is therefore a convenient way to track modifications in
      bundles.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle-getheaders">
      <title>Retrieving Manifest Headers</title>

      <para>The <code>Bundle</code> interface defines two methods to return
      manifest header information: <code>getHeaders()</code> and
      <code>getHeaders(String)</code>.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.getHeaders--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns a <code>Dictionary</code> object
          that contains the bundle's manifest headers and values as key/value
          pairs. The values returned are localized according to the default
          locale returned by <code>java.util.Locale.getDefault</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.getHeaders-String-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns a <code>Dictionary</code> object
          that contains the bundle's manifest headers and values as key/value
          pairs. The returned values are localized using the specified locale.
          The locale may take the following values:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><code>null</code> - The default locale returned by
              <code>java.util.Locale.getDefault</code> is used. This makes
              this method identical to the <code>getHeaders()</code>
              method.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis>Empty string</emphasis> - The dictionary will
              contain the raw (unlocalized) manifest headers including any
              leading '%'.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis>A Specific Locale</emphasis> - The given locale
              is used to localize the manifest headers.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the bundle is a multi-release JAR, see <xref
      linkend="framework.module-multireleasejar"/>, then the returned manifest
      header information must be the supplemented manifest information. That
      is, the main manifest with the replacement values from a supplemental
      manifest, if any, for the current Java platform version.</para>

      <para>Localization is performed according to the description in <xref
      linkend="framework.module.localization"/>. If no translation is found
      for a specific key, the <code>Dictionary</code> returned by
      <code>Bundle.getHeaders</code> will return the raw values as specified
      in the manifest header values without the leading '%' character.</para>

      <para>These methods require <code>AdminPermission[&lt;bundle&gt;,</code>
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.AdminPermission.METADATA"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>] because some of the manifest header information
      may be sensitive, such as the packages listed in the Export-Package
      header. Bundles always have permission to read their own headers.</para>

      <para>The <code>getHeaders</code> methods must continue to provide the
      manifest header information after the bundle enters the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.UNINSTALLED" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      state. After the bundle has been uninstalled, this method will only
      return manifest headers that are raw or localized for the default locale
      at the time the bundle was uninstalled.</para>

      <para>A framework implementation must use only the raw (unlocalized)
      manifest headers when processing manifest headers. Localizations must
      not influence the operations of the Framework.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Loading Classes</title>

      <para>In certain cases, it is necessary to load classes as if they were
      loaded from inside the bundle. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.loadClass-String-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method gives access to the bundle class loader.
      This method can be used to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Load plugins from another bundle</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Start an application model activator</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Interact with legacy code</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For example, an application model could use this feature to load
      the initial class from the bundle and start it according to the rules of
      the application model.</para>

      <programlisting>void appStart() {
    Class initializer =  bundle.loadClass(activator);
    if ( initializer != null ) {
      App app = (App) initializer.newInstance();
      app.activate();
   }
}</programlisting>

      <para>Loading a class from a bundle can cause it to be activated if the
      bundle uses a lazy activation policy.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3258563">
      <title>Access to Resources</title>

      <para>The resources from a bundle can come from different sources. They
      can come from the raw JAR file, Fragment bundles, imported packages, or
      the bundle class path. Different use cases require a different resource
      search strategy. The <code>Bundle</code> interface provides a number of
      methods that access resources but use different strategies. The
      following search strategies are supported:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Class Space</emphasis> - The
          <code>getResource(String)</code> and
          <code>getResources(String)</code> provide access to resources that
          is consistent with the class space as described in <xref
          linkend="framework.module.overallsearchorder"/>. Following the
          search order can make certain parts of the JAR files inaccessible.
          These methods require that the bundle is resolved. If the bundle is
          not resolved, the Framework must attempt to resolve it.</para>

          <para>The search order can hide certain directories of the JAR file.
          Split packages are taken into account; therefore, resources with the
          same package names can come from different JARs. If the bundle is
          unresolved (or cannot be resolved), the <code>getResource</code> and
          <code>getResources</code> methods must only load resources from the
          bundle class path. This search strategy should be used by code that
          wants to access its own resources. Calling either method can cause
          the creation of a class loader and force the bundle to become
          resolved.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>JAR File</emphasis> - The
          <code>getEntry(String)</code> and <code>getEntryPaths(String)</code>
          methods provide access to the resources in the bundle's JAR file. No
          searching is involved, only the raw JAR file is taken into account.
          The purpose of these methods is to provide low-level access without
          requiring that the bundle is resolved.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Space</emphasis> - The
          <code>findEntries(String,String,boolean)</code> is an intermediate
          form. Useful when configuration or setup information is needed from
          another bundle. It considers Fragment bundles but it must never
          create a class loader or use the bundle class path. The method
          provides access to all directories in the associated JAR
          files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For example, consider the following setup:</para>

      <programlisting>A: Require-Bundle: D
   Import-Package: q,t
   Export-Package: t
B: Export-Package: q,t
C: Fragment-Host: A
D: Export-Package: s</programlisting>

      <para>This setup is depicted in <xref linkend="i2787402"/>.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i2787402">
        <title>Setup for showing the difference between getResource and
        getEntry</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.858in"
                       contentwidth="7.418in"
                       fileref="getresource-v-getentry.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The following table shows the effect of getting a resource from
      this setup when bundle <code>A</code> is resolved.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Differences between getResource, getEntry, and findEntries for
        resolved bundle A</title>

        <tgroup cols="4">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Resource</entry>

              <entry>getResource</entry>

              <entry>getEntry</entry>

              <entry>findEntries</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>q</code></entry>

              <entry><code>B.q</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>p</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.p &gt; C.p</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.p</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.p &gt; C.p</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>r</code></entry>

              <entry><code>C.r</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>

              <entry><code>C.r</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>s</code></entry>

              <entry><code>D.s</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>t</code></entry>

              <entry><code>B.t</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.t</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.t</code></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>The following table shows the same cases as the previous table but
      now for an unresolved bundle <code>A</code>.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Differences between getResource, getEntry, and findEntries for
        an unresolved bundle A</title>

        <tgroup cols="4">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Resource</entry>

              <entry>getResource</entry>

              <entry>getEntry</entry>

              <entry>findEntries</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>q</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>p</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.p</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.p</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.p</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>r</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>s</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>

              <entry><code>null</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>t</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.t</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.t</code></entry>

              <entry><code>A.t</code></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3351251">
      <title>Permissions of a Bundle</title>

      <para>The <code>Bundle</code> interface defines a method for returning
      information pertaining to a bundle's permissions:
      <code>hasPermission(Object)</code>. This method returns
      <code>true</code> if the bundle's Protection Domain has the specified
      permission, and <code>false</code> if it does not, or if the object
      specified by the argument is not an instance of
      <code>java.security.Permission</code>. Fragments also have their own
      Protection Domain.</para>

      <para>The parameter type is <code>Object</code> so that the Framework
      can be implemented on Java platforms that do not support Java based
      security.</para>

      <para>See <xref linkend="service.condpermadmin.permissioncheck"/> for
      more information about the permission checks.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i3264631">
      <title>Access to a Bundle's Bundle Context</title>

      <para>Bundles that have been started have a Bundle Context. This object
      is a <emphasis>capability</emphasis>; it is intended to be used only by
      the bundle. However, there are a number of cases where bundles must act
      on behalf of other bundles. For example, the Service Component Runtime
      registers services on behalf of other bundles. The framework therefore
      provides access to another bundle's context via the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.getBundleContext--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. If there is no Bundle Context for that
      Bundle because the bundle is a fragment bundle or the bundle state is
      not in <code>{ STARTING, ACTIVE, STOPPING }</code>, then
      <code>null</code> must be returned.</para>

      <para>This method is potentially harmful because it allows any bundle to
      act as any other bundle. In a secure system, the method is protected by
      requiring <code>AdminPermission[*,CONTEXT]</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle.adaptations">
      <title>Adaptations</title>

      <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.adapt-Class-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method allows the Bundle to be
      <emphasis>adapted</emphasis> to different types. The purpose of this
      method is to provide more specialized access to the Bundle object,
      access that is not always needed by most clients of the interface. For
      example, the <code>adapt</code> method can be used to adapt a Bundle
      object to the current <code>BundleWiring</code> object (if resolved).
      The adapt method is used as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>BundleWiring bw = aBundle.adapt(BundleWiring.class);</programlisting>

      <para>The following table shows the minimum list of types that can be
      used in the adapt method. However, implementations and specifications
      can extend this list.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Minimum set of classes that can be adapted from Bundle</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Class</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para><code>AccessControlContext</code></para></entry>

              <entry><para>The Access Control Context for this bundle
              according to <xref linkend="i3351251"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleContext"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>The Bundle Context for this bundle.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleRevision"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>The current Bundle Revision for this bundle, see
              <xref linkend="framework.wiring"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleRevisions"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>All existing Bundle Revision objects for this
              bundle, see <xref linkend="framework.wiring"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.BundleStartLevel"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>The Bundle Start Level for this bundle, see <xref
              linkend="framework.startlevel"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>The Bundle Wiring for the current Bundle Revision,
              see <xref linkend="framework.wiring"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.launch.Framework"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>The Framework object from the launching API if this
              bundle is the System Bundle, see <xref
              linkend="framework.lifecycle-frameworks"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel.FrameworkStartLevel"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>The Framework Start Level if this is the System
              Bundle, see <xref
              linkend="framework.startlevel"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><para>The Framework Wiring if this bundle is the System
              Bundle. See <xref linkend="framework.wiring"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle-bundlecontext">
    <title>The Bundle Context</title>

    <para>The relationship between the Framework and its installed bundles is
    realized by the use of <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleContext"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> objects. A <code>BundleContext</code> object
    represents the execution context of a single bundle within the OSGi
    framework, and acts as a proxy to the underlying Framework.</para>

    <para>A <code>BundleContext</code> object is created by the Framework when
    a bundle is started. The bundle can use this private
    <code>BundleContext</code> object for the following purposes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Installing new bundles into the OSGi environment. See <xref
        linkend="i1314099"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Interrogating other bundles installed in the OSGi environment.
        See <xref linkend="i1237198"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Obtaining a persistent storage area. See <xref
        linkend="i1236436"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Retrieving service objects of registered services. See <xref
        linkend="framework.service.servicereferences"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Registering services in the Framework service. See <xref
        linkend="framework.service.registeringservices"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Subscribing or unsubscribing to events broadcast by the
        Framework. See <xref linkend="i3032481"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>When a bundle is started, the Framework creates a
    <code>BundleContext</code> object and provides this object as an argument
    to the <code>start(BundleContext)</code> method of the bundle's Bundle
    Activator. Each bundle is provided with its own <code>BundleContext</code>
    object; these objects should not be passed between bundles, since the
    <code>BundleContext</code> object is related to the security and resource
    allocation aspects of a bundle.</para>

    <para>After the <code>stop(BundleContext)</code> method has returned, the
    <code>BundleContext</code> object must no longer be used. Framework
    implementations must throw an exception if the <code>BundleContext</code>
    object is used after a bundle is stopped.</para>

    <para>The <code>BundleContext</code> object is only valid during the
    <code>{ STARTING, ACTIVE, STOPPING }</code> states of a bundle. However,
    the <code>BundleContext</code> object becomes invalid after
    <code>stop(BundleContext)</code> returns (if the bundle has a Bundle
    Activator). The <code>BundleContext</code> object becomes invalid before
    disposing of any remaining registered services and releasing any remaining
    services in use. Since those activities can result in other bundles being
    called (for example, Service Listeners for <code>UNREGISTERING</code>
    events and Service Factories for unget operations), those other bundles
    can observe the stopping bundle in the <code>STOPPING</code> state but
    with an invalid <code>BundleContext</code> object.</para>

    <section xml:id="i1237198">
      <title>Getting Bundle Information</title>

      <para>The <code>BundleContext</code> interface defines methods to
      retrieve information about bundles installed in the OSGi
      framework:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleContext.getBundle--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns the single <code>Bundle</code>
          object associated with the <code>BundleContext</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleContext.getBundles--"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns an array of the bundles currently
          installed in the Framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleContext.getBundle-long-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returns the <code>Bundle</code> object
          specified by the unique identifier, or <code>null</code> if no
          matching bundle is found.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Bundle access is not restricted; any bundle can enumerate the set
      of installed bundles. Information that can identify a bundle, however
      (such as its location, or its header information), is only provided to
      callers that have
      <code>AdminPermission[&lt;bundle&gt;,METADATA]</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1236436">
      <title>Persistent Storage</title>

      <para>The Framework should provide a private persistent storage area for
      each installed bundle on platforms with some form of file system
      support.</para>

      <para>The <code>BundleContext</code> interface defines access to this
      storage in terms of the <code>File</code> class, which supports
      platform-independent definitions of file and directory names.</para>

      <para>The <code>BundleContext</code> interface defines a method to
      access the private persistent storage area:
      <code>getDataFile(String)</code>. This method takes a relative file name
      as an argument. It translates this file name into an absolute file name
      in the bundle's persistent storage area. It then returns a
      <code>File</code> object. This method returns <code>null</code> if there
      is no support for persistent storage.</para>

      <para>The Framework must automatically provide the bundle with
      <code>FilePermission[&lt;storage area&gt;, READ | WRITE | DELETE]</code>
      to allow the bundle to read, write, and delete files in that storage
      area.</para>

      <para>If <code>EXECUTE</code> permissions is required, then a relative
      path name can be used in the File Permission definition. For example,
      <code>FilePermission[bin/*,EXECUTE] specifies</code> that the
      sub-directory in the bundle's private data area may contain executables.
      This only provides execute permission within the Java environment and
      does not handle the potential underlying operating system issues related
      to executables.</para>

      <para>This special treatment applies only to <code>FilePermission</code>
      objects assigned to a bundle. Default permissions must not receive this
      special treatment. A <code>FilePermission</code> for a relative path
      name assigned via the <code>setDefaultPermission</code> method must be
      ignored.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i2068690">
      <title>Environment Properties</title>

      <para>The <code>BundleContext</code> interface defines a method for
      returning information pertaining to Framework properties:
      <code>getProperty(String)</code>. This method can be used to return the
      Framework launching properties; see <xref
      linkend="framework.lifecycle.launchingproperties"/>. This method will
      examine the System properties if the requested property is not available
      in the launching properties.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i3070515">
    <title>The System Bundle</title>

    <para xml:id="i3070521">In addition to normal bundles, the Framework
    itself is represented as a bundle. The bundle representing the Framework
    is referred to as the <emphasis>system bundle</emphasis>. Through the
    system bundle, the Framework may register services that can be used by
    other bundles. Examples of such a service is the Conditional Permission
    Admin service.</para>

    <para>The system bundle resembles the framework object when a framework is
    launched, but implementations are not required to use the same object for
    the framework object and the system bundle. However, both objects must
    have bundle id 0, same location, and bundle symbolic name.</para>

    <para>The system bundle is listed in the set of installed bundles returned
    by <code>BundleContext.getBundles()</code>, although it differs from other
    bundles in the following ways:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The system bundle is always assigned a bundle identifier of zero
        (<code>0</code>).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The system bundle <code>getLocation</code> method returns the
        string: "<code>System Bundle</code>", as defined in the
        <code>Constants</code> interface.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The system bundle has a bundle symbolic name that is unique for
        a specific version. However, the name <code>system.bundle</code> must
        be recognized as an alias to this implementation-defined name.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem xml:id="i3070525">
        <para>The system bundle's life cycle cannot be managed like normal
        bundles. Its life cycle methods must behave as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist xml:id="i3070527">
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis> start</emphasis> - Does nothing because the
            system bundle is already started.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem xml:id="i3070529">
            <para><emphasis> stop</emphasis> - Returns immediately and shuts
            down the Framework on another thread.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem xml:id="i3070531">
            <para><emphasis> update</emphasis> - Returns immediately, then
            stops and restarts the Framework on another thread.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem xml:id="i3070534">
            <para><emphasis> uninstall</emphasis> - The Framework must throw a
            <code>BundleException</code> indicating that the system bundle
            cannot be uninstalled.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>See <xref linkend="framework.lifecycle-frameworks"/> for more
        information about the starting and stopping of the Framework.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section xml:id="i3293513">
      <title>System Bundle Information</title>

      <para>The capabilities of the system bundle are obtained by adapting the
      system bundle to a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      as described in <xref linkend="framework.lifecycle.adaptations"/>. This
      is in preference to parsing the system bundle's headers.</para>

      <para>The system bundle's <code>Bundle.getHeaders</code> method returns
      a <code>Dictionary</code> object with implementation-specific manifest
      headers. The following headers of this OSGi specification can be
      returned in this dictionary. Headers not mentioned in this table should
      not be used.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Supported headers in the system bundle getHeaders
        method</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="3*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Header</entry>

              <entry>Type</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-ContactAddress</code></entry>

              <entry><code>optional</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Recommended to provide the framework vendor's
              contact address.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-Copyright</code></entry>

              <entry><code>optional</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Recommended to provide the framework's copyright
              information.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-Description</code></entry>

              <entry><code>optional</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Recommended description of the
              framework.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-DocURL</code></entry>

              <entry><code>optional</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Recommended documentation URL pointing to further
              information about the framework. </para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-Icon</code></entry>

              <entry><code>optional</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Recommended pointer to a preferably PNG icon
              representing this framework.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-Localization</code></entry>

              <entry><code>optional</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Recommended localization
              information.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-License</code></entry>

              <entry><code>optional</code></entry>

              <entry><para>License information about this framework
              implementation.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-ManifestVersion</code></entry>

              <entry><code>mandatory</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The maximum version of the manifest version
              understood by this framework.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-Name</code></entry>

              <entry><code>optional</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Recommended human readable name of this
              framework.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><code>Bundle-Required«</code></para><para><code>&#160;ExecutionEnvironment</code></para></entry>

              <entry><code>mandatory</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Mandatory: the list of execution environments
              supported by this framework. This header is deprecated, see
              <xref linkend="framework.namespaces.osgi.ee"/>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-SymbolicName</code></entry>

              <entry><code>mandatory</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The implementation name for this
              framework.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-Vendor</code></entry>

              <entry><code>optional</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Recommended vendor information</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Bundle-Version</code></entry>

              <entry><code>mandatory</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The version of this framework
              implementation.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Export-Package</code></entry>

              <entry><code>mandatory</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Contains packages that are exported by the
              Framework like <code>org.osgi.framework</code> but also the
              packages listed in the framework property
              <code>org.osgi.framework.system.packages</code> or
              <code>org.osgi.framework.system.packages.extra</code>.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i3032483">
    <title>Events</title>

    <para>The OSGi Framework Life Cycle layer supports the following types of
    events:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Reports changes in the life cycle of
        bundles.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Reports that the Framework is started, start
        level has changed, packages have been refreshed, or that an error has
        been encountered.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The actual event that is reported is available with the
    <code>getType</code> method. The integer that is returned from this method
    can be one of the constant names that are described in the class. However,
    events can, and will be, extended in the future. Unrecognized event types
    should be ignored.</para>

    <section xml:id="i3032481">
      <title>Listeners</title>

      <para>A listener interface is associated with each type of event. The
      following list describes these listeners.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleListener"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.SynchronousBundleListener"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Called with an event of type
          <code>BundleEvent</code> when a bundle's life cycle information has
          been changed.</para>

          <para><code>SynchronousBundleListener</code> objects are called
          synchronously during the processing of the event and must be called
          before any <code>BundleListener</code> object is called. The
          following events are sent by the Framework after it has moved to a
          different state:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.INSTALLED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent after a bundle is installed. The
              state is now Bundle <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.INSTALLED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.RESOLVED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent when the Framework has resolved a
              bundle. The state is now the Bundle <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.RESOLVED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.LAZY_ACTIVATION"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The bundle has specified an activation
              policy; its activation is deferred to a later point in time. The
              state is set to the Bundle <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.STARTING"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state. This is only sent to
              <code>SynchronousBundleListener</code> objects.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.STARTING"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent when the Framework is about to
              activate a bundle. This is only sent to
              <code>SynchronousBundleListener</code> objects. The state is now
              the Bundle <xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.STARTING"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.STARTED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent when the Framework has started a
              bundle. The state is now the Bundle <xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.ACTIVE"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> state.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.STOPPING"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent when the Framework is about to
              stop a bundle or the start method of the Bundle Activator has
              thrown an exception and the bundle is stopped. This event
              indicates that the Bundle Context will be destroyed. This event
              is only sent to <code>SynchronousBundleListener</code>
              objects.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent when the Framework has stopped a
              bundle.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.UNINSTALLED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent when the Framework has
              uninstalled a bundle</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.UNRESOLVED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent when the Framework detects that a
              bundle becomes unresolved; this could happen when the bundle is
              refreshed or updated. When a set of bundles are refreshed using
              the Wiring API then each bundle in the set must have an
              <code>UNRESOLVED</code> BundleEvent published. The
              <code>UNRESOLVED</code> BundleEvent must be published after all
              the bundles in the set have been stopped and, in the case of a
              synchronous bundle listener, <emphasis>before</emphasis> any of
              the bundles in the set are re-started. <code>RESOLVED</code> and
              <code>UNRESOLVED</code> do not have to paired.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.UPDATED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent after a bundle is updated.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkListener"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Called with an event of type
          <code>FrameworkEvent</code>. Framework events are of type:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.ERROR"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Important error that requires the
              immediate attention of an operator.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.INFO"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - General information that is of
              interest in special situations.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.PACKAGES_REFRESHED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Framework has refreshed the
              packages.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleEvent.STARTED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The Framework has performed all
              initialization and is running in normal mode.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STARTLEVEL_CHANGED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Is sent by the Framework after a new
              start level has been set and processed.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent by the Framework because of a
              stop operation on the system bundle.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED_BOOTCLASSPATH_MODIFIED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent by the Framework because of a
              stop operation on the system bundle and a boot class path
              extension bundle has been installed or updated.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.STOPPED_UPDATE"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Sent by the Framework because of an
              update operation on the system bundle. The Framework will be
              restarted after this event is fired.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.WARNING"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A warning to the operator that is not
              crucial but may indicate a potential error situation.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.framework.FrameworkEvent.WAIT_TIMEDOUT"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Returned from the
              <code>waitForStop</code> method when the Framework did not stop
              before the given wait time-out expired.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleContext"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface methods are defined which can be used
      to add and remove each type of listener.</para>

      <para>Events can be asynchronously delivered, unless otherwise stated,
      meaning that they are not necessarily delivered by the same thread that
      generated the event. The thread used to call an event listener is not
      defined.</para>

      <para>The Framework must publish a <code>FrameworkEvent.ERROR</code> if
      a callback to an event listener generates an unchecked exception -
      except when the callback happens while delivering a
      <code>FrameworkEvent.ERROR</code> (to prevent an infinite loop).</para>

      <para>Synchronous events have the unfortunate effect that, in rare
      cases, events can be delivered out of order to a listener. For example,
      a Service Event <code>UNREGISTERING</code> can be delivered before its
      corresponding Service Event <code>REGISTERED</code>. One pathological
      case is when a service listener (for example a Service Tracker)
      unregisters a service that it receives in the <code>REGISTERED</code>
      event for. If there are listeners queued behind the pathological
      listener then they see the unregistering before they see the
      registration.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i2708484">
      <title>Delivering Events</title>

      <para>If the Framework delivers an event asynchronously, it must:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Collect a snapshot of the listener list at the time the event
          is published (rather than doing so in the future just prior to event
          delivery), but before the event is delivered, so that listeners do
          not enter the list after the event happened.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ensure, at the time the snapshot is taken, that listeners on
          the list still belong to active bundles at the time the event is
          delivered.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It is possible to use more than one thread to deliver events.
          If this is the case then each handler must receive the events in the
          same order as the events were posted. This ensures that handlers see
          events in the expected order.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the Framework did not capture the current listener list when
      the event was published, but instead waited until just prior to event
      delivery, then the following error could occur: a bundle could have
      started and registered a listener, and then the bundle could see its own
      <code>BundleEvent.INSTALLED</code> event.</para>

      <para>The following three scenarios illustrate this concept.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Scenario one event sequence:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Event A is published.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Listener 1 is registered.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Asynchronous delivery of Event A is attempted.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Expected Behavior: Listener 1 must not receive Event A,
          because it was not registered at the time the event was
          published.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Scenario two event sequence:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Listener 2 is registered.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Event B is published.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Listener 2 is unregistered.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Asynchronous delivery of Event B is attempted.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Expected Behavior: Listener 2 receives Event B, because
          Listener 2 was registered at the time Event B was published.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Scenario three event sequence:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Listener 3 is registered.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Event C is published.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The bundle that registered Listener 3 is stopped.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Asynchronous delivery of Event C is attempted.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Expected Behavior: Listener 3 must not receive Event C,
          because its Bundle Context object is invalid.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i2708513">
      <title>Synchronization Pitfalls</title>

      <para>Generally, a bundle that calls a listener should not hold any Java
      monitors. This means that neither the Framework nor the originator of a
      synchronous event should be in a monitor when a callback is
      initiated.</para>

      <para>The purpose of a Java monitor is to protect the update of data
      structures. This should be a small region of code that does not call any
      code the effect of which cannot be overseen. Calling the OSGi Framework
      from synchronized code can cause unexpected side effects. One of these
      side effects might be <emphasis>deadlock</emphasis>. A deadlock is the
      situation where two threads are blocked because they are waiting for
      each other.</para>

      <para>Time-outs can be used to break deadlocks, but Java monitors do not
      have time-outs. Therefore, the code will hang forever until the system
      is reset (Java has deprecated all methods that can stop a thread). This
      type of deadlock is prevented by not calling the Framework (or other
      code that might cause callbacks) in a synchronized block.</para>

      <para>If locks are necessary when calling other code, use the Java
      monitor to create semaphores that can time-out and thus provide an
      opportunity to escape a deadlocked situation.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle.adminpermission">
      <title>Admin Permission</title>

      <para>The Admin Permission is a permission used to grant the right to
      manage the Framework with the option to restrict this right to a subset
      of bundles, called <emphasis>targets</emphasis>. For example, an
      Operator can give a bundle the right to only manage bundles of a signer
      that has a subject name of ACME:</para>

      <programlisting>org.osgi.framework.AdminPermission(
    "(signer=\*, o=ACME, c=us)", ... )</programlisting>

      <para>The actions of the Admin Permission are fine-grained. They allow
      the deployer to assign only the permissions that are necessary for a
      bundle. For example, an HTTP implementation could be granted access to
      all resources of all bundles.</para>

      <programlisting>org.osgi.framework.AdminPermission("*",
    "resource" )</programlisting>

      <para>Code that needs to check Admin Permission must always use the
      constructor that takes a bundle as parameter: <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.AdminPermission.AdminPermission-Bundle-String-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> with a single action.</para>

      <para>For example, the implementation of the <code>loadClass</code>
      method must check that the caller has access to the class space:</para>

      <programlisting>public class BundleImpl implements Bundle{

    Class loadClass(String name) {
        securityManager.checkPermission( 
            new AdminPermission(this,"class") );
            ...
    }
}</programlisting>

      <para>The Admin Permission takes a filter as its name. Filter based
      permissions are described in <xref
      linkend="framework.security.filterbasedpermissions"/>.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Actions</title>

        <para>The action parameter of Admin Permission will specify the subset
        of privileged administrative operations that are allowed by the
        Framework. The actions that are architected are listed in the
        following table. Future versions of the specification, as well as
        additional system services, can add additional actions. The given set
        should therefore not be assumed to be a closed set.</para>

        <table>
          <title>Admin Permission actions</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>

            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="2.7*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Action</entry>

                <entry>Used in</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><code>METADATA</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>Bundle.getHeaders</code></para><para><code>Bundle.getLocation</code></para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>RESOURCE</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>Bundle.getResource</code></para><para><code>Bundle.getResources</code></para><para><code>Bundle.getEntry</code></para><para><code>Bundle.getEntryPaths</code></para><para><code>Bundle.findEntries</code></para><para>Bundle
                resource/entry URL creation</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>CLASS</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>Bundle.loadClass</code></para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>LIFECYCLE</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>BundleContext.installBundle</code></para><para><code>Bundle.update</code></para><para><code>Bundle.uninstall</code></para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>EXECUTE</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>Bundle.start</code></para><para><code>Bundle.stop</code></para><para><code>BundleStartLevel.setBundleStartLevel</code></para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>LISTENER</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>BundleContext.addBundleListener</code> for
                SynchronousBundleListener
                </para><para><code>BundleContext.removeBundleListener</code>
                for SynchronousBundleListener</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>EXTENSIONLIFECYLE</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>BundleContext.installBundle</code> for
                extension bundles</para><para><code>Bundle.update</code> for
                extension bundles</para><para><code>Bundle.uninstall</code>
                for extension bundles</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>RESOLVE</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>FrameworkWiring.refreshBundles</code></para><para><code>FrameworkWiring.resolveBundles</code></para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>STARTLEVEL</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>FrameworkStartLevel.setStartLevel</code></para><para><code>FrameworkStartLevel.setInitialBundleStartLevel</code></para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>CONTEXT</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>Bundle.getBundleContext</code></para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>WEAVE</code></entry>

                <entry><para><code>WovenClass.setBytes</code></para><para><code>WovenClass.getDynamicImports</code></para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>The special action <code>"*"</code> will represent all
        actions.</para>

        <para>Each bundle must be given <code>AdminPermission(&lt;bundle
        identifier&gt;, "resource,metadata,class,context")</code> so that it
        can access its own resources and context. This is an implicit
        permission that must be automatically given to all bundles by the
        Framework.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="framework.lifecycle.privilegedcallbacks">
      <title>Privileged Callbacks</title>

      <para>The following interfaces define bundle callbacks that are invoked
      by the Framework:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>BundleActivator</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>ServiceFactory</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>BundleListener</code>, <code>ServiceListener</code>, and
          <code>FrameworkListener</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Framework hook services</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>When any of these callbacks are invoked by the Framework, the
      bundle that caused the callback may still be on the stack. For example,
      when one bundle installs and then starts another bundle, the installer
      bundle may be on the stack when the <code>BundleActivator.start</code>
      method of the installed bundle is called. Likewise, when a bundle
      registers a service object, it may be on the stack when the Framework
      calls back the <code>serviceChanged</code> method of all qualifying
      <code>ServiceListener</code> objects.</para>

      <para>Whenever any of these bundle callbacks try to access a protected
      resource or operation, the access control mechanism should consider not
      only the permissions of the bundle receiving the callback, but also
      those of the Framework and any other bundles on the stack. This means
      that in these callbacks, bundle programmers normally would use
      <code>doPrivileged</code> calls around any methods protected by a
      permission check (such as getting or registering service
      objects).</para>

      <para>In order to reduce the number of <code>doPrivileged</code> calls
      by bundle programmers, the Framework must perform a
      <code>doPrivileged</code> call around any bundle callbacks. The
      Framework should have <code>java.security.AllPermission</code>.
      Therefore, a bundle programmer can assume that the bundle is not further
      restricted except for its own permissions.</para>

      <para>Bundle programmers do not need to use <code>doPrivileged</code>
      calls in their implementations of any callbacks registered with and
      invoked by the Framework.</para>

      <para>For any other callbacks that are registered with a service object
      and therefore get invoked by the service-providing bundle directly,
      <code>doPrivileged</code> calls must be used in the callback
      implementation if the bundle's own privileges are to be exercised.
      Otherwise, the callback must fail if the bundle that initiated the
      callback lacks the required permissions.</para>

      <para>A framework must never load classes in a <code>doPrivileged</code>
      region, but must instead use the current stack. This means that static
      initializers and constructors must not assume that they are privileged.
      Any privileged code in a static initializer must be guarded with a
      <code>doPrivileged</code> region in the static initializer. Likewise, a
      framework must not instantiate a <code>BundleActivator</code> object in
      a <code>doPrivileged</code> region, but must instead use the current
      stack. This means that the <code>BundleActivator</code> constructor must
      not assume that it is privileged.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Lazy Activation</title>

      <para>The activation policy, see <xref linkend="i3270439"/>, can
      indirectly cause the activation of a bundle.
      <code>AdminPermission[*,CLASS ]</code> therefore implies the
      <code>EXECUTE</code> action during a <code>loadClass</code> method
      call.</para>

      <para>Normal class loading caused by executing Java class code must not
      require <code>AdminPermission[*,EXECUTE ]</code>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1296051"><title>The Standard for the Format of
      ARPA Internet Text Messages</title>STD 11, RFC 822, UDEL, August
      1982<?line-break ?><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc822.txt"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1296055"><title>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol -
      HTTP/1.1</title>RFC 2068 DEC, MIT/LCS, UC Irvine, January
      1997<?line-break ?><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2068.txt"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1199923"><title>Java Language
      Specification</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/specs/"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1199796"><title>A String Representation of LDAP
      Search Filters</title>RFC 1960, UMich, 1996<?line-break ?><biblioid
      class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1960.txt"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1200042"><title>Java Security
      Architecture</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/technotes/guides/security/spec/security-spec.doc.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1201324"><title>Java Package Versioning
      Specification</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/technotes/guides/versioning/index.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1304871"><title>Codes for the Representation of
      Names of Languages</title>ISO 639, International Standards
      Organization<?line-break ?><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://lcweb.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/langhome.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i2164952"><title>Manifest Format</title><biblioid
      class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/technotes/guides/jar/jar.html#JAR_Manifest"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i2461629"><title>W3C EBNF</title><biblioid
      class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.w3c.org/TR/REC-xml#sec-notation"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i2467175"><title>Interval Notation</title><biblioid
      class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.math.ohio-state.edu/courses/math104/interval.pdf"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3287541"><title>OSGi Reference
      Names</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://www.osgi.org/developer/specifications/reference/"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3290992"><title>JKS Keystore Format (reverse
      engineered)</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://metastatic.org/source/JKS.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3300085"><title>Java Service Provider
      Configuration</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/technotes/guides/jar/jar.html#Service_Provider"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i3324333"><title>IETF RFC 1422 A Universally Unique
      IDentifier (UUID) URN Namespace</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4122.txt"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Launching property <code>org.osgi.framework.storage</code> must
        be set when default value used.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added support for multi-release JARs. See <xref
        linkend="framework.lifecycle-lastmodified"/> and <xref
        linkend="framework.lifecycle-getheaders"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
