<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="52" revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="service.url"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>URL Handlers Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.url-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.url"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This specification standardizes the mechanism to extend the Java
    run-time with new URL schemes and content handlers through bundles.
    Dynamically extending the URL schemes that are supported in an OSGi
    framework is a powerful concept.</para>

    <para xml:id="i1294025">This specification is necessary because the
    standard Java mechanisms for extending the <code>URL</code> class with new
    schemes and different content types is not compatible with the dynamic
    aspects of an OSGi framework. The registration of a new scheme or content
    type is a one time only action in Java, and once registered, a scheme or
    content type can never be revoked. This singleton approach to registration
    makes the provided mechanism impossible to use by different, independent
    bundles. Therefore, it is necessary for OSGi Framework implementations to
    hide this mechanism and provide an alternative mechanism that can be
    used.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Multiple Access</emphasis> - Multiple bundles should
          be allowed to register <code>ContentHandler</code> objects and
          <code>URLStreamHandler</code> objects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Existing Schemes Availability</emphasis> - Existing
          schemes in an OSGi framework should not be overridden.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>life cycle Monitored</emphasis> - The life cycle of
          bundles must be supported. Scheme handlers and content type handlers
          must become unavailable when the registering bundle is
          stopped.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Simplicity</emphasis> - Minimal effort should be
          required for a bundle to provide a new URL scheme or content type
          handler.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Scheme</emphasis> - An identifier for a specific
          protocol. For example, <code>"http"</code> is a scheme for the Hyper
          Text Transfer Protocol. A scheme is implemented in a
          <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> sub-class.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Content Type</emphasis> - An identifier for the type
          of the content. Content types are usually referred to as MIME types.
          A content type handler is implemented as a
          <code>java.net.ContentHandler</code> sub-class.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Uniform Resource Locator (URL)</emphasis> - An
          instance of the <code>java.net.URL</code> class that holds the name
          of a scheme with enough parameters to identify a resource for that
          scheme.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Factory</emphasis> - An object that creates other
          objects. The purpose is to hide the implementation types (that may
          vary) from the caller. The created objects are a
          subclass/implementation of a specific type.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Proxy</emphasis> - The object that is registered
          with Java and that forwards all calls to the real implementation
          that is registered with the service registry.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>java.net.URLStreamHandler</emphasis> - An instance
          of the <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> class that can create
          <code>URLConnection</code> objects that represent a connection for a
          specific protocol.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Singleton Operation</emphasis> - An operation that
          can only be executed once.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>URLStreamHandlerService</emphasis> - An OSGi service
          interface that contains the methods of the
          <code>URLStreamHandler</code> class with public visibility so they
          can be called from the Framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>AbstractURLStreamHandlerService</emphasis> - An
          implementation of the <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> interface
          that implements the interface's methods by calling the
          implementation of the super class
          (<code>java.net.url.URLStreamHandler</code>). This class also
          handles the setting of the <code>java.net.URL</code> object via the
          <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerSetter</code> interface.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>URLStreamHandlerSetter</emphasis> - An interface
          needed to abstract the setting of the <code>java.net.URL</code>
          object. This interface is related to the use of a proxy and security
          checking.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</emphasis> - A
          factory, registered with the <code>java.net.URL</code> class, that
          is used to find <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> objects
          implementing schemes that are not implemented by the Java
          environment. Only one <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</code>
          object can be registered with Java.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>java.net.URLConnection</emphasis> - A connection for
          a specific, scheme-based protocol. A
          <code>java.net.URLConnection</code> object is created by a
          <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> object when the
          <code>java.net.URL.openConnection</code> method is invoked.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>java.net.ContentHandler</emphasis> - An object that
          can convert a stream of bytes to a Java object. The class of this
          Java object depends on the MIME type of the byte stream.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>java.net.ContentHandlerFactory</emphasis> - A
          factory that can extend the set of
          <code>java.net.ContentHandler</code> objects provided by the
          <code>java.net.URLConnection</code> class, by creating new ones on
          demand. Only one <code>java.net.ContentHandlerFactory</code> object
          can be registered with the <code>java.net.URLConnection</code>
          class.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>MIME Type</emphasis> - A namespace for byte stream
          formats. See <xref linkend="i1260753"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following class diagram is surprisingly complex due to the
      complicated strategy that Java uses to implement extendable stream
      handlers and content handlers.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Class Diagram, java.net (URL and associated classes)</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="5.424in"
                       contentwidth="6.500in" fileref="url-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Operation</title>

      <para>A bundle that can implement a new URL scheme should register a
      service object under the <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> interface
      with the OSGi Framework. This interface contains public versions of the
      <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> class methods, so that these
      methods can be called by the <emphasis>proxy</emphasis> (the object that
      is actually registered with the Java run-time).</para>

      <para>The OSGi Framework implementation must make this service object
      available to the underlying <code>java.net</code> implementation. This
      must be supported by the OSGi Framework implementation because the
      <code>java.net.URL</code>.<code>setStreamHandlerFactory</code> method
      can only be called <emphasis>once</emphasis>, making it impossible to
      use by bundles that come and go.</para>

      <para xml:id="i1294041">Bundles that can convert a content-typed stream
      should register a service object under the name
      <code>java.net.ContentHandler</code>. These objects should be made
      available by the OSGi Framework to the
      <code>java.net.URLConnection</code> class.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Factories in java.net</title>

    <para>Java provides the <code>java.net.URL</code> class which is used by
    the OSGi Framework and many of the bundles that run on the OSGi framework.
    A key benefit of using the <code>URL</code> class is the ease with which a
    URL string is translated into a request for a resource.</para>

    <para>The extensibility of the <code>java.net.URL</code> class allows new
    schemes (protocols) and content types to be added dynamically using
    <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</code> objects. These new handlers
    allow existing applications to use new schemes and content types in the
    same way as the handlers provided by the Java run-time environment. This
    mechanism is described in the Javadoc for the
    <code>URLStreamHandler</code> and <code>ContentHandler</code>
    class.</para>

    <para>For example, the URL <code>http://www.osgi.org/sample.txt</code>
    addresses a file on the OSGi web server that is obtained with the HTTP
    scheme (usually a scheme provided by the Java run-time). A URL such as
    <code>rsh://www.acme.com/agent.zip</code> is addressing a ZIP file that
    can be obtained with the non-built-in RSH scheme. A
    <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</code> object must be registered
    with the <code>java.net.URL</code> class prior to the successful use of an
    RSH scheme.</para>

    <para>There are several problems with using only the existing Java
    facilities for extending the handlers used by the
    <code>java.net.URL</code> class:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Factories Are Singleton Operations</emphasis> - One
        <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</code> object can be registered
        <emphasis>once</emphasis> with the <code>java.net.URL</code> class.
        Similarly, one <code>java.net.ContentHandlerFactory</code> object can
        be registered once with the <code>java.net.URLConnection</code> class.
        It is impossible to undo the registration of a factory or register a
        replacement factory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Caching Of Schemes</emphasis> - When a previously
        unused scheme is first used by the <code>java.net.URL</code> class,
        the <code>java.net.URL</code> class requests a
        <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> object for that specific scheme
        from the currently registered
        <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</code> object. A returned
        <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> object is cached and subsequent
        requests for that scheme use the same
        <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> object. This means that once a
        handler has been constructed for a specific scheme, this handler can
        no longer be removed, nor replaced, by a new handler for that scheme.
        This caching is likewise done for <code>java.net.ContentHandler</code>
        objects.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Both problems impact the OSGi operating model, which allows a bundle
    to go through different life cycle stages that involve exposing services,
    removing services, updating code, replacing services provided by one
    bundle with services from another, etc. The existing Java mechanisms are
    not compatible when used by bundles.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Framework Procedures</title>

    <para>The OSGi Framework must register a
    <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</code> object and a
    <code>java.net.ContentHandlerFactory</code> object with the
    <code>java.net.URL.setURLStreamHandlerFactory</code> and
    <code>java.net.URLConnection.setContentHandlerFactory</code> methods,
    respectively.</para>

    <para>When these two factories are registered, the OSGi Framework service
    registry must be tracked for the registration of
    <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> services and
    <code>java.net.ContentHandler</code> services.</para>

    <para>A URL Stream Handler Service must be associated with a service
    registration property named <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.url.URLConstants.URL_HANDLER_PROTOCOL"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The value of this
    <code>url.handler.protocol</code> property must be an array of scheme
    names (<code>String[]</code> or <code>String</code>).</para>

    <para>A Content Handler service must be associated with a service
    registration property named <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.url.URLConstants.URL_CONTENT_MIMETYPE"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The value of the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.url.URLConstants.URL_CONTENT_MIMETYPE"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> property must be an array of MIME types names
    (<code>String[]</code> or <code>String</code>) in the form type/subtype.
    See <xref linkend="i1260753"/>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Constructing a Proxy and Handler</title>

      <para>When a URL is used with a previously unused scheme, it must query
      the registered <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</code> object
      (that should have been registered by the OSGi Framework). The OSGi
      Framework must then search the service registry for services that are
      registered under <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> and that match the
      requested scheme.</para>

      <para>If one or more service objects are found, a proxy object must be
      constructed. A proxy object is necessary because the service object that
      provides the implementation of the
      <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> object can become unregistered
      and Java does not provide a mechanism to withdraw a
      <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> object once it is returned from a
      <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</code> object.</para>

      <para>Once the proxy is created, it must track the service registry for
      registrations and unregistrations of services matching its associated
      scheme. The proxy must be associated with the service that matches the
      scheme and has the highest value for the
      <code>org.osgi.framework.Constants.SERVICE_RANKING</code> service
      registration property (see <xref
      linkend="framework.service.serviceproperties"/> ) at any moment in time.
      If a proxy is associated with a URL Stream Handler Service, it must
      change the associated handler to a newly registered service when that
      service has a higher value for the ranking property.</para>

      <para>The proxy object must forward all method requests to the
      associated URL Stream Handler Service until this service object becomes
      unregistered.</para>

      <para>Once a proxy is created, it cannot be withdrawn because it is
      cached by the Java run-time. However, service objects can be withdrawn
      and it is possible for a proxy to exist without an associated
      <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code>/<code>java.net.ContentHandler</code>
      object.</para>

      <para>In this case, the proxy must handle subsequent requests until
      another appropriate service is registered. When this happens, the proxy
      class must handle the error.</para>

      <para xml:id="i1359486">In the case of a URL Stream Handler proxy, it
      must throw a <code>java.net.MalformedURLException</code> exception if
      the signature of a method allows throwing this exception. Otherwise, a
      <code>java.lang.IllegalStateException</code> exception is thrown.</para>

      <para>In the case of a Content Handler proxy, it must return InputStream
      to the data.</para>

      <para>Bundles must ensure that their
      <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> or
      <code>java.net.ContentHandler</code> service objects throw these
      exceptions also when they have become unregistered.</para>

      <para>Proxies for Content Handler services operate slightly differently
      from URL Stream Handler Service proxies. In the case that
      <code>null</code> is returned from the registered
      <code>ContentHandlerFactory</code> object, the factory will not get
      another chance to provide a <code>ContentHandler</code> object for that
      content-type. Thus, if there is no built-in handler, nor a registered
      handler for this content-type, a <code>ContentHandler</code> proxy must
      be constructed that returns the <code>InputStream</code> object from the
      <code>URLConnection</code> object as the content object until a handler
      is registered.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1413781">
      <title>Built-in Handlers</title>

      <para>Implementations of Java provide a number of sub-classes of
      <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> classes that can handle protocols
      like HTTP, FTP, NEWS etc. Most Java implementations provide a mechanism
      to add new handlers that can be found on the class path through class
      name construction.</para>

      <para>If a registered <code>java.net.URLStreamHandlerFactory</code>
      object returns <code>null</code> for a built-in handler (or one that is
      available through the class name construction mechanism), it will never
      be called again for that specific scheme because the Java implementation
      will use its built-in handler or uses the class name
      construction.</para>

      <para>As a result, even though it is not forbidden for URL Handlers
      Service implementations to override built-in handlers, it is not
      possible to guarantee that a registered
      <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> object will be used when it is
      overriding a built-in handler. For consistency reasons, it is therefore
      recommended to never override built-in handlers.</para>

      <para>The Content Handler Factory is implemented using a similar
      technique and has therefore the same problems.</para>

      <para>To facilitate the discovery of built-in handlers that are
      available through the name construction, the method described in the
      next section must be used by the Framework before any handlers are
      searched for in the service registry.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Finding Built-in Handlers</title>

      <para>If the system properties <code>java.protocol.handler.pkgs</code>
      or <code>java.content.handler.pkgs</code> are defined, they must be used
      to locate built-in handlers. Each property must be defined as a list of
      package names that are separated by a vertical line (<code>'|'
      \u007C</code>) and that are searched in the left-to-right order (the
      names must <emphasis>not</emphasis> end in a full stop (<code>'.'
      \u002E</code>). For example:</para>

      <programlisting>org.osgi.impl.handlers | com.acme.url</programlisting>

      <para>The package names are the prefixes that are put in front of a
      scheme or content type to form a class name that can handle the scheme
      or content-type.</para>

      <para>A URL Stream Handler name for a scheme is formed by appending the
      string <code>".Handler"</code> to the scheme name. Using the packages in
      the previous example, the <code>rsh</code> scheme handler class is
      searched by the following names:</para>

      <programlisting>org.osgi.impl.handlers.rsh.Handler
com.acme.url.rsh.Handler</programlisting>

      <para xml:id="i1294084">MIME type names contain the solidus (<code>'/'
      \u002F</code>) character and can contain other characters that must not
      be part of a Java class name. A MIME type name must be processed as
      follows before it can be converted to a class name:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>First, all solidi in the MIME name must be converted to a full
          stop (<code>'.' \u002E</code>). All other characters that are not
          allowed in a Java class name must be converted to an underscore
          (<code>'_' \u005F</code>).</para>

          <para><programlisting>application/zip   application.zip
text/uri-list     text.uri_list
image/vnd.dwg     image.vnd_dwg</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>After this conversion, the name is appended to the list of
          packages specified in <code>java.content.handler.pkgs</code>. For
          example, if the content type is <code>application/zip</code>, and
          the packages are defined as in the previous example, then the
          following classes are searched:</para>

          <para><programlisting>org.osgi.impl.handlers.application.zip
com.acme.url.application.zip</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The Java run-time specific packages should be listed in the
      appropriate properties so that implementations of the URL Stream Handler
      Factory and Content Handler Factory can be made aware of these
      packages.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1407205">
      <title>Protected Methods and Proxy</title>

      <para xml:id="i1294132">Implementations of
      <code>java.net.URLStreamHandler</code> class cannot be registered in the
      service registry for use by the proxy because the methods of the
      <code>URLStreamHandler</code> class are protected and thus not available
      to the proxy implementation. Also, the <code>URLStreamHandler</code>
      class checks that only the <code>URLStreamHandler</code> object that was
      returned from the <code>URLStreamHandlerFactory</code> object can invoke
      the <code>setURL</code> method. This means that
      <code>URLStreamHandler</code> objects in the service registry would be
      unable to invoke the <code>setURL</code> method. Invoking this method is
      necessary when implementing the <code>parseURL</code> method.</para>

      <para>Therefore, the <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> and
      <code>URLStreamHandlerSetter</code> interfaces were created. The
      <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> interface provides public versions
      of the <code>URLStreamHandler</code> methods, except that the
      <code>setURL</code> method is missing and the <code>parseURL</code>
      method has a new first argument of type
      <code>URLStreamHandlerSetter</code>. In general, sub-classes of the
      <code>URLStreamHandler</code> class can be converted to
      <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> classes with minimal code changes.
      Apart from making the relevant methods public, the <code>parseURL</code>
      method needs to be changed to invoke the <code>setURL</code> method on
      the <code>URLStreamHandlerSetter</code> object that the
      <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> object was passed, rather then the
      <code>setURL</code> method of <code>URLStreamHandler</code>
      class.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i1292833">
        <title>Proxy Issues</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.700in"
                       contentwidth="6.243in" fileref="proxy-issues.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To aid in the conversion of <code>URLStreamHandler</code>
      implementation classes, the <code>AbstractURLStreamHandlerService</code>
      has been provided. Apart from making the relevant methods public, the
      <code>AbstractURLStreamHandlerService</code> stores the
      <code>URLStreamHandlerSetter</code> object in a private variable. To make the
      <code>setURL</code> method work properly, it overrides the
      <code>setURL</code> method to invoke the <code>setURL</code> method on
      the saved <code>URLStreamHandlerSetter</code> object rather then the
      <code>URLStreamHandler.setURL</code> method. This means that a subclass
      of <code>URLStreamHandler</code> should be changed to become a sub-class
      of the <code>AbstractURLStreamHandlerService</code> class and be
      recompiled.</para>

      <para>Normally, the <code>parseURL</code> method will have the following
      form:</para>

      <programlisting>class URLStreamHandlerImpl {
    ...
    protected URLStreamHandlerSetter realHandler;
    ... 
    public void parseURL(
        URLStreamHandlerSetter realHandler,
            URL u, String spec, int start, int limit) {
            this.realHandler = realHandler;
            parseURL(u, spec, start, limit);
    }
    protected void setURL(URL u,
        String protocol, String host,
        int port, String authority,
        String userInfo, String path,
        String query,String ref) {
            realHandler.setURL(u, protocol, host, 
                port, authority, userInfo, path,
                query, ref);
    }
    ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>URLStreamHandler.parseURL</code> method will call the
      <code>setURL</code> method which must be invoked on the proxy rather
      than <code>this</code>. That is why the <code>setURL</code> method is
      overridden to delegate to the <code>URLStreamHandlerSetter</code> object
      in <code>realHandler</code> as opposed to <code>super</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="i1405077">
      <title>Stream Handlers that use java.net.Proxy</title>

      <para>Java 1.5 introduced a new method on the
      <code>URLStreamHandler</code> class: <code>URLConnection</code>
      <code>openConnection(URL,Proxy)</code>. Adding this method to the URL
      Stream Handler service poses the following problems:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>It would have broken all existing implementations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The references to the java.net.Proxy class would make the API
          dependent on Java 1.5</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Therefore, scheme providers can optionally implement the
      <code>openConnection(URL,Proxy)</code> method as a public method. If the
      scheme provider implements this method, then the framework must call it
      (using reflection). If this method is not implemented in the URL Stream
      Handler service an Unsupported Operation Exception must be
      thrown.</para>

      <para>Framework implementations should be careful not to create unwanted
      dependencies on Java 1.5. This will require two different implementation
      classes for the URLStreamHandler class that is used to proxy the URL
      Stream Handler services.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Providing a New Scheme</title>

    <para xml:id="i1294185">The following example provides a scheme that
    returns the path part of the URL. The first class that is implemented is
    the <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code>. When it is started, it registers
    itself with the OSGi Framework. The OSGi Framework calls the
    <code>openConnection</code> method when a new
    <code>java.net.URLConnection</code> must be created. In this example, a
    <code>DataConnection</code> object is returned.</para>

    <programlisting xml:id="i1294186">public class DataProtocol 
    extends AbstractURLStreamHandlerService         
    implements BundleActivator {
    public void start( BundleContext context ) {
        Hashtable               properties = new Hashtable();
        properties.put( URLConstants.URL_HANDLER_PROTOCOL, 
            new String[] { "data" } );
        context.registerService(
            URLStreamHandlerService.class.getName(), 
            this, properties );
    }
    public void stop( BundleContext context ) {}

    public URLConnection openConnection( URL url ) {
        return new DataConnection(url); 
    }
}</programlisting>

    <para xml:id="i1294203">The following example <code>DataConnection</code>
    class extends <code>java.net.URLConnection</code> and overrides the
    constructor so that it can provide the <code>URL</code> object to the
    super class, the <code>connect</code> method, and the
    <code>getInputStream</code> method. This last method returns the path part
    of the URL as an <code>java.io.InputStream</code> object.</para>

    <programlisting>class DataConnection extends java.net.URLConnection{
    DataConnection( URL url ) {super(url);}
    public void connect() {}
    
    public InputStream getInputStream() throws IOException {
        String s = getURL().getPath();
        byte [] buf = s.getBytes();
        return new ByteArrayInputStream(buf,1,buf.length-1);
    }
    public String getContentType() {
        return "text/plain";
    }   
}</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Providing a Content Handler</title>

    <para xml:id="i1294206">A Content Handler should extend the <code>
    java.net.ContentHandler</code> class and implement the
    <code>getContent</code> method. This method must get the
    <code>InputStream</code> object from the
    <code>java.net.URLConnection</code> parameter object and convert the bytes
    from this stream to the applicable type. In this example, the MIME type is
    <code>text/plain</code> and the return object is a <code>String</code>
    object.</para>

    <programlisting>public class TextPlainHandler extends ContentHandler 
    implements BundleActivator {

    public void start( BundleContext context ) {
        Hashtable   properties = new Hashtable();
        properties.put( URLConstants.URL_CONTENT_MIMETYPE, 
            new String[] { "text/plain" } );
        context.registerService(
            ContentHandler.class.getName(), 
            this, properties );
    }
    public void stop( BundleContext context ) {}

    public Object getContent( URLConnection conn ) 
            throws IOException {
        InputStream in = conn.getInputStream();
        InputStreamReader r = new InputStreamReader( in );      
        StringBuffer sb = new StringBuffer();
        int c;
        while ( (c=r.read()) &gt;= 0 )
            sb.append( (char) c );
        r.close(); in.close();
        return sb.toString(); 
    }   
}</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security Considerations</title>

    <para>The ability to specify a protocol and add content handlers makes it
    possible to directly affect the behavior of a core Java VM class. The
    <code>java.net.URL</code> class is widely used by network applications and
    can be used by the OSGi Framework itself.</para>

    <para>Therefore, care must be taken when providing the ability to register
    handlers. The two types of supported handlers are
    <code>URLStreamHandlerService</code> and
    <code>java.net.ContentHandler</code>. Only trusted bundles should be
    allowed to register these services and have
    <code>ServicePermission[URLStreamHandlerService|ContentHandler,
    REGISTER]</code> for these classes. Since these services are made
    available to other bundles through the <code>java.net.URL</code> class and
    <code>java.net.URLConnection</code> class, it is advisable to deny the use
    of these services (<code>ServicePermission[&lt;name&gt;, GET]</code>) to
    all, so that only the Framework can get them. This prevents the
    circumvention of the permission checks done by the
    <code>java.net.URL</code> class by using the
    <code>URLStreamHandlerServices</code> service objects directly.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.url.xml"/>

  <section xml:id="service.url.references">
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed><title>URLs</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1738.txt"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1260753"><title>MIME Multipurpose Internet Mail
      Extension</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.nacs.uci.edu/indiv/ehood/MIME/MIME.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1260756"><title>Assigned MIME Media
      Types</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
