<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="7" revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="framework.wiring"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Bundle Wiring API Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework.wiring-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>A key aspect of the OSGi framework is managing the dependencies
    between the bundles. These dependencies are expressed as manifest headers
    that can be grouped into <emphasis>requirements</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>capabilities</emphasis> as defined in <xref
    linkend="framework.resource"/>. For example, an Export-Package clause is a
    capability and an Import-Package clause is a requirement. During the
    resolving phase the requirements are resolved to matching capabilities by
    creating a <emphasis>Bundle Wire</emphasis>. Some of the wires can
    influence how the classes are loaded from bundles during runtime.</para>

    <para>This section outlines the API to introspect the wiring between the
    requirements and capabilities of resolved bundles.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Revision</emphasis> - Represents the
          class/resource container of an install or update (that is, the JAR,
          directory, or other form of archive). Each update creates a new
          Bundle Revision and an uninstall removes the Bundle Revisions. A
          Bundle Revision is modeled after a Resource.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Namespace</emphasis> - Bundle Requirements and
          Bundle Capabilities are defined in a namespace, namespaces define
          the semantics of the requirements and capabilities. The
          <code>osgi.wiring.bundle</code>, <code>osgi.wiring.host</code> and
          <code>osgi.wiring.package</code> from the Framework Namespaces are
          defined in <xref linkend="framework.namespaces"/>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Requirement</emphasis> - Represents a
          requirement header, either the Require-Capability header or any of
          the manifest headers referred to in the <xref
          linkend="framework.namespaces"/> that map to a requirement.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Capability</emphasis> - A quality of a Bundle
          Revision that is provided when the revision is installed.
          Implemented as a set of attributes that are part of a namespace. A
          Bundle Capability represents either the Provide-Capability manifest
          header clauses, or any headers defined in the OSGi namespaces that
          map to a capability.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Wiring</emphasis> - Created each time when a
          Bundle Revision is resolved for holding the wires to other Bundle
          Wirings as well as maintaining the run time state. Used by the
          framework to control class loading depending on the semantics of the
          OSGi namespaces.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Bundle Wire</emphasis> - Connects a Bundle
          Requirement to a Bundle Capability as well as the requirer Bundle
          Wiring and provider Bundle Wiring.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Framework Wiring</emphasis> - Provides access to
          manage and initiate refresh and resolving.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure pgwide="1">
        <title>Class Diagram org.osgi.framework.wiring (with relations to
        org.osgi.resource)</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="5.000in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="wiring-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="framework.wiring.usingthewiringapi">
    <title>Using the Wiring API</title>

    <para>This section explains how the wiring API can be used without fully
    explaining all the concepts in depth. The next sections outline the formal
    specification.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>The Bundle Context <code>installBundle</code> method installs a
      bundle and returns a <code>Bundle</code> object. This install provides
      the classes and resources in a JAR, directory or some other form, as an
      <emphasis>environment</emphasis>. This resource is represented as a
      <emphasis>Bundle Revision</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>A Bundle Revision <emphasis>declares</emphasis> a number of
      <emphasis>Bundle Capabilities</emphasis> as well as a number of
      <emphasis>Bundle Requirements</emphasis>. A capability represents a set
      of attributes and a requirement is a filter on those attributes. For a
      requirement to be applicable to a capability, they must reside in the
      same <emphasis>namespace</emphasis>. The namespace groups requirements
      and capabilities and defines the semantics for a resolved
      requirement/capability pair. This pair is represented as a
      <emphasis>Bundle Wire</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Capabilities can be anything: certificates, screen size, the
      packages, the bundle itself or the capability to act as host for a
      fragment. Some capabilities and requirements are from the
      Provide-Capability and Require-Capability headers, others are defined by
      the OSGi headers defined in <xref linkend="framework.module"/>, the
      namespaces for these OSGi specific headers are defined in <xref
      linkend="framework.namespaces"/>.</para>

      <para>The framework wires the Bundle Requirements to Bundle Capabilities
      during the resolving operation. The framework must resolve all the
      requirements to matching capabilities according to the semantics of
      their namespaces before it can declare a bundle to be resolved. For
      generic namespaces it is sufficient to find a matching capability for
      each requirement. However, for the OSGi namespaces additional rules are
      implied. For example, the <code>osgi.wiring.host</code> namespace
      implies all the rules around OSGi fragment bundles.</para>

      <para>Once a bundle is in the <code>RESOLVED</code> state it gets a
      <emphasis>Bundle Wiring</emphasis>, the Bundle Wiring represents the run
      time state of the Bundle Revision. The Bundle Wiring holds the
      <emphasis>Bundle Wires</emphasis>. A Bundle Wire ties a single Bundle
      Requirement to a single Bundle Capability as well as tying the Bundle
      Wiring that holds the requirement to the Bundle Wiring that holds the
      capability. The Bundle Wires that flow from a Bundle Wiring's
      Requirement to a capability are the <emphasis>required wires</emphasis>,
      they can be obtained with <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.getRequiredWires-String-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. Bundle Wires that come from a Bundle Wiring's
      Capability to a requirement are the <emphasis>provided wires,
      </emphasis>they can be obtained with <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.getProvidedWires-String-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The same requirements and capabilities can be
      used in different wires.</para>

      <para>Namespace rules can be complex. For example, in the case of
      fragments they imply that any capabilities from the fragment are
      actually available from its hosts. In the case of exported packages that
      are also imported the resolver can choose to pick either. These examples
      demonstrate that the resolver must be able to differentiate between the
      Bundle Revision's declared requirements and capabilities and the run
      time state, the Bundle Wiring, of the corresponding Bundle Revision. A
      Bundle Revision's Bundle Wiring therefore provides the actual run time
      requirements and capabilities as chosen by the resolver with the Bundle
      Wiring's <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.getRequirements-String-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.getCapabilities-String-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods. Any optional declared requirements that
      were not satisfied are not in the list of requirements. All dynamic
      requirements that can potentially be satisfied at run time are in this
      requirements list.</para>

      <para>The <code>BundleWiring</code> objects are therefore not
      necessarily associated with the same Bundle Revisions that originate the
      declared Bundle Requirement and the declared Bundle Capability. It is
      therefore that the diagramming technique used in <xref
      linkend="i1740286"/> uses dotted lines for the Bundle Wiring connection.
      That is, the connections from the Bundle Wire to the requirer
      <code>BundleWiring</code> object and to the provider
      <code>BundleWiring</code> object. It then uses solid lines for the
      connection to the declared requirement and capability in their Bundle
      Revisions. This technique makes it possible to depict fragments where a
      capability in the fragment is actually available from the host's Bundle
      Wiring.</para>

      <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="i1740286">
        <title>Requirements and Capabilities Diagramming</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.500in"
                       contentwidth="6.199in" fileref="req-cap-legend.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><code>BundleWiring</code> objects can continue to exist and
      operate as long as there are wires from other <code>BundleWiring</code>
      objects, even after a bundle is updated. The only way to break this
      non-current wiring is to <emphasis>refresh</emphasis> the bundles that
      are involved. The refresh operation computes a transitive closure of all
      dependent bundles, and re-resolves them. Any active bundles in this
      closure will be stopped and restarted. This operation can be activated
      on the <emphasis>Framework Wiring</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>The wiring API is based on the <code>Bundle.adapt()</code> method,
      see <xref linkend="framework.lifecycle.adaptations"/>. This method
      allows the <code>Bundle</code> object to be adapted to another type. For
      example:</para>

      <programlisting>BundleWiring current = bundle.adapt(BundleWiring.class);
if ( current != null ) {
  ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>For this API, the following adaptations of the Bundle object are
      supported:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleRevision"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Provides access to the current revision at
          the time of the <code>adapt</code> method call. A Bundle will always
          have a current Bundle Revision until it is uninstalled.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Provides access to the current Bundle
          Wiring at the time of the <code>adapt</code> method call. A current
          Bundle Wiring object only exists (the adapt method returns
          non-<code>null</code>) when the bundle is resolved.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleRevisions"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Provides access to all the
          <code>BundleRevision</code> objects that are still in use. A Bundle
          always has a <code>BundleRevisions</code> object, the
          <code>adapt</code> method must never return
          <code>null</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Can only be adapted from the system bundle
          with bundle id 0. Provides access to the management methods like
          refresh and resolve, and information about bundles that are pending
          removal, and the dependency closure of a set of bundles.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Bundle Wiring API is usable during launching after the
      <code>init</code> method has returned.</para>

      <para>After an uninstall the adapt method will always return
      <code>null</code> for <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleRevision"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> or <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. However, it is possible that the Bundle
      Revision and/or its Bundle Wiring are reachable through other
      bundles.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Finding the Imported Packages</title>

      <para>Packages are reflected in the <code>osgi.wiring.package</code>
      namespace. An Import-Package clause is mapped to an
      <code>osgi.wiring.package</code> requirement and an Export-Package
      clause is mapped into the corresponding capability. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>Import-Package: com.acme.foo;version=1
Export-Package: com.acme.foo;version=1</programlisting>

      <para>In the Requirements/Capabilities model this is depicted as in
      <xref linkend="i1748298"/>.:</para>

      <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="i1748298">
        <title>Example Import/Export Package with Requirements/Capabilities
        Model</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="0.500in"
                       contentwidth="6.199in" fileref="package-req-cap.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The following code prints the bundles that bundle A is wired to
      through Import-Package statements:</para>

      <programlisting>void printImports( Bundle A ) {
    BundleWiring wA = A.adapt( BundleWiring.class );
    for ( BundleWire wire :
     wA.getRequiredWires(<xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.namespace.PackageNamespace.PACKAGE_NAMESPACE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>)) {
     String pack = (String) wire.getCapability().getAttributes()
         .get(<xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.namespace.PackageNamespace.PACKAGE_NAMESPACE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>);
     Bundle bundle = wire.getProviderWiring()
          .getBundle());
     System.out.println(pack + " - " + bundle.getLocation());
    }
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Attached Fragments</title>

      <para>Fragments use the <code>osgi.wiring.host</code> namespace to
      control their attachment. A fragment has a requirement for a host
      capability, this is a capability with the bundle symbolic name and
      version. If a fragment is attached then there is a wire from the
      fragment's Bundle Wiring to the host's Bundle Wiring.</para>

      <para>The following snippet finds the attached fragments of a
      bundle:</para>

      <programlisting>Set&lt;BundleWiring&gt; attachedFragments( BundleA ) {
    Set&lt;BundleWiring&gt; result = new HashSet&lt;BundleWiring&gt;();
    BundleWiring wA = A.adapt( BundleWiring.class );

    for ( BundleWire wire : wA.getProvidedWires(<xref
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.namespace.HostNamespace.HOST_NAMESPACE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>)) {
        result.add( wire.getRequirerWiring() );
    }
    return result;
}</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Bundle Wiring</title>

    <para>A bundle provides a simplified view of the state of the framework:
    it is either resolved or not. If it is resolved, bundles can become active
    and collaborate with other resolved bundles. During the time a bundle is
    resolved, and thus can see the environment, it will see a consistent
    stable state with respect to its code dependencies. Other bundles can be
    started and stopped, installed, updated, and uninstalled during the life
    cycle of a bundle. However, as long as a bundle is resolved it will
    continue to load classes from the bundle revisions it was wired to when it
    was initially resolved, even if those bundles are updated or
    uninstalled.</para>

    <para>The consequence of this model is that each bundle can have multiple
    <emphasis>revisions</emphasis>, and each revision can have an optional
    <emphasis>wiring</emphasis> at any moment in time. Management agents have
    the need to see this more complex state to be able to predict the impact
    of management actions and to help diagnose problems.</para>

    <para>There are two important event types that complicate the overall
    state. The install and update events provide a new <emphasis>Bundle
    Revision</emphasis> for a bundle and the uninstall event disconnects any
    Bundle Revisions from the bundle. The Bundle Revision contains the
    resources and the metadata defining, among other things, what type of
    bundle it is and what its dependencies are. An update can therefore change
    every aspect of a bundle. For example, an update could turn a non-fragment
    bundle into a fragment.</para>

    <para>The other event types that is of interest here are the
    <code>RESOLVED</code> and <code>UNRESOLVED</code> events. Resolving a
    bundle creates a <emphasis>Bundle Wiring</emphasis> based on the then
    current Bundle Revision. During resolving, a Bundle Wiring uses the
    requirements from the Bundle Revision to create <emphasis>wires</emphasis>
    to other Bundle Revisions; the wires are used to control the class loading
    process. Once a Bundle Wiring is required by another Bundle Wiring, or it
    is the current wiring, it is said to be <emphasis>in use</emphasis>. This
    model is depicted in <xref linkend="i1714190"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1714190">
      <title>Relationship between events, revisions, and wirings</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.250in"
                     contentwidth="7.000in"
                     fileref="events-revisions-wirings.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The framework never eagerly disconnects the wires between Bundle
    Wirings, a disconnect happens only under control of the management agent
    when the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.refreshBundles-Collection-FrameworkListener...-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is called or when all requiring bundles
    become uninstalled. When a bundle is updated, its existing
    <code>BundleWiring</code> objects will continue to serve classes and
    resources to bundles that use it. The update, even though it provides a
    new revision, has no effect on resolved bundles with respect to class
    loading. Also, the installation of a new bundle could allow new wires but
    they must not affect the existing wiring until <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.refreshBundles-Collection-FrameworkListener...-"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> is called (with the exception for dynamic
    imports). Though the class loading wires remain in place, proper bundles
    should react to the changes in the dynamic state. That is, when a bundle
    is updated it will be stopped, allowing others to remove any references
    they have to that bundle. However, even in those cases the wirings will
    remain until the bundle is unresolved during a refresh cycle.</para>

    <para>After an update, the existing Bundle Wiring is no longer
    <emphasis>current</emphasis> for the bundle.</para>

    <para>Bundle Wirings that are not in use (no other Bundle Wiring is wired
    to it) can be removed immediately but in-use Bundle Wirings must remain in
    place until they become no longer in use. These non-current in-use Bundle
    Wirings are called <emphasis>pending for removal</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>To forcefully remove all these non-current in use Bundle Wirings the
    framework can <emphasis>refresh</emphasis> a set of bundles at the request
    of a management agent. The refresh will create a transitive dependency
    graph on an initial set of bundles and then unresolves each bundle in the
    graph, which will make any of the stale Bundle Wirings no longer in use so
    they can be cleaned up. After this refresh, any previously active bundles
    will be restored to their previous state.</para>

    <para>The purpose of this non-eager behavior is to allow for efficient
    handling of multiple updates/installs/uninstalls. Refreshing the wires
    after each such event requires the start and stop of the dependent
    bundles, disrupting the operations of the system unnecessary often. It is
    therefore better to batch up a number of such operations and then
    <emphasis>refresh</emphasis> the system once. However, the implication of
    this optimization is that the actual wiring between bundles can quickly
    become an intricate web of connections between revisions of
    bundles.</para>

    <para>For example, assume a bundle <code>A</code> is installed. At
    installation, it will have a single Bundle Revision, called
    <code>A.0</code>. Next, bundle <code>B</code> is installed, it will have a
    Bundle Revision <code>B.0</code>. Assuming Bundle Revision
    <code>A.0</code> requires a capability in bundle <code>B</code>, resolving
    bundle <code>A</code> and bundle <code>B</code> will create a Bundle
    Wiring for Bundle Revision <code>A.0</code> linking to a Bundle Wiring for
    Bundle Revision <code>B.0</code>. If bundle <code>B</code> is now updated,
    it will create a second Bundle Revision, <code>B.1</code>.However, the
    current Bundle Wiring for bundle <code>A</code> (Bundle Revision
    <code>A.0</code>) will remain wired to Bundle Revision <code>B.0</code> as
    long as bundle <code>A</code> and bundle <code>B</code> remain resolved,
    even though the current Bundle Revision for bundle <code>B</code> has now
    become <code>B.1</code>. As long as Bundle Revision <code>A.0</code>
    remains resolved, bundle <code>B</code>'s resolved state has no
    impact.</para>

    <para>Bundles are only actually unresolved when they are
    <emphasis>refreshed</emphasis>, the <code>UNRESOLVED</code> event only
    indicates that a Bundle is updated or uninstalled. Refreshing happens on a
    per bundle basis but takes any Bundle Wirings into account that depend on
    the refreshed bundle. In the previous example, if bundle <code>B</code> is
    refreshed, it will automatically refresh bundle <code>A</code> because
    <code>A</code> is wired to <code>B</code>. That is, bundle <code>B</code>
    is in use by <code>A</code>. The refresh will stop bundles <code>A</code>
    and <code>B</code> and then unresolve both of them. Unresolving basically
    means removing any reference from the framework to the Bundle Wirings of
    the involved bundles. This unreferencing will allow the garbage collector
    to remove any remains, like for example the class loader and the
    activator, unless some bundles illegally hold on to references. Once a
    Bundle Wiring is no longer required by the framework, it is set to be not
    in use, regardless of stale references.</para>

    <para>Normally, after unresolving, the bundles are started again in their
    original state, forcing them to resolve again. In the previous example,
    Bundle Revision <code>A.0</code> will then be connected to the Bundle
    Revision <code>B.1</code> through newly created <code>BundleWiring</code>
    objects. The old Bundle Wiring for <code>B.0</code> will no longer be in
    use and will thus be garbage collected.</para>

    <para>This example is depicted in <xref linkend="i1714323"/>. This picture
    shows when the different objects are created and discarded. In this
    picture bundle <code>B</code> is not started.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1714323">
      <title>The Bundle Revisions and Bundle Wirings over time</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.865in"
                     contentwidth="4.930in"
                     fileref="revisions-wirings-over-time.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The resolver is responsible for wiring Bundle Requirements and
    Bundle Capabilities to each other while adhering to the semantics defined
    in their namespace. For each paired Bundle Requirement and Bundle
    Capability the resolver creates a Bundle Wire that links the Bundle
    Requirement, the requiring Bundle Wiring, the providing Bundle Wiring, and
    the Bundle Capability. The relationships between a bundle <code>A</code>
    and bundle <code>B</code>, where <code>A</code> requires some capability
    in <code>B</code>, is depicted in <xref linkend="i1735263"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1735263">
      <title>Bundle A requires Bundle B Wiring Instances</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.313in"
                     contentwidth="6.213in" fileref="a-requires-b-wiring.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The OSGi framework can add wires and new requirements and
    capabilities after resolving during run time. This mechanism is for
    example used in DynamicImport-Package, dynamic attaching of fragments, and
    byte code weaving.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="framework.wiring-fragments">
    <title>Fragments</title>

    <para>The type of a bundle is available on the Bundle Revision because a
    Bundle can change from a fragment to a normal bundle or vice versa after
    an update. The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleRevision.getTypes--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is used to obtain a bitmap that is either 0
    or has the following bit set:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleRevision.TYPE_FRAGMENT"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - If this bit is set the Bundle Revision is a
        fragment.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The type is a bitmap allowing future versions of this specification
    to add new types that can be a combination of existing and new types. The
    following example displays how a Bundle is checked to be a
    fragment:</para>

    <programlisting>BundleRevision rev = aBundle.adapt(BundleRevision.class);
if ( rev != null &amp;&amp; (rev.getTypes() &amp; TYPE_FRAGMENT)!= 0 ){
  ... // do the fragment thing
}</programlisting>

    <para>A fragment bundle will show all its declared capabilities and
    requirements on its Bundle Revision but during resolving the resolver only
    considers the <code>osgi.wiring.host</code> and <code>osgi.ee</code>
    requirements and the <code>osgi.identity</code> capability and
    requirements.</para>

    <para>The <code>osgi.wiring.host</code> requirement represents the
    Fragment-Host header. A fragment can be attached to different hosts and
    each attachment creates a wire from the fragment's Bundle Wiring to the
    host's Bundle Wiring. The <code>osgi.ee</code> requirement is also never
    hosted.</para>

    <para>The <code>osgi.identity</code> capability of a fragment is part of
    the fragment's Bundle Wiring and is not part of a host bundle's Bundle
    Wiring. That is, each Bundle Wiring has exactly one
    <code>osgi.identity</code> capability. However, <code>osgi.identity</code>
    requirements declared by a fragment are not part of the fragment's Bundle
    Wiring and are instead hosted by the host bundle's Bundle Wiring.</para>

    <para>Any other requirements and capabilities in a fragment bundle never
    become part of the fragment's Bundle Wiring; they are treated as part of
    the host's requirements and capabilities when the fragment is attached to
    that host.</para>

    <para>To find the attached fragment for a host bundle it is necessary to
    find the wires for the <code>osgi.wiring.host</code> capability. The
    requiring end of such a wire is the attached fragment and the providing
    end is the attaching host.</para>

    <para>For example, bundle <code>A</code> is a host and bundle B is a
    fragment as depicted in <xref linkend="i1743622"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1743622">
      <title>Fragments and Wiring</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.056in"
                     contentwidth="6.242in" fileref="fragments-wiring.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Then, to find the attached fragments for Bundle Revision
    <code>A0:</code></para>

    <programlisting>List&lt;BundleWiring&gt; attached = new ArrayList&lt;BundleWiring&gt;();
for ( BundleWire wire : A0.getBundleWiring().getProvidedWires(HOST_NAMESPACE)) 
    attached.add( wire.getRequirerWiring() );</programlisting>

    <para>It is also possible to calculate the reverse dependency for finding
    the hosts of a fragment. For the previous example, the bundles that attach
    fragment <code>B</code> can be found with:</para>

    <programlisting>List&lt;BundleWiring&gt; hosts = new ArrayList&lt;BundleWiring&gt;();
for ( BundleWire wire :  B0.getBundleWiring().getRequiredWires(HOST_NAMESPACE)) 
    hosts.add( wire.getProviderWiring() );</programlisting>

    <para>The <code>osgi.wiring.host</code> namespace mandates that the
    resolver moves the Bundle Requirements and Bundle Capabilities from the
    fragment in all other namespaces than the <code>osgi.wiring.host</code>,
    <code>osgi.identity</code> and <code>osgi.ee</code> namespaces to the host
    bundle. For example, if the fragment exports a package <code>p</code>,
    then this package is exported by the host. In such a case, the
    <code>BundleRequirement</code> and <code>BundleCapability</code> objects
    remain associated with the Bundle Revision of the fragment. However, the
    Bundle Wire has the appropriate Bundle Wiring of the host. This is
    depicted in <xref linkend="i1743831"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>. Package <code>p</code> is
    declared a capability in fragment <code>B.0</code> but when wired the
    Bundle Wiring of host <code>A.0</code> will be the provider.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1743831">
      <title>Exporting a Package from a Fragment</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.450in"
                     contentwidth="6.242in"
                     fileref="fragment-export-package.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The previous example is also depicted as an instance diagram in
    <xref linkend="i1743855"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>.</para>

    <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="i1743855">
      <title>Fragments Wiring Instances</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.600in"
                     contentwidth="7.000in"
                     fileref="fragment-wiring-instances.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Framework Actions</title>

    <para>There are a number of actions that are global in a framework and not
    associated with a specific bundle. These actions are associated with the
    framework; this is the reason for the Framework Wiring adaptation. The
    system bundle (bundle 0) can be adapted to a <code>FrameworkWiring</code>
    object:</para>

    <programlisting>FrameworkWiring fw = systemBundle.adapt(FrameworkWiring.class);</programlisting>

    <para>The Framework Wiring provides the following actions:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.findProviders-Requirement-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The find providers method returns
        capabilities available in the framework that match the given
        requirement. This method can be used to search for capabilities
        provided by bundles in the framework. For example, an exported package
        with a specific package name.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.getDependencyClosure-Collection-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The dependency closure method takes a seed
        of bundles for a dependency closure and then add any bundles that
        depend a bundle in the dependency closure, recursively. The result can
        be used to calculate the impact of a refresh operation. If the
        framework is refreshed the result of this method provides the bundles
        that will be affected.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.getRemovalPendingBundles--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Bundles that have a Bundle Wiring that is in
        use but not current. Such bundles are pending removal.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.refreshBundles-Collection-FrameworkListener...-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - See <xref
        linkend="framework.wiring.refreshing"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.resolveBundles-Collection-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Attempt to resolve all the bundles in the
        given collection. This action can also cause bundles to become
        resolved outside the given collections.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section xml:id="framework.wiring.refreshing">
      <title>Refreshing</title>

      <para>The update of bundles will create new Bundle Revisions while the
      existing Bundle Wirings remain wired to their previous Bundle Revisions.
      This stale wiring must be cleaned up and the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.refreshBundles-Collection-FrameworkListener...-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method achieves this.</para>

      <para>The <code>refreshBundles</code> method works from an initial
      collection of bundles that is used to seed the calculation of the
      <emphasis>dependency closure</emphasis>. The dependency closure is
      calculated by expanding the seed dependency closure to include any
      bundle that has a Bundle Wiring that depends on any bundle in the
      dependency closure. This is a recursive definition so the dependency
      closure contains the list of transitive dependencies on the initial seed
      collection.</para>

      <para>This dependency closure can be obtained separately with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.getDependencyClosure-Collection-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method providing it with the same seed. If no
      seed is provided, that is a <code>null</code> argument is given, the
      <code>refreshBundles</code> method will be identical to calling it with
      the result of the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.getRemovalPendingBundles--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method as the seed collection. This default will
      ensure that all stale Bundle Wirings will be cleaned up.</para>

      <para>The refresh process will stop any bundles in the considered
      collection while recording their state and, if active, their starting
      option (for example <code>START_TRANSIENT</code>). Stopping must take
      any start level rules into account.</para>

      <para>The refresh must then unresolve all the bundles in the considered
      collection. Unresolving will cause all the removal pending Bundle
      Wirings to become no longer in use because there are no longer any
      bundles requiring them. This will make the Bundle Wirings available for
      garbage collection because they are then no longer reachable from the
      framework API.</para>

      <para>The framework must then attempt to restore the state as it was
      before the refresh taking all the framework rules into account,
      including start levels, start options, and activation options.</para>

      <para>The actual refresh operation will take place in the background
      because it can be a long running operation. The refresh operation will
      send out a global framework event <code>PACKAGES_REFRESHED</code>.
      However, catching this event properly is non-trivial. For this reason,
      the <code>refreshBundle</code> method also allows a callback by
      specifying an optional Framework Listener in the method invocation that
      will only be called when the method is finished. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>fw.refreshBundles( null, new FrameworkListener(){
  public void frameworkEvent(FrameworkEvent ev) {
     System.out.println("Refresh finished");
  }
});</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Container Scanning</title>

    <para>A resolved bundle can consist of a number of containers: the basic
    bundle container (usually a JAR), embedded JARs or directories, and
    fragments. Containers contain <emphasis>entries</emphasis> but the
    Bundle-ClassPath header turns these entries into a single namespace,
    called <emphasis>resources</emphasis>. These concepts are fully defined in
    <xref linkend="framework.module.bundleclasspath"/>.</para>

    <para>The wiring API provides two different ways to iterate over the
    contents in the containers that constitute a resolved bundle:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Bundle Class Path Order</emphasis> - Scan the bundle
        class path containers.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Entry Order</emphasis> - Scan all the entries that
        constitute a bundle and its attached fragments.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>These two different ways are outlined in the following
    sections.</para>

    <section xml:id="framework.wiring-bundleclasspathorder">
      <title>Bundle Class Path Order</title>

      <para>Once a bundle is resolved all its container namespaces are
      flattened to a single namespace that is then used by the class loader.
      Flattening has as a consequence that certain resources will disappear
      from the view, which resource remains and which disappear depends on the
      order of the flattening. The OSGi specification defines exactly what
      this order is. However, the rules for this ordering are many and
      non-trivial. For this reason, a Bundle Wiring allows the iteration over
      the resources of a bundle in the bundle class path order, reflecting the
      same flattening as that what the class loader will do. A bundle must be
      resolved to be able to iterate over its resources.</para>

      <para>The method used to iterate over the resources in bundle class path
      order is <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.listResources-String-String-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This method takes a starting path in the
      namespace, a pattern to match (for example <code>*.class</code> for
      class resources) and a flag to indicate if the scan should recurs into
      directories or not.</para>

      <para>When the bundle class path has a multi-release container, see
      <xref linkend="framework.module-multireleasecontainer"/>, and an
      argument to the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.listResources-String-String-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method would include a resource name in the
      method result if the resource was not available from the root directory
      but is available from a versioned directory visible on the current Java
      version, then the method result must include the resource name from the
      root directory. For example, if the multi-release container has the
      following entry</para>

      <programlisting>META-INF/versions/9/com/foo/resource.txt</programlisting>

      <para>and the call <code>listResources(“/com/foo”, “*.txt”, 0)</code> is
      made when running on Java 9, or later, the result must include</para>

      <programlisting>com/foo/resource.txt</programlisting>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.listResources-String-String-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method has no counterpart in the standard class
      loader API.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entry Order</title>

      <para>A Bundle Wiring reflects a resolved bundle. This wiring
      constitutes the bundle and any attached fragments. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.findEntries-String-String-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method is similar to the
      <code>Bundle.</code><xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.Bundle.findEntries-String-String-boolean-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The Bundle's method will be identical
      when the bundle can be resolved, if the bundle cannot resolve the
      Bundle's <code>findEntries</code> method has a fallback that allows
      iteration without attached fragments. The Bundle Wiring's <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.findEntries-String-String-int-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> is always against a resolved bundle because it
      is on a Bundle Wiring.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Class Loader Access</title>

      <para>The class loader can also be obtained from the
      <code>BundleWiring</code> class with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring.getClassLoader--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>The Bundle Wiring API requires Adapt Permission with action
    <code>ADAPT</code> for the following types:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleWiring</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleRevision</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>org.osgi.framework.wiring.BundleRevisions</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring</code></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Framework Wiring methods that mutate state require an additional
    Admin Permission with the action:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>RESOLVE</code> (for the system bundle) - For <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.refreshBundles-Collection-FrameworkListener...-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring.FrameworkWiring.resolveBundles-Collection-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Added support for multi-release JARs. See <xref
        linkend="framework.wiring-bundleclasspathorder"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
