<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="113"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xml:id="service.event"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Event Admin Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.event-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.event"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Nearly all the bundles in an OSGi framework must deal with events,
    either as an event publisher or as an event handler. So far, the preferred
    mechanism to disperse those events have been the service interface
    mechanism.</para>

    <para>Dispatching events for a design related to X, usually involves a
    service of type <code>XListener</code>. However, this model does not scale
    well for fine grained events that must be dispatched to many different
    handlers. Additionally, the dynamic nature of the OSGi environment
    introduces several complexities because both event publishers and event
    handlers can appear and disappear at any time.</para>

    <para>The Event Admin service provides an inter-bundle communication
    mechanism. It is based on a event <emphasis>publish</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>subscribe</emphasis> model, popular in many message based
    systems.</para>

    <para>This specification defines the details for the participants in this
    event model.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Simplifications</emphasis> - The model must
          significantly simplify the process of programming an event source
          and an event handler.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dependencies</emphasis> - Handle the myriad of
          dependencies between event sources and event handlers for proper
          cleanup.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Synchronicity</emphasis> - It must be possible to
          deliver events asynchronously or synchronously with the
          caller.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Window</emphasis> - Only event handlers that
          are active when an event is published must receive this event,
          handlers that register later must not see the event.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Performance</emphasis> - The event mechanism must
          impose minimal overhead in delivering events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Selectivity</emphasis> - Event listeners must only
          receive notifications for the event types for which they are
          interested</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Reliability</emphasis> - The Event Admin must ensure
          that events continue to be delivered regardless the quality of the
          event handlers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Security</emphasis> - Publishing and receiving
          events are sensitive operations that must be protected per event
          type.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Extensibility</emphasis> - It must be possible to
          define new event types with their own data types.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Native Code</emphasis> - Events must be able to be
          passed to native code or come from native code.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>OSGi Events</emphasis> - The OSGi Framework, as well
          as a number of OSGi services, already have number of its own events
          defined. For uniformity of processing, these have to be mapped into
          generic event types.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event</emphasis> - An <code>Event</code> object has
          a topic and a <code>Dictionary</code> object that contains the event
          properties. It is an immutable object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Admin</emphasis> - The service that provides
          the publish and subscribe model to Event Handlers and Event
          Publishers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Handler</emphasis> - A service that receives
          and handles <code>Event</code> objects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Publisher</emphasis> - A bundle that sends
          event through the Event Admin service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Subscriber</emphasis> - Another name for an
          Event Handler.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Topic</emphasis> - The name of an Event type.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Properties</emphasis> - The set of properties
          that is associated with an Event.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>The Event Admin service org.osgi.service.event package</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.865in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="eventadmin-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>The Event Admin service provides a place for bundles to publish
      events, regardless of their destination. It is also used by Event
      Handlers to subscribe to specific types of events.</para>

      <para>Events are published under a topic, together with a number of
      event properties. Event Handlers can specify a filter to control the
      Events they receive on a very fine grained basis.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What To Read</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Architects</emphasis> - The <xref
          linkend="i1487590"/> provides an overview of the Event Admin
          service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Publishers</emphasis> - The <xref
          linkend="i1399436"/> provides an introduction of how to write an
          Event Publisher. The <xref linkend="i1487590"/> provides a good
          overview of the design.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Event Subscribers/Handlers</emphasis> - The <xref
          linkend="i1557230"/> provides the rules on how to subscribe and
          handle events.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1487590">
    <title>Event Admin Architecture</title>

    <para>The Event Admin is based on the
    <emphasis>Publish-Subscribe</emphasis> pattern. This pattern decouples
    sources from their handlers by interposing an <emphasis>event
    channel</emphasis> between them. The publisher posts events to the
    channel, which identifies which handlers need to be notified and then
    takes care of the notification process. This model is depicted in <xref
    linkend="i1450302"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i1450302">
      <title>Channel Pattern</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="0.995in"
                     contentwidth="4.940in" fileref="channel-pattern.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In this model, the event source and event handler are completely
    decoupled because neither has any direct knowledge of the other. The
    complicated logic of monitoring changes in the event publishers and event
    handlers is completely contained within the event channel. This is highly
    advantageous in an OSGi environment because it simplifies the process of
    both sending and receiving events.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Event</title>

    <para>Events have the following attributes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Topic</emphasis> - A topic that defines what happened.
        For example, when a bundle is started an event is published that has a
        topic of <code>org/osgi/framework/BundleEvent/STARTED</code>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Properties</emphasis> - Zero or more properties that
        contain additional information about the event. For example, the
        previous example event has a property of <code>bundle.id</code> which
        is set to a <code>Long</code> object, among other properties.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Topics</title>

      <para>The topic of an event defines the <emphasis>type</emphasis> of the
      event. It is fairly granular in order to give handlers the opportunity
      to register for just the events they are interested in. When a topic is
      designed, its name should not include any other information, such as the
      publisher of the event or the data associated with the event, those
      parts are intended to be stored in the event properties.</para>

      <para>The topic is intended to serve as a first-level filter for
      determining which handlers should receive the event. Event Admin service
      implementations use the structure of the topic to optimize the
      dispatching of the events to the handlers.</para>

      <para>Topics are arranged in a hierarchical namespace. Each level is
      defined by a token and levels are separated by solidi (<code>'/'
      \u002F</code>). More precisely, the topic must conform to the following
      grammar:</para>

      <programlisting>  topic ::= token ( '/' token ) *    // See General Syntax Definitions in Core</programlisting>

      <para>Topics should be designed to become more specific when going from
      left to right. Handlers can provide a prefix that matches a topic, using
      the preferred order allows a handler to minimize the number of prefixes
      it needs to register.</para>

      <para>Topics are case-sensitive. As a convention, topics should follow
      the reverse domain name scheme used by Java packages to guarantee
      uniqueness. The separator must be a solidus (<code>'/' \u002F</code>)
      instead of the full stop (<code>'.' \u002E</code>).</para>

      <para>This specification uses the convention
      <code>fully/qualified/package/ClassName/ACTION</code>. If necessary, a
      pseudo-class-name is used.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Properties</title>

      <para>Information about the actual event is provided as properties. The
      property name is a case-sensitive string and the value can be any
      object. Although any Java object can be used as a property value, only
      <code>String</code> objects and the eight primitive types (plus their
      wrappers) should be used. Other types cannot be passed to handlers that
      reside external from the Java VM.</para>

      <para>Another reason that arbitrary classes should not be used is the
      mutability of objects. If the values are not immutable, then any handler
      that receives the event could change the value. Any handlers that
      received the event subsequently would see the altered value and not the
      value as it was when the event was sent.</para>

      <para>The topic of the event is available as a property with the key
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EVENT_TOPIC"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This allows filters to include the topic as a
      condition if necessary.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>High Performance</title>

      <para>An event processing system can become a bottleneck in large
      systems. One expensive aspect of the Event object is its properties and
      its immutability. This combination requires the Event object to create a
      copy of the properties for each object. There are many situations where
      the same properties are dispatched through Event Admin, the topic is
      then used to signal the information. Creating the copy of the properties
      can therefore take unnecessary CPU time and memory. However, the
      immutability of the Event object requires the properties to be
      immutable.</para>

      <para>For this reason, this specification also provides an immutable Map
      with the Event Properties class. This class implements an immutable map
      that is recognized and trusted by the Event object to not mutate. Using
      an Event Properties object allows a client to create many different
      Event objects with different topics but sharing the same properties
      object.</para>

      <para>The following example shows how an event poster can limit the
      copying of the properties.</para>

      <programlisting>void foo(EventAdmin eventAdmin) {
   Map&lt;String,Object&gt; props = new HashMap&lt;String,Object&gt;();
   props.put("foo", 1);
   EventProperties eventProps = new EventProperties( props);

   for ( int i=0; i&lt;1000; i++)
      eventAdmin.postEvent( new Event( "my/topic/" + i, eventProps));
}</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1557230">
    <title>Event Handler</title>

    <para>Event handlers must be registered as services with the OSGi
    framework under the object class
    <code>org.osgi.service.event.EventHandler</code>.</para>

    <para>Event handlers should be registered with a property (constant from
    the <code>EventConstants</code> class) <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EVENT_TOPIC"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The value being a <code>String</code>,
    <code>String[]</code> or <code>Collection&lt;String&gt;</code> object that
    describes which <emphasis>topics</emphasis> the handler is interested in.
    A wildcard asterisk (<code>'*' \u002A</code>) may be used as the last
    token of a topic name, for example <code>com/action/*</code>. This matches
    any topic that shares the same first tokens. For example,
    <code>com/action/*</code> matches <code>com/action/listen</code>.</para>

    <para>Event Handlers which have not specified the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EVENT_TOPIC"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service property must not receive events.</para>

    <para>The value of each entry in the <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EVENT_TOPIC"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service registration property must conform to the
    following grammar:</para>

    <programlisting>topic-scope ::= '*' | ( topic '/*'?  )</programlisting>

    <para>Event handlers can also be registered with a service property named
    <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EVENT_FILTER"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The value of this property must be a string
    containing a Framework filter specification. Any of the event's properties
    can be used in the filter expression.</para>

    <programlisting>event-filter ::= filter              //  See Filter Syntax in Core</programlisting>

    <para>Each Event Handler is notified for any event which belongs to the
    topics the handler has expressed an interest in. If the handler has
    defined a <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EVENT_FILTER"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service property then the event properties must
    also match the filter expression. If the filter is an error, then the
    Event Admin service should log a warning and further ignore the Event
    Handler.</para>

    <para>For example, a bundle wants to see all Log Service events with a
    level of <code>WARNING</code> or <code>ERROR</code>, but it must ignore
    the <code>INFO</code> and <code>DEBUG</code> events. Additionally, the
    only events of interest are when the bundle symbolic name starts with
    <code>com.acme</code>.</para>

    <programlisting>public AcmeWatchDog implements BundleActivator, 
        EventHandler {
    final static String [] topics = new String[] {
        "org/osgi/service/log/LogEntry/LOG_WARNING",
        "org/osgi/service/log/LogEntry/LOG_ERROR" };

    public void start(BundleContext context) {
        Dictionary d = new Hashtable();
        d.put(EventConstants.EVENT_TOPIC, topics );
        d.put(EventConstants.EVENT_FILTER, 
            "(bundle.symbolicName=com.acme.*)" );
        context.registerService( EventHandler.class.getName(),
            this, d );
    }
    public void stop( BundleContext context) {}

    public void handleEvent(Event event ) {
        //...
    }
}</programlisting>

    <para>If there are multiple Event Admin services registered with the
    Framework then all Event Admin services must send their published events
    to all registered Event Handlers.</para>

    <section xml:id="i1556001">
      <title>Ordering</title>

      <para>In the default case, an Event Handler will receive posted
      (asynchronous) events from a single thread in the same order as they
      were posted. Maintaining this ordering guarantee requires the Event
      Admin to serialize the delivery of events instead of, for example,
      delivering the events on different worker threads. There are many
      scenarios where this ordering is not really required. For this reason,
      an Event Handler can signal to the Event Admin that events can be
      delivered out of order. This is notified with the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EVENT_DELIVERY"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service property. This service property can be
      used in the following way:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Not set or set to both - The Event Admin must deliver the
          events in the proper order.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.DELIVERY_ASYNC_ORDERED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Events must be delivered in order.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.DELIVERY_ASYNC_UNORDERED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - Allow the events to be delivered in any
          order.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1399436">
    <title>Event Publisher</title>

    <para>To fire an event, the event source must retrieve the Event Admin
    service from the OSGi service registry. Then it creates the event object
    and calls one of the Event Admin service's methods to fire the event
    either synchronously or asynchronously.</para>

    <para>The following example is a class that publishes a time event every
    60 seconds.</para>

    <programlisting>public class TimerEvent extends Thread 
    implements BundleActivator {
    Hashtable      time = new Hashtable();
    ServiceTracker tracker;

    public TimerEvent() { super("TimerEvent"); }

    public void start(BundleContext context ) {
        tracker = new ServiceTracker(context,
            EventAdmin.class.getName(), null );
        tracker.open();
        start();
    }

    public void stop( BundleContext context ) {
        interrupt();
        tracker.close();
    }

    public void run() {
        while ( ! Thread.interrupted() ) try {
            Calendar c = Calendar.getInstance();
            set(c,Calendar.MINUTE,"minutes");
            set(c,Calendar.HOUR,"hours");
            set(c,Calendar.DAY_OF_MONTH,"day");
            set(c,Calendar.MONTH,"month");
            set(c,Calendar.YEAR,"year");

            EventAdmin ea =
                (EventAdmin) tracker.getService();
            if ( ea != null )
                ea.sendEvent(new Event("com/acme/timer",
                    time ));
            Thread.sleep(60000-c.get(Calendar.SECOND)*1000);
        } catch( InterruptedException e ) {
            return;
        }
    }

    void set( Calendar c, int field, String key ) {
        time.put( key, new Integer(c.get(field)) );
    }
}       </programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Specific Events</title>

    <section>
      <title>General Conventions</title>

      <para>Some handlers are more interested in the contents of an event
      rather than what actually happened. For example, a handler wants to be
      notified whenever an Exception is thrown anywhere in the system. Both
      Framework Events and Log Entry events may contain an exception that
      would be of interest to this hypothetical handler. If both Framework
      Events and Log Entries use the same property names then the handler can
      access the Exception in exactly the same way. If some future event type
      follows the same conventions then the handler can receive and process
      the new event type even though it had no knowledge of it when it was
      compiled.</para>

      <para>The following properties are suggested as conventions. When new
      event types are defined they should use these names with the
      corresponding types and values where appropriate. These values should be
      set only if they are not <code>null</code></para>

      <para>A list of these property names can be found in the following
      table.</para>

      <table>
        <title>General property names for events</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="4*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Name</entry>

              <entry>Type</entry>

              <entry>Notes</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.BUNDLE_SIGNER"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>String | Collection &lt;String&gt;</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A bundle's signers DN</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.BUNDLE_VERSION"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>Version</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A bundle's version</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.BUNDLE_SYMBOLICNAME"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>String</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A bundle's symbolic name</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EVENT"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>Object</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The actual event object. Used when rebroadcasting
              an event that was sent via some other event
              mechanism</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EXCEPTION"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>Throwable</code></entry>

              <entry><para>An exception or error</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EXCEPTION_MESSAGE"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>String</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Must be equal to
              <code>exception.getMessage()</code>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EXCEPTION_CLASS"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>String</code></entry>

              <entry><para>Must be equal to the name of the
              <code>Exception</code> class.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.MESSAGE"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>String</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A human-readable message that is usually not
              localized.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.SERVICE"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>Service Reference</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A Service Reference</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.SERVICE_ID"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A service's id</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.SERVICE_OBJECTCLASS"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>String[]</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A service's <code>objectClass</code></para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.SERVICE_PID"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>String | Collection &lt;String&gt;</code></entry>

              <entry><para>A service's persistent identity. A PID that is
              specified with a <code>String[]</code> must be coerced into a
              <code>Collection&lt;String&gt;</code>.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para><xref
              linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.TIMESTAMP"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para></entry>

              <entry><code>Long</code></entry>

              <entry><para>The time when the event occurred, as reported by
              <code>System.currentTimeMillis()</code></para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>The topic of an OSGi event is constructed by taking the fully
      qualified name of the event class, substituting a solidus (<code>'/'
      \u002F</code>)for every full stop, and appending a solidus followed by
      the name of the constant that defines the event type. For example, the
      topic of</para>

      <programlisting>BundleEvent.STARTED</programlisting>

      <para>Event becomes</para>

      <programlisting>org/osgi/framework/BundleEvent/STARTED</programlisting>

      <para>If a type code for the event is unknown then the event must be
      ignored.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>OSGi Events</title>

      <para>In order to present a consistent view of all the events occurring
      in the system, the existing Framework-level events are mapped to the
      Event Admin's publish-subscribe model. This allows event subscribers to
      treat framework events exactly the same as other events.</para>

      <para>It is the responsibility of the Event Admin service implementation
      to map these Framework events to its queue.</para>

      <para>The properties associated with the event depends on its class as
      outlined in the following sections.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Framework Event</title>

      <para>Framework Events must be delivered asynchronously with a topic
      of:</para>

      <programlisting>org/osgi/framework/FrameworkEvent/&lt;eventtype&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The following event types are supported:</para>

      <programlisting>STARTED 
ERROR   
PACKAGES_REFRESHED
STARTLEVEL_CHANGED
WARNING
INFO</programlisting>

      <para>Other events are ignored, no event will be send by the Event
      Admin. The following event properties must be set for a Framework
      Event.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>event</code> - (<code>FrameworkEvent</code>) The
          original event object.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the <code>FrameworkEvent getBundle</code> method returns a
      non-<code>null</code> value, the following fields must be set:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.id - (Long</code>) The source's bundle id.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.symbolicName</code> - (<code>String)</code> The
          source bundle's symbolic name. Only set if the bundle's symbolic
          name is not <code>null</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.version</code> - <code>(Version)</code> The
          version of the bundle, if set.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.signer</code> -
          <code>(String|Collection&lt;String&gt;)</code> The DNs of the
          signers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle</code> - (<code>Bundle</code>) The source
          bundle.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the <code>FrameworkEvent</code> <code>getThrowable</code>
      method returns a non-<code>null</code> value:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>exception.class</code> - (<code>String</code>) The
          fully-qualified class name of the attached Exception.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>exception.message</code> -( <code>String)</code> The
          message of the attached exception. Only set if the Exception message
          is not <code>null</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>exception</code> - (Throwable) The Exception returned by
          the <code>getThrowable</code> method.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bundle Event</title>

      <para>Framework Events must be delivered asynchronously with a topic
      of:</para>

      <programlisting>org/osgi/framework/BundleEvent/&lt;event type&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The following event types are supported:</para>

      <programlisting>INSTALLED
STARTED
STOPPED
UPDATED
UNINSTALLED
RESOLVED
UNRESOLVED</programlisting>

      <para>Unknown events must be ignored.</para>

      <para>The following event properties must be set for a Bundle Event. If
      listeners require synchronous delivery then they should register a
      Synchronous Bundle Listener with the Framework.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>event</code> - (<code>BundleEvent</code>) The original
          event object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.id - (Long</code>) The source's bundle id.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.symbolicName</code> - (<code>String)</code> The
          source bundle's symbolic name. Only set if the bundle's symbolic
          name is not <code>null</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.version</code> - <code>(Version)</code> The
          version of the bundle, if set.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle.signer</code> -
          <code>(String|Collection&lt;String&gt;)</code> The DNs of the
          signers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>bundle</code> - (<code>Bundle</code>) The source
          bundle.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="service.event.serviceevent">
      <title>Service Event</title>

      <para>Service Events must be delivered asynchronously with the
      topic:</para>

      <programlisting>org/osgi/framework/ServiceEvent/&lt;eventtype&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The following event types are supported:</para>

      <programlisting>REGISTERED
MODIFIED
UNREGISTERING</programlisting>

      <para>Unknown events must be ignored.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>event</code> - (<code>ServiceEvent</code>) The original
          Service Event object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service</code> - (<code>ServiceReference</code>) The
          result of the <code>getServiceReference</code> method</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.id</code> - (<code>Long</code>) The service's
          ID.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.pid</code> - (<code>String or
          Collection&lt;String&gt;</code>) The service's persistent identity.
          Only set if not <code>null</code>. If the PID is specified as a
          <code>String[]</code> then it must be coerced into a
          <code>Collection&lt;String&gt;</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.objectClass</code> - (<code>String[]</code>) The
          service's object class.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Other Event Sources</title>

      <para>Several OSGi service specifications define their own event model.
      It is the responsibility of these services to map their events to Event
      Admin events. Event Admin is seen as a core service that will be present
      in most devices. However, if there is no Event Admin service present,
      applications are not mandated to buffer events.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Event Admin Service</title>

    <para>The Event Admin service must be registered as a service with the
    object class <code>org.osgi.service.event.EventAdmin</code>. Multiple
    Event Admin services can be registered. Publishers should publish their
    event on the Event Admin service with the highest value for the
    <code>SERVICE_RANKING</code> service property. This is the service
    selected by the <code>getServiceReference</code> method.</para>

    <para>The Event Admin service is responsible for tracking the registered
    handlers, handling event notifications and providing at least one thread
    for asynchronous event delivery.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Synchronous Event Delivery</title>

      <para>Synchronous event delivery is initiated by the
      <code>sendEvent</code> method. When this method is invoked, the Event
      Admin service determines which handlers must be notified of the event
      and then notifies each one in turn. The handlers can be notified in the
      caller's thread or in an event-delivery thread, depending on the
      implementation. In either case, all notifications must be completely
      handled before the <code>sendEvent</code> method returns to the
      caller.</para>

      <para>Synchronous event delivery is significantly more expensive than
      asynchronous delivery. All things considered equal, the asynchronous
      delivery should be preferred over the synchronous delivery.</para>

      <para>Callers of this method will need to be coded defensively and
      assume that synchronous event notifications could be handled in a
      separate thread. That entails that they must not be holding any monitors
      when they invoke the <code>sendEvent</code> method. Otherwise they
      significantly increase the likelihood of deadlocks because Java monitors
      are not reentrant from another thread by definition. Not holding
      monitors is good practice even when the event is dispatched in the same
      thread.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Asynchronous Event Delivery</title>

      <para>Asynchronous event delivery is initiated by the
      <code>postEvent</code> method. When this method is invoked, the Event
      Admin service must determine which handlers are interested in the event.
      By collecting this list of handlers during the method invocation, the
      Event Admin service ensures that only handlers that were registered at
      the time the event was posted will receive the event notification. This
      is the same as described in <emphasis>Delivering Events</emphasis> of
      <xref linkend="intro.core.release" xrefstyle="template:%t"/>.</para>

      <para>The Event Admin service can use more than one thread to deliver
      events. If it does then it must guarantee that each handler receives the
      events in the same order as the events were posted, unless this handler
      allows unordered deliver, see <xref linkend="i1556001"/>. This ensures
      that handlers see events in their expected order. For example, for some
      handlers it would be an error to see a <code>destroyed</code> event
      before the corresponding <code>created</code> event.</para>

      <para>Before notifying each handler, the event delivery thread must
      ensure that the handler is still registered in the service registry. If
      it has been unregistered then the handler must not be notified.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Order of Event Delivery</title>

      <para>Asynchronous events are delivered in the order in which they
      arrive in the event queue. Thus if two events are posted by the same
      thread then they will be delivered in the same order (though other
      events may come between them). However, if two or more events are posted
      by different threads then the order in which they arrive in the queue
      (and therefore the order in which they are delivered) will depend very
      much on subtle timing issues. The event delivery system cannot make any
      guarantees in this case. An Event Handler can indicate that the ordering
      is not relevant, allowing the Event Admin to more aggressively
      parallelize the event deliver, see <xref linkend="i1556001"/>.</para>

      <para>Synchronous events are delivered as soon as they are sent. If two
      events are sent by the same thread, one after the other, then they must
      be guaranteed to be processed serially and in the same order. However,
      if two events are sent by different threads then no guarantees can be
      made. The events can be processed in parallel or serially, depending on
      whether or not the Event Admin service dispatches synchronous events in
      the caller's thread or in a separate thread.</para>

      <para>Note that if the actions of a handler trigger a synchronous event,
      then the delivery of the first event will be paused and delivery of the
      second event will begin. Once delivery of the second event has
      completed, delivery of the first event will resume. Thus some handlers
      may observe the second event before they observe the first one.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reliability</title>

    <section>
      <title>Exceptions in callbacks</title>

      <para>If a handler throws an Exception during delivery of an event, it
      must be caught by the Event Admin service and handled in some
      implementation specific way. If a Log Service is available the exception
      should be logged. Once the exception has been caught and dealt with, the
      event delivery must continue with the next handlers to be notified, if
      any.</para>

      <para>As the Log Service can also forward events through the Event Admin
      service there is a potential for a loop when an event is reported to the
      Log Service.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Dealing with Stalled Handlers</title>

      <para>Event handlers should not spend too long in the
      <code>handleEvent</code> method. Doing so will prevent other handlers in
      the system from being notified. If a handler needs to do something that
      can take a while, it should do it in a different thread.</para>

      <para>An event admin implementation can attempt to detect stalled or
      deadlocked handlers and deal with them appropriately. Exactly how it
      deals with this situation is left as implementation specific. One
      allowed implementation is to mark the current event delivery thread as
      invalid and spawn a new event delivery thread. Event delivery must
      resume with the next handler to be notified.</para>

      <para>Implementations can choose to blacklist any handlers that they
      determine are misbehaving. Blacklisted handlers must not be notified of
      any events. If a handler is blacklisted, the event admin should log a
      message that explains the reason for it.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interoperability with Native Applications</title>

    <para>Implementations of the Event Admin service can support passing
    events to, and/or receiving events from native applications.</para>

    <para>If the implementation supports native interoperability, it must be
    able to pass the topic of the event and its properties to/from native
    code. Implementations must be able to support property values of the
    following types:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>String</code> objects, including full Unicode
        support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>Integer, Long, Byte, Short, Float, Double, Boolean,
        Character</code> objects</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Single-dimension arrays of the above types (including
        <code>String</code>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Single-dimension arrays of Java's eight primitive types
        (<code>int, long, byte, short, float, double, boolean,
        char</code>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Implementations can support additional types. Property values of
    unsupported types must be silently discarded.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.event-capabilities">
    <title>Capabilities</title>

    <section>
      <title>osgi.implementation Capability</title>

      <para>The Event Admin implementation bundle must provide the <link
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.implementation.namespace"><code>osgi.implementation</code></link>
      capability with the name <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.event.EventConstants.EVENT_ADMIN_IMPLEMENTATION"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This capability can be used by provisioning
      tools and during resolution to ensure that an Event Admin implementation
      is present. The capability must also declare a uses constraint for the
      <code>org.osgi.service.event</code> package and provide the version of
      this specification:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.implementation;
       osgi.implementation="osgi.event";
       uses:="org.osgi.service.event";
       version:Version="<xref endterm="org.osgi.service.event-version.number"
          linkend="org.osgi.service.event"/>"</programlisting>

      <para>This capability must follow the rules defined for the <xref
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.implementation.namespace"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>osgi.service Capability</title>

      <para>The bundle providing the Event Admin service must provide a
      capability in the <link
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"><code>osgi.service</code></link>
      namespace representing this service. This capability must also declare a
      uses constraint for the <code>org.osgi.service.event</code>
      package:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.service;
  objectClass:List&lt;String&gt;="org.osgi.service.event.EventAdmin";
  uses:="org.osgi.service.event"</programlisting>

      <para>This capability must follow the rules defined for the <xref
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <section>
      <title>Topic Permission</title>

      <para>The <code>TopicPermission</code> class allows fine-grained control
      over which bundles may post events to a given topic and which bundles
      may receive those events.</para>

      <para>The target parameter for the permission is the topic name.
      <code>TopicPermission</code> classes uses a wildcard matching algorithm
      similar to the <code>BasicPermission</code> class, except that solidi
      (<code>'/' \u002F</code>) are used as separators instead of full stop
      characters. For example, a name of <code>a/b/*</code> implies
      <code>a/b/c</code> but not <code>x/y/z</code> or
      <code>a/b</code>.</para>

      <para>There are two available actions: <code>PUBLISH</code> and
      <code>SUBSCRIBE</code>. These control a bundle's ability to either
      publish or receive events, respectively. Neither one implies the
      other.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Required Permissions</title>

      <para>Bundles that need to register an event handler must be granted
      <code>ServicePermission</code>[<code>org.osgi.service.event.EventHandler</code>,
      <code>REGISTER</code>]. In addition, handlers require
      <code>TopicPermission[ &lt;topic&gt;, SUBSCRIBE ]</code> for each topic
      they want to be notified about.</para>

      <para>Bundles that need to publish an event must be granted
      <code>ServicePermission[ org.osgi.service.event.EventAdmin, GET]</code>
      so that they may retrieve the Event Admin service and use it. In
      addition, event sources require <code>TopicPermission[ &lt;topic&gt;,
      PUBLISH]</code> for each topic they want to send events to.</para>

      <para>Bundles that need to iterate the handlers registered with the
      system must be granted
      <code>ServicePermission[org.osgi.service.event.EventHandler, GET]</code>
      to retrieve the event handlers from the service registry.</para>

      <para>Only a bundle that contains an Event Admin service implementation
      should be granted <code>ServicePermission[
      org.osgi.service.event.EventAdmin, REGISTER]</code> to register the
      event channel admin service.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Security Context During Event Callbacks</title>

      <para>During an event notification, the Event Admin service's Protection
      Domain will be on the stack above the handler's Protection Domain. In
      the case of a synchronous event, the event publisher's protection domain
      can also be on the stack.</para>

      <para>Therefore, if a handler needs to perform a secure operation using
      its own privileges, it must invoke the <code>doPrivileged</code> method
      to isolate its security context from that of its caller.</para>

      <para>The event delivery mechanism must not wrap event notifications in
      a <code>doPrivileged</code> call.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.event.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.event.annotations.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.event.propertytypes.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Added <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.event.annotations"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.event.propertytypes" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        packages.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added <xref linkend="service.event-capabilities"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
