<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="1" revision="$Id$"
         version="5" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>The OSGi™ Alliance was founded in March 1999. Its mission is to create
  open specifications for the network delivery of managed services to local
  networks and devices. The OSGi organization is the leading standard for
  next-generation Internet services to homes, cars, mobile phones, desktops,
  small offices, and other environments.</para>

  <para>The OSGi Core specification delivers an open, common architecture for
  service providers, developers, software vendors, gateway operators and
  equipment vendors to develop, deploy and manage services in a coordinated
  fashion. It enables an entirely new category of smart devices due to its
  flexible and managed deployment of services. OSGi specifications target
  set-top boxes, service gateways, cable modems, consumer electronics, PCs,
  industrial computers, cars, mobile phones, and more. Devices that implement
  the OSGi specifications will enable service providers like telcos, cable
  operators, utilities, and others to deliver differentiated and valuable
  services over their networks.</para>

  <para>This is the sixth release of the OSGi Core specification developed by
  representatives from OSGi member companies. The OSGi Core <xref
  endterm="core.book-release" linkend="core.book"/> mostly extends the
  existing APIs into new areas. The few modifications to existing APIs are
  backward compatible so that applications for previous releases should run
  unmodified on <xref endterm="core.book-release" linkend="core.book"/>
  Frameworks. The built-in version management mechanisms allow bundles written
  for the new release to adapt to the old Framework implementations, if
  necessary.</para>

  <section>
    <title>OSGi Framework Overview</title>

    <para>The Framework forms the core of the OSGi Specifications. It provides
    a general-purpose, secure, and managed Java framework that supports the
    deployment of extensible and downloadable applications known as
    <emphasis>bundles</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>OSGi-compliant devices can download and install OSGi bundles, and
    remove them when they are no longer required. The Framework manages the
    installation and update of bundles in an OSGi environment in a dynamic and
    scalable fashion. To achieve this, it manages the dependencies between
    bundles and services in detail.</para>

    <para>It provides the bundle developer with the resources necessary to
    take advantage of Java's platform independence and dynamic code-loading
    capability in order to easily develop services for small-memory devices
    that can be deployed on a large scale.</para>

    <para>The functionality of the Framework is divided in the following
    layers:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Security Layer</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Module Layer</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Life Cycle Layer</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Service Layer</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Actual Services</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>This layering is depicted in <xref linkend="i478414"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i478414">
      <title>Layering</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.881in"
                     contentwidth="4.816in" fileref="layering.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Security Layer is based on Java security but adds a number of
    constraints and fills in some of the blanks that standard Java leaves
    open. It defines a secure packaging format as well as the runtime
    interaction with the Java security layer. The Security Layer is described
    in <xref linkend="framework.security"/>.</para>

    <para>The Module Layer defines a modularization model for Java. It
    addresses some of the shortcomings of Java's deployment model. The
    modularization layer has strict rules for sharing Java packages between
    bundles or hiding packages from other bundles. The Module Layer can be
    used without the life cycle and Service Layer. The Life Cycle Layer
    provides an API to manage the <emphasis>bundles</emphasis> in the Module
    Layer, while the Service Layer provides a communication model for the
    bundles. The Module Layer is described in <xref
    linkend="framework.module"/>.</para>

    <para>The Life Cycle Layer provides a life cycle API to bundles. This API
    provides a runtime model for bundles. It defines how bundles are started
    and stopped as well as how bundles are installed, updated and uninstalled.
    Additionally, it provides a comprehensive event API to allow a management
    bundle to control the operations of the OSGi framework. The Life Cycle
    Layer requires the Module Layer but the Security Layer is optional. A more
    extensive description of the Life Cycle layer can be found at <xref
    linkend="framework.lifecycle"/>.</para>

    <para>The Service Layer provides a dynamic, concise and consistent
    programming model for Java bundle developers, simplifying the development
    and deployment of service bundles by de-coupling the service's
    specification (Java interface) from its implementations. This model allows
    bundle developers to bind to services only using their interface
    specifications. The selection of a specific implementation, optimized for
    a specific need or from a specific vendor, can thus be deferred to
    run-time.</para>

    <para>The framework uses the service layer to provide an extension
    mechanism, called hooks. Hooks are services that are used by the framework
    to provide additional functionality.</para>

    <para>A consistent programming model helps bundle developers cope with
    scalability issues in many different dimensions - critical because the
    Framework is intended to run on a variety of devices whose differing
    hardware characteristics may affect many aspects of a service
    implementation. Consistent interfaces insure that the software components
    can be mixed and matched and still result in stable systems.</para>

    <para>The Framework allows bundles to select an available implementation
    at run-time through the Framework service registry. Bundles register new
    services, receive notifications about the state of services, or look up
    existing services to adapt to the current capabilities of the device. This
    aspect of the Framework makes an installed bundle extensible after
    deployment: new bundles can be installed for added features or existing
    bundles can be modified and updated without requiring the system to be
    restarted.</para>

    <para>The Service Layer is described in <xref
    linkend="framework.service"/>.</para>

    <para>The interactions between the layers is depicted in <xref
    linkend="i478247"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="i478247">
      <title>Interactions between layers</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.549in"
                     contentwidth="4.775in" fileref="layer-interactions.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i476430">
    <title>Reader Level</title>

    <para>This specification is written for the following audiences:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Application developers</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Framework and system service developers (system
        developers)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Architects</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The OSGi Specifications assume that the reader has at least one year
    of practical experience in writing Java programs. Experience with embedded
    systems and server environments is a plus. Application developers must be
    aware that the OSGi environment is significantly more dynamic than
    traditional desktop or server environments.</para>

    <para>System developers require a <emphasis>very</emphasis> deep
    understanding of Java. At least three years of Java coding experience in a
    system environment is recommended. A Framework implementation will use
    areas of Java that are not normally encountered in traditional
    applications. Detailed understanding is required of class loaders, garbage
    collection, Java security, and Java native library loading.</para>

    <para>Architects should focus on the introduction of each subject. This
    introduction contains a general overview of the subject, the requirements
    that influenced its design, and a short description of its operation as
    well as the entities that are used. The introductory sections require
    knowledge of Java concepts like classes and interfaces, but should not
    require coding experience.</para>

    <para>Most of these specifications are equally applicable to application
    developers and system developers.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conventions and Terms</title>

    <section>
      <title>Typography</title>

      <para>A fixed width, non-serif typeface (<code>sample</code>) indicates
      the term is a Java package, class, interface, or member name. Text
      written in this typeface is always related to coding.</para>

      <para>Emphasis (<emphasis>sample</emphasis>) is used the first time an
      important concept is introduced. Its explanation usually follows
      directly after the introduction.</para>

      <para>When an example contains a line that must be broken into multiple
      lines, the <code>«</code> character is used. Spaces must be ignored in
      this case. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>http://www.acme.com/sp/ «
file?abc=12</programlisting>

      <para>is equivalent to:</para>

      <programlisting>http://www.acme.com/sp/file?abc=12</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="framework.general.syntax">
      <title>General Syntax Definitions</title>

      <para>In many cases in these specifications, a syntax must be described.
      This syntax is based on the following symbols:</para>

      <programlisting>*           Repetition of the previous element zero or
            more times, e.g. ( ',' element )*
+           Repetition one or more times
?           Previous element is optional
( ... )     Grouping
'...'       Literal
|           Or
[...]       Set (one of)
..          list, e.g. 1..5 is the list 1 2 3 4 5
&lt;...&gt;       Externally defined token
~           Not</programlisting>

      <para>The following terminals are pre defined and used throughout the
      specifications:</para>

      <programlisting>ws              ::= &lt;see Character.isWhitespace&gt;
digit           ::= [0..9]
alpha           ::= [a..zA..Z]
alphanum        ::= alpha | digit
token           ::= ( alphanum | '_' | '-' )+
number          ::= digit+
jletter         ::= &lt;see <xref linkend="i487605"/>
                     for JavaLetter&gt;
jletterordigit  ::= &lt;see <xref linkend="i487605"/>
                     for JavaLetterOrDigit&gt;

qname           ::= &lt;see <xref linkend="i487605"/>
                     for fully qualified class names&gt;
identifier      ::= jletter jletterordigit *
extended        ::= ( alphanum | '_' | '-' | '.' )+
quoted-string   ::= '"' ( ~["\#x0D#x0A#x00] | '\"' | '\\' )* '"'
argument        ::= extended  | quoted-string
parameter       ::= directive | attribute
directive       ::= extended ':=' argument
attribute       ::= extended '=' argument

unique-name     ::= identifier ( '.' identifier )*
symbolic-name   ::= token ( '.' token )*
package-name    ::= unique-name

path            ::= special-chars+ | quoted-string
special-chars   ::= ~["\#x0D#x0A#x00:=;,&lt;see <xref linkend="i487605"/>
                                         for whitespace&gt;]</programlisting>

      <para>Whitespaces between terminals are ignored unless specifically
      noted. Any value that contains a space, a comma, colon, semi-colon,
      equal sign or any other character that is part of a terminal in the
      grammar must be quoted.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Object Oriented Terminology</title>

      <para>Concepts like classes, interfaces, objects, and services are
      distinct but subtly different. For example, "LogService" could mean an
      instance of the class <code>LogService</code>, could refer to the class
      <code>LogService</code>, or could indicate the functionality of the
      overall Log Service. Experts usually understand the meaning from the
      context, but this understanding requires mental effort. To highlight
      these subtle differences, the following conventions are used.</para>

      <para>When the class is intended, its name is spelled exactly as in the
      Java source code and displayed in a fixed-width typeface: for example,
      the "<code>HttpService</code> class", "a method in the <code>HttpContext
      class</code>" or "a <code>javax.servlet.Servlet</code> object". A class
      name is used in its fully qualified form, like
      <code>javax.servlet.Servlet</code>, when the package is not obvious from
      the context, nor is it in one of the well known java packages like
      <code>java.lang</code>, <code>java.io</code>, <code>java.util</code> and
      <code>java.net</code>. Otherwise, the package is omitted like in
      <code>String</code>.</para>

      <para>In many cases, a type can be used as a scalar but also a
      collection of that type or an array of that type. In those cases, a
      simple + will be suffixed to the type. For example <code>String+</code>,
      indicates that a <code>String</code>, a <code>String[]</code>, and a
      <code>Collection&lt;String&gt;</code> are all valid forms.</para>

      <para>Exception and permission classes are not followed by the word
      "object". Readability is improved when the "object" suffix is avoided.
      For example, "to throw a Security Exception" and to "to have File
      Permission" is more readable then "to have a <code>FilePermission</code>
      object".</para>

      <para>Permissions can further be qualified with their actions.
      <code>ServicePermission[com.acme.*,GET|REGISTER]</code> means a
      <code>ServicePermission</code> with the action <code>GET</code> and
      <code>REGISTER</code> for all service names starting with
      <code>com.acme</code>. A <code>ServicePermission[Producer|Consumer,
      REGISTER]</code> means the <code>ServicePermission</code> for the
      <code>Producer</code> or <code>Consumer</code> class with
      <code>REGISTER</code> action.</para>

      <para>When discussing functionality of a class rather than the
      implementation details, the class name is written as normal text. This
      convention is often used when discussing services. For example, "the
      User Admin service" is more readable.</para>

      <para>Some services have the word "Service" embedded in their class
      name. In those cases, the word "service" is only used once but is
      written with an upper case S. For example, "the Log Service
      performs".</para>

      <para>Service objects are registered with the OSGi Framework.
      Registration consists of the service object, a set of properties, and a
      list of classes and interfaces implemented by this service object. The
      classes and interfaces are used for type safety <emphasis>and</emphasis>
      naming. Therefore, it is said that a service object is registered
      <emphasis>under</emphasis> a class/interface. For example, "This service
      object is registered under <code>PermissionAdmin</code>."</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Diagrams</title>

      <para>The diagrams in this document illustrate the specification and are
      not normative. Their purpose is to provide a high-level overview on a
      single page. The following paragraphs describe the symbols and
      conventions used in these diagrams.</para>

      <para>Classes or interfaces are depicted as rectangles, as in <xref
      linkend="i309274"/>. Interfaces are indicated with the qualifier
      <code>&lt;&lt;interface&gt;&gt;</code> as the first line. The name of
      the class/interface is indicated in bold when it is part of the
      specification. Implementation classes are sometimes shown to demonstrate
      a possible implementation. Implementation class names are shown in plain
      text. In certain cases class names are abbreviated. This is indicated by
      ending the abbreviation with a full stop.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i309274">
        <title>Class and interface symbol</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="0.697in"
                       contentwidth="6.500in" fileref="type-symbols.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If an interface or class is used as a service object, it will have
      a black triangle in the bottom right corner.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Service symbol</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="0.500in"
                       contentwidth="6.500in" fileref="service-symbol.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Service are crucial interaction elements and they can occur many
      times in diagrams describing services. Therefore, an alternative service
      symbol is the triangle. Triangles can be connected in different ways,
      representing different meanings:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Point</emphasis> - Connections to the point of a
          triangle indicate the registration. This makes the point of the
          triangle point to the object that receives the method calls from the
          service users.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Straight Side</emphasis> - Connections to the
          straight side indicate service clients. Clients call the methods of
          the service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Angled Side</emphasis> - The angled side is reserved
          for service listeners.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Alternative Service symbol</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.214in"
                       contentwidth="6.500in"
                       fileref="service-symbol-alternative.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Inheritance (the <code>extends</code> or <code>implements</code>
      keyword in Java class definitions) is indicated with an arrow. <xref
      linkend="i313614"/> shows that the <code>AdminPermission</code> class
      implements or extends the <code>Permission</code> class.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i313614">
        <title>Inheritance (implements or extends) symbol</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="0.500in"
                       contentwidth="6.500in" fileref="symbol-inheritance.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Relations are depicted with a line. The cardinality of the
      relation is given explicitly when relevant. <xref linkend="i309856"/>
      shows that each (1) <code>BundleContext</code> object is related to 0 or
      more <code>BundleListener</code> objects, and that each
      <code>BundleListener</code> object is related to a single
      <code>BundleContext</code> object. Relations usually have some
      description associated with them. This description should be read from
      left to right and top to bottom, and includes the classes on both sides.
      For example: "A <code>BundleContext</code> object delivers bundle events
      to zero or more <code>BundleListener</code> objects."</para>

      <figure xml:id="i309856">
        <title>Relations symbol</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="0.500in"
                       contentwidth="6.500in" fileref="symbol-relations.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Associations are depicted with a dashed line. Associations are
      between classes, and an association can be placed on a relation. For
      example, "every <code>ServiceRegistration</code> object has an
      associated <code>ServiceReference</code> object." This association does
      not have to be a hard relationship, but could be derived in some
      way.</para>

      <para>When a relationship is qualified by a name or an object, it is
      indicated by drawing a dotted line perpendicular to the relation and
      connecting this line to a class box or a description. <xref
      linkend="i313192"/> shows that the relationship between a
      <code>UserAdmin</code> class and a <code>Role</code> class is qualified
      by a name. Such an association is usually implemented with a
      <code>Dictionary</code> or <code>Map</code> object.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i313192">
        <title>Associations symbol</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="0.819in"
                       contentwidth="6.500in"
                       fileref="symbol-associations.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Bundles are entities that are visible in normal application
      programming. For example, when a bundle is stopped, all its services
      will be unregistered. Therefore, the classes/interfaces that are grouped
      in bundles are shown on a grey rectangle as is shown in <xref
      linkend="i429419"/>.</para>

      <figure xml:id="i429419">
        <title>Bundles</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="1.572in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="bundles.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Key Words</title>

      <para>This specification consistently uses the words
      <emphasis>can</emphasis>, <emphasis>should,</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>must</emphasis>. Their meaning is well-defined in:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>must</emphasis> - An absolute requirement. Both the
          Framework implementation and bundles have obligations that are
          required to be fulfilled to conform to this specification.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>should</emphasis> - Recommended. It is strongly
          recommended to follow the description, but reasons may exist to
          deviate from this recommendation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>may</emphasis> or <emphasis>can</emphasis> -
          Optional. Implementations must still be interoperable when these
          items are not implemented.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="framework.numbered.lists">
      <title>Numbered Lists</title>

      <para>When a specification uses a numbered list, unless otherwise
      specified, the intention is that the actions described by the items in
      the list happen in the numerical order of the items. From a Java
      concurrency point-of-view, this means that the actions described in
      lower numbered items <emphasis>happens-before</emphasis> the actions
      described in higher numbered items.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Version Information</title>

    <para>This document specifies OSGi Core <xref endterm="core.book-release"
    linkend="core.book"/>. This specification is backward compatible to all
    prior releases.</para>

    <para>All Security, Module, Life Cycle and Service Layers are part of the
    Framework Specification</para>

    <para>Components in this specification have their own specification
    version, independent of the document release number. The following table
    summarizes the packages and specification versions for the different
    subjects.</para>

    <para>When a component is represented in a bundle, a version is needed in
    the declaration of the Import-Package or Export-Package manifest
    headers.</para>

    <table pgwide="1">
      <title>Packages and versions OSGi Core</title>

      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="3*"/>

        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3.5*"/>

        <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="0.8*"/>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Item</entry>

            <entry>Package</entry>

            <entry>Version</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Framework Specification (all layers)</entry>

            <entry><code><xref linkend="org.osgi.framework"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework-version"
            linkend="framework.api"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><link linkend="framework.lifecycle-frameworks">Framework
            Launching</link></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.launch"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework.launch-version"
            linkend="framework.lifecycle-frameworks"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="framework.resource"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref linkend="org.osgi.resource"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.resource-version"
            linkend="framework.resource"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="framework.wiring"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.wiring"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework.wiring-version"
            linkend="framework.wiring"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="framework.namespaces"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.namespace"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework.namespace-version"
            linkend="framework.namespaces"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="framework.startlevel"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.startlevel"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.framework.startlevel-version"
            linkend="framework.startlevel"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="service.condpermadmin"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.condpermadmin"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            endterm="org.osgi.service.condpermadmin-version"
            linkend="service.condpermadmin"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="service.permissionadmin"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.permissionadmin"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            endterm="org.osgi.service.permissionadmin-version"
            linkend="service.permissionadmin"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="service.url"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.url"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.url-version"
            linkend="service.url"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="framework.resolverhooks"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            endterm="org.osgi.framework.hooks.resolver-version"
            linkend="framework.resolverhooks"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="framework.bundlehooks"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.bundle"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            endterm="org.osgi.framework.hooks.bundle-version"
            linkend="framework.bundlehooks"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="framework.servicehooks"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            endterm="org.osgi.framework.hooks.service-version"
            linkend="framework.servicehooks"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="framework.weavinghooks"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            endterm="org.osgi.framework.hooks.weaving-version"
            linkend="framework.weavinghooks"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="framework.dto"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref linkend="org.osgi.dto"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.dto-version"
            linkend="framework.dto"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="service.resolver"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.resolver"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.resolver-version"
            linkend="service.resolver"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><xref linkend="util.tracker"
            xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.util.tracker"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.util.tracker-version"
            linkend="util.tracker"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><link linkend="org.osgi.annotation.versioning">Versioning
            Annotations</link></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.annotation.versioning"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            endterm="org.osgi.annotation.versioning-version"
            linkend="org.osgi.annotation.versioning"/></code></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><link linkend="org.osgi.annotation.bundle">Bundle
            Annotations</link></entry>

            <entry><code><xref
            linkend="org.osgi.annotation.bundle"/></code></entry>

            <entry><code><xref endterm="org.osgi.annotation.bundle-version"
            linkend="org.osgi.annotation.bundle"/></code></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>A compliant framework implementation must implement all of the
    specifications in this document except as outlined below.</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="service.condpermadmin"
          xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/> and <xref
          linkend="service.permissionadmin" xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/> are
          mandatory only if <xref linkend="framework.security"
          xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/> is supported and a Security Manager is
          installed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="service.url" xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/> is
          mandatory if the framework implementation system bundle exports the
          <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.url"/> package.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="util.tracker" xrefstyle="template:%n %t"/> is
          optional.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i487605"><title>Java Language
      Specification</title>http://docs.oracle.com/javase/specs/</bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Added <xref linkend="framework.numbered.lists"/> to specify the
        <emphasis>happens-before</emphasis> relationship between items in
        numbered lists.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added <xref linkend="org.osgi.annotation.bundle"/>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="service.resolver"/> moved to Core from OSGi
        Compendium, Chapter 136.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
