<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter label="139"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="service.enocean"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Device Service Specification for EnOcean™ Technology</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.enocean-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>EnOcean is a standard wireless communication protocol designed for
    low-cost and low-power devices by EnOcean Alliance.</para>

    <para>EnOcean is widely supported by various types of devices such as
    smart meters, lights and many kinds of sensors in the residential area.
    OSGi applications need to communicate with those EnOcean devices. This
    specification defines how OSGi bundles can be developed to discover and
    control EnOcean devices on the one hand, and act as EnOcean devices and
    interoperate with EnOcean clients on the other hand. In particular, a Java
    mapping is provided for the standard representation of EnOcean devices
    called EnOcean Equipment Profile (EEPs). See <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_10_5"/>.</para>

    <para>The specification also describes the external API of an EnOcean Base
    Driver according to Device Access specification.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Essentials</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Scope</emphasis> - This specification is
        limited to general device discovery and control aspects of the
        standard EnOcean specifications. Aspects concerning the representation
        of specific or proprietary EnOcean profiles is not addressed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Transparency</emphasis> - EnOcean devices discovered
        on the network and devices locally implemented on the platform are
        represented in the OSGi service registry with the same API.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Lightweight implementation option</emphasis> - The
        full description of EnOcean device services on the OSGi platform is
        optional. Some base driver implementations may implement all the
        classes including EnOcean device description classes while
        Implementations targeting constrained devices are able to implement
        only the part that is necessary for EnOcean device discovery and
        control.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Network Selection</emphasis> - It must be possible to
        restrict the use of the EnOcean protocols to a selection of the
        connected devices.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Event handling</emphasis> - Bundles are able to listen
        to EnOcean events.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Discover and control EnOcean devices as OSGi services
        </emphasis> - Available learned (via an EnOcean teach-in procedure)
        EnOcean external endpoints are dynamically reified as OSGi services on
        the service registry upon discovery.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>OSGi services as exported EnOcean devices</emphasis> -
        OSGi services implementing the API defined here and explicitly set to
        be exported should be made available to networks with EnOcean-enabled
        endpoints in a transparent way.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Entities</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>EnOcean Base Driver</emphasis> - The bundle that
        implements the bridge between OSGi and EnOcean networks, see <xref
        linkend="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_11h12_46"
        xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>. It is responsible for
        accessing the various EnOcean gateway chips on the execution machine,
        and ensures the reception and translation of EnOcean messages into
        proper objects. It is also used to send messages on the EnOcean
        network, using whatever chip it deems most appropriate.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>EnOcean Host</emphasis> - The EnOceanHost object is a
        link between the software and the EnOcean network. It represents the
        chip configuration (gateway capabilities) described in <xref
        linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_46_9"/>. It is
        registered as an OSGi service.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>EnOcean Device</emphasis> - An EnOcean device. This
        entity is represented by a EnOceanDevice interface and registered as a
        service within the framework. It carries the unique chip ID of the
        device, and may represent either an imported or exported device, which
        may be a pure transmitter or a transceiver.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>EnOcean Message</emphasis> - Every EnOcean reporting
        equipment is supposed to follow a “profile”, which is essentially the
        way the emitted data is encoded. In order to reflect this standard as
        it is defined in <xref
        linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_10_5"/>,
        manufacturers are able to register the description of “Messages”, the
        essence of a profile, along with their associated payload (as
        Channels). See “EnOcean Channels” below for more information.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>EnOcean Channel</emphasis> - EnOcean channels are
        available as an array inside EnOceanMessage objects. They are a useful
        way to define any kind of payload that would be put inside of an
        EnOcean Message.</para>

        <para>EnOcean Messages and their associated Channels can be described
        with EnOceanMessageDescription and EnOceanChannelDescription
        interfaces. Description providers aggregate these descriptions in sets
        that they register with EnOceanMessageDescriptionSet and
        EnOceanChannelDescriptionSet interfaces within the framework.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>EnOcean RPC</emphasis> - An interface that enables the
        invocation of vendor-specific Remote Procedure Calls and Remote
        Management Commands. These are particular types of Messages and are
        not linked to any EnOcean Profile, so that their descriptions are
        defined and registered in another way. The RPCs are documented via the
        EnOceanRPCDescription objects gathered into registered
        EnOceanRPCDescriptionSet services.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>EnOcean Handler</emphasis> - Enables clients to
        asynchronously get answers to their RPCs.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>EnOcean Client</emphasis> - An application that is
        intended to control EnOcean device services.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>EnOcean Exception</emphasis> - Delivers errors during
        EnOceanMessage serialization/deserialization or during execution
        outside transmission.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure xml:id="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_11h12_46">
      <title>EnOcean Service Specification class diagram.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="3.5in"
                     contentwidth="5.000in"
                     fileref="enocean_service_specification_class_diagram_RFC_EnOcean_ClassDiagram_Rev18.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Operation Summary</title>

    <para>To make an EnOcean device service available to EnOcean clients on
    the OSGi platform, it must be registered under the EnOceanDevice interface
    within the OSGi framework.</para>

    <para>The EnOcean Base Driver is responsible for mapping external devices
    into EnOceanDevice objects, through the use of an EnOcean gateway. See
    <xref linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h02_51_3"/>. The
    latter is represented on OSGi framework as an object implementing
    EnOceanHost interface. EnOcean “teach-in” messages will trigger this
    behavior, this is called a device import situation, see <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_11h32_54"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_11h32_54">
      <title>EnOcean device import.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.5in"
                     contentwidth="5.000in"
                     fileref="enocean_device_import_DeviceImport-1.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Client bundles may also expose framework-internal (local)
    EnOceanDevice instances, registered within the framework, see <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_11h43_01"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>. The Base Driver then should
    emulate those objects as EnOcean devices on the EnOcean network. This is a
    device export situation, made possible by the use of the 127 virtual base
    IDs available on an EnOcean gateway. For more information about this
    process, see <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-export.enocean.device"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_11h43_01">
      <title>EnOcean device export.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.5in"
                     fileref="enocean_device_export_DeviceExport-1.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>EnOcean clients send RPCs (Remote Procedure Calls) to EnOcean
    devices and receives RPC responses and messages from them. Messages coming
    from EnOcean devices are accessible through Event Admin.</para>

    <para>RPCs and messages content are specified by EnOcean Alliance or
    vendor-specific descriptions. Those descriptions may be provided on the
    OSGi platform by any bundle through the registration of
    EnOceanRPCDescriptionSet, EnOceanMessageDescriptionSet and
    EnOceanChannelDescriptionSet services. Every service is a set of
    description that enables applications to retrieve information about
    supported RPCs, messages or channels that compose messages.</para>

    <figure xml:id="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_11h53_00">
      <title>Using a set of message descriptions.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.5in"
                     fileref="using_a_set_of_message_descriptions_message_description_set.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>EnOcean Base Driver</title>

    <para>Most of the functionality described in the operation summary is
    implemented in an EnOcean base driver. This bundle implements the EnOcean
    protocol and handles the interaction with bundles that use the EnOcean
    devices. An EnOcean base driver is able to discover EnOcean devices on the
    network and map each discovered device into an OSGi registered
    EnOceanDevice service. It is also the receptor, through EventAdmin service
    and OSGi service registry, of all the events related to local devices and
    clients. It enables bidirectional communication for RPC and Channel
    updates.</para>

    <para>Several base drivers may be deployed on a residential OSGi device,
    one for every supported network technology. An OSGi device abstraction
    layer may then be implemented as a layer of refinement drivers above a
    layer of base drivers. The refinement driver is responsible for adapting
    technology-specific device services registered by the base driver into
    device services of another model, see AbstractDevice interface in <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_14h51_11"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/>. In the case of a generic
    device abstraction layer, the model is agnostic to technologies.</para>

    <para>The EnOcean Alliance defines their own abstract model with EnOcean
    Equipment Profiles and refinement drivers may provide the implementation
    of all EEPs with EnOcean specific Java interfaces. The AbstractDevice
    interface of <xref linkend="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_14h51_11"
    xrefstyle="template:Figure %n on page %p"/> is then replaced by an EEP
    specific Java interface in that case. The need and the choice of the
    abstraction depends on the targeted application domain.</para>

    <figure xml:id="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_14h51_11">
      <title>EnOcean Base Driver and a refinement driver representing devices
      in an abstract model.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.5in"
                     contentwidth="5.000in"
                     fileref="enocean_base_driver_and_a_refinement_driver_representing_devices_in_an_abstract_model_RefinedDriver-2.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>EnOcean Host</title>

    <para>The EnOcean host represents an EnOcean gateway chip. Any EnOcean
    device service implementation should rely on at least one Gateway Chip in
    order to send and receive messages on the external EnOcean network. This
    interface enables standard control over an EnOcean compatible chip. Every
    EnOceanHost object should at least be identified by its unique chip
    ID.</para>

    <para>The EnOceanHost interface enables OSGi applications to:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Get or set gateway metadata (version, name, etc);</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Reset the gateway chip device;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Retrieve a chip ID (derived from EnOcean's BASE_ID) for the
        given Service PID of a device.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>EnOcean Device</title>

    <section>
      <title>Generics</title>

      <para>A physical EnOcean device is reified as an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      object within the framework.</para>

      <para>An EnOcean device holds most of the natural properties for an
      EnOcean object: its unique ID, the profile, a friendly name, its
      security information, and its available RPCs – along with the associated
      getters (and setters when applicable). All those properties MUST be
      persistent across restart so that teach-in procedures are made only
      once.</para>

      <para>It also holds methods that reflect the natural actions a user
      application may physically trigger on such a device: send a message to
      the device, send a teach-in message to the device, or switch the device
      to learning mode.</para>

      <para>Every EnOcean Device keeps a service PID property that is assigned
      either by the base driver or by any service-exporting bundle. The
      property value format is free and the value must be unique on the
      framework.</para>

      <para>The properties on which EnOceanDevice services can be filtered on
      are: the device's service PID and chip ID, and its profile identifiers
      (RORG / FUNC / TYPE integers).</para>

      <para>The EnOceanDevice also keeps security features as defined in the
      EnOcean Security Draft, <xref
      linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_46_9"/>, which
      allow for a security level format (integer mask), an encryption key
      and/or a rolling authentication code.</para>

      <para>The EnOceanDevice service MUST also be registered with the
      <code>DEVICE_CATEGORY</code> service property, see <xref
      linkend="service.device-device.service.registration"/>, that describes a
      array of categories to which the device belongs. One value MUST be
      <code>EnOcean</code> which is specified in <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice.DEVICE_CATEGORY"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>

      <para>Values for the additional service properties,
      <code>DEVICE_DESCRIPTION</code>, <code>DEVICE_SERIAL</code> as defined
      in <xref linkend="service.device-device.service.registration"/>, are not
      specified here as no description nor application-level serial number are
      provided in the EnOcean standard protocol.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Import Situation</title>

      <para>In import situations, the device's chip ID is uniquely set by the
      Base Driver, according to the one present in the teach-in message that
      originated the Device's creation. The service PID, see <xref
      linkend="service.enocean-reference.service.pid"/>, should also be
      generated and deterministically derived from the chip ID to allow
      reconstruction of a device without a new teach-in process after a
      framework restart.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="service.enocean-export.enocean.device">
      <title>Export Situation</title>

      <para>In export situations:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The registering Client bundle sets the service PID of the
          EnOceanDevice object by itself, in a unique manner, and registers
          that object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The chip ID (this device's EnOcean source ID when it issues
          messages) will be allocated by the Base Driver. The latter keeps a
          dictionary of the currently allocated chip IDs. The Client bundle
          must also set an <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice.ENOCEAN_EXPORT"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> property in the registered device's Property
          Map.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The standard way to programmatically retrieve an exported chip ID
      from a given service PID is by using EnOceanHost's dedicated interface
      for this use.</para>

      <para>The Base Driver MUST ensure the persistence of the
      CHIP_ID:SERVICE_PID mapping.</para>

      <para>As an application developer, please refer to the documentation of
      your Base Driver to know its policies concerning exported chip ID
      updating, deletion and exhaustion.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Interface</title>

      <para>The EnOceanDevice interface enables client bundles to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Get or set the security features of the device in a protected
          way;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Retrieve the currently paired devices in the case of a
          receiver, as a collection of device IDs;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Get the ID-based list of currently available RPCs for the
          device, as a Map of {manufacturerID:[functionId1,
          functionId2,...]};</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Invoke RPCs onto the device, through the <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice.invoke-EnOceanRPC-EnOceanHandler-"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> call.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>EnOcean Messages</title>

    <para>EnOcean Messages are at the core of the EnOcean application layer as
    a whole and the EnOcean Equipment Profile specification, <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_10_5"/>, in
    particular. Every exchange of information within EnOcean networks is done
    with a dedicated message. The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanMessage" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
    interface provides a set of getters. The latter enables OSGi applications
    to get the information contained in the payload of an EnOcean message and
    defined as data and optional data of the EnOcean Serial Protocol Type 1
    (RADIO) message (see Table 2 in Section "1.6.1 Packet description" of
    <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_37_8"/>).</para>

    <para>This model enables reading both the EnOcean radio telegram data and
    the associated metadata that may be attached to it in a single object,
    EnOceanMessage.</para>

    <para>In case the 'Optional Data' section gets missing at the lowest level
    (the radio access layer not following ESP protocol for instance) it is the
    responsibility of the Base Driver to mock the missing field's (dBm,
    destinationID, …) values.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Mode of operation</title>

      <para>Any EnOceanMessage object creation will be mirrored to Event
      Admin.</para>

      <para>Details about the available topics, filters and properties can be
      found in <xref linkend="service.enocean-event.api"/>.</para>

      <para>EnOceanMessage objects will be created only if the originating
      device has already been registered in the OSGi Service Registry, along
      with profile information.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Identification</title>

      <para>The RORG of a message defines its shape and generic type; all the
      RORGs are defined in the EnOcean Radio Specification.</para>

      <para>An addressed message will be encapsulated into an Addressed
      Telegram (ADT) by the base driver transparently; this means that from
      the application level, it will be represented under its original RORG,
      but with a valid destinationID.</para>

      <para>A particular EnOcean Equipment Profile message is identified by
      three numbers: its RORG, and its FUNC, TYPE and EXTRA subtypes. In
      EnOcean, a (RORG, FUNC, TYPE) triplet is enough to identify a profile;
      though an EXTRA identifier is sometimes needed to identify a particular
      message layout for that profile.</para>

      <para>Those identifiers allow for retrieving <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanMessageDescription"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> objects within a registered <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanMessageDescriptionSet"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, which give the application more information to
      parse the message.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Interface</title>

      <para>The methods available in the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanMessage"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Identification methods, retrieving the message's profile,
          sender ID, optional destination ID, status;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A method to get the raw bytes of payload data in the message.
          This data can then be passed to the deserializer of the <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanMessageDescription"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object to be converted to <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanChannel"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, which may -again- be documented (through
          <xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> objects) or not.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Link quality information read-only methods that mirror some of
          the 'Optional Data' header information.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>EnOcean Message Description</title>

    <para><xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanMessageDescription"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> objects exposes only two methods:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanMessageDescription.deserialize-byte---"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>: makes the user able to deserialize the
        payload bytes of a raw <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanMessage"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object, into a collection of <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanChannel"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> objects.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanMessageDescription.serialize-EnOceanChannel---"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>: serializes the input <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanChannel"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> objects into a collection of bytes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>EnOcean Channel</title>

    <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanChannel"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface is the first step of an abstraction to
    generate or interpret <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanMessage" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
    channels with plain Java types.</para>

    <para>The simple EnOceanChannel interface provides a way to separate the
    different fields in a message payload, knowing their offset and size in
    the byte array that constitutes the full message's payload.</para>

    <para>At the EnOceanChannel level, the only way to get/set the information
    contained in the channel is through a pair of <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanChannel.getRawValue--"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanChannel.setRawValue-byte---"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods, which act on plain bytes.</para>

    <para>Those bytes are meant right-aligned, and the number of those bytes
    is the size of the data field, floored up to the next multiple of 8. For
    instance, a 3-bit long channel would be encoded on one byte, all the
    necessary information starting from bit 0.</para>

    <para>Every EnOceanMessage as described in the EEP Specification contains
    a various amount of channels, each of them being identified by their
    unique ID.</para>

    <para>This ID, or channelID, is constituted of the “Shortcut” field of
    this channel from the EEP 2.5 Specification, <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_10_5"/>, and a
    number fixed by the order of appearance of such a “Shortcut” in the
    specification.</para>

    <para>This unique identifier links a Channel to an <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object that provides more information to encode
    and decode that channel's information; see below for more details. This
    enables for loose coupling of the raw Channel itself and a richer,
    3rd-party provided, information.</para>

    <para>As an example, if the platform being developed is an electronic
    display that waits for Messages from a well-known temperature sensor, the
    Client bundle on the platform may interpret the Temperature Channels in
    every Temperature Message without needing an appropriate
    TemperatureChannelDescription object; it may directly cast and convert the
    Byte[] array of every received message to a properly valued Double and
    display that.</para>

    <para>Otherwise, it could as well use the channelID to get a
    TemperatureChannelDescription object that would properly handle the
    deserialization process from the raw bytes to a proper, physical
    unit-augmented, result.</para>

    <figure xml:id="service.enocean-figure_id_20140603_16h48_38">
      <title>EnOcean channel and EnOcean channel descriptions.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.5in"
                     contentwidth="5.000in"
                     fileref="enocean_channel_and_enocean_channel_descriptions_channel_diagram_v5.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>EnOcean Channel Description</title>

    <para>The <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface enables the description of all the
    various channels as specified in the EnOcean specification, as well as the
    description of channels issued by 3rd party actors.</para>

    <para>Those description objects are retrieved from the registered <xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescriptionSet"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface using an unique ID known as the
    channelID.</para>

    <para>Here are the Channel types defined in this specification:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.TYPE_RAW"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>: A collection of bytes. This type is used when
        the description is not provided, and is thus the default. For this
        type, the <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.deserialize-byte---"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> call actually returns a byte[] collection. The
        encryption key or a device ID on 4 bytes are examples of such raw
        types.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.TYPE_DATA"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>: A scaled physical value. Used when the data
        can be mapped to a physical value; for instance, the 'WND – Wind
        Speed' channel is a raw binary value, in a range from 0 to 255, that
        will be mapped as a wind speed between 0 and 70 m/s. For this type,
        the <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.deserialize-byte---"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> call actually returns a Double value.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.TYPE_FLAG"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>: A boolean value. Used when the Channel value
        can be either 1 or 0. The “Teach-In” Channel is a well-known example;
        this 1-bit field may either be 0 or 1, depending whether the Message
        is a teach-in one or not. For this type, the <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.deserialize-byte---"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> call actually returns a Boolean value.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.TYPE_ENUM"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>: An enumeration of possible values. Used when
        the Channel can only take a discrete number of values. More
        complicated than <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.TYPE_FLAG"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, enumerated types may have thresholds: for
        instance, the A5-30 “Digital Input- Input State (IPS)” channel is a
        8-bit value which means “Contact closed” between 0 and 195, and
        “Contact open” from 196 to 255. For this type, the <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.deserialize-byte---"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> call actually returns an <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelEnumValue"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>According to the channel type, the actual description object should
    implement one of the following specialized interfaces. This will ease the
    use of casting to the specialized interfaces on documented
    channels.</para>

    <section>
      <title>EnOcean Data Channel Description</title>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanDataChannelDescription"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface inherits from <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface.</para>

      <para>Two more methods give access to the integer input domain of the
      data channel (such as 0-255) and to the floating-point output range of
      it (such as -30.0°C – 24.5°C). A method is also present to retrieve the
      physical unit of the channel. The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.serialize-Object-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.deserialize-byte---"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods are implemented to easily convert from
      the raw byte[] collection to a Double, and vice versa.</para>

      <para>Here are a few samples of such Channels:</para>

      <table>
        <title>EnOcean Data Channel Description example</title>

        <tgroup align="left" cols="6" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="3*"/>

          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="1*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Short</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>

              <entry>Possible implemented name</entry>

              <entry>Domain</entry>

              <entry>Range</entry>

              <entry>Unit</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>TMP</entry>

              <entry>Temperature</entry>

              <entry>TemperatureScaledChannel_X</entry>

              <entry>0..255</entry>

              <entry>-10°..+30°</entry>

              <entry>°C</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>HUM</entry>

              <entry>Humidity</entry>

              <entry>HumidityScaledChannel_X</entry>

              <entry>0..250</entry>

              <entry>0..100</entry>

              <entry>%</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>EnOcean Flag Channel Description</title>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanFlagChannelDescription"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface inherits from the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface.</para>

      <para>Those channels, are typically used for On/Off reporting values
      (like a switch); they have no additional methods, though the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.deserialize-byte---"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method converts the input bit into a proper
      Boolean object.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>EnOcean Enumerated Channel Description</title>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanEnumChannelDescription"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface inherits from the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface.</para>

      <para>The additional method provided to this interface is <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanEnumChannelDescription.getPossibleValues--"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, which returns an array of the available <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelEnumValue"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> objects accessible to this channel. Every <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelEnumValue"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object contains its integer input range and a
      String identifier that defines its meaning.</para>

      <para>The <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.serialize-Object-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelDescription.deserialize-byte---"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods of an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanEnumChannelDescription"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object thus convert an integer input value (say,
      156) to an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelEnumValue"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, and vice versa.</para>

      <para>Here is an example that shows the input range and the associated
      <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.EnOceanChannelEnumValue"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>:</para>

      <table>
        <title>EnOcean Enumerated Channel Description example</title>

        <tgroup align="left" cols="5" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="3*"/>

          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="3*"/>

          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="2*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Device profile</entry>

              <entry>EnOceanChannelEnumValue</entry>

              <entry>Start</entry>

              <entry>Stop</entry>

              <entry>Meaning</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry morerows="3" valign="top"><para> Fan speed stage
              switch</para></entry>

              <entry>FanStageSwitch_Stage3</entry>

              <entry>0</entry>

              <entry>144</entry>

              <entry>Fan speed: Stage 3</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>FanStageSwitch_Stage2</entry>

              <entry>145</entry>

              <entry>164</entry>

              <entry>Fan speed: Stage 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>FanStageSwitch_Stage1</entry>

              <entry>165</entry>

              <entry>189</entry>

              <entry>Fan speed: Stage 1</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>FanStageSwitch_Stage0</entry>

              <entry>190</entry>

              <entry>209</entry>

              <entry>Fan speed: Stage 0</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>EnOcean Remote Management</title>

    <para>Remote Management is a feature which allows EnOcean devices to be
    configured and maintained over the air using radio messages.</para>

    <para>The Remote Procedure Calls, or RPCs - as defined by the EnOcean
    Remote Management specification, <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_19_6"/> - are not
    related to any EnOcean Equipment Profile.</para>

    <para>Note that EnOcean Remote Commissioning is detailed in an additional
    EnOcean document, <xref
    linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20150105_16h26_16_99"/>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>EnOcean RPC</title>

      <para>An <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanRPC"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object enables client bundles to remotely manage
      EnOcean devices using already defined behavior.</para>

      <para>RPCs are defined by a <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanRPC.MANUFACTURER_ID"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> (11 bits, 0x7FF for the EnOcean alliance) and a
      unique <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanRPC.FUNCTION_ID"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> code on 12 bits.</para>

      <para>RPCs are called directly onto an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      object via the <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice.invoke-EnOceanRPC-EnOceanHandler-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, which accepts also a non-mandatory <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanHandler"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> object as a parameter to retrieve the
      asynchronous answer.</para>

      <para>Broadcasted RPCs can be addressed directly to the Base Driver
      using the relevant Event Admin topic; see <xref
      linkend="service.enocean-event.api"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>EnOcean Handler</title>

      <para>Responses to RPCs are processed by the driver and sent back to a
      handler using <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanHandler.notifyResponse-EnOceanRPC-byte---"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method when an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanHandler"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> is passed to the base driver.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Working With an EnOcean Device</title>

    <section>
      <title>Service Tracking</title>

      <para>All discovered EnOcean devices in the local networks are
      registered under <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface within the OSGi framework. Every time
      an EnOcean device appears or quits the network, the associated OSGi
      service is registered or unregistered in the OSGi service registry.
      Thanks to the EnOcean Base Driver, the OSGi service availability in the
      registry mirrors EnOcean device availability on EnOcean network, <xref
      linkend="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h02_51_3"/>.</para>

      <para>Thanks to service events, a bundle is able to track the addition,
      modification and removal of an <xref
      linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      service.</para>

      <para>The following example shows using a ServiceTracker to track
      EnOceanDevice services.</para>

      <programlisting>ServiceTracker&lt;EnOceanDevice, EnOceanDevice&gt; enOceanTracker = 
    new ServiceTracker&lt;&gt;(bundleContext, EnOceanDevice.class, null);
enOceanTracker.open(); // open the tracker

...

// get a snaphot of the current EnOceanDevice services
EnOceanDevice[] enOceanDeviceSnapshot = 
    enOceanTracker.getServices(new EnOceanDevice[0]);

...

enOceanTracker.close(); // close the tracker</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.enocean-event.api">
    <title>Event API</title>

    <para>EnOcean events must be delivered to the EventAdmin service by the
    EnOcean implementation, if present. EnOcean event topic follow the
    following form:
    <code>org/osgi/service/enocean/EnOceanEvent/</code><emphasis>SUBTOPIC</emphasis>.</para>

    <para><code>MESSAGE_RECEIVED</code> and <code>RPC_BROADCAST</code> are the
    two available subtopics.</para>

    <section>
      <title>MESSAGE_RECEIVED</title>

      <para>Properties (every event may dispatch some or all of the following
      properties):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice.CHIP_ID"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – . The chip ID of the sending
          device.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.pid</code> – The service PID of the exported
          device.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice.RORG"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The RORG (Radio Telegram Type) of the
          sending device.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice.FUNC"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The FUNC profile identifier of the sending
          device.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanDevice.TYPE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The TYPE profile identifier of the sending
          device.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanEvent.PROPERTY_MESSAGE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The EnOceanMessage object associated with
          this event.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanEvent.PROPERTY_EXPORTED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The presence of this property means that
          this message has actually been exported from a locally implemented
          EnOcean Device.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>RPC_BROADCAST</title>

      <para>This event is used whenever an RPC is broadcasted on EnOcean
      networks, in IMPORT or EXPORT situations.</para>

      <para>Properties (every event may dispatch some or all of the following
      properties):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanRPC.MANUFACTURER_ID"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The RPC's manufacturer ID.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanRPC.FUNCTION_ID"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The RPC's function ID .</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanEvent.PROPERTY_EXPORTED"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The presence of this property means that
          this RPC has actually been exported from a locally implemented
          EnOcean Device.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanEvent.PROPERTY_RPC"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The EnOceanRPC object associated with this
          event.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>EnOcean Exceptions</title>

    <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanException"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> can be thrown and holds information about the
    different EnOcean layers. Here below, ESP stands for <emphasis>EnOcean
    Serial Protocol</emphasis>. The following errors are defined:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanException.ESP_UNEXPECTED_FAILURE"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – Operation was not successful.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanException.ESP_RET_NOT_SUPPORTED"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The ESP command was not supported by the
        driver.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanException.ESP_RET_WRONG_PARAM"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The ESP command was supplied wrong
        parameters.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanException.ESP_RET_OPERATION_DENIED"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The ESP command was denied
        authorization.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.enocean.EnOceanException.INVALID_TELEGRAM"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> – The message was invalid.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>It is recommended that
    <code>ServicePermission[EnOceanDevice|EnOceanHost, REGISTER|GET]</code> be
    used sparingly and only for bundles that are trusted.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.enocean.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.enocean.descriptions.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h02_51_3"><title>Pervasive
      Service Composition in the Home Network</title>Bottaro, A., Gérodolle,
      A., Lalanda, P., 21st IEEE International Conference on Advanced
      Information Networking and Applications (AINA-07), Niagara Falls,
      Canada, May 2007</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_10_5"><title>EnOcean
      Equipment Profiles v2.6.2</title><biblioid class="uri">EnOcean Alliance, <link
      xlink:href="https://www.enocean-alliance.org/en/enocean_standard/"/>, November 19,
      2014</biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_19_6"><title>EnOcean
      System Specification - Remote Management v2.0</title>EnOcean Alliance,
      March 06, 2014</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_37_8"><title>EnOcean
      System Specification - EnOcean Serial Protocol v1.17</title>EnOcean
      Alliance, August 2, 2011</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20140602_17h03_46_9"><title>EnOcean
      System Specification - Security of EnOcean Radio Networks
      v1.9</title>EnOcean Alliance, July 26, 2013</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.enocean-bibliomixed_id_20150105_16h26_16_99"><title>EnOcean
      Remote Commissioning Summary v1.0</title><biblioid class="uri">EnOcean Alliance, <link
      xlink:href="https://www.enocean-alliance.org/en/downloads/"/>, December 01,
      2014</biblioid></bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed
      xml:id="service.enocean-reference.service.pid"><title>Persistent
      Identifier (PID)</title>OSGi Core Release, Service Layer</bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
