<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright (c) Contributors to the Eclipse Foundation
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
   
    SPDX-License-Identifier: Apache-2.0 
 -->

<chapter label="107"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="service.useradmin"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>User Admin Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.useradmin-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.useradmin"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>OSGi frameworks are often used in places where end users or devices
    initiate actions. These kinds of actions inevitably create a need for
    authenticating the initiator. Authenticating can be done in many different
    ways, including with passwords, one-time token cards, biometrics, and
    certificates.</para>

    <para>Once the initiator is authenticated, it is necessary to verify that
    this principal is authorized to perform the requested action. This
    authorization can only be decided by the operator of the OSGi environment,
    and thus requires administration.</para>

    <para>The User Admin service provides this type of functionality. Bundles
    can use the User Admin service to authenticate an initiator and represent
    this authentication as an <code>Authorization</code> object. Bundles that
    execute actions on behalf of this user can use the
    <code>Authorization</code> object to verify if that user is
    authorized.</para>

    <para>The User Admin service provides authorization based on who runs the
    code, instead of using the Java code-based permission model. See <xref
    linkend="i1307817"/>. It performs a role similar to <xref
    linkend="i1307810"/>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Authentication</emphasis> - A large number of
          authentication schemes already exist, and more will be developed.
          The User Admin service must be flexible enough to adapt to the many
          different authentication schemes that can be run on a computer
          system.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Authorization</emphasis> - All bundles should use
          the User Admin service to authenticate users and to find out if
          those users are authorized. It is therefore paramount that a bundle
          can find out authorization information with little effort.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Security</emphasis> - Detailed security, based on
          the Framework security model, is needed to provide safe access to
          the User Admin service. It should allow limited access to the
          credentials and other properties.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Extensibility</emphasis> - Other bundles should be
          able to build on the User Admin service. It should be possible to
          examine the information from this service and get real-time
          notifications of changes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Properties</emphasis> - The User Admin service must
          maintain a persistent database of users. It must be possible to use
          this database to hold more information about this user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Administration</emphasis> - Administering
          authorizations for each possible action and initiator is
          time-consuming and error-prone. It is therefore necessary to have
          mechanisms to group end users and make it simple to assign
          authorizations to all members of a group at one time.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <para>This Specification defines the following User Admin service
      entities:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>User Admin</emphasis> - This interface manages a
          database of named roles which can be used for authorization and
          authentication purposes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Role</emphasis> - This interface exposes the
          characteristics shared by all roles: a name, a type, and a set of
          properties.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>User</emphasis> - This interface (which extends
          <code>Role</code>) is used to represent any entity which may have
          credentials associated with it. These credentials can be used to
          authenticate an initiator.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Group</emphasis> - This interface (which extends
          <code>User</code>) is used to contain an aggregation of named
          <code>Role</code> objects (<code>Group</code> or <code>User</code>
          objects).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Authorization</emphasis> - This interface
          encapsulates an authorization context on which bundles can base
          authorization decisions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>User Admin Event</emphasis> - This class is used to
          represent a role change event.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>User Admin Listener</emphasis> - This interface
          provides a listener for events of type <code>UserAdminEvent</code>
          that can be registered as a service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>User Admin Permission</emphasis> - This permission
          is needed to configure and access the roles managed by a User Admin
          service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Role.USER_ANYONE</emphasis> - This is a special User
          object that represents <emphasis>any</emphasis> user, it implies all
          other User objects. It is also used when a Group is used with only
          basic members. The <code>Role.USER_ANYONE</code> is then the only
          required member.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure pgwide="1">
        <title>User Admin Service, org.osgi.service.useradmin</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="4.681in"
                       contentwidth="6.500in" fileref="useradmin-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Operation</title>

      <para>An Operator uses the User Admin service to define OSGi framework
      users and configure them with properties, credentials, and
      <emphasis>roles</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>A <code>Role</code> object represents the initiator of a request
      (human or otherwise). This specification defines two types of
      roles:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>User</emphasis> - A <code>User</code> object can be
          configured with credentials, such as a password, and properties,
          such as address, telephone number, and so on.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Group</emphasis> - A <code>Group</code> object is an
          aggregation of <emphasis>basic</emphasis> and
          <emphasis>required</emphasis> roles. Basic and required roles are
          used in the authorization phase.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>An OSGi framework can have several entry points, each of which
      will be responsible for authenticating incoming requests. An example of
      an entry point is the Http Service, which delegates authentication of
      incoming requests to the <code>handleSecurity</code> method of the
      <code>HttpContext</code> object that was specified when the target
      servlet or resource of the request was registered.</para>

      <para>The OSGi framework entry points should use the information in the
      User Admin service to authenticate incoming requests, such as a password
      stored in the private credentials or the use of a certificate.</para>

      <para>A bundle can determine if a request for an action is authorized by
      looking for a <code>Role</code> object that has the name of the
      requested action.</para>

      <para>The bundle may execute the action if the <code>Role</code> object
      representing the initiator <emphasis>implies</emphasis> the
      <code>Role</code> object representing the requested action.</para>

      <para>For example, an initiator <code>Role</code> object
      <emphasis>X</emphasis> implies an action <code>Group</code> object
      <emphasis>A</emphasis> if:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>X</emphasis> implies at least one of
          <emphasis>A</emphasis>'s basic members, and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>X</emphasis> implies all of <emphasis>A</emphasis>'s
          required members.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>An initiator <code>Role</code> object <emphasis>X</emphasis>
      implies an action <code>User</code> object <emphasis>A</emphasis>
      if:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>A</emphasis> and <emphasis>X</emphasis> are
          equal.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The <code>Authorization</code> class handles this non-trivial
      logic. The User Admin service can capture the privileges of an
      authenticated <code>User</code> object into an
      <code>Authorization</code> object. The
      <code>Authorization.hasRole</code> method checks if the authenticate
      <code>User</code> object has (or implies) a specified action
      <code>Role</code> object.</para>

      <para>For example, in the case of the Http Service, the
      <code>HttpContext</code> object can authenticate the initiator and place
      an <code>Authorization</code> object in the request header. The servlet
      calls the <code>hasRole</code> method on this <code>Authorization</code>
      object to verify that the initiator has the authority to perform a
      certain action. See <xref
      linkend="service.http.authentication"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Authentication</title>

    <para>The authentication phase determines if the initiator is actually the
    one it says it is. Mechanisms to authenticate always need some information
    related to the user or the OSGi framework to authenticate an external
    user. This information can consist of the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A secret known only to the initiator.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Knowledge about cards that can generate a unique token.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Public information like certificates of trusted signers.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Information about the user that can be measured in a trusted
        way.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Other specific information.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Repository</title>

      <para>The User Admin service offers a repository of <code>Role</code>
      objects. Each <code>Role</code> object has a unique name and a set of
      properties that are readable by anyone, and are changeable when the
      changer has the <code>UserAdminPermission</code>. Additionally,
      <code>User</code> objects, a sub-interface of <code>Role</code>, also
      have a set of private protected properties called credentials.
      Credentials are an extra set of properties that are used to authenticate
      users and that are protected by <code>UserAdminPermission</code>.</para>

      <para>Properties are accessed with the <code>Role.getProperties()</code>
      method and credentials with the <code>User.getCredentials()</code>
      method. Both methods return a <code>Dictionary</code> object containing
      key/value pairs. The keys are <code>String</code> objects and the values
      of the <code>Dictionary</code> object are limited to <code>String</code>
      or <code>byte[ ]</code> objects.</para>

      <para>This specification does not define any standard keys for the
      properties or credentials. The keys depend on the implementation of the
      authentication mechanism and are not formally defined by OSGi
      specifications.</para>

      <para>The repository can be searched for objects that have a unique
      property (key/value pair) with the method
      <code>UserAdmin.getUser(String,String)</code>. This makes it easy to
      find a specific user related to a specific authentication mechanism. For
      example, a secure card mechanism that generates unique tokens could have
      a serial number identifying the user. The owner of the card could be
      found with the method</para>

      <programlisting>User owner = useradmin.getUser(
    "secure-card-serial", "132456712-1212" );</programlisting>

      <para>If multiple <code>User</code> objects have the same property (key
      <emphasis>and</emphasis> value), a <code>null</code> is returned.</para>

      <para>There is a convenience method to verify that a user has a
      credential without actually getting the credential. This is the
      <code>User.hasCredential(String,Object)</code> method.</para>

      <para>Access to credentials is protected on a name basis by
      <code>UserAdminPermission</code>. Because properties can be read by
      anyone with access to a <code>User</code> object,
      <code>UserAdminPermission</code> only protects change access to
      properties.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Basic Authentication</title>

      <para>The following example shows a very simple authentication algorithm
      based on passwords.</para>

      <para>The vendor of the authentication bundle uses the property
      <code>"com.acme.basic-id"</code> to contain the name of a user as it
      logs in. This property is used to locate the <code>User</code> object in
      the repository. Next, the credential <code>"com.acme.password"</code>
      contains the password and is compared to the entered password. If the
      password is correct, the <code>User</code> object is returned. In all
      other cases a <code>SecurityException</code> is thrown.</para>

      <programlisting>public User authenticate(
        UserAdmin ua, String name, String pwd )
    throws SecurityException {
    User user = ua.getUser("com.acme.basicid",
        username);
    if (user == null)
        throw new SecurityException( "No such user" );

    if (!user.hasCredential("com.acme.password", pwd))
        throw new SecurityException( 
            "Invalid password" );
    return user;
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Certificates</title>

      <para>Authentication based on certificates does not require a shared
      secret. Instead, a certificate contains a name, a public key, and the
      signature of one or more signers.</para>

      <para>The name in the certificate can be used to locate a
      <code>User</code> object in the repository. Locating a <code>User</code>
      object, however, only identifies the initiator and does not authenticate
      it.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The first step to authenticate the initiator is to verify that
          it has the private key of the certificate.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Next, the User Admin service must verify that it has a
          <code>User</code> object with the right property, for example
          <code>"com.acme.certificate"="Fudd"</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The next step is to see if the certificate is signed by a
          trusted source. The bundle could use a central list of trusted
          signers and only accept certificates signed by those sources.
          Alternatively, it could require that the certificate itself is
          already stored in the repository under a unique key as a
          <code>byte[]</code> in the credentials.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In any case, once the certificate is verified, the associated
          <code>User</code> object is authenticated.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Authorization</title>

    <para>The User Admin service authorization architecture is a
    <emphasis>role-based model</emphasis>. In this model, every action that
    can be performed by a bundle is associated with a
    <emphasis>role</emphasis>. Such a role is a <code>Group</code> object
    (called group from now on) from the User Admin service repository. For
    example, if a servlet could be used to activate the alarm system, there
    should be a group named <code>AlarmSystemActivation</code>.</para>

    <para>The operator can administrate authorizations by populating the group
    with <code>User</code> objects (users) and other groups. Groups are used
    to minimize the amount of administration required. For example, it is
    easier to create one <code>Administrators</code> group and add
    administrative roles to it rather than individually administer all users
    for each role. Such a group requires only one action to remove or add a
    user as an administrator.</para>

    <para>The authorization decision can now be made in two fundamentally
    different ways:</para>

    <para>An initiator could be allowed to carry out an action (represented by
    a <code>Group</code> object) if it implied any of the <code>Group</code>
    object's members. For example, the <code>AlarmSystemActivation
    Group</code> object contains an <code>Administrators</code> and a
    <code>Family Group</code> object:</para>

    <programlisting>    Administrators        = { Elmer, Pepe,Bugs }
    Family                = { Elmer, Pepe, Daffy }

    AlarmSystemActivation = { Administrators, Family}</programlisting>

    <para>Any of the four members <code>Elmer</code>, <code>Pepe</code>,
    <code>Daffy</code>, or <code>Bugs</code> can activate the alarm
    system.</para>

    <para>Alternatively, an initiator could be allowed to perform an action
    (represented by a <code>Group</code> object) if it implied
    <emphasis>all</emphasis> the <code>Group</code> object's members. In this
    case, using the same <code>AlarmSystemActivation</code> group, only
    <code>Elmer</code> and <code>Pepe</code> would be authorized to activate
    the alarm system, since <code>Daffy</code> and <code>Bugs</code> are
    <emphasis>not</emphasis> members of <emphasis>both</emphasis> the
    <code>Administrators</code> and <code>Family Group</code> objects.</para>

    <para>The User Admin service supports a combination of both strategies by
    defining both a set of <emphasis>basic members</emphasis> (any) and a set
    of <emphasis>required members</emphasis> (all).</para>

    <programlisting>Administrators            = { Elmer, Pepe, Bugs}
Family                    = { Elmer, Pepe, Daffy }

AlarmSystemActivation 
    required              = { Administrators }
    basic                 = { Family }</programlisting>

    <para>The difference is made when <code>Role</code> objects are added to
    the <code>Group</code> object. To add a basic member, use the
    <code>Group.addMember(Role)</code> method. To add a required member, use
    the <code>Group.addRequiredMember(Role)</code> method.</para>

    <para>Basic members define the set of members that can get access and
    required members reduce this set by requiring the initiator to
    <emphasis>imply</emphasis> each required member.</para>

    <para>A <code>User</code> object implies a <code>Group</code> object if it
    implies the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>All</emphasis> of the Group's required members,
        and</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>At <emphasis>least</emphasis> one of the Group's basic
        members</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A <code>User</code> object always implies itself.</para>

    <para>If only required members are used to qualify the implication, then
    the standard user <code>Role.</code><xref
    linkend="org.osgi.service.useradmin.Role.USER_ANYONE"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> can be obtained from the User Admin service and
    added to the <code>Group</code> object. This <code>Role</code> object is
    implied by anybody and therefore does not affect the required
    members.</para>

    <section>
      <title>The Authorization Object</title>

      <para>The complexity of authorization is hidden in an
      <code>Authorization</code> class. Normally, the authenticator should
      retrieve an <code>Authorization</code> object from the User Admin
      service by passing the authenticated <code>User</code> object as an
      argument. This <code>Authorization</code> object is then passed to the
      bundle that performs the action. This bundle checks the authorization
      with the <code>Authorization.hasRole(String)</code> method. The
      performing bundle must pass the name of the action as an argument. The
      <code>Authorization</code> object checks whether the authenticated user
      implies the <code>Role</code> object, specifically a <code>Group</code>
      object, with the given name. This is shown in the following
      example.</para>

      <programlisting>public void activateAlarm(Authorization auth) {
    if ( auth.hasRole( "AlarmSystemActivation" ) ) {
        // activate the alarm
        ...
    }
    else throw new SecurityException( 
        "Not authorized to activate alarm" );
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Authorization Example</title>

      <para>This section demonstrates a possible use of the User Admin
      service. The service has a flexible model and many other schemes are
      possible.</para>

      <para>Assume an Operator installs an OSGi framework. Bundles in this
      environment have defined the following action groups:</para>

      <programlisting>AlarmSystemControl
InternetAccess
TemperatureControl
PhotoAlbumEdit
PhotoAlbumView
PortForwarding</programlisting>

      <para>Installing and uninstalling bundles could potentially extend this
      set. Therefore, the Operator also defines a number of groups that can be
      used to contain the different types of system users.</para>

      <programlisting>Administrators
Buddies
Children
Adults
Residents</programlisting>

      <para>In a particular instance, the Operator installs it in a household
      with the following residents and buddies:</para>

      <programlisting>Residents:      Elmer, Fudd, Marvin, Pepe
Buddies:        Daffy, Foghorn</programlisting>

      <para>First, the residents and buddies are assigned to the system user
      groups. Second, the user groups need to be assigned to the action
      groups.</para>

      <para>The following tables show how the groups could be assigned.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Example Groups with Basic and Required Members</title>

        <tgroup cols="7">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1.5*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="5" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="6" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="7" colwidth="1*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Groups</entry>

              <entry>Elmer</entry>

              <entry>Fudd</entry>

              <entry>Marvin</entry>

              <entry>Pepe</entry>

              <entry>Daffy</entry>

              <entry>Foghorn</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>Residents</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Buddies</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Children</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Adults</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>Administrators</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <table>
        <title>Example Action Groups with their Basic and Required
        Members</title>

        <tgroup cols="6">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="5" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec colnum="6" colwidth="1*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Groups</entry>

              <entry>Residents</entry>

              <entry>Buddies</entry>

              <entry>Children</entry>

              <entry>Adults</entry>

              <entry>Admin</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><code>AlarmSystemControl</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Required</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>InternetAccess</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Required</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>TemperatureControl</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Required</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>PhotoAlbumEdit</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>PhotoAlbumView</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><code>PortForwarding</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Basic</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>-</code></entry>

              <entry><code>Required</code></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Repository Maintenance</title>

    <para>The <code>UserAdmin</code> interface is a straightforward API to
    maintain a repository of <code>User</code> and <code>Group</code> objects.
    It contains methods to create new <code>Group</code> and <code>User</code>
    objects with the <code>createRole(String,int)</code> method. The method is
    prepared so that the same signature can be used to create new types of
    roles in the future. The interface also contains a method to remove a
    <code>Role</code> object.</para>

    <para>The existing configuration can be obtained with methods that list
    all <code>Role</code> objects using a filter argument. This filter, which
    has the same syntax as the Framework filter, must only return the
    <code>Role</code> objects for which the filter matches the
    properties.</para>

    <para>Several utility methods simplify getting <code>User</code> objects
    depending on their properties.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="i1529238">
    <title>User Admin Events</title>

    <para>Changes in the User Admin service can be determined in real time.
    Each User Admin service implementation must send a
    <code>UserAdminEvent</code> object to any service in the Framework service
    registry that is registered under the <code>UserAdminListener</code>
    interface. This event must be send asynchronously from the cause of the
    event. The way events must be delivered is the same as described in
    <emphasis>Delivering Events</emphasis> of <xref
    linkend="intro.core.release" xrefstyle="template:%t"/>.</para>

    <para>This procedure is demonstrated in the following code sample.</para>

    <programlisting>class Listener implements UserAdminListener{
    public void roleChanged( UserAdminEvent event ) {
        ...
    }
}
public class MyActivator 
    implements BundleActivator {
    public void start( BundleContext context ) {
        context.registerService( 
            UserAdminListener.class.getName(),
            new Listener(), null );
    }
    public void stop( BundleContext context ) {}
}</programlisting>

    <para>It is not necessary to unregister the listener object when the
    bundle is stopped because the Framework automatically unregisters it. Once
    registered, the <code>UserAdminListener</code> object must be notified of
    all changes to the role repository.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Event Admin and User Admin Change Events</title>

      <para>User Admin events must be delivered asynchronously to the Event
      Admin service by the implementation, if present. The topic of a User
      Admin Event is:</para>

      <programlisting>org/osgi/service/useradmin/UserAdmin/&lt;eventtype&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The following event types are supported:</para>

      <programlisting>ROLE_CREATED
ROLE_CHANGED
ROLE_REMOVED</programlisting>

      <para>All User Admin Events must have the following properties:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>event</code> - (<code>UserAdminEvent</code>) The event
          that was broadcast by the User Admin service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>role</code> - (<code>Role</code>) The <code>Role</code>
          object that was created, modified or removed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>role.name</code> - (<code>String</code>) The name of the
          role.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>role.type</code> - (<code>Integer</code>) One of
          <code>ROLE, USER</code> or <code>GROUP</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service</code> - (<code>ServiceReference</code>) The
          Service Reference of the User Admin service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.id</code> - (<code>Long</code>) The User Admin
          service's ID.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.objectClass</code> - (<code>String[]</code>) The
          User Admin service's object class (which must include
          <code>org.osgi.service.useradmin.UserAdmin</code>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>service.pid</code> - (<code>String)</code> The User
          Admin service's persistent identity</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>The User Admin service is related to the security model of the OSGi
    framework, but is complementary to the <xref linkend="i1307817"/>. The
    final permission of most code should be the intersection of the Java 2
    Permissions, which are based on the code that is executing, and the User
    Admin service authorization, which is based on the user for whom the code
    runs.</para>

    <section>
      <title>User Admin Permission</title>

      <para>The User Admin service defines the
      <code>UserAdminPermission</code> class that can be used to restrict
      bundles in accessing credentials. This permission class has the
      following actions:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>changeProperty</code> - This permission is required to
          modify properties. The name of the permission is the prefix of the
          property name.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>changeCredential</code> - This action permits changing
          credentials. The name of the permission is the prefix of the name of
          the credential.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>getCredential</code> - This action permits getting
          credentials. The name of the permission is the prefix of the
          credential.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the name of the permission is <code>"admin"</code>, it allows
      the owner to administer the repository. No action is associated with the
      permission in that case.</para>

      <para>Otherwise, the permission name is used to match the property name.
      This name may end with a <code>".*"</code> string to indicate a
      wildcard. For example, <code>com.acme.*</code> matches
      <code>com.acme.fudd.elmer</code> and <code>com.acme.bugs</code>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Relation to JAAS</title>

    <para>At a glance, the Java Authorization and Authentication Service
    (JAAS) seems to be a very suitable model for user administration. The OSGi
    organization, however, decided to develop an independent User Admin
    service because JAAS was not deemed applicable. The reasons for this
    include dependency on Java SE version 1.3 ("JDK 1.3") and existing
    mechanisms in the previous OSGi Service Gateway 1.0 specification.</para>

    <section>
      <title>JDK 1.3 Dependencies</title>

      <para>The authorization component of JAAS relies on the
      <code>java.security.DomainCombiner</code> interface, which provides a
      means to dynamically update the <code>ProtectionDomain</code> objects
      affiliated with an <code>AccessControlContext</code> object.</para>

      <para>This interface was added in JDK 1.3. In the context of JAAS, the
      <code>SubjectDomainCombiner</code> object, which implements the
      <code>DomainCombiner</code> interface, is used to update
      <code>ProtectionDomain</code> objects. The permissions of
      <code>ProtectionDomain</code> objects depend on where code came from and
      who signed it, with permissions based on who is running the code.</para>

      <para>Leveraging JAAS would have resulted in user-based access control
      on the OSGi framework being available only with JDK 1.3, which was not
      deemed acceptable.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Existing OSGi Mechanism</title>

      <para>JAAS provides a plugable authentication architecture, which
      enables applications and their underlying authentication services to
      remain independent from each other.</para>

      <para>The Http Service already provides a similar feature by allowing
      servlet and resource registrations to be supported by an
      <code>HttpContext</code> object, which uses a callback mechanism to
      perform any required authentication checks before granting access to the
      servlet or resource. This way, the registering bundle has complete
      control on a per-servlet and per-resource basis over which
      authentication protocol to use, how the credentials presented by the
      remote requester are to be validated, and who should be granted access
      to the servlet or resource.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Future Road Map</title>

      <para>In the future, the main barrier of 1.3 compatibility will be
      removed. JAAS could then be implemented in an OSGi environment. At that
      time, the User Admin service will still be needed and will provide
      complementary services in the following ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The authorization component relies on group membership
          information to be stored and managed outside JAAS. JAAS does not
          manage persistent information, so the User Admin service can be a
          provider of group information when principals are assigned to a
          <code>Subject</code> object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The authorization component allows for credentials to be
          collected and verified, but a repository is needed to actually
          validate the credentials.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In the future, the User Admin service can act as the back-end
      database to JAAS. The only aspect JAAS will remove from the User Admin
      service is the need for the <code>Authorization</code> interface.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.useradmin.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1307817"><title>The Java Security Architecture for
      JDK 1.2</title>Version 1.0, Sun Microsystems, October 1998</bibliomixed>

      <bibliomixed xml:id="i1307810"><title>Java Authentication and
      Authorization Service</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/tech/index-jsp-136007.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>
</chapter>
