<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright (c) Contributors to the Eclipse Foundation
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
   
    SPDX-License-Identifier: Apache-2.0 
 -->
<chapter label="125"
         revision="$Id$"
         version="5.0" xml:id="service.jdbc"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Data Service Specification for JDBC™ Technology</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.jdbc-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The Java Database Connectivity (JDBC) standard provides an API for
    applications to interact with relational database systems from different
    vendors. To abstract over concrete database systems and vendor specific
    characteristics, the JDBC specification provides various classes and
    Service Provider Interfaces (SPI) that can be used for database
    interaction. Implementations are database specific and provided by the
    corresponding driver. This specification defines how OSGi-aware JDBC
    drivers can provide access to their implementations. Applications can rely
    on this mechanism to transparently access drivers and to stay independent
    from driver specific classes. Additionally, this mechanism helps to use
    common OSGi practices and to avoid class loading problems.</para>

    <para>This specification uses a number of packages that are defined in
    Java SE 1.4 or later.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Registration</emphasis> - Provide a mechanism for
          JDBC driver announcements.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Lookup</emphasis> - Inspect available database
          drivers and provide means for driver access.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Services</emphasis> - Uses a service model for
          getting the driver objects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Compatible</emphasis> - Minimize the amount of work
          needed to support this specification for existing drivers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Relational Database Management Systems</emphasis> -
          (RDBMS) An external database system.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Database Driver</emphasis> - JDBC-compliant database
          driver that is delivered in a bundle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Data Source Factory</emphasis> - Provides one of the
          different Data Sources that gives access to a database
          driver.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Application</emphasis> - The application that wants
          to access a relational database system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>JDBC Class/Service Overview</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="2.156in"
                       contentwidth="7.000in" fileref="jdbc-classes.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Dependencies</title>

      <para>The classes and interfaces used in this specification come from
      the following packages:</para>

      <programlisting>javax.sql
java.sql</programlisting>

      <para>These packages have no associated version. It is assumed they come
      from the runtime environment. This specification is based on Java SE 1.4
      or later.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>

      <para>A JDBC <emphasis>Database Driver</emphasis> is the software that
      maps the JDBC specification to a specific implementation of a relational
      database. For OSGi, JDBC drivers are delivered as driver bundles. A
      driver bundle registers a Data Source Factory service when it is
      <code>ACTIVE</code>. Service properties are used to specify the database
      driver name, version, etc. The Data Source Factory service provides
      methods to create <code>DataSource</code>,
      <code>ConnectionPoolDataSource</code>, <code>XADataSource</code>, or
      <code>Driver</code> objects. These objects are then used by an
      application to interact with the relational database system in the
      standard way.</para>

      <para>The application can query the service registry for available Data
      Source Factory services. It can select particular drivers by filtering
      on the service properties. This service based model is easy to use with
      dependency injection frameworks like Blueprint or Declarative
      Services.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Database Driver</title>

    <para>A Database Driver provides the connection between an
    <emphasis>Application</emphasis> and a particular database. A single OSGi
    Framework can contain several Database Drivers simultaneously. To make
    itself available to Applications, a Database Driver must register a Data
    Source Factory service. Applications must be able to find the appropriate
    Database Driver. The Database Driver must therefore register the Data
    Source Factory service with the following service properties:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.OSGI_JDBC_DRIVER_CLASS"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>String</code>) The required name of
        the driver implementation class. This property is the primary key to
        find a driver's Data Source Factory. It is not required that there is
        an actual class with this name.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.OSGI_JDBC_DRIVER_NAME"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>String</code>) The optional driver
        name. This property is informational.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.OSGI_JDBC_DRIVER_VERSION"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - (<code>String</code>) The driver version.
        The version is not required to be an OSGi version, it should be
        treated as an opaque string. This version is likely not related to the
        package of the implementation class or its bundle.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The previous properties are vendor-specific and are meant to further
    describe the Database Driver to the Application.</para>

    <para>Each Data Source Factory service must relate to a single Database
    Driver. The Database Driver implementation bundle does not necessarily
    need to be the registrar of the Data Source Factory service. Any bundle
    can provide the Data Source Factory service and delegate to the
    appropriate driver specific implementation classes. However, as JDBC
    driver implementations evolve to include built-in support for OSGi they
    can provide the Data Source Factory service themselves. This implies that
    the same driver can be registered multiple times.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Life Cycle</title>

      <para>A Data Source Factory service should be registered while its
      Driver Bundle is in the <code>ACTIVE</code> state or when it has a
      <code>lazy</code> activation policy and is in the <code>STARTING</code>
      state.</para>

      <para>What happens to the objects created by the Data Source Factory
      service, and the objects they created, is undefined in this
      specification. Database Drivers are not mandated to track the proper
      life cycle of these objects.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Package Dependencies</title>

      <para>A Database Driver must import the <code>javax.sql</code> package.
      The <code>java.sql</code> package that contains the <code>Driver</code>
      and <code>SQLException</code> interface is automatically visible because
      it starts with <code>java.</code>. Both packages are contained in the
      JRE since Java SE 1.4. These packages are not normally versioned with
      OSGi version numbers. Bundles using the Data Source Factory must
      therefore ensure they get the proper imports, which is usually from the
      JRE. Due to the lack of specified metadata, the deployer is responsible
      for ensuring this.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Applications</title>

    <section>
      <title>Selecting the Data Source Factory Service</title>

      <para>Applications can query the OSGi service registry for available
      Database Drivers by getting a list of Data Source Factory services.
      Normally, the application needs access to specific drivers that match
      their needed relational database type. The service properties can be
      used to find the desired Database Driver. This model is well supported
      by dependency injection frameworks like Blueprint or Declarative
      Services. However, it can of course also be used with the basic service
      methods. The following code shows how a Service Tracker can be used to
      get a Database Driver called ACME DB.</para>

      <programlisting>Filter filter = context.createFilter(
    "(&amp;(objectClass="  + 
        DataSourceFactory.class.getName() + 
    ")(" + 
        DataSourceFactory.OSGI_JDBC_DRIVER_CLASS + "=com.acme.db.Driver))");

ServiceTracker tracker = new ServiceTracker(context, filter, null);
tracker.open();

DataSourceFactory dsf = (DataSourceFactory) tracker.getService();</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using Database Drivers</title>

      <para>The Data Source Factory service can be used to obtain instances
      for the following JDBC related types:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.sql.DataSource</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.sql.ConnectionPoolDataSource</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>javax.sql.XADataSource</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>java.sql.Driver</code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Which type of Connection provider that is actually required
      depends on the Application and the use case. For each type, the Data
      Source Factory service provides a method that returns the corresponding
      instance. Each method takes a <code>Properties</code> object as a
      parameter to pass a configuration to the Database Driver implementation.
      The configuration is driver-specific and can be used to specify the URL
      for the database and user credentials. Common property names for these
      configuration properties are also defined in the
      <code>DataSourceFactory</code> interface.</para>

      <para>A Data Source Factory service is not required to implement all of
      the factory methods. To indicate which factory method is implemented,
      the Data Source Factory service must be registered with the service
      property <code>osgi.jdbc.datasourcefactory.capability</code> having one
      or more of the following values.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>driver</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>datasource</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>connectionpooldatasource</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>xadatasource</code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If an implementation does not support a particular type then it
      must throw a SQL Exception.</para>

      <para>The following code shows how a <code>DataSource</code> object
      could be created.</para>

      <programlisting>Properties props = new Properties(); 
props.put(DataSourceFactory.JDBC_URL,      "jdbc:acme:ACMEDB"); 
props.put(DataSourceFactory.JDBC_USER,     "foo"); 
props.put(DataSourceFactory.JDBC_PASSWORD, "secret"); 
DataSource dataSource = dsf.createDataSource(props);</programlisting>

      <para>The <code>DataSourceFactory</code> interface has several static
      fields that represent common property keys for the
      <code>Properties</code> instance. General properties are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_DATABASE_NAME"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_DATASOURCE_NAME"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_DESCRIPTION"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_NETWORK_PROTOCOL"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_PASSWORD"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_PORT_NUMBER"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_ROLE_NAME"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_SERVER_NAME"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_USER"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_URL"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following additional property keys are provided for
      applications that want to create a <code>ConnectionPoolDataSource</code>
      object or a <code>XAPoolDataSource</code> object:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_INITIAL_POOL_SIZE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_MAX_IDLE_TIME"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_MAX_POOL_SIZE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_MAX_STATEMENTS"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_MIN_POOL_SIZE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref
          linkend="org.osgi.service.jdbc.DataSourceFactory.JDBC_PROPERTY_CYCLE"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Which property keys and values are supported depends on the driver
      implementation. Drivers can support additional custom configuration
      properties.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using JDBC in OSGi and Containers</title>

      <para>The JDBC service provides JDBC driver services, not
      <emphasis>container</emphasis> services. A typical client would only use
      the <code>DataSourceFactory.createDataSource()</code> method to procure
      a regular Data Source from which they can obtain (usually non-pooled)
      connections.</para>

      <para>Containers generally offer connection pools and support XA
      transactions. The container manages the pools and does this by using
      Pooled Connection or XA Connection objects from a driver-implemented
      respective Connection Pool Data Source or XA Data Source. To support
      containers, frameworks, or any client that wants to manage a pool, these
      Data Source types are included in the Data Source Factory service.
      Drivers are permitted to implement their own Data Source using an
      underlying connection pooling scheme. This is driver-dependent and not
      related to the OSGi specifications.</para>

      <para>The usual set of JDBC properties are defined in the services for
      use with the Data Source types. They are the same as what is defined for
      JDBC and the caller should know which properties make sense when passed
      to a given Data Source type. The same result should occur in OSGi as
      occurs outside of OSGi. If the driver does not support a given property
      with a given Data Source type then it can ignore it or it can throw an
      Exception.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>This specification depends on the JDBC specification for
    security.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.jdbc.xml"/>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliolist>
      <bibliomixed><title>Java SE</title><biblioid class="uri"><link
      xlink:href="https://www.oracle.com/java/technologies/java-se-glance.html"/></biblioid></bibliomixed>
    </bibliolist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Added the service property
        <code>osgi.jdbc.datasourcefactory.capability</code> to
        DataSourceFactory.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
