<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright (c) Contributors to the Eclipse Foundation
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
   
    SPDX-License-Identifier: Apache-2.0 
 -->
<chapter label="160"
         version="5.0" xml:id="service.feature.launcher"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Feature Launcher Service Specification</title>

  <info>
    <releaseinfo><xref endterm="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher-version"
    linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher"/></releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The <xref linkend="service.feature"/> defines a model to 
      design and declare Complex Applications and reusable Sub-Components that are
      composed of multiple bundles, configurations and other metadata. These
      models are, however, only descriptive and have no standard mechanism
      for installing them into an OSGi framework.</para>
      
    <para>This specification focuses on turning these Features into a running system,
      by introducing the Feature Launcher and Feature Runtime. The Feature Launcher 
      takes a Feature definition, obtains a framework instance for it and then starts 
      the Feature in that environment. The Feature Runtime extends this capability to
      a running system, enabling one or more Features to be installed, updated, and 
      later removed from a running OSGi framework.</para>
      
    <para>The Launcher and Runtime also interact with the Configuration Admin Service, 
      that is, they provide configuration to the system if it is present in the 
      Feature being launched or installed.</para>
      
    <section>
      <title>Essentials</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dynamic</emphasis> - The Feature Runtime dynamically
          adds, updates and removes Features in a running system.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Parameterizable</emphasis> - Feature installation may
          be customised using local parameters if the Feature supports it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Zero code</emphasis> - The Feature Launcher can launch a framework
          containing an installed Feature in an implementation independent way without a 
          user writing any code .</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entities</title>

      <para>The following entities are used in this specification:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Feature</emphasis> - A Feature as defined by the
          <xref linkend="service.feature"/></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Artifact Repository</emphasis> - A means of 
          accessing the installable bytes for bundles in a Feature</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Feature Launcher</emphasis> - A Feature Launcher
          obtains an OSGi Framework instance and installs a Feature into it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Framework</emphasis> - A running implementation of
          the OSGi core specification.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Launch Properties</emphasis> - Framework launching
          properties defined in a Feature.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Feature Parameters</emphasis> - Key value pairs that
          can be used to customise the installation of a Feature.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Configuration</emphasis> - A configuration 
          for the Configuration Admin service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Feature Runtime</emphasis> - A Feature Runtime is
          an OSGi service capable of installing Features into the running OSGi 
          framework, removing installed Features from the OSGi framework, and 
          updating an installed Feature with a new Feature definition.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Installed Feature</emphasis> - A representation of
          a Feature installed by the Feature Runtime.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Installed Configuration</emphasis> - A representation of
          a Configuration installed by the Feature Runtime.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure pgwide="1">
        <title>Features Entity overview</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="5.100in"
                       contentwidth="6.000in" fileref="feature.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-ar">
    <title>Features and Artifact Repositories</title>
    
    <para>OSGi Features exist either as JSON documents, or as runtime objects
    created by the Feature Service API. The primary purpose of a Feature is 
    to define a list of bundles and configurations that should be installed,
    however the Feature provides no information about the location of the
    bundle artifacts. A key challenge with installing a Feature is therefore
    finding the appropriate artifacts to install.
    </para>
    
    <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepository"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> interface is designed to be implemented by users
      of the Feature Launcher Service to provide a way for the Feature Launcher
      Service to find an installable <code>InputStream</code> of bytes for a
      given bundle artifact using the <xref 
      linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepository.getArtifact-ID-"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. Artifact Repository implementations are free 
      to use any mechanism for locating the bundle artifact data. If no artifact 
      can be found for the supplied <code>ID</code> then the implementation of 
      the Artifact Repository should return <code>null</code>. If the Artifact 
      Repository throws an exception then this must be logged by the Feature 
      Launcher Service and then treated in the same manner as a <code>null</code>
      return value.</para>
      
    <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-arf">
      <title>The Artifact Repository Factory</title>
      
      <para>In order to support the <emphasis>Zero Code</emphasis> objective
      of this specification, and to simplify usage for most users, the
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> provides a factory for commonly used repository
      types.</para>
      
      <section>
        <title>Obtaining an Artifact Repository Factory</title>
      
        <para>The Artifact Repository Factory is useful both for the Feature Launcher
        and the Feature Runtime, and as such it must be easy to access both inside
        and outside an OSGi framework. The Feature Launcher Service implementation 
        must provide an implementation of the Artifact Repository Factory interface. 
        A user of the Artifact Repository Factory service may use the following ways 
        to find an instance.
        </para>
      
        <para>When outside OSGi:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Using the Java ServiceLoader API to find instances of 
            <code>org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory</code></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>From configuration, and then using <code>Class.forName</code>,
            <code>getConstructor()</code> and <code>newInstance()</code></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>By hard coding the implementation and using the <code>new</code>
            operator.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>When inside an OSGi framework:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Using the OSGi service registry to find instances of 
            <code>org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory</code></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Using the Java ServiceLoader API and the OSGi Service Loader
            Mediator to find instances of 
            <code>org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory</code></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>By hard coding the implementation type and using the <code>new</code>
            operator.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Local Repositories</title>
        
        <para>A Local Repository is one that exists on a locally accessible file
        system. Note that this does not require that the file system is local,
        and technologies such as NFS or other network file systems would still
        be considered as Local Repositories. The key aspects of a Local
        Repository are that:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The root of the repository can be accessed and resolved
            as a <code>java.nio.file.Path</code> or <code>file:</code> URI.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The repository uses the Maven2 Repository Layout</para>
            <remark>Add bibliography link to https://maven.apache.org/repository/layout.html#maven2-repository-layout</remark>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>An Artifact Repository representing a Local Repository can be 
        created using the <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory.createRepository-Path-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, passing in the path to the root of the repository.
        A <code>NullPointerException</code> must be thrown if the path is <code>null</code>
        and an <code>IllegalArgumentException</code> must be thrown if the path does not
        exist, or represents a file which is not a directory.</para>
        
        <para>An Artifact Repository representing a Local Repository can also
        be created using the <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory.createRepository-URI-Map-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, passing a URI using the <code>file</code> scheme
        which points to the root of the repository. A <code>NullPointerException</code> 
        must be thrown if the URI is <code>null</code> and an <code>IllegalArgumentException</code> 
        must be thrown if the path does not exist, or represents a file which is not a 
        directory.</para>
        
        <para>Once created this Artifact Repository will search the supplied repository
        for any requested artifact data. Implementations are free to optimise checks using
        repository metadata.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Remote Repositories</title>
        
        <para>A Remote Repository is one that exists with an accessible
        <code>http</code> or <code>https</code> endpoint for retrieving artifact data.
        Note that this does not require that the repository is on a remote machine,
        only that the means of accessing data is via <code>HTTP</code> requests.
        The key aspects of a Remote Repository are that:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The root of the repository can be accessed and resolved
            as a <code>http</code> or <code>https</code> <code>URI</code></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The repository uses the Maven2 Repository Layout</para>
            <remark>Add bibliography link to https://maven.apache.org/repository/layout.html#maven2-repository-layout</remark>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>An Artifact Repository representing a Remote Repository can be 
        created using the <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory.createRepository-URI-Map-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, passing in the uri to the root of the repository.
        A <code>NullPointerException</code> must be thrown if the uri is <code>null</code>
        and an <code>IllegalArgumentException</code> must be thrown if the uri does not
        use the <code>http</code> or <code>https</code> scheme.</para>
        
        <para>In addition to the repository <code>URI</code> the user may pass
        configuration properties in a <code>Map</code>. Implementations may support custom
        configuration properties, but those properties should use Reverse Domain Name keys.
        Keys not using the reverse DNS naming scheme are reserved for OSGi use. Implementations
        must ignore any configuration property keys that they do not recognise. All 
        implementations must support the following properties:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.REMOTE_ARTIFACT_REPOSITORY_NAME"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The name for this repository</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.REMOTE_ARTIFACT_REPOSITORY_USER"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The user name to use for authenticating with this repository</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.REMOTE_ARTIFACT_REPOSITORY_PASSWORD"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The password to use for authenticating with this repository</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.REMOTE_ARTIFACT_REPOSITORY_BEARER_TOKEN"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A bearer token to use when authenticating with this repository</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.REMOTE_ARTIFACT_REPOSITORY_SNAPSHOTS_ENABLED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A <code>Boolean</code> indicating that SNAPSHOT versions are 
              supported. Defaults to <code>true</code></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.REMOTE_ARTIFACT_REPOSITORY_RELEASES_ENABLED"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A <code>Boolean</code> indicating that release versions are 
              supported. Defaults to <code>true</code></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.REMOTE_ARTIFACT_REPOSITORY_TRUST_STORE"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A trust store to use when validating a server certificate. May be a file
              system path or a <code>data</code> URI.</para>
              <remark>Add bibliography link to https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_URI_scheme</remark>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.REMOTE_ARTIFACT_REPOSITORY_TRUST_STORE_FORMAT"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The format of the trust store to use when validating a server certificate.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.REMOTE_ARTIFACT_REPOSITORY_TRUST_STORE_PASSWORD"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The password to use when validating the trust store integrity.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>Once created this Artifact Repository will search the supplied repository
        for any requested artifact data. Implementations are free to optimise checks using
        repository metadata.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Common themes</title>
    
    <para>This specification includes support for bootstrapping an OSGi
    runtime, for ongoing management of an OSGi runtime, and for merging features. 
    There are many concepts that apply across more than one of these scenarios,
    and so they are described here.</para>
    
    <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-variable.overrides">
      <title>Overriding Feature variables</title>
        
      <para>Some Feature definitions include variables which can be used to customise
      their deployment. These variables are intended to be set at the point where
      a Feature is installed, and may contain default values. To enable these 
      variables to be overridden there are overloaded versions of methods which 
      permit a <code>Map</code> of variables to be provided. The keys in this 
      map must be strings and the values must be one of the types permitted 
      by the <xref linkend="service.feature"/></para>
        
      <para>If a Feature declares a variable with no default value then this variable
      <emphasis>must</emphasis> be provided. If no value is provided then the method
      must fail to launch by throwing a <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-start.levels">
      <title>Setting the bundle start levels</title>
        
      <para>An OSGi framework contains a number of bundles which collaborate to produce
      a functioning application. There are times when some bundles require the system
      to have reached a certain state before they can be started. To address this use
      case the OSGi framework has the concept of <emphasis>start levels</emphasis>.
        <remark>Add a link to the core specification</remark>
      </para>
        
      <para>Setting the initial start level for the OSGi framework when bootstrapping
      can easily be achieved using the framework launch property 
      <code>org.osgi.framework.startlevel.beginning</code> as defined by the
      OSGi core specification.</para>
        
      <para>Controlling the start levels assigned to the bundles in a feature is
      managed through the use of Feature Bundle metadata. Specifically the Feature
      Launcher will look for a Feature Bundle metadata property named <xref 
       linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.BUNDLE_START_LEVEL_METADATA"
       xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> which is of type integer and has a value between
      <code>1</code> and <code>2147483647</code> inclusive. If the property does 
      not exist then the default start level will be used. If the property does 
      exist and is not a suitable integer then launching must fail with a <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
      </para>
        
      <para>Setting the default start level for the bundles, and the minimum start
      level required for an installed Feature is accomplished by using a Feature Extension named <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.BUNDLE_START_LEVELS"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> with <code>Type</code> <code>JSON</code>. The JSON
      contained in this extension is used to configure the default start level for
      the bundles, and the target start level for the framework.
      The schema of this JSON is as follows: <remark>Add Schema in build</remark></para>
        
      <programlisting>
{
  "$schema": "https://json-schema.org/draft/2020-12/schema",
  "$id": "http://www.osgi.org/jsonschema/featurelauncher/bundle-start-levels/v1.0.0",
  "title": "bundle-start-levels",
  "description": "The definition of the bundle-start-levels feature extension",
   "type": "object",
   "properties": {
      "version": {
        "description": "The version of the Feature Launcher extension",
        "const": "1.0.0"
      },
      "defaultStartLevel": {
         "description": "The default start level for bundles in the feature",
         "type": "integer",
         "minimum": 1,
         "maximum": 2147483647
      },
      "minimumStartLevel": {
         "description": "The minimum required start level for the framework after feature installation",
         "type": "integer",
         "minimum": 1,
         "maximum": 2147483647
      }
   },
   "required": [ "version", "defaultStartLevel", "minimumStartLevel" ]
}
        </programlisting>
        
        
      <para>Setting the default start level for bundles installed by the framework is
      achieved using the <code>defaultStartLevel</code> property of the <code>JSON</code>
      extension. This must be an integer greater than zero and less than 
      <code>Integer.MAX_INT</code>, or the special marker value <code>null</code>. A
      <code>null</code> value is used to indicate that the default start level for newly
      installed bundles is the current framework start level, or <code>1</code> if the 
      current framework start level is <code>0</code>. If the value is not valid then a <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      must be thrown when attempting to use the feature.</para>
        
      <para>The minimum final start level for the OSGi framework required by the feature
      can be set using the <code>minimumStartLevel</code> property. of the <code>JSON</code>
      extension. This must be an integer greater than zero and less than <code>Integer.MAX_INT</code>.
      If the value is not valid then a <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      must be thrown when attempting to use the feature. This property sets the minimum
      start level that the OSGi framework must use to complete the installation of a
      Feature.</para>
      
      <para>Finally the <code>version</code> property defines the version of the extension
      schema being used. This can be used by the implementation to determine whether the 
      Feature is targeting a newer version of the specification. If the version is not
      understood by the implementation then a <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      must be thrown when attempting to use the feature.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-feature.decoration">
      <title>Feature Decoration</title>
      
      <para>Feature Decoration is a process by which features can be pre-processed before they
      are installed or updated. This gives users an opportunity to modify the feature, accept
      it as is, or block the operation from proceeding. There are two types of decorator:</para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Feature Decorators</emphasis> - called for all operations. Can re-write the bundles, configurations,
          variables and extensions present in a feature.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Feature Extension Handlers</emphasis> - called operations where the
          feature defines the named extension. Can re-write the bundles, configurations and
          variables present in a feature, but not the extensions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>Both types of decorator may pass through the feature unchanged by returning the feature
      object passed into them. This will cause the operation to continue as normal. Decorators may 
      also block an operation from proceeding by throwing an <xref
       linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.AbandonOperationException"
       xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. This will cause the operation to be immediately halted, and
       an exception thrown to the caller who requested the operation.</para>
      
      <section>
        <title>Building decorated features</title>

        <para>Feature objects are expected to be immutable, and therefore a decorator cannot, and
        should not, change the feature object that is passed to them. Instead the decorator must
        create a new feature object which includes the decorated content.</para>
        
        <para>To enable this both types of decorator are passed two builders, the first of 
        which implements <xref 
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.BaseFeatureDecorationBuilder"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and the second of which implements <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.DecoratorBuilderFactory"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para> 
         
         <para>The former builder is similar to a <xref 
         linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.FeatureBuilder" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
         but with three important differences:</para>
         
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>The builder is pre-populated with the information from the existing feature, such that
             immediately calling <xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.BaseFeatureDecorationBuilder.build--"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> would create a feature with identical content to the original.</para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>Except where explicitly stated the builder configuration methods
             <emphasis>replace</emphasis> content rather than adding to it</para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>Only a limited subset of the feature content can be changed.</para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         
         <para>The latter builder is similar to a <xref 
         linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.BuilderFactory" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> but it
         cannot create <xref 
         linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.FeatureBuilder" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instances.</para>
         
         <para>By using these two builders a decorated feature can be configured and created.
         This decorated feature can then be returned from the decorator. Note that the
         <emphasis>only</emphasis> valid way to create a decorated feature is by using the builder.
         Any attempt to return a feature object which is not either:</para>
         
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>The original feature object.</para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>The object returned by <xref 
              linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.BaseFeatureDecorationBuilder.build--"
              xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         
         <para>is an error and will result in the operation being abandoned.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Using Decorators</title>
        
        <para>Decorators may be included using one of the relevant builder methods for
        a launch or runtime operation:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher.LaunchBuilder.withDecorator-FeatureDecorator-"
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher.LaunchBuilder.withExtensionHandler-String-FeatureExtensionHandler-"
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.OperationBuilder.withDecorator-FeatureDecorator-"
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref 
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.OperationBuilder.withExtensionHandler-String-FeatureExtensionHandler-"
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
         
        <para>When registering a <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.FeatureExtensionHandler"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> the name of the extension to be handled must be passed, and cannot be <code>null</code>.
        This defines the name of the extension that the Feature Extension Handler will be used to process.</para>

        <para>If multiple <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.FeatureDecorator" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        instances are registered then they will be called in the order that they were added.</para>

        <para>If multiple <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.FeatureExtensionHandler" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        instances are registered for the same extension name then the earlier instances will be discarded. It is not possible
        to register more than one Feature Extension Handler for a single extension.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>The Feature Launcher</title>
    
    <para>The <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher"
      xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> is the main entry point for creating a running OSGi
      framework containing the bundles and configurations defined in a Feature.
      As such the Feature Launcher is primarily designed for use outside of an
      OSGi framework.</para>
      
    <para>To support usage in a non-OSGi environment implementations of the
    Feature Launcher Service must register the following implementation classes 
    with the Java ServiceLoader API, and any necessary module metadata.</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher</code></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory</code></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>    
      
    <section>
      <title>Obtaining and configuring a Feature Launcher</title>
      
      <para>A Feature Launcher Service implementation must provide an implementation
      of the Feature Launcher interface. A user of the Feature Launcher service may
      use the following ways to find this class and create an instance:
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Using the Java ServiceLoader API to find instances of 
          <code>org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher</code></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>From configuration, and then using <code>Class.forName</code>,
          <code>getConstructor()</code> and <code>newInstance()</code></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>By hard coding the implementation type and using the <code>new</code>
          operator.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>Once instantiated the Feature Launcher may be supplied with a
      Feature, either as a <code>Reader</code> providing access to the JSON text of 
      a Feature document or a parsed <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.Feature"
       xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> to create  a <xref
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher.LaunchBuilder"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The Launch Builder can be configured in a fluent
        manner using the <xref 
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher.LaunchBuilder.withConfiguration-Map-"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher.LaunchBuilder.withVariables-Map-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher.LaunchBuilder.withFrameworkProperties-Map-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher.LaunchBuilder.withRepository-ArtifactRepository-"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> methods. Configuration properties for the Feature
        Launcher are implementation specific, and any unrecognised property names
        should be ignored. Artifact Repository instances may be created by the user
        using as described in <xref linkend="service.featurelauncher-arf" 
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, or using custom implementations.</para>
        
        <section>
          <title>Thread Safety</title>
          
          <para>Instances of the Feature Launcher and Launch Builder are not required to 
            be Thread Safe, and should not be shared between threads. Changing the 
            configuration of a Launch Builder instance only affects that instance, and 
            not any other instances that exist.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Using a Feature Launcher</title>
      
      <para>Once a configured Launch Builder instance has been created the <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncher.LaunchBuilder.launchFramework--"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method can be used to launch an OSGi framework 
      containing the supplied Feature. 
      The Feature Launcher will then return a running <code>Framework</code> instance
      representing the launched OSGi framework and the Feature that it contains. If
      an error occurs creating the framework, or locating and installing any of the 
      feature bundles, then a <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> must be thrown.</para>
        
      <para>Once the caller has received their framework instance they may carry on
      with other work, or they may wait for the OSGi framework to stop using the
      <code>waitForStop()</code> method.</para>
      
      <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-framework.props">
        <title>Providing Framework Launch Properties</title>
        
        <para>Framework launch properties are key value pairs which are passed to
        the OSGi framework as it is created. They can control many behaviours,
        including operations which happen before the framework starts, meaning 
        that is not always possible to set them <emphasis>after</emphasis> startup.</para>
        
        <para>Feature definitions that require particular framework launch properties
        can define them using a Feature Extension named <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.FRAMEWORK_LAUNCHING_PROPERTIES"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The Type of this Feature Extension must be 
        <code>TEXT</code>, where each entry is in the form <code>key=value</code>
        All implementations of the Feature Launcher must support this extension,
        and use it to populate the Framework Launch Properties.</para>
        
        <para>In addition to Framework Launch properties defined inside the Feature,
        users of the Feature Launcher can add and override Framework Launch Properties
        using one of the <code>withFrameworkProperties</code> method that permits a 
        <code>Map</code> of framework properties to be provided. Any key value pairs 
        defined in this map must take precedence over those defined in the Feature. A 
        key with a <code>null</code> value must result in the removal of a key value 
        pair if it is defined in the Feature.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-select.framework">
        <title>Selecting a framework implementation</title>
        
        <para>When defining a feature it is not always possible to be framework independent.
        Sometimes specific framework APIs, or licensing restrictions, will require that a
        particular implementation is used. In this case a Feature Extension named <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.LAUNCH_FRAMEWORK"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> with <code>Type</code> <code>ARTIFACTS</code> can be used
          to list one or more artifacts representing OSGi framework implementations.
        </para>
        
        <para>The list of artifacts is treated as a preference order, with the first listed
        artifact being used if available, and so on, until a framework is found. If a
        listed artifact is not an OSGi framework implementation then the Feature Launcher 
        must log a warning and continue on to the next artifact in the list. If the
        <code>Kind</code> of the feature is <code>MANDATORY</code> and none of
        the listed artifacts are available then launching must fail with a <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
        </para>
        
        <para>The Feature Launcher implementation may identify that an artifact is an OSGi
        framework implementation in any way that it chooses, however it must recognise
        framework implementations that provide the Framework Launch API using the 
        service loader pattern.
        <remark>Link to the framework launch API</remark>
        </para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>A simple example</title>
        
        <para>The following code snippet demonstrates a simple example of using the Feature Launcher
        to start an OSGi framework containing one or more bundles.</para>
        
        <programlisting>// Load the Feature Launcher
ServiceLoader&lt;FeatureLauncher&gt; sl = ServiceLoader.load(FeatureLauncher.class);
FeatureLauncher launcher = sl.iterator().next();
		
// Set up a repository
ArtifactRepository localRepo = launcher.createRepository(Paths.get("bundles"));
		
// Launch the framework
Framework fw = launcher
        .launch(Files.newBufferedReader(Paths.get("myfeature.json")))
        .withRepository(localRepo)
        .launchFramework();

fw.waitForStop(0);

    </programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>The Feature Launching Process</title>
      
      <para>The following section defines the process through which the Feature Launcher
      must locate, initialize and populate an OSGi framework when launching a feature.
      Unless explicitly stated implementations may perform one or more parts of this
      process in a different order to that described in the specification.</para>
      
      <section>
        <title>Feature Decoration</title>
        <para>The first stage of launching is to determine the feature that
        should be launched by running the configured feature decoration handlers.</para>
        
        <para>First the Feature Launcher must execute any registered <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.FeatureDecorator"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instances in the order that they were registered.
          The feature returned by each decorator is used as input to the next.</para>
          
        <para>Once the decoration is complete the Feature Launcher must iterate through
        the Feature Extensions defined by the feature. For each Feature Extension the
        launcher must:</para>
        
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>Identify the Feature Extension Handler for the named extension.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>If no Feature Extension Handler can be found, and the extension name is
          one of:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.LAUNCH_FRAMEWORK"
                 xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.FRAMEWORK_LAUNCHING_PROPERTIES"
                 xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.BUNDLE_START_LEVELS"
                 xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>then create an empty Feature Extension Handler which may validate the <xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.FeatureExtension.Type" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> of the extension
             and must return the original feature.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para>If no Feature Extension Handler has been found or created then check the
          <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.FeatureExtension.Kind" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> of the
          extension. If it is <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.FeatureExtension.Kind.MANDATORY"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> then the launch fails with a <code>LaunchException</code></para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Otherwise call the Feature Extension Handler, and use its result as input when
          calling any subsequent Feature Extension Handlers.</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        
        <para>If any of the decorators throws an <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.AbandonOperationException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        then the launch operation must immediately fail.</para>      
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Locating a framework implementation</title>
        
        <para>Before a framework instance can be created the Feature Launcher must identify
        a suitable implementation using the following search order:</para>
        
        <orderedlist>
          
          <listitem><para>If any provider specific configuration has been given to the
          Feature Launcher implementation then this should be used to identify the framework.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>If the Feature declares an Extension <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.LAUNCH_FRAMEWORK"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> then the Feature Launcher implementation must use the
          first listed artifact that can be found in any configured Artifact Repositories,
          as described in <xref linkend="service.featurelauncher-select.framework" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
            <remark>Currently this only fails if the extension is mandatory</remark>
          </listitem>
          
          
          <listitem><para>If no framework implementation is found in the previous steps then the Feature
          Launcher implementation must search the classpath using the Thread Context Class Loader,
          or, if the Thread Context Class Loader is not set, the Class Loader which loaded the 
          caller of the Feature Launcher's <code>launch</code> method. The first
          suitable framework instance located is the instance that will be used.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>In the event that no suitable OSGi framework can be found by any
          of the previous steps then the Feature Launcher implementation may provide a
          default framework implementation to be used.</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        
        <para>If no suitable OSGi framework implementation can be found then the Feature Launcher
        implementation must throw a <code>LaunchException</code>.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Creating a Framework instance</title>
        
        <para>Once a suitable framework implementation has been located the Feature Launcher 
        implementation must create and initialize a framework instance. Implementations are
        free to use implementation specific mechanisms for framework implementations that
        they recognise. The result of this initialization must be the same as if the
        Feature Launcher used the <code>org.osgi.framework.launch.FrameworkFactory</code>
        registered by the framework implementation to create the framework instance.</para>
        
        <para>When creating the framework any framework launch properties defined in
        the Feature must be used. These are defined as described in <xref 
          linkend="service.featurelauncher-framework.props" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> and
        must include any necessary variable replacement as defined by <xref
          linkend="service.featurelauncher-variable.overrides" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
          
        <para>Once instantiated the framework must be initialised appropriately so that it
        has a valid <code>BundleContext</code>. Once initialised the framework is ready for
        the Feature Launcher implementation to begin populating the framework.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Installing bundles and configurations</title>
        
        <para>The Feature Launcher must iterate through the list of bundles in the feature,
        installing them in the same order that they are declared in the feature. If
        bundle start levels have been defined, as described in <xref 
        linkend="service.featurelauncher-start.levels" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, then
        the Feature Launcher must ensure that the start level is correctly set for
        each installed bundle. If no start level metadata or extension is defined 
        then all bundles are installed with the framework default start level.</para>
        
        <para>If the installation of a bundle fails because it is determined by
        the framework to be a duplicate of an existing bundle then the Feature Launcher
        must treat the installation as a success. The start level of such a bundle
        must be set to the lower of its current value and the start level defined
        for the feature bundle that failed to install.</para>

        <para>If a Feature defines one or more Feature Configurations then these cannot be
        guaranteed to be made available until the <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.cm.ConfigurationAdmin" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service
        has been registered. A Feature Launcher implementation may provide an implementation
        specific way to pre-register configurations, however in general the Feature Launcher
        should listen for the registration of the <code>ConfigurationAdmin</code> service
        and immediately create the defined configurations when it becomes available.
        Configurations must be created in the same order as they are defined in the
        Feature.</para>
        
        <para>If the <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.CONFIGURATION_TIMEOUT"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> configuration property is set to <code>0</code>, and one or more
        Feature Configurations are defined in the Feature being installed, then the implementation
        must throw a <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
        unless it is capable of pre-registering those configurations in an implementation specific
        way.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Starting the framework</title>
        
        <para>Once all of the the bundles listed in the feature are installed, and any necessary
        configuration listener is registered, the implementation must start the OSGi framework.
        This action will automatically start the installed bundles as defined by the initial
        start level of the framework, and the start levels of the installed bundles.</para>
        
        <para>The Feature Launcher implementation must delay returning control to the caller
        until all configurations have been created, subject to the timeout defined by <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.CONFIGURATION_TIMEOUT"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The default timeout is <code>5000</code> milliseconds,
        and it determines the maximum length of time that the Feature Launcher implementation
        should wait to begin creating the configurations. A value of <code>-1</code> indicates
        that the Feature Launcher implementation must not wait, and must continue immediately,
        even if the configurations have not yet been created. If it is not possible to begin before
        the timeout expires then a  <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException"
        xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> must be thrown.</para>
        
        <para>Finally, if the <code>minimumStartLevel</code> has been set by the <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.BUNDLE_START_LEVELS"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> extension then the Feature Launcher implementation must check
          the current start level of the framework. If the current start level is less than the
          value of <code>minimumStartLevel</code> then the framework's start level must be set 
          to this value.
        </para>
        
        <para>Once the start process is complete the Framework instance must be returned
        to the caller.</para>
        
        <para>The following failure modes must all result in a <xref 
        linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.LaunchException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> 
        being thrown:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A bundle fails to resolve. If one of the installed bundles fails to resolve this
            is an error <emphasis>unless</emphasis> the Feature is not complete. For Features that
            are not complete resolution failures must be logged, but not cause a failure.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A resolved bundle fails to start. If one of the resolved bundles fails to start
            this is an error <emphasis>unless</emphasis> the bundle is a fragment or an extension 
            bundle, which the Feature Launcher should not attempt to start.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A configuration cannot be created. If a configuration cannot be created then
            this must result in a start failure</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>If a launching failure is triggered by an exception, for example a <xref 
          linkend="org.osgi.framework.BundleException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> then this must be
        set as the <code>cause</code> of the <code>LaunchException</code> that is thrown.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Cleanup after failure</title>
        
        <para>If the Feature Launcher implementation fails to launch a feature then any intermediate
        objects must be properly closed and discarded. For example if an OSGi framework instance
        has been created then it must be stopped and discarded.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>The Feature Runtime Service</title>
    
    <para>The Feature Runtime Service can be thought of as an equivalent of the Feature Launcher for
    an existing, running OSGi framework. The Feature Runtime Service therefore does not offer any 
    mechanism for launching a framework, but instead allows one or more features to be installed
    into the running framework. As an OSGi framework is a dynamic environment the Feature Runtime 
    Service also provides snapshots describing the currently installed Features, allows installed 
    Features to be updated, and allows Features to be removed from the system.</para>
    
    <para>An important difference between the Feature Launcher and Feature Runtime Service is
    that because the Feature Runtime Service allows multiple Features to be installed it must
    be able to identify and resolve simple conflicts. For example if two Features include the
    same bundle at different versions then the resolution may be to install only the higher 
    version, or both versions.</para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Using the Feature Runtime</title>
      
      <para>The Feature Runtime must be registered as a service in the service registry.
      Management agents that wish to install, manage or introspect Features in the framework 
      must obtain this service. The Feature Service Runtime service must advertise the
      <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
      interface.</para>
      
      <section>
        <title>Thread Safety</title>
        
        <para>Instances of the Feature Runtime are Thread Safe, regardless of whether the
        service is implemented as a singleton or otherwise. Any <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.OperationBuilder"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instances created by the Feature Runtime are
        <emphasis>not</emphasis> thread safe and must not be shared between threads.</para>
        
        <para>Despite the Operation Builders not being Thread Safe the underlying Feature
        Runtime must remain Thread Safe, specifically if two Operation Builders complete
        at the same time then these calls should be handled sequentially such that there
        are never partially deployed Features present when installing, updating or removing 
        a Feature.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Introspecting the installed Features</title>
        
        <para>An important role for any management agent is being able to
        introspect the system to discover its current state. The Feature
        Runtime enables this through the <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.getInstalledFeatures--" 
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method, which returns a snapshot of
        the current state of the system.</para>
        
        <para>The returned list of snapshots contains one <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledFeature" 
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> entry for each installed Feature, in the order
        that they were installed, and may be empty if no Features have been 
        installed. If the framework was started using a Feature Launcher from the
        same implementation as the Feature Runtime then the Feature Runtime may 
        choose to represent the launched Feature in the snapshot list. If the launched 
        Feature is included in the snapshot list then it must set <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledFeature.isInitialLaunch--" 
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> to <code>true</code>. Launch features cannot be 
         removed or updated by the Feature Runtime, and any attempt to do so must
         throw a <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntimeException"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
        
        <para>Each Installed Feature provides:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.ID" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> of the 
            Feature from <xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledFeature.getFeatureId--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <code>List</code> of <xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledBundle" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> 
            from <xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledFeature.getInstalledBundles--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> listing the bundles installed by the Runtime on behalf of the Feature.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <code>List</code> of <xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledConfiguration" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> 
            from <xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledFeature.getInstalledConfigurations--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> listing the configurations installed by the feature.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
             
        <para>The <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledBundle" 
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> snapshots each represent a bundle installed
        by the Feature Runtime on behalf of the Feature. The Installed Bundle 
        contains the following information:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledBundle.getBundleId--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The <code>ID</code> of the bundle that was installed.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledBundle.getAliases--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A <code>Collection</code> of one or more <code>ID</code>s that
             are known to correspond to this bundle. This list will always contain the 
             <code>bundleId</code> and may contain additional IDs if their attempted 
             installation resulted in a collision.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledBundle.getBundle--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The actual bundle that was installed into the runtime.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledBundle.getStartLevel--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The calculated start level for this bundle. Note that
             this start level may have been affected by other features.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledBundle.getOwningFeatures--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A <code>List</code> of the ids of the features which 
             <emphasis>own</emphasis> the installed bundle. Ownership of a bundle is tracked 
             by the Feature Runtime, and it is used to identify when the same bundle forms 
             part of more than one Feature. Bundles that are owned 
             by more than one Feature will not be removed until <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the 
             Features that own them are removed.</para>
             <para>In the case where a bundle was not installed by the Feature
             Runtime, but later became owned by an installed Feature, that bundle
             will also be owned by the virtual <code>org.osgi.service.featurelauncher:external:1.0.0</code> 
             Feature to indicate that they will not be removed if the other owning
             Feature is removed.
             <remark>Make a constant for this</remark></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> 
      
        <para>In addition to bundles Features can contain configurations. The <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledConfiguration" 
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> snapshots each represent a
        configuration created by the Feature Runtime on behalf of the Feature.
        The Installed Configuration contains the following information:</para>
         
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledConfiguration.getPid--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The configuration pid of this configuration.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledConfiguration.getFactoryPid--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The factory pid of this configuration, or an empty
            <code>Optional</code> if the configuration is not a factory configuration.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledConfiguration.getProperties--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - The merged configuration properties that result
             from the full set of installed Features contributing to this configuration.
             Note that there is no dynamic link to Configuration Admin and so any 
             configuration changes made outside the Feature Runtime will not be reflected.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref
             linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledConfiguration.getOwningFeatures--" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> - A <code>List</code> of the ids of the features which 
             <emphasis>own</emphasis> the configuration. Ownership of a configuration is tracked 
             by the Feature Runtime, and it is used to identify when the same configuration, as
             defined by its pid, forms part of more than one Feature. Configurations that are owned 
             by more than one Feature will not be removed until <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the 
             Features that own them are removed.</para>
             <para>In the case where a configuration was not installed by the Feature
             Runtime, but later became owned by an installed Feature, that configuration
             will also be owned by the virtual <code>org.osgi.service.featurelauncher:external:1.0.0</code> 
             Feature to indicate that they will not be deleted if the other owning
             Feature is removed.
             <remark>Make a constant for this</remark></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> 
      </section>
      
      
      <section>
        <title>Installing a feature</title>
        
        <para>Installing a Feature uses one of the <code>install</code> methods present
        on the Feature Runtime. These methods allow the caller to provide the Feature
        to be installed and return an <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.InstallOperationBuilder"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> to allow the caller to configure their installation
        operation. Configuration of operations includes:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.variable-overrides" 
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.artifact-repositories" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><xref linkend="service.featurelauncher-feature.decoration" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Adding <xref linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.merge.strategies"
             xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> 
        
        <para>Once the operation is fully configured then the caller uses the
        <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.InstallOperationBuilder.install--"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method to begin the installation. The end result of 
        installing a Feature is that all of the bundles listed in the Feature are 
        installed, all of the Feature Configurations have been created, all bundles 
        have been marked as persistently started, and the framework start level is at 
        least the minimum level required by the Feature.</para>
        
        <para>Start levels for the bundles in the Feature may be controlled as
        described in <xref linkend="service.featurelauncher-start.levels"
          xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. If any bundles are installed with a start level 
        higher than the current framework start level then they will be
        marked persistently started but will not start until the framework start
        level is changed.
        </para>
        
        <para>In more complex cases, where multiple features are installed with
        overlapping bundles or configurations then <xref 
         linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.merge.strategies"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> will be applied to determine which bundles
        are installed, and what configuration properties will be used when
        creating or updating a configuration.</para>
        
        <para>If a failure occurs during the installation of a Feature then the
        Feature Runtime must make every effort to return the system to its pre-existing
        state. After a failure no new bundles should be installed, any altered configurations
        returned to their previous states, and the framework start level should be the same 
        as it was prior to the failed installation.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.artifact-repositories">
        <title>Setting the available Artifact Repositories</title>
        
        <para>As with the Feature Launcher, in order to successfully locate the bundles
        listed in a feature the Feature Runtime must have access to one or more Artifact 
        Repositories capable of locating the bundles. These Artifact Repositories are
        configured into each Operation Builder by the user.</para>
        
        
        <para>A configured Feature Runtime will typically include one or more pre-defined 
        Artifact Repositories. These pre-defined repositories are available to view via
        the <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.getDefaultRepositories--"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. By default all Operation Builders will have access to
        these repositories when completing. This behaviour can be changed using the
        <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.OperationBuilder.useDefaultRepositories-boolean-"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method.</para>
        
        <para>Additional Artifact Repositories can be added to an Operation Builder by calling the <xref 
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.OperationBuilder.addRepository-String-ArtifactRepository-"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The supplied <code>name</code> is used to identify
         the repository. If the supplied name is already used for an existing
         Artifact Repository then it will be replaced or, if the supplied Artifact Repository
         is <code>null</code>, removed. A named Artifact Repository added in this way will
         override a default Artifact Repository with the same name.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.variable-overrides">
        <title>Setting variable overrides</title>
        
        <para>As described in <xref linkend="service.featurelauncher-variable.overrides"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink" /> a feature may define zero or more overridable properties
        which can be used to alter the deployment of the feature. These properties may be
        configured into each Operation Builder by calling the <xref 
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.OperationBuilder.withVariables-Map-"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method. The supplied <code>Map</code> contains the
         keys and values that will override the variables in the Feature.</para>
      
      </section>
      
      <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.merge.strategies">
        <title>Merging strategies</title>
        <para>Merge operations occur when two or more features reference the same, or 
        similar, items to be installed. The purpose of a merge operation is to avoid
        unnecessary duplication, and to resolve conflicts.</para>
        
        <para>Merging potentially applies whenever a Feature is installed, updated or 
        removed, and may result in different outcomes depending on the strategy used.
        All runtime merge functions therefore receive a <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.MergeOperationType"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> indicating which type of operation is currently 
         running.</para>
        <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.merge.strategies.bundles">
          <title>Merging Bundles</title>
          <para>Features may define bundles to be installed by including Feature Bundle
          entries. If two or more Features include Feature Bundles which have IDs with
          the same group id and artifact id, but which are not the same, then this 
          situation requires a merge to resolve the possible conflict. Determining
          whether two IDs are the same is accomplished by checking whether they
          return equal strings from <code>toString()</code>.</para>
          
          <para>When a possible conflict is detected the Feature Runtime must call a <xref
            linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.RuntimeBundleMerge"
           xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> to identify the correct actions to take. These actions
           include:</para>
           
           <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Whether to install the candidate Feature Bundle or not</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Whether to re-designate the ownership of any existing Installed Bundles</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Whether to remove any existing Feature Bundles</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          
          <para>Although the obvious time for a bundle merge operation to occur is during
          an <code>INSTALL</code> operation, merges may also occur during <code>UPDATE</code>
          and <code>REMOVE</code> operations. During an <code>UPDATE</code> the existing
          bundles from the Feature being updated will remain available so that the updated
          Feature may be merged into the existing runtime. During a <code>REMOVE</code>
          a merge will occur to allow Feature ownership to be re-allocated if a shared bundle
          is being removed.</para>
          
          <para>Merges are resolved by the <code>mergeBundle</code> method which receives:</para>
           
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The type of the operation, one of <code>INSTALL</code>, <code>UPDATE</code>
              or <code>REMOVE</code>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The Feature being operated on</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The Feature Bundle which requires merging</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A <code>Collection</code> of Installed Bundles representing the currently installed bundles
              which have an overlapping <code>groupId</code> and <code>artifactId</code>. Note that
              in the case of an <code>UPDATE</code> or <code>REMOVE</code> operation the Feature being updated
              or removed will not be present in the collection of owning features for any of the Installed Bundles.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A <code>List</code> of <xref 
               linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.RuntimeBundleMerge.FeatureBundleDefinition"
               xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> representing the existing Features which form
              part of the merge operation. Note that in the case of an <code>UPDATE</code> or <code>REMOVE</code>
              operation the Feature Bundle being updated or removed will not be present in the list.
              Entries in the list are present in the order that the Features were installed into the runtime.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>The result of the merge function is a <code>Stream</code> of <xref 
           linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.RuntimeBundleMerge.BundleMapping"
           xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. Each Bundle Mapping links a bundle <code>ID</code> to <code>List</code> of feature 
          <code>ID</code>s. The Bundle Mapping's bundle id must only be a <code>bundleId</code> found in the list of Installed 
          Bundles or, in the case of an <code>INSTALL</code> or <code>UPDATE</code> operation, the <code>id</code> of the
          Feature Bundle being merged. The mapped Feature ids must contain the <code>id</code> of every Feature in the supplied 
          Feature Bundle Definitions, and, in the case of an <code>INSTALL</code> or <code>UPDATE</code> operation, the <code>id</code> of the
          Feature being merged. If the <code>id</code> of any Installed Bundle is not present in the returned Stream
          then that bundle will be removed as part of the ongoing operation. If the same bundle id is present more than once
          the the two mappings will be combined using the union of the mapped Feature ids.</para>
          
          <para>A simple example of a merge strategy which combines configurations by upgrading Features to the
          highest compatible version could be implemented as follows:</para>
          
          <programlisting>
public Map&lt;ID,List&lt;ID&gt;&gt; mergeBundle(MergeOperationType operation,
		Feature feature, FeatureBundle toMerge,
		List&lt;InstalledBundle&gt; installedBundles,
		Map&lt;FeatureBundle,Feature&gt; existingFeatureBundles) {

	Map&lt;ID,List&lt;ID&gt;&gt; result;

	if (operation == MergeOperationType.REMOVE) {
		// Just keep everything the same
		result = installedBundles.stream()
				.filter(i -&gt; !i.getOwningFeatures().isEmpty())
				.collect(Collectors.toMap(i -&gt; i.getBundleId(),
						i -&gt; i.getOwningFeatures()));
	} else {
		// Find the Installed bundles we might replace
		Version v = RuntimeMerges.getOSGiVersion(toMerge.getID());

		List&lt;InstalledBundle&gt; sameMajor = new ArrayList&lt;&gt;();
		List&lt;InstalledBundle&gt; differentMajor = new ArrayList&lt;&gt;();

		installedBundles.forEach(i -&gt; {
			if (i.getBundle().getVersion().getMajor() == v.getMajor()) {
				sameMajor.add(i);
			} else {
				differentMajor.add(i);
			}
		});

		// Bundles with a different major version stay the same
		result = differentMajor.stream()
				.filter(i -&gt; !i.getOwningFeatures().isEmpty())
				.collect(Collectors.toMap(i -&gt; i.getBundleId(),
						i -&gt; i.getOwningFeatures()));

		// Find the biggest existing version and see if it's bigger than v
		Optional&lt;InstalledBundle&gt; max = sameMajor.stream()
				.max((a, b) -&gt; a.getBundle().getVersion()
						.compareTo(b.getBundle().getVersion()))
				.filter(m -&gt; m.getBundle().getVersion().compareTo(v) &gt;= 0);

		// Use the old version if it's bigger, or the new if not
		ID key = max.isPresent() ? max.get().getBundleId() : toMerge.getID();

		Stream&lt;ID&gt; featureIds = sameMajor.stream()
				.flatMap(i -&gt; i.getOwningFeatures().stream());

		result.put(key,
				Stream.concat(Stream.of(feature.getID()), featureIds)
						.collect(Collectors.toList()));
	}
	return result;
}
</programlisting>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.merge.strategies.configs">
          <title>Merging Configurations</title>
          <para>Features may define configurations by including Feature Configuration
          entries. If two or more Features include properties for the same configuration
          PID then this situation requires a merge to resolve the conflict.</para>
          
          <para>Merges are resolved by a <xref 
           linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.RuntimeConfigurationMerge"
           xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> which receives:</para>
           
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The type of the operation, one of <code>INSTALL</code>, <code>UPDATE</code>
              or <code>REMOVE</code>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The Feature being operated on</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The Feature Configuration which requires merging</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The Installed Configuration representing the current state of the configuration. Note that
              in the case of an <code>UPDATE</code> or <code>REMOVE</code> operation the Feature being updated
              or removed will not be present in the list of owning features.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A <code>List</code> of <xref 
               linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.RuntimeConfigurationMerge.FeatureConfigurationDefinition"
               xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> representing the existing Features which form
              part of the merge operation. Note that in the case of an <code>UPDATE</code> or <code>REMOVE</code>
              operation the Feature Configuration being updated or removed will not be present in the list.
              Entries in the list are present in the order that the Features were installed into the runtime.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          
          <para>The result of the merge function is a map of configuration properties that should be used to
          update the configuration. If the map is <code>null</code> then the configuration should be deleted.</para>
          
          <para>A simple example of a merge strategy which combines configurations by overlaying each in turn
          and ignoring <code>null</code> configurations could be implemented as follows:</para>
          
          <programlisting>
public Map&lt;String,Object&gt; mergeConfiguration(MergeOperationType operation,
		Feature feature, FeatureConfiguration toMerge, InstalledConfiguration configuration,
		List&lt;FeatureConfigurationDefinition&gt; existingFeatureConfigurations) {

	boolean addedSomething = false;

	Map&lt;String,Object&gt; result = new HashMap&lt;&gt;();

	for (FeatureConfigurationDefinition fcd : existingFeatureConfigurations) {
		FeatureConfiguration fc = fcd.getFeatureConfiguration();
		if(fc.getValues() != null) {
			result.putAll(fc.getValues());
			addedSomething = true;
		}
	}
				
	if(operation != MergeOperationType.REMOVE &amp;&amp; toMerge.getValues() != null) {
		result.putAll(toMerge.getValues());
		addedSomething = true;
	}

	return addedSomething ? result : null;
}</programlisting>
          
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Removing a Feature</title>
        <para>Removing a feature from the Feature Runtime Service uses the <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.remove-ID-"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> method to uninstall and remove a feature from
        the framework. Removing a feature is a comparatively simple operation, and therefore does 
        not require the configuration of an <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime.OperationBuilder"
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
         
        <para>Once the <code>remove</code> method returns the feature will have been removed
        from the Feature Runtime, and any links to installed bundles and configurations will
        have been removed. If this leaves any installed bundles or installed configurations
        with no owners then these will be uninstalled or deleted from the system as appropriate.</para>

        <para>If a failure occurs during the removal of a feature then the
        Feature Runtime must make every effort to fully remove the feature, for example
        by continuing to remove installed bundles that no longer have any owners.
        Exceptions that occur must be logged, and upon completion the Feature Runtime must
        throw a <code>FeatureRuntimeException</code> which indicates the incomplete removal.</para>
        
        <para>It is not an error to remove a feature which does not exist in the Feature Runtime
        and this must return without error, and without altering the state of the system. It is
        an error to attempt to remove any feature that returns <code>true</code> for <xref
         linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.InstalledFeature.isInitialLaunch--" 
         xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>, and any attempt to do so must result in a 
        <code>FeatureRuntimeException</code>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Updating a Feature</title>
        <para>Bundles</para>
        <para>Configurations</para>
        <para>refreshing packages</para>
        <para>Action on failure</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>The Feature Runtime Behaviour</title>
      
      <para>The following section provides normative requirements for the
      behaviour of the Feature Runtime when it is used. This includes the
      necessary end states after installation, update and removal of
      Features.</para>
      
      <section>
        <title>The Feature installation process</title>
        
        <para>The Feature Installation process has four main phases:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The feature decoration phase, where the Feature is decorated and validated</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The bundle installation phase, where Feature bundles are installed</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The configuration creation phase, where Feature Configurations are created</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Feature Start phase, where Bundles are started.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The feature decoration phase must complete before any other phases
        can begin. The the bundle installation phase and the configuration creation
        phase may happen in any order, or even with interleaved steps, however
        the Feature Start phase must not begin until the bundle installation
        and configuration creation phases are complete.</para>
        
        <section>
          <title>Feature Decoration</title>
          <para>The first stage of the operation is to determine the feature that
          should be used by running the configured feature decoration handlers.</para>
        
          <para>First the Feature Runtime must execute any registered <xref 
           linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.FeatureDecorator"
           xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> instances in the order that they were registered.
          The feature returned by each decorator is used as input to the next.</para>
          
          <para>Once the decoration is complete the Feature Runtime must iterate through
          the Feature Extensions defined by the feature. For each Feature Extension the
          Feature Runtime must:</para>
        
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem><para>Identify the Feature Extension Handler for the named extension.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>If no Feature Extension Handler can be found, and the extension name is
            one of:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.LAUNCH_FRAMEWORK"
                   xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.FRAMEWORK_LAUNCHING_PROPERTIES"
                   xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.FeatureLauncherConstants.BUNDLE_START_LEVELS"
                   xrefstyle="hyperlink"/></para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
              <para>then create an empty Feature Extension Handler which may validate the <xref
               linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.FeatureExtension.Type" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> of the extension
               and must return the original feature.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para>If no Feature Extension Handler has been found or created then check the
            <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.FeatureExtension.Kind" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> of the
            extension. If it is <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.FeatureExtension.Kind.MANDATORY"
            xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> then the operation fails with a <code>FeatureRuntimeException</code></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Otherwise call the Feature Extension Handler, and use its result as input when
            calling any subsequent Feature Extension Handlers.</para></listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        
          <para>If any of the decorators throws an <xref
           linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.AbandonOperationException" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
          then the operation must immediately fail.</para>      
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.feature.bundle.install">
          <title>Bundle Installation</title>
          <para>When a feature is being installed the Feature Runtime identifies the
          bundles to be installed. The Feature Runtime also gathers the set of bundles
          that are already installed, and then computes the overlap between these. Bundles
          are deemed to overlap if they have the same group id, artifact id, type and
          classifier but they may differ in version.</para>
        
          <para>If the overlap list contains entries 
          which overlap exactly, that is they have the same version in the runtime and the
          Feature being installed, then those bundles are removed from the list of bundles
          to be installed and the existing bundles are marked as <emphasis>owned</emphasis>
          by the Feature being installed. If the marked bundles were not previously
          owned by any other feature then they also marked as owned by the 
          osgi.external Feature to indicate that they will not be removed if the
          Feature being installed is removed.
          <remark>Make a constant for this</remark></para>
        
          <para>Any remaining overlap entries are processed according to the merge
          strategy for the feature, as described in <xref 
           linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.merge.strategies.bundles"
           xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. The final list of bundles to install, which
          excludes any already installed bundles, is then installed in the same order 
          as it was defined by the feature. Each bundle in the feature, including
          bundles that were already installed, is then marked as owned by the 
          installing feature.</para>
          
          <para>If the installation of a bundle fails because it is determined by
          the framework to be a duplicate of an existing bundle then the Feature Runtime
          must treat the installation as a success and add the ID as an alias for the existing
          Installed Bundle. The start level of such a bundle
          must be set to the lower of its current value and the start level defined
          for the feature bundle that failed to install.</para>
          
          <para>Once the installation of bundles is complete the Feature Runtime must
          uninstall any bundles which were identified for removal as part of any 
          merge processes.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
          <title>Configuration Creation</title>
          <para>As part of the initial Feature installation the Feature Runtime
          must also process and create any Feature Configurations that are defined in
          the Feature. Feature Configurations cannot be guaranteed to be made available 
          until a <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.cm.ConfigurationAdmin" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
          service has been registered. A Feature Runtime implementation should therefore
          listen for the registration of a <code>ConfigurationAdmin</code> service
          and immediately create or update any pending configurations when it becomes available.
          Configurations must be created or updated in the same order as they are defined in the
          Feature.</para> 
        
          <para>If the same configuration, as identified by its configuration pid, 
          is defined in one or more existing installed Features then the configuration
          properties to be used are determined by merging the previous configuration
          properties with the new properties defined in the Feature, as described in <xref 
           linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.merge.strategies.configs"
           xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
          If at the point where the FeatureRuntime attempts to create or update a
          Feature Configuration there are already configuration properties defined in
          <code>ConfigurationAdmin</code> then these must be ignored and replaced using
          <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.cm.Configuration.updateIfDifferent-Dictionary-"
           xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> unless the <code>Configuration</code> is marked as <xref
           linkend="org.osgi.service.cm.Configuration.ConfigurationAttribute.READ_ONLY"
           xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. If a <code>READ_ONLY</code> configuration does exist
           then the Feature Runtime must log a warning and skip that configuration.
          </para>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.feature.start">
          <title>Feature Start</title>
          <para>Once all of the bundles listed by the feature are installed then the 
          bundles' start levels are assigned as described in <xref 
            linkend="service.featurelauncher-start.levels"  xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>. 
          This includes any pre-existing bundles and the results of any merge operations. 
          If no start level configuration is defined in the feature for a particular bundle 
          then the start level for that bundle is set to the current start level of the 
          framework.</para>
          
          <para>The Feature Runtime must then identify the lowest start level referenced
          in the Feature, and repeatedly run through the list of bundles, in the order that
          they are defined in the Feature, looking for bundles which match the identified 
          start level. For each bundle the Feature Runtime must:</para>
          
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If the bundle was installed in the Bundle Installation phase then set the
              start level for the bundle.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>If the bundle was already installed then update the start level for the bundle
             if, and only if, the new start level is lower than the existing start level.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Mark the bundle as persistently started unless it is a 
              <emphasis>fragment</emphasis> bundle.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          
          <para>The Feature Runtime must then identify the next lowest start level referenced
          in the Feature and repeat this process until all bundles have been persistently
          started. Once this process is complete then the framework start level must be
          increased to the minimum start level required by the Feature, or returned to the
          original framework start level if this is higher and was decreased as part of
          <xref linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.merge.strategies.bundles"
           xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.</para>
          
        </section>
        
        <section>
          <title>Failure scenarios</title>
          <para>The following is a non-exhaustive list of possible failure scenarios that
          must be handled.</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The feature being installed is already known to the Feature Runtime. This must
              be treated as a failure as the configuration of the <code>InstallOperationBuilder</code>
              may not be the same as the previous installation. The Feature Runtime must make no changes
              and immediately throw a <code>FeatureRuntimeException</code>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A Feature Bundle cannot be found by any configured <xref 
               linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepository" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A <code>BundleException</code> is thrown during <xref 
               linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.feature.bundle.install" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A <code>BundleException</code> is thrown during <xref 
               linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.feature.start" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A Feature Configuration cannot be created by the <xref 
               linkend="org.osgi.service.cm.ConfigurationAdmin" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>An <code>Exception</code> is thrown by any configured <xref 
               linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepository" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>,
               <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.RuntimeBundleMerge" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
              or <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.RuntimeConfigurationMerge"
               xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
               </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          
          <para>In all cases the first exception must be treated as a failure, with the installation process
          halting immediately. The feature must then be removed from the runtime in a similar manner to
          calling <code>remove</code> for the feature id. Once the feature removal is complete the failure
          may be used in creating the <code>FeatureRuntimeException</code> that must be thrown by this method.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The Feature removal process</title>
        <para>The Feature removal process has four main phases:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The feature removal phase, where the feature is removed from the Feature Runtime.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The bundle stop phase, where Installed Bundles without owners are stopped.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The configuration deletion phase, where Installed Configurations without owners are removed</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The bundle removal phase, stopped bundles are uninstalled</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The the feature removal and bundle stop phases may happen in any order, 
        or even with interleaved steps. The same is true for the configuration deletion
        phase and the bundle removal phase, however these phases must not begin until 
        the bundle stop phase is complete.</para>
        
        <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.feature.removal">
          <title>Feature Removal</title>
          <para>Feature removal is a simple operation which removes any reference to
          the Installed Feature from the Feature Runtime. This includes the list of
          installed features, and the ownership lists of any Installed Bundles or
          Installed configurations in the Feature Runtime. After removal is complete
          the <code>ID</code> of the removed feature should not appear anywhere in
          the Feature Runtime.</para>
          
          <para>Installed Bundles and Installed Configurations which have zero
          owners after the removal of the feature are now considered eligible
          for removal. Their removal processes are described in the next phases.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.bundle.stop">
          <title>Bundle Stop</title>
          <para>The Feature Runtime must identify the highest start level set by the
          list of Installed Features, excluding the Feature being removed. If no start
          level is defined by this list of features then no action is taken, otherwise
          the framework start level is set to the newly identified start level. 
          </para>
          
          <para>For each installed bundle updated in <xref 
           linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.feature.removal" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
          the Feature Runtime checks to see whether there are now zero owners for the installed
          bundle. If there are then this bundle becomes eligible for removal.</para> 
          
          <para>Bundles that are eligible for removal are then stopped in the reverse order
          in which they were started by <xref
           linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.feature.start" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
          This is accomplished by stopping the bundles with the highest start level first,
          using the reverse order of declaration in the feature where the start level is the
          same. If an eligible bundle is already stopped then they may be skipped.
          </para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
          <title>Configuration Removal</title>
          
          <para>Once the <xref 
           linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.bundle.stop" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
          phase has completed the Feature Runtime may begin removing configurations
          that are eligible. As with bundles, configurations become eligible for removal
          if they are no longer owned by any feature. Eligible configurations must be
          removed in the reverse order of creation, that is the reverse order that
          they were listed in the feature being removed.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="service.featurelauncher-runtime.bundle.removal">
          <title>Bundle Removal</title>
          
          <para>Once the <xref 
           linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.bundle.stop" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>
          phase has completed the Feature Runtime may begin uninstalling bundles from 
          the OSGi framework. These bundles must only be eligible bundles identified
          and stopped as part of the previous phase. Bundles are uninstalled in reverse
          installation order, that is the reverse of the order in which they are listed
          in the feature.</para> 
          
          <para>If one or more bundles have been uninstalled, and once all eligible
          bundles have been uninstalled, the Feature Runtime must refresh the framework
          wiring by calling <code>FrameworkWiring.refreshBundles</code>, passing the
          list of uninstalled bundles. This will cause the framework to completely
          remove the uninstalled bundles, and any wirings that link to them.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
          <title>Failure scenarios</title>
          <para>The following is a non-exhaustive list of possible failure scenarios that
          must be handled.</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The feature being removed is not known to the Feature Runtime. This must
              not be treated as a failure, and should simply return immediately.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>One or more <code>BundleExceptions</code> are thrown during <xref 
               linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.bundle.stop" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
              These exceptions should be logged when they occur, but then ignored.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>One or more <code>BundleExceptions</code> are thrown during <xref 
               linkend="service.featurelauncher-runtime.bundle.removal" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>.
              These exceptions should be logged when they occur, with the Feature Runtime 
              continuing despite the errors. Once the feature removal is complete the
              failures may be used in creating the <code>FeatureRuntimeException</code>
              that must be thrown by this method.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>One or more Installed Configurations are missing from the <xref 
               linkend="org.osgi.service.cm.ConfigurationAdmin" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service.
              These missing configurations should be logged with a warning, but not treated
              as an error.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>One or more Installed Configurations cannot be deleted missing from the <xref 
               linkend="org.osgi.service.cm.ConfigurationAdmin" xrefstyle="hyperlink"/> service.
              These exceptions should be logged when they occur, with the Feature Runtime 
              continuing despite the errors. Once the feature removal is complete the
              failures may be used in creating the <code>FeatureRuntimeException</code>
              that must be thrown by this method.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Capabilities</title>

    <para>The Feature Launcher must provide the following capabilities.</para>
    
    <section>
      <title>osgi.service Capability</title>

      <para>The bundle providing the Feature Runtime service must provide
      capabilities in the <link
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"><code>osgi.service</code></link>
      namespace representing the services it is required to register. This
      capability must also declare uses constraints for the relevant service
      packages:</para>

      <programlisting>Provide-Capability: osgi.service;
 objectClass:List&lt;String&gt;="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime";
 uses:="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime",
 osgi.service;
 objectClass:List&lt;String&gt;="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory";
 uses:="org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository"</programlisting>

      <para>This capability must follow the rules defined for the <xref
      linkend="service.namespaces-osgi.service.namespace"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>
    <para>When Java permissions are enabled, the following security procedures apply.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Required Permissions</title>

      <para>Bundles that need to make use of the Feature Runtime or Artifact Repository Factory
      services must be granted permission to get the relevant service, for example
      <code>ServicePermission[ org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime,
      GET]</code> so that they may retrieve the service and use it.</para>

      <para>Only a bundle that provides a Feature Runtime implementation should be
      granted <code>ServicePermission[
      org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.FeatureRuntime, REGISTER]</code> and
      <code>ServicePermission[
      org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.ArtifactRepositoryFactory, REGISTER]</code>
      to register the services defined by this specification.</para>

      <para>The Feature Runtime implementation must also be granted
      <code>ServicePermission[org.osgi.service.cm.ConfigurationAdmin,
      GET]</code>,
      <code>AdminPermission[*, execute]</code>,
      <code>AdminPermission[*, lifecycle]</code>,
      <code>AdminPermission[*, metadata]</code>,
      <code>AdminPermission[*, resolve]</code>,
      <code>AdminPermission[*, startlevel]</code>,
      <code>AdminPermission[*, context]</code>,
      as these actions are all required to implement the
      specification.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

<!--   <section>
    <title>Handling Bundles</title>
    <para>All bundles listed in the Feature will first be installed, then resolved
    and finally started in the Framework chosen by the launcher.</para>
    
    <para>Bundle fragments are installed and resolved and attached to their host(s).
    </para>
    
    <para>If a Bundle cannot resolve or start a <code>LauncherException</code> must be
    thrown.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Handling Configuration</title>
    <para>If configuration is found in the Feature then it is passed to the Configuration
    Admin service. If a Feature contains a <code>configuration</code> section but the Configuration
    Admin service is not found in the running system, the launcher will abort with an 
    <code>LauncherException</code>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Specifying Framework Properties</title>
    <para>Framework Launching Properties can be provided in the Feature through
    the <code>framework-launching-properties</code> extension.
    The launcher must ensure that the Framework it provides for the feature has these
    properties set. If it cannot provide a Framework with the requested Framework properties
    set it must fail with a <code>LauncherException</code>.</para>
    
    <para>For example, to ensure the <code>org.osgi.framework.bsnversion</code> Framework
    property is set for the Feature, specify the following in the Feature: 
    <programlisting>  "extensions": {
    "framework-launching-properties": {
      "type": "json",
      "kind": "mandatory",
      "json": {
          "org.osgi.framework.bsnversion": "multiple"
      }
    }
  }</programlisting>      
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Specifying Runtime Preconditions</title>
    <para>A Feature can specify the preconditions it places on its runtime environment. That is,
    the Framework used to run the Feature in, must satisfy these constraints. If the Launcher
    cannot provide a Framework with the specified conditions, it must fail.</para>
    
    <para>
    Preconditions are specified as requirements in the Feature.
    If no preconditions are specified, the Launcher is free to choose a Java and OSGi implementation
    of its choice.
    </para>
    
    <para>For example:<programlisting>  "requirements": [
    {
      "namespace": "osgi.ee", 
      "filter":    "(&amp;(osgi.ee=JavaSE)(version=11))"
    }, {
      "namespace": "osgi.wiring.package", 
      "filter":    "(&amp;(osgi.wiring.package=org.osgi.framework)(version=1.10))"    
    }
  ]</programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Specifying Variables</title>
    <para>Variables allow for late binding of configuration values and Framework properties.
    Variables are provided through the <xref linkend="org.osgi.service.feature.launcher.LauncherFactory"
    xrefstyle="hyperlink"/>:
    <programlisting>Map&lt;String,Object&gt; variables = new HashMap&lt;&gt;();
variables.put("user.name", "scott");
variables.put("db.driver", "postgresql");
    
LauncherFactory factory = ... // From Service Registry or Service Loader
Launcher launcher = factory.newLauncher(
  new URL("https://repo.maven.apache.org/maven2/org/foo/Bar/1.0.0/Bar-1.0.0.osgifeature"),
  variables);
  
launcher.start();</programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Specifying Extension Handlers</title>
    <para></para>
    <remark>TODO</remark>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Specifying Post-processors</title>
    <para></para>
    <remark>TODO</remark>
  </section>  -->
  
  <!-- Specifying merge conflict handlers -->

  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.annotation.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.decorator.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.repository.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="../../generated/javadoc/docbook/org.osgi.service.featurelauncher.runtime.xml"/>


</chapter>



